<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>1061316_23052017</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>14.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>14.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>50.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>50.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>59.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>69.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing of the admissibility and merits in the case of Sargi and others versus Albania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>69.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>82.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on 19 February, 2016 under Article 34 of the Convention by 18 Albanian nationals and one Italian national.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>82.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>91.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the first section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>91.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>98.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on 19 April, 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>98.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>105.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent government are represented by their agent, Mrs. Alma Hicka,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>105.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>110.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Mr. Agim Hysi, Mr. Roden Hoxha,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>110.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>114.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mrs. Evi Sadushaj, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>114.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>118.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mr. Andrea Saccucci</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>118.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>122.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Studio Legale Sacucci Fares and Partners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>122.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>131.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some other applicants are also represented by Mrs. Giulia  Borgna of Studio Legale Sacucci Fares</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>131.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>136.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Partners and Mrs. Erinda Ballanca, who</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>136.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>139.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is also one of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>139.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>143.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two other applicants are also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>143.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>147.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>147.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>152.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome the following groups of judges who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>152.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>165.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The delegation of Latvian judges, the delegation of Norwegian judges, the delegation of Polish judges, and the delegation of Russian judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>165.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>175.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representatives of the parties of the applicants, I have determined the order of address as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>175.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>179.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Hicka for the government will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>179.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>184.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mr. Saccucci and Mrs. Borgna for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>184.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>202.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting into Polish and into Russian has been authorized for the benefit of the group of judges from Russia and Poland, respectively.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>202.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>214.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>214.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>215.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mrs. Hicka.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>220.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>225.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President, honorable members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>225.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>246.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before addressing the court detailed interest in the question asked, as a representative of the government in this procedure, I would like to summarize with two sentences the special situation of the applicant's treatment and the overall situation in which the authorities have operated in this area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>246.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>272.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government, for the facts, wished to point out that the matter under consideration belongs to a situation where initially the applicant property was considered as a construction without the regular permission issued by the authorities until the issuance of the decision of the administrative court dated 7 November 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>272.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>283.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And subsequently, it was expropriated under the domestic legal framework, being presumed to be a legitimate construction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>283.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>293.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the site of the applicant property, a project of infrastructure of public interest will be built and with an environment impact too.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>293.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>300.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this constitutes a cause for expropriation pursuant to the domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>300.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>314.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While regarding the general situation, it should be noted that finding itself in a massive illegal construction situation with over 400,000 illegal buildings for 2.8 million</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>314.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>324.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of inhabitants, the government, constituted out of the June election of 2013, started to take a quick step to normalize it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>324.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>335.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And through the acceleration of the legalization process, where construction fulfilled the conditions laid down by law, or demolishing illegal construction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>335.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>342.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In three years, have been legalized around 100,000 buildings, mostly homes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>342.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>352.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But on the other hand, illegal constructions which have blocked the competition of major infrastructure work have been demolished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>352.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>364.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was certainly a novelty in 25 years old situation, where illegal construction were tolerating this being the rule, not the exception.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>364.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>388.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In general terms, the relevant legislation provide that where a public interest project is to be constructed, and there are illegal construction, or construction overcoming the building condition, and therefore illegal, these are demolished to open the way for the implementation of the project based on public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>388.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>397.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While legitimate ones, or ones to be presumed as legitimate, are expropriated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>397.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>402.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The apical situation was not simple in appearance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>402.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>421.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were found to have a property registered in the immovable registration property office on the basis of a permit issued by the municipality of Lora, on a territory in which the competence was of the National Territorial Council.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>421.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>432.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The building stood in a substantial part of itself on the water, which is evident also from the property registration document as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>432.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>447.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under this condition, the National Urbanistic Construction Inspectorate began to operate on a property which, in their assessment, according to the competence given by law, was an illegal construction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>447.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>458.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant appealed to the Lora Administrative Court of First Instance, which issued the interim decision of 7 November 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>458.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>466.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government retains that the interim decision, dated 7 November 2013, was fully implemented.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>466.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>477.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To be clear on this issue, we should not read only the enacting clause of the decision, but should look at the decision as a whole, interpreting it in good faith.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>477.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>490.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A court decision, the court decision is addressed to certain authorities and laid down the obligation which were implemented in good faith by the authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>490.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>520.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decision of the First Instance Administrative Court of Lora reads, acceptance of the request and taking provisional measures of assurance of the claim by suspending the performance of the administrative actions by any subject of the state administration that impede the applicant from the peaceful enjoyment of their property in the object situated in the place called Uiftod Vlar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>520.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>527.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government retains that the decision of 7 November 2013 was fully implemented.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>527.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>540.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This decision was addressed to both inspectorate and was fully implemented by them, a fact which was confirmed by the institution themselves in the written form and filed to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>540.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>558.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither the applicant opposed the implementation of the decision by all this institution, but they considered that the decision of the Council of Ministers for the expropriation as the one not implementing the court decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>558.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>576.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it can be clearly seen, it is this interested institution which were determined by the applicant themselves and have been summoned to trial with a clear proposal that the decision was implemented by this institution, not the Council of Minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>576.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>589.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decision was mainly related to the inspectorate's action of 3 November 2013, which were subsequently found illegal by the domestic courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>589.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>618.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was the applicant who addressed the domestic court on this matter, but did not continue the trial and waive the rights ordered on the decision of 7 November 2013, while at the same time continuing the trial for the declaration of the inspectorate actions of 3 November 2013 as illegal and were awarded a decision in their favor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>618.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>633.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any irregularities of the administrative bodies related to the action of 3 November 2013 have been addressed by the domestic courts, so basically in the domestic level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>633.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>644.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The very object of the lawsuit filed by the applicant as a result of the interim measure clearly refers as the respondent party, the inspectorates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>644.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>665.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concretely, in their object of the lawsuit, the applicant has sought the obligation of the administrative body, NUCI, and NUCI Vlor to stop the performance of the other administrative actions necessary to protect the rights of the plaintiff.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>665.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>705.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This procedure has been completed and found as a definitive solution with the decision of the domestic court, that of the Vlora Administrative Court of First Instance, which was the decision number 59 dated 28 January 2014, which among others held the finding as unlawful of the administrative actions committed by a respondent, meaning the inspectorate dated 3 November 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>705.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>716.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decision of the 28 January 2014 found the actions of the inspectorate dated 3 November 2013 illegal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>716.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>733.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No compensation was sought by the applicant in the domestic court on this matter, neither in this procedure, not in any other parallel proceeding, despite the fact that the court decided in their favor in finding a violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>733.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>737.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case was abandoned by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>737.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>754.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indemnification could also be provided under the law for the non-contractual liability of the state bodies, and also by the law that regulates the inspectorate's competence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>754.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>760.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both procedures have been proven successful at domestic level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>760.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>790.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court order dated 7 November 2013 has extended the effect according to its lawsuit until 27 November 2013, the date in which, according to the government interpretation, the applicant lose the right to ownership over the property because of the expropriation procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>790.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>802.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, after 28 January 2014, the effects have fallen due to the will of the applicants themselves, who abandoned the process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>802.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>812.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The order dated 7 November 2013 requires that the applicant be allowed to enjoy their property in peace.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>812.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>823.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This order is neither binding nor prohibiting the expropriation, nor does it address the counsel of ministers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>823.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>830.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, no parallelism can be made with the case of Okay and others versus Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>830.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>847.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Okay case, the authorities address specifically the court decision, and with the government decision decided not to implement it, while in the current case there is no analogy, except for the fact that we are dealing with a government decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>847.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>858.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decision of the counsel of minister is the final administrative act defined in the Albanian expropriation legislation for expropriating.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>858.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>863.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is related to the second set of procedure against the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>863.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>879.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to the findings of the administrative court and its order, the authorities could no longer deal with the applicant building as prima facie illegal construction until this issue was resolved by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>879.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>886.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But on the other hand, there was still a public interest in the construction of infrastructure project.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>886.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>898.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the construction was assumed as legal and procedure foreseen by law for the expropriation of legal construction for the public interest were initiated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>898.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>910.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Every expropriation is performed according to certain procedure in the law, and this procedure determines at the end the issuance of the decision of the counsel of minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>910.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>917.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the current case, this cannot be an exception from the general rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>917.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>925.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the contrary, expropriation cannot be performed by any other act other than decision of the counsel of minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>925.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>941.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The law on expropriation for public interest recognized the applicant or any other entity the right to appeal to court for invalidation of the expropriation due to violation of the procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>941.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>945.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There have been successful cases in domestic court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>945.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>964.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or to oppose the expropriation price, indeed, the local court have recognized the right of the subject even for de facto expropriation where the subject for different reason is not included in the decision of the counsel of minister for expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>964.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>971.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The overwhelming majority of the subject choose to oppose the expropriation price.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>971.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>986.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the right to claim compensation in court for de facto expropriation has been recognized regularly if it has not been remedied by the administrative authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>986.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>992.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants choose not to challenge the procedure, but only the price.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>992.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>999.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the applicant have accepted the expropriation procedure as a legitimate one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>999.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1006.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any allegation or illegality of the proceeding is not directed at the domestic authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1006.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1010.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And consequently, the domestic remedies has not been exhausted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1010.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1017.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants suggested that there are no effective domestic remedies mixing the claimed rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1017.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1039.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the regularity of the proceedings, the court interim decision of 7 November 2014 and the decision of 28 January 2014 are the clearest indication that the courts cannot be considered ineffective as long they have decided in the favor of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1039.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1057.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has submitted evidence by the authority that such allegations were seriously dealt with, both in civil and criminal law, despite the fact that it is impossible to provide detailed data due to the manner in which the statistics are kept.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1060.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1068.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For each claim filed by the applicant, the court has expressed himself and five in their interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1068.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1084.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In no case, as far as this procedure is concerned, the applicant has sought any form of compensation for damages that may have been caused by the alleged unlawful activity of the administrative bodies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1084.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1109.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding similar cases in which the authorities have strictly enforced domestic court orders for the suspension of the administrative activities on the construction site until the conclusion of the review of the merit of the lawsuit fined by the party, NUCI refers to these decisions being addressed very seriously.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1109.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1123.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The administrative body has referred only to only one case in which the state employees are suspected of being found to be in violation of the security measures provided by the domestic court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1123.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1129.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, criminal proceeding has started for the criminal offense of abuse of power.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1129.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1134.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case is still pending under consideration between the domestic courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1134.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1141.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The prosecutor has also referred that such allegations are investigated very seriously and diligently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1141.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1155.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those domestic legislation authorities treat with the utmost seriousness the situation of violation of court orders going as far as the act contrary to these orders constituting even a criminal offense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1155.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1210.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the applicant's claims for the yellow crime scene tape, the issuing of the criminal proceeding against state officials for abuse of power, considering the regularity of the restitution process in respect of the applicant's property, and the declaration of the Deputy Minister of Transport regarding the construction, the applicant are suggesting that the surrounding of the building with the yellow tape, the commencement of the criminal proceeding related to the regularity of the process of the property restitution, and the statement of the Deputy Minister of Transport and Infrastructure on the building hence infringed their rights under Article 6, Paragraph 2, and Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1210.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1235.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does not become clear from their claims if they refer to the right of reputation as part of the right to private life and the presumption of innocence under Article 6, Paragraph 2, or tie this with the right of residence and are suggesting that the court extends the right to reputation to the building itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1235.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1256.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government states that the right to reputation cannot extend to the right to respect of a residence, and that the applicant had not shown any case law of the court in this regard, that there is in itself a right of reputation for the presumption of a construction as a legitimate, and that this right is protected by the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1256.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1273.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the authorities' action on the building cannot be related and extended if they infringe the applicant's private life and that the presumption of innocence under Article 6, Paragraph 2 implies in itself a presumption of legitimate property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1273.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1284.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The practice of the court so far has considered the violation of the presumption of innocence under Article 6, 2, also a violation of the right of reputation under Article 6.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1284.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1295.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this is primarily related to a subject, to a person, to a subject of law, and also related to a criminal case or criminal investigations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1295.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1305.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the government stated that there have been no inquiries, investigation, or criminal charges against the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1305.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1323.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The criminal case against the state civil servants, despite the fact that is related to the process of the restitution of the applicant property, does not provide them with the status of the victim, more so that the applicant are not the initial beneficiaries of this process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1323.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1326.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, there is a lack of casual link.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1326.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1335.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the government position is that the Article 6, Paragraph 2 is not applicable, and Article 8 is not applicable in this situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1335.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1353.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As for the question of exhausting of domestic remedies, it is the government opinion that they have not been fully exhausted because, in the government view, the action of the authorities toward the building property of the applicant should be considered related to the expropriation process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1353.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1365.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, even the domestic remedies which are necessary to be exhausted are in the defense of their property right, but do not constitute the expropriation process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1365.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1375.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But which also deal with the elements in defense of Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1375.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1399.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, with regard to the applicant's complaint due to the use of yellow colored tape to prevent their entry into their residence, it should first be noted that after the judgment of 7 November, 2013, the applicant themselves admitted that they were allowed to enter in the apartment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1399.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1410.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further to this, the domestic court, in their decision of 21 January, 2040, declared that the expectorate section of 3 November, 2013 as unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1410.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1421.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No compensation was claimed, although it could have been claimed in this procedure or even within a period of three years from the finding of violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1421.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1436.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, in any cases, if the reputation of the applicant has been violated, this right as part of the violation of the honor and dignity of the person can be remite through the compensation of damages in domestic level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1436.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1467.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the right to reputation or any other pecuniary or non-pecuniary damages are alleged to have been caused by the public authorities, such a lawsuit might be addressed to the domestic courts using the legal means for the compensation of the moral damages under the civil code, under the law on the liability of the damages of the public administration bodies, and under the law on the construction expectorate that also provides compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1467.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1479.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would like to recall at this point that those allegations addressed to the domestic courts regarding the yellow band have been recognized, but no compensation have been claimed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1479.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1488.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The criminal case initiated by the applicant has been abandoned by them after the decision of the prosecutor not to initiate proceeding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1488.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1514.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant agreed with the decision, not challenging it under Article 329 of the criminal procedure code, although they had the right to do that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1514.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1538.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the alleged interference with the applicant's right to respect for their home within the meaning of Article 8, and if that interference was in accordance with the law, the government is of the opinion that the issue of respect for the right of residence under Article 8.1 of the Convention</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1538.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1544.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>should be closely related to the examination of the case under Article 1, Protocol 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1544.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1563.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government reaffirms its position that the applicant's building was expropriated by decision of the Council of Ministers dated 27 of November 2013, person to the law, with the aim of building an infrastructure project those in the public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1563.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1571.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the government does not deem it necessary for the matter to be examined by the court under Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1571.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1584.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if the court is to review it under this article, the applicant deprivation for their apartment was conducted on the basis of well-defined legal framework.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1584.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1597.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the intervention has been defined in the law and has been necessary in democratic society while maintaining the balance between the right of the applicants and the broad public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1597.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1611.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government emphasized that the applicant's apartment were mainly summer homes, and the applicant did not carry too much burden related to the public interest in interfering with their rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1611.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1622.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The authorities do not have any information that any of the applicants have suffered any sort of housing problems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1622.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1635.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the domestic legislation, the right to housing is protected in the same manner as the right to property by the criminal and civil law, and the applicants have not raised any such claim under domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1635.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1643.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have only objected to the expropriation value, despite having available a whole range of remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1643.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1653.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the applicants have not exhausted domestic remedies available to them for the claims that they are addressing today to this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1657.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1684.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding their claims under Article 1, Protocol 1, while acknowledging that there has been an interference with the applicant's property right over the expropriation procedure, the government retains its position that there has been no interference in the applicant's right to peaceful enjoyment of property as a result of his demolition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1684.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1706.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The demolition property, the property demolished, was no longer owned by the applicant, who, as a consequence of the administrative act, the decision of the Council of Ministers dated 27 November 2013, lost any right over that property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1706.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1724.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The property was expropriated under the law 8561, dated 22 of December 1999, on expropriation and temporary use of the private property for public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1724.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1732.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicants did not contest this fact, the expropriation, but only the expropriation value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1732.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1742.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cause of the expropriation is provided in Article 8 of the law, letter C, it's an Albanian letter of the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1742.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1759.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 26 of the law provides for the invalidity of the expropriation in case of, but for the invalidity of the expropriation procedure in case of expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1759.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1777.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the compensation of the damages and also the procedure for regulation of the restitution of the property right if the expropriation is found invalid by the domestic court under this article.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1777.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1795.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant claim for the first time before this court that the expropriation was not legitimate or in the public interest, inter alia, because the government project was not clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1795.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1806.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And according to them, the government initially declared the interference in the interest of the environment and subsequently carried out a requalification of the area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1806.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1812.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, these two claims are not trustful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1812.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1829.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There have been, as the law requires, a project for the infrastructure intervention, which included also requalification of the area and intervention in the environment, mainly due to the problems of flooding in the area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1829.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1840.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, beyond the delays and difficulties in the implementation of the project is now apparent and almost completed and so effective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1840.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1845.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the most part of the project, it has come into use today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1845.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1855.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government retraits that the legitimate interest in expropriating the applicant was the realization of the infrastructure project.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1855.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1883.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While on 27 November 2013, the property was expropriated, was transferred, person to the law, to the Vlora municipality, which also requested the National Urbanistic Central Institute assistance in demolishing what was its property now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1883.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1897.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The legitimate interest of the Vlora municipality for the demolishing of the building was the enforcement of the obligation under the expropriation law and the respective decision of the Council of Ministers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1897.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1912.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Vlora municipality could not keep in its possession a building which property was transferred to it with the sole objective of demolishing and realization of the infrastructure project.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1912.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1918.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Vlora municipality was the subject requesting the expropriation under the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1918.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1935.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government retains the explanation given in the first question regarding the enforcement of the court decision of 7 November 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1935.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1956.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant intentionally seek to confuse the court by claiming that the decision in question implied an obligation to restrain from demolishing of the building, while no such obligation has been determined by enacting clause of this decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1960.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1979.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the domestic legislation, there are several laws and decisions of the Council of Ministers that are legal basis for the expropriation, which were seated in our submissions to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1979.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1991.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I'm not going to read them all, because I don't want to lose any time on sitting this decisions and laws.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1991.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1997.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we reiterate that the authorities' actions have been in accordance with the expropriation law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1997.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2008.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And however, the applicant had the opportunity under Article 26 of the law on the expropriation to declare this action invalid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2008.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2013.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But they have opted not to exercise that right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2013.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2031.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant claimed that they were temporarily unable to act because of the expropriation decision of the Council of Ministers was issued on 27 November, but was published only on 3 December 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2031.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2040.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Initially, we want to underline that the applicant's claim regarding their notification are contradictory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2040.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2043.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They say they didn't know about expropriation decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2043.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2053.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then they claim that on 29 November, Prime Minister publicly announced the infrastructure project of Lungomare.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2053.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2060.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then they refer to the publishing of the decision of Council of Ministers on 3 December.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2060.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2078.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the applicant's actions alone prove that if they had filed a claim before the domestic court and their claim would have been grounded, they have at their disposal all the time needed for its review and for it to be successful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2078.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2093.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their first request for issuing the order of 7 November 2013 was filed in the administrative court only on 4 November, three days before, according to the applicant's own declaration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2093.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2103.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it is clear, the court needed only three days to review the petition and hold the decision in favor of the applicant, suspending the action of the authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2103.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2138.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those for the decision of 27 November, date of issuing of the decision by the Council of Ministers, or 29 November, the date of the public statement of Prime Minister, or in the worst case, 3 December, when the decision of the Council of Ministers was published, until 8 December, when the building was demolished, the applicant had the opportunity to address the court to issue a suspension order on basis of urgency.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2138.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2157.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The simple fact is that the applicant had never been interested in challenging the expropriation procedure, since they have been fully aware that there would be an infrastructure construction that would constitute a fully legitimate expropriation cause.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2157.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2164.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, their request to domestic court was only to the expropriation value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2164.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2175.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were aware that even if the expropriation procedure were found to be irregular, the cause of the expropriation existed and could not disappear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2175.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2188.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants claimed that they have no chances, but their requirement for procedural irregularities would have been successful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2188.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2191.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we state that this is not true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2191.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2193.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The truth is quite different.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2193.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2202.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if the procedure was declared irregular by the domestic court, the cause of the expropriation existed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2202.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2211.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nothing could limit the authorities from repeating the proceeding in a valid manner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2211.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2216.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those, the invalidity of the proceeding, would simply delay the expropriation in time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2216.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2234.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this expropriation would take place one day, while the proposal of the applicant, whether in the domestic court or in the proceeding before this court, is to obtain the value they think is right as a reward for their property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2234.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2252.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For this reason, all these claims have never been raised to the domestic court, but are raised for the first time before this court to create a situation of alleged discrimination and irregularities in order to obtain the award as soon as possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2252.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2264.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government clarified that the expropriation price determined by decision of the Council of Ministers has not been claimed or even withdrawn by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2264.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2272.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even the price was at their disposal before the issuing of the decision of the Council of Ministers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2272.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2294.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The expropriation value was available to the applicant before the decision of the Council of Ministers issued and never had the applicant submitted a request for the withdrawal of the award, neither to present to the bank account number where the award would be transferred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2294.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2312.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The procedure for the transfer of the fund are provided in the Ministry of Finance guideline number 7, dated 7 May 2007, and are intended to guarantee that the expropriation award is paid to the expropriation subject.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2312.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2337.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While the court proceedings are under examination before the Supreme Court, the Civil Procedure Code established as an enforceable decision the decision of the Court of Appeal if its enforcement is not suspended by the Supreme Court under the examination by this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2337.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2344.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those until a final decision on the matter is held by the domestic authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2344.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2369.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We here want to reiterate that this court had decided in Julie Casin and other case law that the Supreme Court decision of the Albanian authorities is to be considered final for the exhausting of the domestic remedies and for the purpose of addressing this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2369.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2379.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decision of the Supreme Court is given in camera, meaning the decision for the suspending of the enforcement procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2379.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2400.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this decision is given in camera under Article 479 of the Civil Procedure Code, which provides the Supreme Court suspend the execution of the decision when the immediate execution of the decision would have serious and irreparable consequences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2400.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2410.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And these are the legal basis for the Supreme Court to have suspended the enforcement of the decision of the Court of Appeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2410.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2420.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the execution of the decision for the provision of compensation for expropriation, there has never been any problem at the domestic level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2420.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2424.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Decisions are executed as soon as they are issued.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2424.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2454.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, it is the applicant themselves who did not apply for the compensation granted by decision of the Council of Minister 26 November 2013 as amended by decision of Council of Minister 9 April 2014, which sets the amount of compensation and is the only enforceable decision at the domestic level for the time being.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2454.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2465.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court's decision to challenge the amount of compensation determined by the decision of Council of Minister is not yet final.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2465.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2478.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the event of a case of delay in execution, the applicants have the right to benefit from the default interest at the rate set by the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2478.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2508.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And regarding the other effective means they have at their disposal, we should mention the property rights claims, the claims for possession, the claims for protection under expropriation act, and protection under the law for the activity of inspectorates, which all provides not only for remedies, but also compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2508.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2528.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In each case, each and every one of these legislation reward compensation to subject that the rights are violated, and these are proven to be effective in the domestic level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2528.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2528.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2531.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2536.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. I call now Mr. Saccucci. You have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2540.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2543.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished judges of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2543.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2560.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the case under examination today raises grave concerns regarding respect for the fundamental standards of the European Convention and the overall effectiveness of judicial guarantees in Albania, both of which call for the most careful scrutiny by this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2560.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2587.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the gist of the present application is about the respondent government's troubling lack of regard for the rule of law and the principle of separation of powers, which are the cornerstones of the European democracies and essential preconditions for the enjoyment of human rights, as repeatedly highlighted in this court's case law most recently by the Green Chambers in Baca versus Hungary of 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2587.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2593.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The facts of this case and the applicant's multiple complaints should not be addressed in isolation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2593.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2629.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They should rather be framed in the context of a growing governmental interference in the administration of justice, which seriously undermines the independence of the judiciary and puts at risk the legal safeguards of human rights at the domestic level, a situation that has been clamorously denounced by the then Albanian Minister of Justice Ili Maniani in a public interview released on the 31st of January 2017, in which he expressed serious concerns at the government's systematic attempts to influence judicial decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2629.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2631.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, with your permission,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2631.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2641.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will first address question number one and question number three posed by the chamber concerning the applicant's complaint on the Article 6.1 with respect</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2641.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2652.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the authorities' failure to comply with the administrative court's interim injunction and on the Article 8 with respect to the destruction of their homes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2652.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2666.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will then briefly turn to question number two concerning the violation of Article 6, paragraph 2, and Article 8 with respect to the authorities' use of yellow crime scene tape to prevent access to the applicant's flats.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2666.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2668.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My distinguished colleague, Ms. Julia Bona,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2668.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2682.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>will then deal with question number four concerning the violation of the applicant's property rights protected by Article 1 of Protocol 1, and she will also briefly address the issue of just satisfaction on Article 41.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2682.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2689.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court is already familiar with the facts of the case, which have been set out in detail in our written submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2689.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2697.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before dealing with the substance of the applicant's complaints, I will therefore only spotlight the main events for ease of reference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2697.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2726.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Yon residence, complex in Yon, was built by Juvie Chargi and Jaffer Izoufi between 2010 and 2013 on the Vlora coastline on the basis of a valid builder permit issued by the municipality of Vlora on 17 August 2010, and in accordance with the conditions set forth therein and in the relevant domestic legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2726.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2733.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Yon residence was a beautiful seafront residence offering a wide range of facilities and direct access to the beach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2733.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2742.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Many of its flats were sold to private individuals, including the applicants, who furnished their homes and moved in with their belongings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2742.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2769.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Without any previous notice and without any formal administrative decision, on the 3rd of November 2013, officers of the National Urban Construction Inspectorate, supported by state police, seized the Yon residence on account of alleged irregularities and surrounded it with crime scene yellow tape, preventing the applicants from having access to their flats.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2769.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2776.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No explanation was given, let alone an official decision in support of the authorities' actions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2776.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2803.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 4th of November 2013, the applicants filed a complaint together with their request for urgent relief before the Administrative Court of Vlora, and on 7th November, the Court of Vlora issued an interim decision ordering the administrative authorities to refrain from any further action against the Yon residence, let alone its demolition, and to secure the applicants' right to peacefully enjoy their properties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2803.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2811.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This decision was appealed by the inspectorate, and a hearing was scheduled for 23rd December 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2811.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2820.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the meantime, however, the Council of Ministers adopted decision number 1015 on the 27th of November, ordering the expropriation of the Yon residence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2820.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2836.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The expropriation decision was not officially served on the applicants, but it was made public only on the 3rd of December by the press officer of the Minister of Interior, who announced that demolition of the building was going to commence the following day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2836.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2837.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so it was.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2837.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2848.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Between the 4th and the 14th of December, the entire residence was torn down with the extensive use of explosives, and a video of the demolition is available in the case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2848.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2869.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 26th of December 2013, then, the applicants challenged the expropriation decision before the Administrative Court of Law Act, which issued its judgment on the merits on the 6th of March 2014, finding that the expropriation was unlawful and that the applicants were entitled to compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2869.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2891.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, by decision number 210 of 9 April 2014, the Council of Ministers unilaterally cut down by more than 2 third the amount of compensation awarded by the Court of Law Act, which was already much lower than the actual market value of the building, as my colleague will further explain later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2891.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2904.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first instance judgment was later confirmed by the Court of Appeal on the 22nd of September 2014, and further challenged before the Supreme Court by both the state advocate and the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2904.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2916.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Supreme Court is yet to deliver its ruling, and notwithstanding the gravity of the situation and the repeated requests by the applicants, does not seem willing to move the case forward.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2916.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2932.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As of today, the applicants have not received any compensation for the not only unlawful, but also morally repugnant destruction of their rightfully owned properties, including movable assets and personal belongings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2932.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2952.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, they have no reasonable expectation of ever obtaining any form of financial redress, as the government has clearly shown no will to comply with the judgment of the administrative courts, and has not even paid the ludicrous amount awarded in its own decision of 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2952.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2955.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the case at hand is one of the most</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2955.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2976.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>astonishing examples of the recent practice of the Albanian authorities to demolish homes and businesses without legal process, or recourse for owners to receive adequate compensation, as reported in, for instance, the US State Department's Human Rights Report released in March 2017.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2976.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2996.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, coming to question number one, the responding government has not provided any meaningful response to this question, or any plausible justification for the domestic authorities' flattened disregard of the injunction order issued by the administrative court in 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2996.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3014.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is respectfully submitted that the respondents' contention that such decision was taken in violation of the law and was fictitious, as set out in paragraph 50 of their first round of observations, is so utterly preposterous that needs no authority to be refuted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3014.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3028.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same goes for the respondents' contradictory argument that the interim injunction did not, in fact, concern the demolition of the young residents, but only the conduct of the authorities prior to the decision of expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3028.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3047.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, by prohibiting any further action by any state administration against the young residents that could hinder the applicants' right to peaceful enjoyment of their properties, the administrative court's injunction clearly required that the building should not be demolished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3047.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3065.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, it should be noted that there is no public evidence of any demolition order ever being adopted by the municipality of Laura or served on the applicants who learned about the demolition when the demolition was about to start, and only through the press.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3065.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3082.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, the expropriation decision was in itself plainly unlawful, as established by the administrative courts in subsequent proceedings, and it was overtly aimed at circumventing the judicial injunction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3082.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3096.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourth, the Albanian authorities have in any event failed to comply with the injunction, as the applicants were not allowed unrestricted access to their properties following the seizure and the public announcement of demolition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3096.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3117.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fact of the matter is that the Albanian government arrogates to itself the power to disregard or obliterate any enforceable judicial decision that it considers wrong or simply undesirable, or even more troubling, to exert pressure on judges with the aim of securing the intended judicial outcome, as stated by the former Minister of Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3117.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3120.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court, this state of affairs</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3120.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3128.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is clearly reconcilable with the rule of law and the separation of powers, both of which lie at the very heart of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3128.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3143.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As this court has repeatedly pointed out, in a democratic society governed by such principles, it is not open to the executive branch to call into question a binding judicial decision or to prevent its execution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3143.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3150.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To hold the contrary would render illusory the right of access to a court guaranteed by Article 6.1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3150.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3156.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, starting from the grand chamber's judgment in Mikalef v. Marta, 2009, the court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3156.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3162.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>admitted that Article 6 requirements also apply to interim legal protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3162.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3174.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, the court has found in several cases that the state's organ failure to comply with an interim measure issued by a domestic court amounted to violation of Article 6.1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3174.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3183.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I refer in particular to Okyay and others versus Turkey and to Cuba versus Germany of 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3183.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3203.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case at hand, the Albanian authorities' deliberate defiance of the interim injunction and the monstrous demolition of the young residents in just a matter of days have unquestionably curtailed the essence of the applicant's right to access to a court by irreversibly frustrating their claims in the main proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3203.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3211.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of Okay, the court found a breach of Article 6 because of the Council of Ministers' failure to comply with an interim injunction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3211.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3214.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our Mr. President will respectfully submit</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3214.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3219.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that there is no reason for the court to depart from this conclusion in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3219.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3240.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As in Okay, the Albanian authorities' conduct was manifestly unlawful under domestic law, and it was tantamount to circumventing the judicial decision, a situation, and I quote from Okay, that adversely affects the principle of a law-based state founded on the rule of law and the principle of legal certainty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3240.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3267.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Respondent government's interference with the applicant's right of access has even continued in the subsequent judicial proceedings concerning the expropriation, when the Council of Ministers decided to cut down by two-thirds the amount of compensation awarded by the administrative court with the unconcealed intention of circumventing the latter's decision and frustrating again the applicant's quest for fair justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3267.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3273.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to question number three concerning the violation of the right to a home.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3273.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3282.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, I first underline that according to the criteria set out by this court's case law, especially in De Madres v. Turkey,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3282.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3288.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>there is no doubt that the young resident falls under the protection of Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3288.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3301.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Likewise, there is no doubt that the Albanian authorities' seizure of the building and its subsequent demolition do amount to an interference with the applicant's right to a home.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3301.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3317.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question then to be answered is therefore whether the interference was lawful, whether it pursued a legitimate aim, and ultimately whether it was proportionate to the aim pursued according to the requirements laid down in Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3317.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3345.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, my distinguished colleague will deal with these issues in great detail when addressing the complaint under Article 1, Protocol 1, and indeed the settled case law of this court has found that the unlawful and arbitrary demolition of a property in violation of Article 1, P1, automatically entails, and I quote, a breach of Article 8 by reason of the denial of the right of the applicant to respect for his home.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3345.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3352.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I refer in particular to Colonna v. Cyprus of 2007.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3352.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3362.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We respectfully submit that the responding government has manifestly failed to provide any convincing argument to justify the interference with the applicant's right to a home.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3362.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3379.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, it should be reiterated that both the seizure and the demolition of the young residents were carried out in this regard of all domestic provisions governing expropriation by means of a non-transparent, arbitrary and discriminatory process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3379.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3399.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The unlawfulness of the authorities' actions against the young residents has already been firmly established by the Administrative Court of Vlora in its judgment of 28 January 2014, as confirmed by the Court of Appeal on 6 May 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3399.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3431.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the demolition was executed in the absence of any formal decision by the Municipality of Vlora following the adoption of an expropriation order by the Council of Ministers, which was itself flawed by multiple substantive and procedural violations of the law, and even without any prior notification to the applicants, thereby depriving them of the most essential procedural safeguards and of any effective judicial protection against arbitrariness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3431.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3438.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Court concluded in Kalikova v. Azerbaijan of 2015,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3438.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3451.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the impugned interference was not based on the Court's decision or any other legal precept, and was thus not compatible with the rule of law in a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3451.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3462.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, I wish to point out that the interference in question, and particularly the demolition of the property, did not pursue any legitimate objective in the public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3462.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3471.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government's allegations on this point are contradictory and completely unsubstantiated, as my colleague Julia Bornyan will elucidate later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3471.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3485.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me just stress that the alleged purpose of requalification of the Vlora waterfront was clearly not a pressing social need that could justify the hasty demolition of the young residents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3485.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3491.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, the demolition of the applicant's home was not proportionate to the alleged aim pursued.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3491.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3527.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, leaving aside the issue of compensation, which will be addressed on Article 1b1, the facts of the case indisputably demonstrate that there was no compelling reason for which such an extreme measure and irreversible measure had to be carried out with such a husk, and in spite of the interim injunction issued by the Administrative Court, without even affording the applicants any real opportunity to participate in the decision-making process and to enjoy effective judicial protection of their Article 8 rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3527.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3542.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is all the more true, considering that, as the government conceded, the young residents was built in full conformity with the prescriptions of the building permit and that no violation of the law by the applicants was ever found.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3542.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3559.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As in the case Ivanova and Cherkessov v Bulgaria of 2016, the applicants were deprived of a proper judicial examination of proportionality of the intended demolition of their home, including, for instance, the existence of less severe measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3559.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3568.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, they received no compensation for the loss of their homes, personal belongings, nor is there any real prospect of this happening in the future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3568.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3583.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning very briefly to question number two, the applicants claim that the use of yellow tape by the police to prevent them having access to their homes amounted to a breach of a presumption of innocence and the right to reputation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3583.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3595.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The responding government contends that the use of yellow tape is a standard procedure which was not intended to identify the applicants as perpetrators of any criminal offence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3595.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3600.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is no excuse under Article 6 and Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3600.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3617.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Albeit allegedly unintended, the effect of the use of the crime scene tape and of the nationwide media coverage of the events was that of encouraging the public to consider the applicants as guilty of a criminal offence and to cause irreparable damage to their reputation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3617.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3623.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not our proposition that the use of yellow tape would be in general prohibited under the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3623.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3642.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rather, we maintain that in the specific circumstances of the present case, there was clearly no reason which could possibly justify such a procedure and that the resulting interference with the applicants' right to reputation attained the level of severity required to trigger the protection under Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3642.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3654.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, it should be stressed that the government has not indicated an illegal basis for the use of yellow tape and that the absence of a normative framework in this respect gives rise to possible arbitrariness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3654.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3665.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With your permission, I will now give the floor to my colleague, Giulio Bonia, and reserve some further comments for the second round, also in light of any additional matter that the distinguished judges may wish to raise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3665.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3665.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3668.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3670.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3670.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3671.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call now Mrs. Borgna.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3671.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3672.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3674.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3678.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3678.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3686.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with your permission, I will use the time at my disposal to elaborate on the applicant's complaint under Article 1 of Protocol 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3686.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3691.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As my distinguished colleague just explained, the facts of the case are indeed very straightforward.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3691.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3697.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were abruptly, arbitrarily, and unlawfully deprived of their property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3697.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3713.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, I wish to further stress a decisive point, namely that the young resident was a perfectly lawful building, contrary to what the Deputy Minister of Transport declared immediately after the issuing of the injunction order by the Court of Law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3713.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3716.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The constructing company had all the necessary permits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3716.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3721.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The residence was built in full conformity with the prescriptions of the building permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3721.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3728.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicants themselves bought their properties in good faith and in accordance with the relevant domestic legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3728.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3746.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in a country where the problem of illegal constructions is rife and yet unabated, the demolition of a perfectly legit building, such as a young residence, is truly baffling and all the more unreasonable, considering the fierce modalities under which it was carried out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3746.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3753.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That being said, the respondent government has not provided any plausible defense for the demolition of the applicant's property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3753.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3757.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, we sympathize with the representatives</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3757.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3759.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the respondent government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3759.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3773.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have been entrusted with an almost impossible task, that of providing a glimmer of legality to a chain of events which plainly stands outside any predictable, coherent, and lawful normative framework.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3773.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3776.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I shall divide my pleadings into the following parts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3776.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3783.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, I'm going to deal with the unlawfulness of the expropriation and the ensuing demolition of the young residence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3783.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3792.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, I shall move on to the absence of a legitimate objective in the public interest warranting the destruction of the applicant's property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3792.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3796.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, I shall deal with the lack of proportionality of the interference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3796.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3802.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, I shall make a few remarks on the applicant's claims for just satisfaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3802.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3814.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the first issue, it is our proposition that the interference with the applicant's property rights was not in accordance with the conditions provided for by law as required by Article 1P1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3814.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3830.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the expropriation was carried out in brazen disregard of law number 8561 of 1999 and of the Council of Ministers decision number 127 of 2000 governing expropriation procedures in Albania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3830.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3835.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Notably, no application for expropriation was submitted by the municipality of Vlora.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3835.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3839.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No preliminary assessment was carried out by the competent ministry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3839.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3847.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And no public notice of the planned expropriation was given, let alone a direct notification to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3847.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3852.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the mandatory time limits envisaged by the law were patently disregarded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3852.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3860.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the timing of the expropriation procedure in the case at hand is alone troublesome and extremely suspicious.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3860.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3868.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Usually, a lawful expropriation procedure requires, at the very least, from three to six months time to be fully accomplished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3868.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3871.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our case, it lasted only three days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3871.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3880.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These minimum procedural safeguards had been put in place by the domestic legislation precisely to prevent arbitrary deprivation of property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3880.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3886.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet, they were blatantly obliterated by the Albanian authorities in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3886.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3915.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As laid down by the court in a number of cases, for instance, in Capital Bank versus Bulgaria of 2005 and in Bekany versus Hungary of 2015, any interference with property rights, and I quote, must be accompanied by procedural guarantees affording to the individual or entity concerned a reasonable opportunity of presenting their case to the relevant authorities for the purpose of effectively challenging the measures complained of, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3915.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3936.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the instant case, the overt disregard of the procedural safeguards provided for by domestic law and the flagrant obliteration of an enforceable judicial injunction were precisely intended to prevent the applicants from effectively challenging the expropriation procedure and the ensuing demolition of the building.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3936.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3950.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under the court's well-established case law, the fact that the expropriation was not carried out in compliance with the conditions provided for by law would make it unnecessary to ascertain whether or not a fair balance was struck.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3950.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3964.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the applicants contend that the expropriation of the young residents did not pursue a genuine and compelling public interest, let alone one justifying the overnight destruction of their property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3964.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3976.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, the aim supposedly underlying the decision to expropriate and demolish the young residents is all but clear due to the ever-changing and contradictory positions of the Albanian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3976.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3981.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Initially, it was purposes of environmental rehabilitation of the coastline.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3981.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3986.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then it became purposes of public leisure and tourism.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3986.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3996.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its written pleadings, the government argued that the interference was aimed at, I quote, recovery and reconstruction of the marine front of the city.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3996.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4009.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Be that as it may, there is nothing in the available material or in the government's submissions to substantiate that any of these alleged aims existed at the time of the expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4009.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4011.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is quite the opposite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4011.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4021.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is undisputable that no requalification project had been adopted or even envisaged at that time in relation to that specific portion of coastline.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4021.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4030.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Vlora waterfront remained for several years a mere preposition and certainly did not reflect any pressing social need.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4030.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4038.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is compounded by the fact that no lawful building other than the young residents has yet been demolished in the surrounding area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4038.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4044.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that other buildings along the extensive Vlora coastline have been demolished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4044.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4057.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What the government, however, failed to mention is that those buildings were illegal, whereas the young residents was built in full compliance with domestic laws, permits, and regulations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4057.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4070.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the end of the day, the truth is that the authorities intended to target precisely the applicants building and that building alone by means of an unlawful, arbitrary, and discriminatory expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4070.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4080.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The dynamics of the events leading to the demolition of the young residents suggest that this was a premeditated act driven solely by reasons of political propaganda.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4080.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4103.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, it is also worth recalling that this court has recently stated in Volchkova and Mironov versus Russia of 2017 that the criteria relating to the public interest cannot, and I quote, be taken as a carte blanche for recourse to expropriation measures irrespective of their context, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4103.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4109.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With this in mind, I will now turn to the requirement of proportionality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4109.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4116.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The following three factors should be borne in mind by this court when assessing whether a fair balance has been struck.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4116.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4118.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, Mr. President, considering</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4118.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4134.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the building permit was issued in 2010, we are left to wonder what could possibly have changed in the turn of just a few years to justify an extreme measure such as the expropriation and immediate demolition of the young residents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4134.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4151.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The competent authorities should have exercised preventive control of construction to evaluate possible opposing interests well before issuing legitimate building permits, not arbitrarily change their mind immediately after the building was finished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4151.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4159.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This reason alone makes a demolition of the young residents an extreme measure, which falls foul of the principle of proportionality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4159.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4172.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the government has failed to show that the legitimate aim relied upon could not be fulfilled by measures less drastic than the hasty expropriation and demolition of the building.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4172.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4184.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, the disproportionate nature of the interference is corroborated by the fact that the applicants have not yet been paid any compensation for the unlawful demolition of their property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4184.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4199.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The bulk of this argument is eloquently summarized in the court's question on whether the authorities' failure to pay the applicants after three years of the demolition amounted in itself to an interference with their property rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4199.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4217.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, the court has repeatedly stated, for instance, in Jan and others versus Germany of 2005, the compensation terms, I quote, are material to the assessment whether the contested measure respects the requisite fair balance, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4217.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4222.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the instant case, the applicants have not received any compensation over the last four years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4222.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4238.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, not only has the Council of Ministers already unilaterally lowered the amount of compensation awarded by the domestic jurisdictions, but it persistently refuses to make any payment to the applicants in accordance with its own decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4238.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4246.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its questions for the hearing, the courts rightly asked why the authorities have not yet paid any compensation to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4246.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4252.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This question, we believe, is one which still has to be answered by the responding government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4252.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4279.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is perhaps superfluous to stress that the stay in the execution of the appeal judgment ordered on 15 January 2015 by the Supreme Court upon request of the government itself has nothing to do with the 2014 decision of the Council of Minister on Compensation, which is still fully enforced and yet, for unspecified reasons, remains unexecuted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4279.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4291.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, the court asked the parties whether, and I quote, the compensation as awarded by the authorities in 2013 as amended in 2014 was proportionate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4291.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4303.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This brings me to the last part of my pleadings, as the answer to this question is deeply intertwined with the applicants' claims for just satisfaction under Article 41.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4303.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4311.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The responding government forbore, in its written and oral submissions, from providing a response to this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4311.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4337.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has already made clear, for instance, in Guiso-Gallizai versus Italy of 2009, that the unlawfulness of a dispossession, I quote, inevitably affects the criteria to be used for determining the reparation owed by the responding government, since the pecuniary consequences of a lawful taking cannot be assimilated to those of an unlawful dispossession, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4337.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4353.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, given that in the instant case, restituzione integrum is impossible for obvious reasons, the applicants are entitled to a compensation corresponding, at the very least, to the full market value of the property at the date of expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4353.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4371.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, apart from the fact that not a single euro has yet been paid, the amount awarded by the Council of Ministers in 2014 is visibly disproportionate and inadequate to sufficiently mitigate the prejudicial consequences for the loss of the applicant's property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4371.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4384.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Per quota, this amount is approximately 2 thirds less than the amount for which the applicants purchased their flats, let alone the value of their property at the time of expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4384.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4396.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only admissible and reasonable criteria for calculating pecuniary damages is that of the full market value of the premises at the time of the unlawful expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4396.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4421.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, we wish to stress that given the particular circumstances of the case and the evidence submitted in the course of the proceedings, including the independent expert report attached to our observations of 3 May 2017, the question concerning the determination of the pecuniary damages to be awarded to the applicants under Article 41 is fully ready for decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4421.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4442.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is so on the basis of objective criteria, such as the extension of the expropriated property, the applicable inflation and interest rates, the market value of such property at the time of expropriation, and the additional interest accrued on loans, objective criteria that the government did not contend.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4442.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4459.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the court shall also award pecuniary damages for the loss of opportunities ensuing from the seizure and demolition of the property, as well as non-pecuniary damages for the severe moral suffering endured by the applicants as a consequence of the authorities' actions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4459.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4461.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4464.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4466.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much for your submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4466.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4473.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now invite the judges of the chamber wishing to do so to put their questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4473.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4473.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Eicke, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Tim Eicke</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4476.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4478.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4478.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4482.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have four questions, some of which come with sub-questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4482.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4486.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first is one of factual clarification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4486.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4503.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the respondent government submissions in paragraph 38, it is suggested that an appeal against decision 59 of the administrative court of Laura of the 28th of January 2014 is still pending before the Supreme Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4503.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4526.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can I just clarify, is my understanding right that in fact what is pending before the Supreme Court is only an appeal against the decision 269 of 2014 of the administrative court concerning the, and I quote, gross procedural violation, close quote, in the calculation of the compensation for the expropriation by the Council of Ministers?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4526.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4546.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, is it right that the appeal against decision 59 of 2014, declaring that the actions carried out by the state in November 2013 were illegal, was finally determined by a judgment of the administrative court of appeal of May 2016?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4546.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4550.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or in the alternative, did the government appeal against that judgment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4550.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4555.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, what is the status of that appeal?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4555.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4563.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if it is appealed, why was neither of these two appeals, i.e. that to the administrative court of appeal,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4563.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4571.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>nor that to a Supreme Court, if there is one, mentioned by the government in their submissions to this court?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4571.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4575.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question is one of clarification in relation to Albanian law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4575.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4576.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my question is this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4576.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4593.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Does the Albanian law or legislation provide for an effective measure, administrative or other, against the refusal by any party, including an administrative authority, to obey a court order?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4593.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4600.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, akin to the concept of contempt of court proceedings available in common law jurisdictions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4600.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4617.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, have any steps been taken against those responsible for noncompliance with the interim injunction first issued in November 2013?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4617.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4627.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third question relates to the events of the 3rd of November 2013, and is primarily directed at the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4627.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4628.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question is this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4628.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4642.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I understand that the purpose of the administrative action, as you call it in your pleadings of that day, was to check the regularity of the building permits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4642.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4664.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, is it normal practice, and if so, is it provided by law, that in order to check the regularity of a building permit, the building needs to be surrounded by crime scene tape, the administrative authority needs to be supported by police in order to carry out such a check?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4664.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4674.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, why would you say or would you say that that is proportionate in the circumstances of this case?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4674.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4681.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, again to the government, out of fairness, I probably have to ask you this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4681.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4697.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As you will know, Article 38 of the Convention and Articles 44A and 44C of the rules of court reflect some of the basic requirements for the conduct of a party before a court of law, including this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4697.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4720.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These include the duty to cooperate fully in the conduct of the proceedings, the duty to adduce relevant evidence or information, not only when requested, but of its own motion, and the obligation on the member states to furnish all necessary facilities to enable this court to examine the case fully and properly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4720.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4731.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The rules of court make clear, at the very least, noncompliance with these requirements allows this court to draw such inferences as it deems inappropriate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4731.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4780.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I noted in preparing for this hearing and during the oral submissions and the applicants positively assert that the government's submissions, in part, provided an incomplete picture of the factual circumstances of this case, and in particular, the domestic proceedings, and in part, so to say, were deliberately misleading, such as in relation to the outright denial, which you make in paragraphs 50 and 51 of your first written pleadings, that decision one of 2013 had, in fact, been appealed, and as we understand it, on a field being confirmed, only for the applicants to produce both the appeal filed, document 26, and the judgment of the Administrative Appeal Court of 2014 in relation to that appeal, document 28.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4780.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4781.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question is this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4781.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4801.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If this court were minded to consider whether the government has failed to comply with the obligations I identified at the beginning of this question, and whether, and if so, what inferences to draw from such noncompliance, what submissions not already made would you wish this court to take into account before drawing such inferences?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4801.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4801.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4804.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4805.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4805.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4806.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Bianku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ledi Bianku</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4809.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4810.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4810.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4818.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have three questions to the government, and then, with your permission, one to the applicants' representatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4818.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4834.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question, talking of the Supreme Court of Appeal, you assert that the applicants had access to the domestic courts and that their complaints were met, or at least examined, within reasonable time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4834.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4853.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How do you explain what appears to be a complete inactivity of the Supreme Court since its order suspending the execution of Judgment 269, 2014, of 15 January, 2015, more than two years ago?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4853.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4859.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You assert the complexity of the issues and a necessity to call different experts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4859.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4895.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How can that justify complete inactivity for more than two years, where there is no even any evidence of the court having ordered, instructed any experts so far, and where it took the Administrative Court of Appeal seven months to consider and decide the appeal against Judgment 3916-2014, despite the fact that it concerned the same issue and also, at least potentially, required the calling of different experts?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4895.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4911.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second question, as I understand it, Article 142, paragraph 3 of the Albanian Constitution provides that, I quote, state organs must execute judicial decision, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4911.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4927.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Would it be correct, therefore, for me to start from the position that, as a matter of national law, an interim order is binding on all state institutions, including the Council of Ministers?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4927.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4945.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You are asking us to conclude that an interim decision, 1 slash 2013, was taken, I quote, in open violation of the law and practice of the Supreme Court and the Constitutional Court, and turns out to be fictitious, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4945.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4958.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On what basis do you say this court, as an international court and compliant with the principle of subsidiarity, is competent to reach such a conclusion, essentially, of domestic law?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4958.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4968.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, did you raise this submission in the appeal against that decision to the Administrative Appeals Court or the Supreme Court?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4968.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4999.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it right, as the applicants suggest, that the government's appeal against the interim measure was discontinued by the Administrative Appeals Court in its decision of 20 January 2014 because the subject matter of the dispute had become academic, but that that court expressly confirmed the competence of the First Instance Court to have made the interim order and indicated its view that the breach of that order was unlawful?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5004.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5007.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5007.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5015.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can a decision by the Council of Ministers, de facto, amend a court decision in the Albanian legal system?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5015.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5033.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If not, could you explain what the legal impact of the Council of Ministers' decision of 9 April 2014 is on the merits of the lower Administrative Court decision of 6 March 2014, as far as the compensation amount is concerned?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5033.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5036.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the final question to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5036.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5041.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the yellow tape, what is your case before this court today?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5041.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5045.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are you dropping Article 6.2 claim,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5045.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5050.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and are you pleading the yellow tape issue only under Article 8?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5050.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5054.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, reputation limp, could you please elaborate on this point?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5054.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5054.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5058.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5060.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. Other colleagues? Judge Pardalos, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Kristina Pardalos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5062.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5068.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. I would like to ask the government just to clarify in a more detailed manner</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5068.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5074.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which were the measures taken against the police official that surrounded the building with the yellow tape.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5074.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5074.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was already addressed but if you can add some more detail. Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5081.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5083.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5083.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5084.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just Koskelo, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Pauliine Koskelo</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5086.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5089.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. I would have two questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5089.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5094.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first one concerns the question of the transfer of ownership.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5094.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5114.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has argued that the transfer of ownership of these properties took place immediately upon the...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5114.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5125.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and by virtue of the Council of Ministers' decision on expropriation on the 27th of November 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5125.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5159.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is how does the government reconcile this assertion with the fact that, according to our record, the Council of Ministers' decision, 2015 on the 27th of November provided for the expropriation to be performed within 30 days of the entry into force of this decision by the Council of Ministers?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5159.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5165.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question concerns the movable property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5165.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5181.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I understand it, there was a movable property belonging to the applicants which remained in the building and was also destroyed through the demolition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5181.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5201.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the statement of facts that we have, the expropriation order on the 27th of November by the Council of Ministers provided for expropriation of immovable property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5201.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5212.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it does not seem that the expropriation decision by the Council of Ministers covered any movable property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5212.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5229.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the question is, was there some other legal basis for the loss and destruction of the movable property that was situated in the building and that belonged to the applicants?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5229.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5229.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5231.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5233.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. Judge Harutyunyan, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Armen Harutyunyan</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5237.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5239.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5239.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5242.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question to government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5242.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5260.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in terms of compensation, as I understand, it is not your case, but in any way, Supreme Court could reduce the compensation payment due to the applicants below the level fixed by Council of Ministers decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5261.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5268.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can you explain why even this level of compensation has not yet been paid to applicants?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5268.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5269.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5275.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5280.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a last question in the prolongation of Judge Koskelo' question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5280.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5292.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my question is whether it is common practice that the administrative authorities inspect the legality of building and enter their premises without a specific order for that purpose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5292.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5297.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Does this constitute an interference with home under Article 8?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5297.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5304.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And is there an effective remedy against possible abuses in such cases?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5304.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5309.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, the applicant could also comment on this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5309.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5312.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I understand that there are no more questions at this stage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5312.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5321.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now withdraw for 30 minutes to give you the necessary time to prepare for answers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5321.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5329.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Follow which, the parties will be able to submit brief observations in reply to each other's submissions and in reply, of course, to the questions by the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5428.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5428.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5460.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5461.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5469.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5471.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5471.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5475.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I call now Mrs. Hicka from the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5475.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5475.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5482.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5490.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Un d doje fillimisht t jepja prgjigje pyetjeve t drejtuarangaj gjushtart e nderuar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5490.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5490.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dhemopas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5492.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5493.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just a moment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5504.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5505.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you can proceed now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5523.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5545.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sajta konqe shqyts vendimit nmr 59, dat 28 i pari 2014, N nmrria ka v n dispozicion t gjitha materialet q ka q jan pr cjel zyru s agjendit q veritar n momentin pr kats.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5545.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5560.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dhe sht n dispozicion t gjukats t vr n dispozicion gjydoj gjyq gjukata e t shmon relevante n dhnjen e vendimit edhe pas ksa i sant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5560.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5577.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>N kndvshtrimin e qeveriz dhe n pyete q ishim parashtruar, qshtja e vendimit 59, sajta kon faktve, nuk ka patu nd nj debat t madhmi dispalve.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5577.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5584.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Depati ka qn n interpretimin e vendimit dhe dhe riku a i shtrinta efektet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5584.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5611.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nga verifikimet q ne bm gjat pushimit, na rezulton e vrtet q vendimit 59 sht ankimuar dhe gjukata e apelit e kaln n fuqi kt vendim, dhe nj rekurs sht parashtruar n 4 pril 2017 n gjukatn e lart. Pra qshtja sht n shqyrtim n gjukatn e lart.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5611.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5621.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vendimit gjukatas apelit sht je ekzekutushm dhe nuk rezulton tjet pzulluar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5621.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5634.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>M gjithta t nse gjukata e gjen q ka nevoj t siarohat m tej n kt pik, do t krkonim mundsim pr ta konfirmuar kt m pas me shkrym.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5634.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5654.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Gjithashtu edhe vendimit pr ndryshimin e vlers s shpronsimit sht pzulluar n gjukatn e lart dhe kjo nuk ka qnd njr e diskutuar me dispalve.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5654.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5681.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>N tham q kjo qrshtjen nuk ka sht drituar n njr n form pjtsore konkrete dhe nuk ka qn objekt t diskutimi dhe shqyveria s ka patur as njher n nj shullim pr t penguar dhnjen informacionit apo pr t devijuar informacionin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5681.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5688.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>S n njr n lidhje me kt shkrym.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5688.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5715.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>S n refuzimit pr egzekutimin e masave t ndrmjetmet t gjukatos, qyveria ka qndrymin q vendimi i dats 7 n tor fillimisht u egzekutua dhe n rras se nuk do t ishte egzekutuar e i do t prbnd t vbr penale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5715.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5732.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kodi penale i Republiks s Shqypris parashikon nj vbr t posaq me penale pr mos egzekutimin e vendimeve gjyqsore apo pengimin e egzekutimi t vendimeve.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5732.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5769.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nj kohsisht qveria i ka qndru, dhe dhe shpreur n qndrymin e stajq, kohstatimi nga nga gjukatos n vendimin 59, dats 28 janar 2014, i paregulsive t vprimeve t inspektoratit n datn 3 n tor 2013, sht baz pr shprblimin e dmit n nivel vendas, nse do t ishte krkuar nga aplikantt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5769.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5771.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fakti q ndron q aplikantt nuk e ka n krkuar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5771.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5810.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sajta kon vprimeve q kan dour n 3 n tor 2014, pati disa prpytje, sidomos prrethimin me shiritin e verdhske n krimi, t cilat do doja ti adresoja bashk duke thn se gjukatat shqiptare, sht gjukatat e brndshme jan shprehur pr kt t t shshtja, duke konstatuar vprimet t kundraliqme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5810.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5826.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nuk mund t kt nj qndrim t ndryshm nga i gjukatave, por pozicioni i qeveris sht q kjo shkeljo riparrua n nivel t brndshme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5826.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5859.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prpysrththimi me shiritin e verdhske n krimi, par vrsiste, duhet d bjm e di e gjukatan q nuk ka qni qlim shm, e shken disponuar do nj shrit tjetr, gj q nuk ishfajson ato, pr s ri sht konstatuar i paregung n gjukata dhe i palishm gjdo vprimi dats trenn tr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5859.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5884.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pra ndaj, shveria kmungul dhe thot n qndrimin e saj q nse aplikantt do t ishin drejtuar gjukatave vndase pr vprime t tjera, ata kshin t gjitha mundsit pr n t sukceshm.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5884.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5920.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sajtakon gjukimit t qshtjes shprblimit t dhnjs t kompesimit n gjukatn e lart, pra qshtja krsore, fillimisht shveria dshiron t s qaloj se pat drejt aplikantt thon q gjukatt vndase e kan konstatuar shprblimit t palishm.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5921.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5939.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pr kundrazi, kj as nuk ka qn pies e krkess aplikantve drejtuar ktr e gjukatave.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5941.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5970.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nse ne lezojm vndimin e gjukats 269 t dats 6 mars 2014, dele qart q aplikantt q gjukat ka pranuar krkesn e aplikantve pr ndryshimin e vndimit t kshilit ministrave.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5970.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5981.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pra, vndimi i kshilit t ministrave thjesht sht ndryshuar nga gjukats Sajtakon t shmimit dhe si prfaqs s shpronsuar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5981.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5998.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vndimi i kshilit t ministrave nuk sht prekur nga gjukat at vnda se Sajtakon shpronsimit, legitimitetit t shpronsimit, sepse vet aplikantt nuk kan br nj krkes t tijl.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5999.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6012.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pra, gjukat at vnda se Sajtakon csht tjes legitimitetit t shpronsimit e kan l n fuqi vndimin e kshilit t ministrave dhe kan ndryshuar nga vetm t shmiminet t i. Kr ka qn objekti gjysar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6013.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6016.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nj loj ka vndosur dhe gjukat apelit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6017.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6026.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pra, ndaj qeveria kmgull q csht tja e shpronsimit t palishm para shtrohet pr her t par pr para ksa i gjukat.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6029.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6055.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nj kohsisht, aplikantt pretendojn ndryshi ose ndrhyrje n sistemi gjysor pr shkakt ndryshimit t vendimit t kshilit t ministrave t prilit duke i sugjeruar gjukats pr s rritur shum her n parshtresat e tyre q ky vendim ka ndryshuar vendimin e gjukats.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6057.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6061.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kjo sht haptazi e pa mshtetur.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6061.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6078.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>N q ofseletzojm vendimin e kshilit t ministrave, titulliti sht pr disa ndryshime dhe shtesa n vendimin 1510-27-11-2013 t kshilit t ministrave.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6079.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6082.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pra, kshilit t ministrave ka ndryshuar vendimin e vet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6082.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6095.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pse e ka br kt, ka gjetur q disa aplikante t tjer, m fajni disa subjekte prfituest t tjer mungonin dhe i ka shtuar ato n rruga administrative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6096.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6101.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nuk ishte asni pengez t abnte kt gj, sht nj praktik e zakonshme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6101.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6121.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Por kjo nuk ka asni lidhje me vendimin e prril, m fajni me vendimin e gjukatas administrative t shkalls pr vlor t marsit 2014, i cili ka ndryshuar qmimin n favor t aplikantve.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6121.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6133.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>T dya kto akte ka ndryshuar vendimin e 27 n torri 2013, se cila n mnurn e tyre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6133.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6145.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dhe nga gjukata ka rritur vlern pr aplikantt, Kshillit Ministrave ka br disa ndryshimet t tjer t diktuara nga procedurat administrative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6145.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6169.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Asni lidhje nuk ka nrmjet vendimit t Kshillit Ministrave t prrilit 2014 dhe vendimit gjysor, aq m pak q t ket n nj lidhje q ky vendim Kshillit Ministrash ka ullur kompensimin edhe nga gjukata.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6169.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6182.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kyo prmndet shpesher n mnur abusive pa t reguar se ku q ndron lidhja nrmjet kture dy akteve.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6182.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6217.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pra, jo vetm Kshillit Ministrave nuk ka ndrhyr n vrpryndarin e gjukatave, po pr kund razi gjukatat kan le n fqi vendimin baz t shpronsimit t 27 nntorit 2013, 2015, duke ndryshuar vetm t shmimin e ati vendimi, pra sa i takon qshtis t shpronsimit ose legitimimin t shpronsimit, a i vendim sht n fqi dhe asnjr nuk sht kndshtuar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6217.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6272.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>N lidhje me pr afatin e gjukimit n gjukatn e lart, dshiron t bj me di e gjukatn, q gjukat e lart, astu si q shkonstatuar dhe nga qshtjet tjera para ksa e gjukat, ka nj becklock e cila ka vshtirsuar punn e saj, q Republika Shqipriz, i thashtu bj me di e, sht duke ndrmar nj reform n sistemin e drejtsis, e cila prcakton dhe nj procedur pr veting t gjyshtarve dhe prokurorve, dhe t gjitha masat pr mern pr t adresuar problematikat e vonesave n gjukim, duke pr shir edhe ndryshime n kodin e procedurs civile.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6272.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6281.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pr shkak se asnjnga kto nuk sht br efektive n momenti q prflasim, nuk jan para shtruar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6281.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6293.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sajtakon egzekutimit t vendimit pr masn e sigurimit t dats 7.9.2013,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6293.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6304.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>e dhnkjo n kuadr t gjyshkimit t themelit e lidhur me vendimin 59.28.2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6304.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6316.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sigurisht q t gjitha vendimit gjysore jan t zbatushme dhe t gjitha autoritetetet shtetit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6316.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6331.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Por gjdo vendim gjysor krkon nga nj autoritet shtetror i caktuar t ndrmar apo jo hapa, duke lidhur sigurisht me paliqmrin e veprimvet ti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6331.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6344.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Qarta zi gjukata e administrative e shkalls prflor gjeti pa regulsit t veprimve t inspektorateve n dat 3.9.2013,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6344.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6350.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>dhe ajo urdhroj q kto inspektorate t mos kryenin as nj veprim tjetr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6350.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6362.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>N qeveria e shpjegoj dhe m par q fillimisht ndrtesa e aplikantve u konsiderua si nj ndrtim i paliqshm.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6362.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6374.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A shtu si gjvet aplikantt tregojn se ishin konsideruar dhe t gjitha ndrtesat e tjera n bregdet pram prons s tyre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6374.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6385.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madje, ndrtesa e aplikantve u prish e fundit, t gjitha ndrtesat e tjera u prishn me qllim implementimin e projektit n infrastruktur.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6385.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6391.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ato u konsiderua ndrtimet paliqshme dhe u prishn si pasasaj procedur.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6391.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6405.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Duke q ns ndrtesa aplikantve q nndrntn e nj pjes t konsiderushm mbi uj, inspektoratt prezumuan q kisht e pa regullsi n procedurat dhe e konsideruan fydimisht n ndrtim pa leje.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6405.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6414.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Aplikantt shprejn para e gjukats q ata ka nj leje t vlepshme ndrtimi nga bashkia vlar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6414.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6430.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Inspektorati nga to moment dhe si pas kompetenzave q ka, ndrhyri n kt zon sepse ajo sht zon me rndsi komtare.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6430.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6438.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pra leje t ndrtimit nuk je penat zon nga bashkia vlar, por nga kshilli komtari teritorit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6438.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6448.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nuk logarits drets, aplikantt mund t kishim leje n ndrtimit dhe nga bashkia e Strasbourgut, por kjo nuk do t thot q ishte e lichme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6448.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6474.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Me gjitha t, prsa ko gjukata administrative vendosin n dat 7 nntor 2013, q inspektoratt nuk duhet t ndrmrnin as nj veprim, nuk vrshduan me kt konsiderat, por nndrtesa u konsiderua e lichme dhe filluan procedurat e shprsimit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6474.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6480.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jan dy procedurat nndryshme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6480.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6502.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pr kto arsye, qeveria i qndron mendimit saj se nndryshme t rzvatuar nga t gjitha autoritetet kompetente pr at t q fuqi q kishte dhe pr aj sajo ka parashikuar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6502.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6523.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Interpretimi vendimi gjysor n kto rast i mass ssigurimi duhet br duke par dhe ledzuar vendimin e dats 7, dhe vendimin 59, cila t jan pall dhe cila sht kndra lishmria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6523.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6546.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Saj takon nndryshimi t vendimit t gjukats me vendimin e kshillit ministrave, un sht pje gova m lart q vendimi i kshillit ministrave nuk kan ndryshuar n asnj rat vendimin e gjukats. Pr kndra zi, vendimi i kshillit ministrave kan ndryshuar vendimin e vet,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6546.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6549.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>dhe ky sht i shkruar dhe n titullin e vendimit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6549.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6555.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dhe nuk kap s tjepet nj interpretim tjeter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6555.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6578.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>N lidhjeve masat q jan mrn dhe subjekteve q kan rrethuar godinon me shirritin e verdh, n datn 3. nntor 2013, nj kallzim penal sht ngritur nga aplikantt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6578.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6587.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pr kto kallzim penal sht vendosur mos fillimi i procedimit penal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6587.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6593.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pra nuk rezulton tjetmar ndojnj mas ndaj subjekteve.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6593.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6614.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sta i takon transferimit t pronsis, prcaktuar n vendimin e part t shpronsimit, nj mi e 15. dat njsht e 7. nntor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6614.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6624.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>N 2. t ti bjt fjal pr nj afat t rrithi editor, i cili sht nj afat maksimal,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6624.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6627.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>pra nuk mund t te kallohet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6627.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6636.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Por kjo nuk do t thot q transferimi nuk mund t bhet m par.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6636.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6675.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>N mnyr transferimit t drejts t pronsis, para shikojm nga ligj pr shpronsimet, n mnyr q subjekti q ka krkuar shpronsimin t filloi me ndrtimin e veprs pr interes publik, dhe sigurisht t shkatroj n kt ras, dhe mund t kt dhe rast t tjera ku nuk ka vnd pr shkatrim, pr shmbull nse do t shpronsohet njsi prfajt q t filloi nndrtimin nj rrug, atr s'ka qfar shkatrojat.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6675.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6689.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Por nse do ndrtoj nj rrug dhe aty gjendit nj shpi, sigurisht q ajo do t shkatrojhet pr t hapur vnd nndrtimin t rrugs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6689.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6709.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nga kon pretendimeve pr pasurit e luajtshme dhe kompensimin e tyre, qeveria i shndron shpjegimeve t saj q kto pretendime nuk jan ngritur n nivel t brndshm.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6709.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6725.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fillimisht, vet aplikantt t pranojn q pas dats 7 n nn tor 2013 n zbatim t urdrit t gjukatas administrative, ata jan lejuar t fute n banes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6725.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6745.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nga data 7 n nn tor 2013, dheri n dat 8 dhjetor 2014, ka patur nj apsir t konsiderushme kohore pr marjen e gjdo pasurie nse do t'ishte vlersuar e nevojshme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6745.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6772.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prve ksaj, qeveria i shndron objekcioneve t saj q, si do qoft, kto pretendime do e t'isht ngritur n nivel vndas, dhe q ishte pltsisht t mundur t adresoheshin nga gjukata t vndasa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6772.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6790.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ka patur praktik gjysore, por e dhe rastet t ndryshimit, si q dhe prmndm t nj aranshm t vendimit t kshedhit ministrave, pr t adresuar pretendimet t cilat nuk jan adresuar n vendimin e par.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6790.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6801.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Por e dhe rastet t ndryshimit t vendimit t kshedhit ministrave, ishte pikrisht pr sistemuar problematikat q mund kendalj m pas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6801.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6824.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sa i ta kompetjeve sepse nuk sht paguar kompesimi qofta i idhen me VKM, aplikant prgjigja nga Ministria pr kats sht se aplikantt nuk e kan krkuar asni her kt t qmim, asni krkes drejtuar autoriteteve, qoft t dhe prtsiel numrin e logarit bankare ku ata dshirojn t marrin parate tyre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6824.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6861.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>E dhe n ekzekutimin e nj vendimit t ksaj gjukatet t nderuar, sigurish n nivel vndas ka nj minimum procedurash q t garantohet q t qmimi po i paguhet subjektit i cilje ka kt t drejt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6861.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6876.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jo, sajta kom prgjithjave t ngriturangaj gjukata, ku jan br nj konsisht t dhe disa kndrshtime lidhur me prdendimet e aplikanve.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6876.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6891.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pr n nsht krve.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6891.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6894.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Qeveria nuk ka azgjt t jetr pr t shtuan e lidhe me kt cshtje.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6894.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6899.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ju falenderon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6899.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6903.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>M fal, edhe diqka t jetr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6903.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6915.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>N nj nj qeveris, prtendimet si pas njnit nj protokollin nj sajta kong kompensimit jan prematur.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6915.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6919.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ato jan duke ushqirtuar ende nga gjukatate brndshme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6919.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6933.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vlera e akorduar me vendim t kshidit ministrave ka n bit tre vite q sht n dispozicion t aplikandve n nj krheqr nga njtyre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6933.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6946.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Shtesa e Vlers nuk sht akorduar me vendim prfundimtar nga gjukatate nivelit t brndshme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6946.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6974.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kshtu q pretendimet si pas njnit nj protokollin nj dhe si domos pretendimet pr qsht satisfaction jan prematur dhe si domos t mbi vendosura, pasi qdo vendim marje q mund t mndmerte kjoj gjukat mbi kt qshtje, mund t bnde q t mbi vendosej me dhenjen edhe mshprblimit n nivel vndas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6974.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6980.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>N nj kshm t krhsht, nga nj nj njtyre, ne t mund t mbi vendosej me dhenjen pr mund t mndm.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sq</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6980.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6980.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fyndsht t bndshme nga t nj nj t mbi vendosej me t mbi vendosej me t mbi vendosej me t nj nj t mbi vendosej me t nj t t t prkshtitit t tjer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6988.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6992.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. I now call the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6992.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6992.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Borgna.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6996.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7000.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, with your permission, I will use this time to make a few remarks about</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7000.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7008.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>question number five, posed by the chamber concerning the right to an effective remedy guaranteed by Article 13.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7008.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7014.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in doing so, I will also respond to the Albanian government's objection of non-exhaustion of domestic remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7014.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7033.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question of whether the applicants had at their disposal an effective remedy as required by Article 13 is indeed closely intertwined with the question of whether there were accessible and effective remedies in the Albanian legal system for the purposes of Article 35, paragraph 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7033.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7053.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the courts' well-established case law, there is no obligation to have recourse to remedies which are inadequate or ineffective, and a remedy must be effective in practice as well as in law, in the sense that its exercise must not be unjustifiably hindered by the acts or omissions of the authorities of the respondent state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7053.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7060.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer in particular to Iatridis v. Greece of 1999 and to Mocano and others v. Romania</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7060.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7061.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7061.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7087.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as the complaint under Article 6, paragraph 1 is concerned, it is safe to say that by failing to comply with the injunction order of 7 November 2013, the Albanian authorities irreversibly deprived the applicants not only of their rightfully owned properties, but also of the opportunity of having the merits of their complaint effectively examined by a court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7087.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7093.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No ex-boss domestic remedy could ever put right this flagrant denial of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7093.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7104.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is in itself sufficient to find a violation of Article 13 in relation to Articles 8 and 1 of Protocol No. 1, and to respond to the government's objection of alleged non-exhaustion</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7104.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7106.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of domestic remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7106.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7115.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is in fact well established that the defiance of the injunction order deprived the applicants from any effective judicial protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7115.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7131.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, the applicants strongly argue that they cannot be required to wait for the outcome of the proceedings before the Supreme Court, as this is not an effective remedy for the purposes of Articles 13 and 35 for at least four reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7131.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7145.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the proceedings in question concerns only the amount of compensation due for the illawful expropriation, not the issue whether the demolition was in breach of the applicant's right to a home and to respect for their property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7145.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7155.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This proceeding will not lead to any acknowledgement of the violation or to any redress for the serious damages suffered as a consequence of the demolition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7155.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7167.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, it is worth recalling that an undue delay in domestic compensation proceedings may absolve the applicant from the duty to exhaust domestic remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7167.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7174.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Court stated, for instance, in Polanski v. Poland of 2009, it is its well-established</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7174.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7186.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>practice that in cases of a delay in payment of compensation, I quote, there is no need to wait until the relevant proceedings are terminated to lodge an application with the Court, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7186.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7200.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the instant case, the applicant's appeal is pending before the Supreme Court since 2014, and notwithstanding repeated requests for urgent disposal of the case, not even the first hearing has yet been scheduled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7200.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7211.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, this proceeding has no reasonable prospect of success within the meaning of this Court's settled case law, as expounded, for example, in Kodzacioglu v. Turkey of 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7211.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7225.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, even if the case were to move forward in the future, it is highly unlikely that the Supreme Court will uphold the applicant's appeal and compensate their loss at full market value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7225.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7232.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As my colleague explained earlier, the Albanian judicial system is currently subjected to intense political pressure and influence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7232.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7236.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is especially true for judges of the Supreme Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7236.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7241.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed political factors play a decisive role in their appointment and stay in office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7241.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7246.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Parliament approves their nomination and may remove them from office at any time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7246.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7267.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is no coincidence that most recently in its report on Albania of 2017, the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe urged the Albanian authorities to revise appointment procedures in respect of the judges of the Supreme Court with a view to reducing their vulnerability to political interference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7267.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7272.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, we strongly contend that the instant case could never be adjudicated fairly</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7272.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7275.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and impartially at the domestic level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7275.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7291.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We find it hard, if not impossible, to believe that the Supreme Court will rule against the government considering both the high political profile of the present case and the broader context of growing governmental interferences in the administration of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7291.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7301.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourthly, even if the applicant's appeal before the Supreme Court were to be successful, such a decision is doomed to remain unexecuted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7301.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7312.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we have already pointed out, the government has clearly shown no will of complying with judicial decisions concerning this matter, not even with its own decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7312.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7321.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally I would like to address a concern raised by the Albanian government in its pleadings of 3 May 2017.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7321.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7331.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government asks, and I quote, what will happen if these costs are awarded to the applicants by the domestic court system and by the European court at the same time?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7331.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7352.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would like to reassure the responding government by referring to this court's case law, according to which, I quote, by awarding amounts for damage at this stage, there is no risk that the applicants will receive the said dues twice, as the national jurisdictions would inevitably take note of this award when deciding the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7352.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7359.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We refer in particular to Frendo, Randon and others versus Malta of 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7359.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7362.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now give the floor to my distinguished colleague, Andrea Sacucci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7362.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7363.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7366.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7368.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7368.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7369.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Saccucci, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7374.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7376.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7376.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7388.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a few additional comments in response to the court's questions concerning the applicability of Article 6.2 and Article 8,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7388.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7394.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and also to the government's objection of non-exhaustion domestic remedies in relation to these complaints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7394.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7412.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the first issue, also in response to Judge Bianco's question, we respectfully submit that Article 6, paragraph 2, is applicable to the situation complained of, even if the applicants were not themselves charged with any criminal offense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7412.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7419.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the settled case law of the court, which is summarized in Nullan v. United Kingdom of 2013,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7419.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7426.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>presumption of innocence also applies when the person is no longer charged with a criminal offense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7426.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7440.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the conclusion must for sure be the same when the person is, in fact, treated as a suspected criminal offender by the police, although no criminal charge is leveled against him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7440.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7442.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any other interpretation of Article 6.2</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7442.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7449.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>would be at odds with its object and purpose, that is to avoid any unwarranted criminal stigmatization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7449.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7465.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has already had occasion to point to the risk of stigmatization, stemming from the fact that an individual who has never been charged with a criminal offense was nevertheless placed on record as a criminal offender.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7465.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7469.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Notably, in Asenmarper v. United Kingdom 2008,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7469.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7478.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Green Chamber stressed the threat which such practices represent to the principle of the presumption of innocence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7478.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7480.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But even assuming that Article 6.2 was not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7480.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7504.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>applicable in the present case, the applicants complained would, in any event, fall within the scope of Article 8, which also protects the right to one's reputation against any police activity or public officer's statement capable of stigmatizing the individual and having a major impact on his personal situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7504.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7508.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Notably, in Mikolajova v. Slovakia of 2011,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7508.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7517.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the court clearly stated that Article 8 may be relied upon when an individual's reputation has been damaged by the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7517.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7523.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For instance, through the communication of inaccurate or misleading information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7523.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7539.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the government's objection of non-exhaustion, it is respectfully submitted that the applicants had no effective domestic remedies at their disposal to complain about the violation of their convention rights, resulting from the use of the crime scene tape.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7539.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7555.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While the applicants have raised in substance this issue before the administrative court of Lora when challenging the seizure, it is not for that court to adjudicate on the applicant's allegation concerning the breach of the presumption of innocence or of their right to reputation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7555.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7567.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the government contended that the use of yellow crime tape by the police is a lawful standard practice, which is not subject to any specific requirement or normative regulation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7567.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7580.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, any other legal action by the applicants, for instance, a lawsuit for damages against the police based on the law of tort, would be inevitably bound to fail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7580.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7589.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I would like to give a short response also to some of the questions which were raised by the distinguished judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7589.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7603.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We cannot but share the concerns as to the failure of the responding governments to cooperate in good faith with the court by providing misleading or inaccurate information on the facts of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7603.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7612.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, we reiterate that the inspectorate has appealed the interim injunction order of 7 November.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7612.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7620.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The demolition was carried out before the hearing that was scheduled for the 23rd of December.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7620.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7634.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as a result, by a judgment of 20th January 2014, the administrative court of Lora declared an non-lieu as the subject matter of the dispute had ceased to exist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7634.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7649.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the inspectorate has appealed the judgment on the merits delivered by the administrative court of Lora on the 28th of January 2014, which had found that the actions of the authorities were unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7649.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7672.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The administrative court of appeal confirmed the first instance judgment on the 6th of May 2016, and an appeal with the Supreme Court has been lodged, as the government stated earlier, with the registry on the 4th of April 2017, which means almost one year later of the impugned decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7672.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7682.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, the government argued that the applicants have not been yet paid because they did not make a proper request in accordance with the relevant rules.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7682.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7691.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, as a matter of fact, we have here a request that was filed by Mr. Balanza and other applicants</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7691.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7704.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the 9th of December 2013, and which was registered in the protocol of the municipality of Lora on the 10th of December 2013 under number 1461.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7704.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7727.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 20th of January 2014, the municipality of Lora asked the applicants to produce a copy of the certificate of ownership accompanied by the map of the flats issued by the Office of Registration of Immovable Properties of Lora in the last 72 hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7727.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7749.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Appallingly, the Office of Registration refused to issue such certificates to the applicants on the ground that it was common knowledge that the building was meantime demolished and that they cannot issue an ownership certificate for a property that does not exist anymore.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7749.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7759.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourth, it is not true, as contended by the responding government, that the administrative courts have not assessed the lawfulness of the expropriation procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7759.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7775.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the contrary, the applicants have explicitly challenged the expropriation decision both on grounds of substantive and procedural violations, and I refer to page 24 to 28 of the lawsuit filed by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7775.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7784.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The administrative courts have explicitly acknowledged that the expropriation was completely invalid under domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7784.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7821.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to quote from the Court of Appeal judgment of 3 September 2014, where it is stated, page 18, and I quote, the court has analyzed the validity of the expropriation procedures, concluding that the respondent council of ministers and the other subjects involved in the procedure of expropriation have totally and categorically breached or disrespected the procedures provided for by law, and severely breaching the constitutional principle of just satisfaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7821.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7846.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, both courts have reiterated that there was no project produced by the government to justify the public interest, and that the expropriation decision was, and I quote, that destruction of the building soiree has been performed without respecting any notification terms provided by law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7846.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7854.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>About the undue delay of the proceedings before the Supreme Court, the government contends that this is due to the backlog of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7854.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7867.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, we respectfully note that according to the available information, the Supreme Court is currently disposing of cases introduced in 2016, and even in early 2017.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7867.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7880.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on the other hand, we note that the hurdles in timely dealing with incoming applications mainly due to the fact that some judges are still missing because of the lack of political agreement on their appointment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7880.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7887.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, I would like to draw the court's attention to the letter submitted by the government, together with its last submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7887.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7898.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a letter from the National Urban Construction Inspectorate asking for the support of the state police in order to carry out the demolition of the young residents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7898.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7905.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, this letter is dated 2nd of December, 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7905.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7912.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is one day before the expropriation decision has been made public and became enforceable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7912.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7919.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So according to this letter, the demolition should have started already from 8 AM of the 2nd of December.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7919.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7930.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this shows incontestably that the intention of the public authorities was that of demolishing the building, no matter how and irrespective of any judicial decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7930.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7931.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7931.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7931.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7934.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7936.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7936.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7939.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7939.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7945.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their submissions and answers to the Court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7945.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7949.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7949.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7952.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7952.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7957.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7957.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7957.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare this hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
