<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>1273810_13112013</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>21.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>22.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>71.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>79.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Jeunesse against the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>79.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>91.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case was lodged on the 1st of March, 2010, with the court under Article 34 of the Convention by Surinamese national Miss Meriam Margriet Jeunesse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>91.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>101.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to a chamber of the third section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>101.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>110.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was communicated to the government on the 10th of May, 2011, and declared partly admissible on the 4th of December, 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>110.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>121.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 14th of May, 2013, the chamber decided to relinquish jurisdiction in favor of the grand chamber, none of the parties having objected to the relinquishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>121.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>142.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 26th of August, 2013, the president of the grand chamber granted leave to the Immigration Council of Ireland and to Defense for Children International to submit written comments as a third party by virtue of Rule 44, Paragraph 3 of the rules of courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>142.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>166.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government, represented by their deputy agent, Miss Liselot Egmond of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, assisted by Miss Clarinda Coert of the Ministry of Security and Justice, and by Miss Loes Hansen and Miss Nicole Jansen of the Immigration and Naturalization Service Advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>166.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>176.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Miss Gerda Later, assisted by Mr. Albert Jan Eertink, and Miss Maria Inês Marchese,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>176.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>177.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>177.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>181.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>181.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>189.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties and the applicant in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>189.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>206.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome a delegation of judges from the Latvian Supreme Court, another group of visiting Latvian judges from city and regional courts, and a group of visiting trainee judges of the Serbian Judicial Academy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>206.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>216.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>216.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>222.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Miss Later for the applicant will speak first, and then Miss Egmond for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>222.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>239.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpretation between the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpretation to Serbian has been authorized for the benefit of a group from the Judicial Academy of Serbia, who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>239.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>252.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpretation has not been arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>252.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>252.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Miss Later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>258.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>270.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable Court, I first want to thank the Immigrant Council of Ireland and Defense for Children for their very important interventions in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>270.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>281.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their interventions make clear to our opinion what is missing in the policy in the Netherlands and in the arguments of the government in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>281.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>284.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Jornet, here present, was born on 19 October,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>284.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>295.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>1967 in Suriname as a Dutch citizen with a Dutch nationality since Suriname was a Dutch colony.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>295.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>304.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After the takeover in 75, the persons born in Suriname were in the Netherlands kept their Dutch nationality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>304.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>309.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The persons being in Suriname lost their Dutch nationality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>309.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>313.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant stayed in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>313.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>319.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 87, she met her husband, now husband, Mr. Walden.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>319.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>331.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And shortly after that, they stayed together very often in the house of her mother, who was seriously ill, and in the house of his grandfather.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>331.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>335.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After Mrs. Jornet's mother died in 89,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>335.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>339.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>she moved to his grandfather's house.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>339.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>347.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They both applied in 91 for a holiday visa for the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>347.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>350.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Walden's application was granted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>350.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>354.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Jornet's application was denied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>354.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>357.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Walden left on 19 October, 91,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>357.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>360.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to his Dutch father in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>360.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>366.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And he regained his Dutch nationality in 93.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>366.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>372.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Jornet stayed with his grandfather until he died</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>372.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>381.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and stayed with his family until finally a visa was granted in 97.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>381.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>384.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 25 June, 99, they married.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>384.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>399.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in the years following, as you know, three Dutch sons were born, age at this moment, as is known, 13, nearly eight, and nearly three.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>399.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>413.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 97, a foreigner in the Netherlands could receive a residence permit without a professional resident visa if all the conditions were met.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>413.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>418.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Mr. Walden was working for an agency since 93</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>418.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>423.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and had enough income to cover the cost of living for them both.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>423.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>426.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, at that time, both parties were not married.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>426.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>438.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And since their relationship started in 87, it could be considered a steady relationship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>438.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>447.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no criminal background, and the house they lived in was according to the rules at that time for a residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>447.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>460.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if in 97 the ministry had considered the application on the merits, there was no reason not to grant a residence permission then.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>460.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>467.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since 20 October, 97, Mrs. Jornet is trying to receive a residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>467.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>472.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This can be seen from the document from the town hall of registration of the Hague.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>472.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>497.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She has been registered in that administration since 20 October, 97, first living in her first house in Rotterdam and later on since 20 July, 98, during five months in the first house in the Hague, and since 17 December, 98, in the house where she has been living since.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>497.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>506.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You can see that every document shows this address, salary slips, school papers, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>506.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>520.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government repeats itself in the memorial of 2 August concerning the facts, also that part of the facts that cannot follow from the file and have been clarified before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>520.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>525.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in a reply of 5 February, 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>525.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>531.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Jornet has not requested a residence permit for work,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>531.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>543.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>but to stay with her partner, who she knew since 87, as can be seen in the court judgments and even in the different decisions from the ministry itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>543.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>550.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In every procedure, the family life with her husband and children was the item.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>550.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>558.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Contrary to the statement of the government, the only issue was the provisional residence visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>558.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>578.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since our new Aliens Act 2000, effective since 1 March 2001, there had to be clear that the reasons not to need a provisional residence permit in this kind of cases had to be found in exceptional hardship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>578.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>604.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But at this moment, Article 8 of the Convention might as well be a reason not to require a professional residence visa, since the rules have been changed after your court decided, inter alia, in the Rodriguez da Silva case, the way of deciding in these kind of cases was excessive, formalistic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>604.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>613.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to decide on that exemption, there has to be a full review on Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>613.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>626.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Dutch jurisprudence, the ministry has to argue now whether or not Article 8 of the Convention is applicable concerning the professional residence visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>626.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>635.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If Article 8 is not applicable, then the exceptional hardship still has to be considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>635.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>643.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A professional residence visa that was not required in 97, when the former Dutch Mrs. Jonesse</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>643.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>652.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>started her battle to be allowed to stay in the Netherlands with her Dutch husband and her Dutch children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>652.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>659.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government argues decisions have been made within a reasonable time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>659.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>666.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant has already replied on the 5th of February, 2012, paragraph 2.8,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>666.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>673.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and in the memorial of 5 August, paragraph 4, there was not decided within a reasonable time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>673.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>678.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there were no attempts to extradite her since 97.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>678.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>700.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides the repeating of partly wrong facts, the government is focusing on the leave of a nearly complete Dutch family to outside the EU without having in mind any rights in international law or humanitarian law these individuals obtain.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>700.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>705.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I want to cite Article 13 of our Aliens Act 2000.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>705.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>722.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A request for a residence permit will only be granted in case of international obligations, in case the presence of the applicant is essential in the Netherlands, or in the event of compelling humanitarian reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>722.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>728.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Words that seem to have no impact on a policy that is used.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>728.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>738.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Looking at the response of the government in the memorial, it cannot be seen that there is any balancing of interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>738.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>758.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What should have been given in 97 is still denied in 2013 without considering what this means for the Dutch husband and the three Dutch children, who have to be able also to rely on the government to take care of their interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>761.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>770.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You had a question your court asked about the exemption of exceptional hardship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>770.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>779.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You asked from the government how often that is granted in practice, for example, in the last five years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>779.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>782.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government cannot answer the question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>782.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>788.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I can tell you, from every decision, there exists a minute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>788.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>795.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these minutes can be seen how often the exemption is granted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>795.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>799.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When you get to the decision where nothing is happening, it's one page.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>799.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>802.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You get a residence permission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>802.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>806.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in that kind of cases, there is this minute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>806.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>825.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government mentions four very severe cases, but lesser severe cases exist when no professional residence visa is required, often since the change of law because of Article 8 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>825.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>827.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I can give you a few examples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>827.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>840.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A Surinamese lady with a Dutch child, born 13 May 2010, is extradited and re-enters with a short visa for visit in 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>840.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>844.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not with a professional residence visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>844.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>855.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She applies for a residence permit in 2012 with Dutch child, which application is granted without a professional residence visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>855.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>861.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The father, Dutch, but Surinamese origin, works, pays alimony.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>861.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>866.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is a joint custody and are visiting rights with the child living with the mother.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>866.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>869.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it looks like the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>869.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>872.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the next one, it's the neighbor of my client.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>872.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>873.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She comes from Ghana.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>873.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>880.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She has two children, born 29 June 2001 and 15 April 2007.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>880.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>887.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And she has a partner who has also the Ghanese nationality, and he has a residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>887.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>891.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She has medical problems, but they can be treated in Ghana.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>891.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>901.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, she receives a residence permit without professional residence visa to stay with her eldest son.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>901.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>913.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the third one, a man born in 20 February in 79 from Sierra Leone had asylum, but that was withdrawn because of changed policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>913.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>917.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Final decision 10 February 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>917.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>920.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He married a Dutch.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>920.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>922.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is not right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>922.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>925.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yeah, he married a Dutch lady from Sierra Leone origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>925.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>931.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More than two years later on 15 July 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>931.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>943.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then he applied for a residence permission, which was given without a professional residence visa on 11 September 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>943.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>951.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these three examples, no professional residence visa was required because of Article 8 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>951.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>958.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these three examples, there was not said that the family life could take place in the country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>958.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>960.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why not?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>960.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>966.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Often, a decision is made and no professional residence visa is asked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>966.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>969.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No one argues why not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>969.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>980.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If Article 8 is involved, a positive decision on Article 8 is given without making the problems, as in the case of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>980.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>986.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yeah, then the legal issues, Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>986.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>993.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, we are happy that the government agrees that the applicant has a family life, paragraph 49.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>993.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1019.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But according to paragraph 61 of the memorial, the family can settle in Suriname since this family is no broken family, since there are no special educational health issues, and since the fact of being born and grown up in the Netherlands, of having the Dutch nationality is insufficient exceptional.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1019.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1023.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why would the decision in Antwerp versus Norway be applicable here?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1023.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1029.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Wasn't there the criminal behavior of the applicant important?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1029.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1031.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The use of a false identity?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1031.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1033.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were married in Ghana.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1033.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1038.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Jones has always been clear about her identity,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1038.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1041.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and besides, she is a former Dutch citizen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1041.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1045.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Her children have no ties with her country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1045.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1048.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They've never been there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1048.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1052.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The extended family lives in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1052.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1065.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, there are five persons involved, four persons of Dutch nationality, one person of former Dutch nationality, and present Surinamese nationality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1065.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1074.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These four Dutch citizens have a family and private life, according to article 8 as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1074.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1079.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In article 8, paragraph 2, I like to say it here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1079.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1112.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There shall be no interference by a public authority with the exercise of this right, except such as is in accordance with the law and is necessary in a democratic society in the interest of national security, public safety, or the economic well-being of the country, for the prevention of disorder or crime, for the protection of health or morals, or for the protections of the rights and freedoms of others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1112.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1120.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nowhere in the arguments of the government is seen any reference to these important rules.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1120.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1133.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why should a Dutch father with his three Dutch sons leave the country because the government is not willing to grant her a residence permit for 16 years?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1133.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1141.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why should a 13-year-old boy leave his school and his friends because of unclear arguments of the government?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1141.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1154.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why should a seven-year-old boy at school in a special class because he is reading at the level of a 12-year-old leave his school, his friends, his swimming lessons?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1154.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1160.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And why should a nearly three-year-old leave his preschool with his first friends?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1160.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1172.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why should these children born in the Netherlands, grown in the Netherlands, leave their country because their government is not there for them?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1172.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1178.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Research has been done about the effects of the treatment by the government of their mother.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1178.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1191.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The child's best interest did not work for them, was not used for them, when the police broke the front door and took their mother and themselves to the police custody.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1191.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1197.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Trauma should not be brought to children by the government and its organs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1197.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1206.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Children should be protected by their government, a necessity according to the Convention on the Rights of the Child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1206.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1216.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, as the Immigrant Council of Ireland writes, sub 2.3, Article 3, Protocol 4 of the Convention</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1216.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1221.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>prohibits the expulsion and exclusion of all nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1221.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1253.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they say it should also be taken into consideration in case a citizen of a state is not expelled by the state, but is confronted with a stark choice between constructive exile by effectively being forced to leave his or her own state to be with his or her family members, or foregoing family life with non-national family members, including spouse and children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1253.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1271.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has to be taken in consideration as well that it concerns here a former Dutch citizen who is 16 years in the Netherlands, who has a Dutch husband and three Dutch children with no ties in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1271.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1283.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet the Immigrant Council of Ireland argues that in accordance with the law in Article 8 of the Convention is also in accordance with the European law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1283.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1286.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case O.S. and L., both the Court of Justice</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1286.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1298.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the Advocate General asserted the importance of the dependency of the minor EU citizen on a third country national seeking residence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1298.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1308.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, the Finnish children were not legally or financially or emotionally dependent of their stepfathers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1308.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1316.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were dependent on their mothers, who were their custodians and who had a permanent residency in Finland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1316.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1340.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the failure to grant residence permits to the stepfathers would not have compelled the Union to grant a residence permit to the youngest child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1340.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1374.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The youngest child would have to leave the territory of the Union and would be unable to exercise the substance of the rights conferred by his European citizenship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1374.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1389.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Refusing a residence permit to the applicant would therefore constitute an interference that is not in accordance with the law within the meaning of Article 8 paragraph 2 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1389.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1434.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the applicant shares the view that a third-party intervention by Immigration Council of Ireland that simply require a family predominantly composed of European EU citizens to relocate to a territory elsewhere or outside the EU without giving due considerations to the interests involved could be disproportional and would not meet the test articulated in Zambrano and De Regi of giving effective legal protection to minor EU citizens rights enshrined in Article 20 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1434.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1441.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then if the father would join to Suriname, when would anybody be able to return?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1441.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1444.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There will be no income in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1444.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1451.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So how can the children exercise their EU rights?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1451.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1478.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties memorial should deal in particular with the question, as you quite formulated it, what weight is to be given to the best interest of the applicant's children in assessing whether the refusal to grant the applicant a residence permit and her consequential removal is proportionate for the purpose of Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1478.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1496.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addressing the question, what weight should be given to the best interest of the children, the applicant has referred to the landmark judgment of your grand chamber in the case of Neulingen and Sjoerhoek concerning the best interest of the child principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1496.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1513.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this judgment, the grand chamber noted that there is currently a broad consensus, including in international law, in support of the idea that in all decisions concerning children, their best interest must be paramount.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1513.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1518.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Your grand chamber noted that a child's interest comprises two limbs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1518.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1525.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we refer to paragraph 136 and 138.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1525.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1541.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, that a child's ties with its family must be maintained and to ensure its development in a sound environment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1541.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1575.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As was rightly observed in the third party intervention of Defense for Children, the method for determining the best interest of the child combines two of the four essential general principles of the Convention on the Rights of the Child, namely, Article III, best interest of the child shall be a primary consideration in all actions concerning children, and paragraph 6-2, Article 6-2, the rights to development.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1575.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1594.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As appears from the judgment in Neulingen and Sjoerhoek and from the general command number 14 of the Committee on the Rights of the Children, the best interest of the children must be assessed on a case-by-case basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1594.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1600.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The concept of the child's best interest is flexible and adaptable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1600.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1618.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be adjusted and defined on an individual basis according to the specific situation of the child or children concerned, taking into account their personal context, situation, and needs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1618.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1630.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For individual decisions, the child's best interest must be assessed and determined in the light of the specific circumstances of the particular child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1630.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1643.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the interest of the applicant's children, not only their interest is preserving their family unit and their ties with both their parents, but also their right to private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1643.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1654.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And their interests, from a personal development perspective, should be addressed and be given due consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1654.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1661.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is particularly true with regard to the applicant's 13-year-old son, Jesse J. Romeo,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1661.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1665.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and a nearly eight-year-old son, Joshua Max.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1665.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1670.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We refer to the decision in the case Plaza versus Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1670.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1689.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As children mature and become, with the passage of time, able to formulate their own opinions, the courts should give due weight also to their views and feelings as well as to their rights to respect for their family life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1689.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1693.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or Osman versus Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1693.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1706.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, in respecting parental rights, the authorities cannot ignore a child's interest, including its own rights to respect to private and family life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1706.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1717.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant has put forward an expert report from Professor Carl Verboer and her research group of the University of Groningen, as you know.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1717.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1733.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This report contains a full assessment of the best interest of the applicant's children, based on the so-called best interest of the child model.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1733.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1747.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As appears from the third party intervention of Defense for Children, this model connects the rights from Article 3 and Article 6 of the Convention on the Rights of the Child to each other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1747.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1758.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With this model, it's possible to analyze the best interest of the child in the light of his or her development perspective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1758.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1775.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this particular case, the government has not made a full assessment of the best interests of the applicant's children, in accordance with Neulingen-Schuruch and a general command number 14, as mentioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1775.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1791.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is disturbing to note that the government, in her memorial, paragraph 58, does not acknowledge the roots and links of Dutch children to the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1791.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1803.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the more inappropriate, since the children's Dutch nationality and their relationship to the Dutch society is part of their identity and their private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1808.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1818.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the government has not granted primary consideration to the best interest of the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1818.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1830.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From paragraph 58 and further in the memorial, it appears that the state has given paramount consideration to its own interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1830.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1838.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government holds that there is no objective impediment to exercise a shared family life in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1838.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1844.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government further holds that the children are of an adaptable age.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1844.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1858.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These considerations, however, cannot be accepted, nor be decisive, without a full and balanced assessment of the relevant interests involved in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1858.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1866.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if the whole family should leave for Suriname, what perspectives are waiting for the children?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1866.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1872.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No home, no job anymore for their father, no income.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1872.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1876.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only debts remain.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1876.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1882.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Deterioration of the quality of their education, as Carl Verboer writes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1882.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1889.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Separation from family and friends in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1889.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1904.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As has been stated before, a refusal of a residence permit to the applicant would inevitably lead to a separation between the children and one of their parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1904.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1924.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regard to the question as to what weight should be given to the best interest of the children, it's important to realize that the applicant has been in contact with the ministry through their procedures since 1997, all the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1924.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1931.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Has been registered in the town hall administration as well, all the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1931.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1945.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not before 2010 that the ministry started exedution procedures, 13 years after starting her procedures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1945.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1959.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Like in the Nunez case, paragraph 82, it does not appear that the government fulfilled the interests of swiftness and efficiency of immigration control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1959.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1980.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or in the Butt case, paragraph 85, it was questionable whether general immigration policy considerations would carry sufficient weight to regard the refusal of residence necessary in a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1983.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1992.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant also wishes to refer to the circumstances mentioned under paragraph 10 of her memorial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1992.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2000.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, children cannot be held responsible for choices made by their parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2000.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2012.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rooting in the Netherlands, eight, Jesse J is 13 years old, his brother, Ashun Max, nearly eight, and their Dutch citizenship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2012.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2021.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There has to be a conservation about their European Union citizenships and their rights under the European Union law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2021.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2042.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourth, a fact of the threat of living separated from the mother, and the shocking, stressful, and possibly even traumatic experiences because of the police raiding their home and arresting their mother.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2045.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2061.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Far-reaching and dramatic consequences for the children's personal development, their education, and their future perspectives, their private life, and well-being in the case of extradition of their mother.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2061.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2070.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then the inactivity of the government during the procedures that took so many years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2070.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2079.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant has, unlike of the cases, Antwi Nunez Avelo Aponte, no criminal records.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2079.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2083.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicant's husband cannot join to Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2086.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2094.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is furthermore sufficient income, and Mr. Walden has to stay in the Netherlands to provide.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2094.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2101.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The residence permit in 97 would have not been a problem if considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2105.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2127.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>References further made to paragraph eight and nine of the applicant's memorial of August on the principle of the best interest of the child, and the convention on the rights of the child, especially the general comment number 14 on the best interest taken as a primary consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2127.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2134.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As is said above, why would the decision of Antwi versus Norway be applicable here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2135.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2137.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Excuse me, your time has already expired.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2137.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2138.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I ask you to conclude?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2138.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2140.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Okay. I have one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2140.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2142.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm so sorry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2142.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2154.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, without a full assessment and fair balancing of all interests, the refusal cannot be considered as necessary in a democratic society. The government did not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2154.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2159.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>make a full assessment. And nowhere becomes clear why the interest of the State</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2159.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2170.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>outweighs the rights of the applicant's children and their parents, in this case under these various exceptional circumstances. It cannot be said there is a fair</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2170.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2175.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>balance that has been struck. In the applicant's view, the outcome is not proportional</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2175.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2191.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and not necessary within the meaning of Article 8, paragraph 2 of the Convention, completely not according to the best interests of the children, which should be a primary consideration according to Article 3. And as in the Rodriguez-LaSilva case, if considered,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2191.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2195.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a residence permission would have been granted in 1997.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2195.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2211.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is necessary to make a full assessment of all the circumstances and interests involved, especially those of the children. And it is necessary to observe also the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2211.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2223.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>other conditions for a residence permit, if you want to use a formality to interfere with the right under Article 8 of the Convention. Not to do so is, to our opinion,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2223.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2228.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>excessive formalistic. If we look at the cases mentioned above and also the other</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2228.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2246.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>cases mentioned in the answers of the question of your Court of 5 August, it cannot be seen that only in cases with exceptional circumstances a professional residence permission visa is not required. And even if that would be true, the case</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2246.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2250.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Mrs. Genest shows very exceptional circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2254.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2256.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Miss Later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2256.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2258.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Miss Egmond.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2262.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2266.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2266.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2271.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was the decision by the Dutch authorities to refuse Mrs. Schoeness's residence permit</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2271.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2276.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because she did not comply with the requirements in accordance with Article 8?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2276.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2286.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the question to be answered in this case, and the government of the Netherlands strongly believes that the answer to this question should be affirmative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2286.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2296.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I will not repeat all the facts and observations that were already submitted to your court in the government's memorial of the 2nd of August, 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2296.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2306.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, I would like to draw your attention to a few points which, in the context of this specific case, we believe should be highlighted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2306.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2311.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, allow me to begin with a few words on the facts of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2311.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2325.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I will then outline the framework for assessing the competing interests and demonstrate why, in the present case, the interests of the community as a whole should take precedence over the individual interests of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2325.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2331.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will also explain what weight we believe should be given to the best interest of the applicant's children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2335.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2346.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in assessing whether the refusal to grant the applicant a residence permit and her subsequent removal is proportionate for the purposes of Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2346.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2360.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this context, I would also like to make a few remarks about the report of Professor Golvorboor, which, due to its late submission by the applicant, we could not comment on at an earlier stage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2360.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2376.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, I will go into the issue of protection of union citizens under Article 20 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union and any derivative rights for third country nationals under that article.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2376.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2384.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, I will conclude with some remarks in regards to the claim for compensation made by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2384.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2386.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, what is the present case about?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2386.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2389.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant and her husband, Mr. Walden,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2389.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2391.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>are born and raised in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2391.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2396.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They started a relationship when they were both still living there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2396.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2399.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 1991, Mr. Walden traveled from Suriname</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2399.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2403.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the Netherlands to stay with his father.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2403.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2414.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And between 1991 and 1995, the applicant applied five times for a visa for the purposes of visiting various family members in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2414.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2424.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, all of these requests were rejected, ultimately based on the risk that the applicant would overstay the allowed visa period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2424.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2431.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And her sixth request for a visa for the purpose of staying with her sister was finally granted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2431.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2441.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicant arrived in the Netherlands in March 1997, but did not return to Suriname when her visa expired.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2441.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2447.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, strikingly enough, none of those requests mentioned her partner, Mr. Walden.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2447.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2465.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government cannot but think that the applicant did not mention her now husband deliberately with a view to settling in the Netherlands, knowing that she did not meet the requirements for a residence permit, and thus presenting the Dutch authorities with a fait accompli.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2465.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2474.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this view is supported by the applicant's remark in these proceedings that she had no reason to stay in Suriname after her parents died.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2474.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2485.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the fact that the applicant at no stage during her proceedings proved that she met all the requirements for a residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2485.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2488.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the applicant married Mr. Walden in 1999,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2488.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2491.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and a year after their first child was born.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2491.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2495.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The child is a Dutch national, since Mr. Walden was granted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2495.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2498.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dutch citizenship in 1993.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2498.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2506.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And between 1997 and 2010, the applicant filed five requests for a residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2506.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2522.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And apart from the first request, all requests were rejected because the applicant did not hold a valid provisional residence visa, and was not eligible for an exemption from the requirement to hold such a visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2522.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2538.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the applicant's appeal against the refusal of her fifth request for a residence permit is at this moment still pending before the Council of State, which is the highest judicial instance in immigration matters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2538.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2541.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, Mr. President, it is not in dispute</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2541.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2552.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that there is family life within the meaning of Article 8, paragraph 1 of the Convention, between the applicant, her husband, and their children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2552.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2561.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We stress, however, that contrary to what the applicant has said, she has at no time been entitled to a residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2561.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2569.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case is clearly different in that respect from the applicant in the case of Rodriguez da Silva versus the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2569.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2580.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we believe that since the disputed decision did not involve revoking an existing residence permit, there was no interference with the applicant's family life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2580.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2593.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the relevant question is, therefore, whether the Dutch authorities have a positive obligation to allow the applicant to reside in the Netherlands to enable her to enjoy family life with her husband and children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2593.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2608.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, according to the court's case law, regardless of whether a positive or negative obligation exists, a fair balance must be struck between the interests of the alien concerned and the public interests of the state party to the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2608.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2614.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in both contexts, the state enjoys a certain margin of appreciation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2614.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2621.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in the present case, there was, on the one hand, the applicant's right to respect for family life within the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2621.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2628.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on the other hand, the public interest involved regulating immigration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2628.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2639.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, we are convinced that in deciding that in this case, the latter interest should prevail, the authorities did not overstep their margin of appreciation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2639.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2644.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we feel this position is strengthened by the following considerations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2644.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2655.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant established her family life at a time she had no grounds whatsoever for believing that she would be issued with a residence permit to stay in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2655.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2660.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And nor was she given any reason to believe that she would be issued such a permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2660.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2675.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And following your court's case law, it is only in the most exceptional circumstances that family life built up during unlawful residence imposes an obligation on the state to permit residence within its territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2675.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2680.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And are such most exceptional circumstances present in the applicant's case?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2680.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2683.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, we believe not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2683.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2688.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no objective impediments to Mrs. Jeunesse exercising her right to family life</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2688.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2690.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2690.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2695.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nor are there otherwise insurmountable obstacles for doing so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2695.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2700.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both the applicant and her husband are of Surinamese origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2700.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2707.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant lived in Suriname until she was 30 years old, almost twice as long as her stay in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2707.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2711.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And her ties with Suriname must therefore be strong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2711.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2717.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant still has relatives living in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2717.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2727.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no reason to assume that the applicant or her husband may not be able to find a job, find housing, and build up their lives in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2727.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2732.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this brings me to the interest of the applicant's children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2732.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2741.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, there is no doubt that we agree with the applicant that it is generally important for children to grow up in the vicinity of both parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2741.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2749.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in this case, however, that is not an issue, since there is no question of the family being ruptured.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2749.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2757.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Like I said before, there are no objective impediments or insurmountable obstacles to exercising family life elsewhere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2757.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2764.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The children are still young and may be expected to adjust to the Surinamese culture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2764.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2774.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The children would not have to learn a new language, since Dutch is the common language in Suriname and is also the language taught in the educational system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2774.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2780.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this will help the children to adjust to their new school, which they will be able to attend in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2780.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2796.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, we emphasize that no evidence has been admitted to suggest that there are special ties or highly exceptional circumstances linking them to the Netherlands, going beyond the mere integration in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2796.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2803.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the present case is clearly different from the cases of Rodriguez da Silva versus the Netherlands and Nunes versus Norway.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2810.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2823.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In those two cases, the court held that there were exceptional circumstances, which justified the conclusion that expulsion of the mothers would be in breach of Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2823.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2825.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What were the facts in those cases?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2825.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2831.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The children and father in both cases had Dutch and Norwegian nationality, and the mothers did not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2831.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2834.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parents in both those cases were separated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2834.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2848.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was shown that, apart from being integrated in their respective countries, they had become vulnerable after the separation of their parents and the changes in their care and home situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2848.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2868.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, in both cases, a family court deemed it in the best interest of the children to stay in their respective countries and also they could not follow their mothers to their countries of origin as a result of custody and access arrangements that had been put in place by a family court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2868.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2878.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The expulsion of the mothers in those highly exceptional circumstances would have resulted in the family life of those involved being ruptured.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2878.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2887.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in the present case, there is no question of a broken relationship between the parents and therefore no custody or access arrangements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2887.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2894.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither did a family court consider that it would be in the best interest of the children to stay in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2894.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2902.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no objective impediments to exercising the right to family life outside the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2902.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2913.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in summary, the interests of the applicant's children have been thoroughly considered by the immigration authorities and national courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2913.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2915.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Mr. President, this brings me</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2915.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2925.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the Culverboer report, which the applicant submitted in her memorial of the 5th of August, 2013, to support her contention that the return of Mrs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2925.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2932.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jeunesse to Suriname would have a highly adverse effect on her children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2932.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2943.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, first of all, we would like to express our profound surprise that this report was submitted unannounced at such a late stage of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2943.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2947.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's first child was born in 2000.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2947.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2952.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this case was lodged before your court in 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2952.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2962.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For reasons unknown, the applicant waited until mid-2013 to request an investigation to be carried out regarding her children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2962.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2969.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We cannot help but wonder if the referral of this case to the Grand Chamber had anything to do with that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2969.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2972.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But by acting as she did, Ms. Jeunesse</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2972.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2986.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>has deprived the government of the opportunity to take this report into consideration in the national proceedings, and more importantly, to respond to the report as it would have wished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2986.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2996.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, even though we have little time to reflect upon this report, I would like to make a few general remarks and as well respond to its substance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2996.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3000.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, some remarks concerning the report in general.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3000.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3005.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Professor Kalverboer's reports are well known in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3005.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3017.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She has, on a number of occasions, drawn up general reports with regards to the residence and forcible return of asylum seekers' children under the age of 18.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3017.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3037.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, Professor Kalverboer's general view is that the forcible expulsion of asylum seekers' children who have lived in the Netherlands for more than five years is hardly ever acceptable in view of the emotional and psychological damage caused by enforced departure from the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3037.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3043.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also in the report, in the present case, Professor Kalverboer refers to this general view.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3043.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3048.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, the government would like to point out that it doesn't follow this general view.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3048.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3056.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But furthermore, the applicants' children are not asylum seekers' children, and we believe that they cannot be considered similarly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3056.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3063.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Asylum seekers' children live under very different circumstances in the Netherlands compared to the applicants' children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3063.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3074.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, we cannot accept a reference to Professor Kalverboer's general view regarding asylum seekers' children in the context of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3074.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3089.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The opposite would mean that any child having established roots in the Netherlands over five years could no longer be expected to leave the country together with his family on the grounds that it would be harmful for the child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3089.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3096.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we believe that this goes way too far, and there is no support for this principle in the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3096.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3107.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we cannot endorse the conclusion that putting down roots in itself prevents any expectation being made to the applicant and her children to return to Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3107.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3111.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Immigration is by no means an unknown phenomenon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3111.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3117.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, concerning the substantive findings of the report, I would like to make four remarks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3117.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3123.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, we doubt the objectivity of the conclusions of the report.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3123.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3137.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The report was drawn up on the basis of information provided by the applicant and her children, and it is likely that the information given to Professor Kalverboer was influenced by their wish to remain in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3137.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3147.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the report presents a different picture of the applicant's family situation than that presented in the proceedings until then.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3147.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3155.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the report, the children's development is being adversely affected by the situation in which they find themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3155.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3175.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this surprises us, since documents submitted by the applicant earlier in the proceedings emphasize how well the children are doing and how well they are faring and their development is going well in spite of the situation and the uncertainty surrounding the applicant's residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3175.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3179.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No explanation is given for this difference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3179.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3190.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, as for the apprehension and detention of the applicant by the aliens police, we do not deny that this event can have an impact, especially on young children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3190.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3204.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But however, when all proportionate means to bring about the expulsion have been employed to no avail, the apprehension of aliens by the police is an inevitable consequence of unlawful residence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3204.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3215.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that children might witness such an event cannot be a reason for not carrying out forcible expulsions if all other efforts have failed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3215.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3222.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, we believe that the report is incomplete with regards to an essential element.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3222.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3228.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Professor Kalverboer only considers two scenarios in her report.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3228.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3232.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first is that in which the applicant returns to Suriname alone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3232.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3239.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second scenario is that in which the applicant returns to Suriname together with her children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3239.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3247.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But nothing is said, however, about the whole family, including the father returning to Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3247.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3255.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And because it does not address this scenario, the report fails to shed light on what impact it would have on the children's development.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3255.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3268.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We find this all the more surprising since the authors of the report attach great value to the continuity, stability, and care provided within the family as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3268.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3279.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourthly, it is unclear on what grounds Professor Kalverboer bases her conclusion that the applicant would struggle to support herself and her children in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3279.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3295.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as we are aware, Professor Kalverboer has no specific expertise in respect of the general situation in Suriname with regards to education, work, opportunities for development, and other circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3295.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3304.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But moreover, there is no evidence that the family's individual situation upon return to Suriname has been given any consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3304.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3310.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we can, therefore, not attach much value to that conclusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3310.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3328.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, for all these reasons, we believe that the report fails to give sufficient concrete and individual grounds to substantiate the conclusion that there are highly exceptional circumstances that leaving to live in Suriname would seriously jeopardize their development.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3328.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3343.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the government believes that this case is more akin to Antwi versus Norway, in which the court ruled that there were no insurmountable obstacles to the family settling together in the father's country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3343.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3350.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And contrary to what the applicant has said in her pleadings, the decisions show a full balancing of interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3350.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3358.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in sum, I would like to repeat that the applicant had at no time possessed a residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3358.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3365.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She chose to intensify her family life despite the uncertainty about her immigration status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3365.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3377.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the children are not tied to the Netherlands due to custody or access arrangements, and nor is their stay in the Netherlands considered in their best interest by a family court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3377.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3385.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not effectively possible for the applicant and her family to exercise family life in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3385.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3390.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sorry, I meant to say it's not effectively impossible, of course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3390.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3397.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no impediments for the applicant, her husband, and children as a family to rebuild their lives in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3397.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3399.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Dutch language is spoken there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3399.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3405.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have a social network, and the children will be able to attend school.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3405.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3412.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The husband's criminal conviction is no obstacle to the family's exercise of its rights to family life in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3412.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3418.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there is no evidence of any exceptional circumstances relating to the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3418.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3429.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To put it bluntly, in this case, only the fact that the children have Dutch nationality and have resided in the Netherlands since their birth could constitute exceptional circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3429.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3437.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in our view, that is insufficiently exceptional in the light of the court's established case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3437.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3448.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, if the court were to rule that Article 8 had been violated in this case, we believe that that would mark a far-reaching shift in the court's established case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3448.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3464.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In conclusion, taking all the above-mentioned factors into account, there are no facts or circumstances to suggest that the applicant's right to respect for family life requires that the weighing of interests should be decided to her advantage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3464.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3469.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there was no obligation to allow her to stay in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3469.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3475.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, we believe that the decision to refuse her a residence permit was in accordance with Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3479.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3483.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, Mr. President, you have granted leave</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3483.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3492.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the Immigrant Council of Ireland to make written submissions as to the possible rights under Article 20 of the TFEU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3492.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3511.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before going into the question what possible rights the applicant may derive from that article, I would first draw your attention to the fact that ICI notes in its third-party submission of 18 September 2013 that Article 3 of Protocol Number 4 may be engaged in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3511.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3537.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And ICI also invokes Article 14 in conjunction with Article 8 of the convention, stating that EU citizens and their third country national family members are better protected if they have made use of the right of free movement compared to EU citizens and their third country national family members who have never left the member state of which they have the nationality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3537.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3548.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As ICI acknowledges, these parts of the application were declared inadmissible by the court in its decision the 4th of December 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3548.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3569.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, it is obvious that ICI cannot bring forward these complaints in the proceedings, since apart from the fact that ICI is not a party to these proceedings, the case referred to the Grand Chamber by virtue of Article 43 can be no more and no less than the case as it has been declared admissible by the chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3569.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3579.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And according to the court's decision, and in particular paragraph 82, the present case concerns Article 8 of the convention and nothing but Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3579.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3589.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, I will briefly respond to the merits of the complaint based on Article 8 taken together with Article 14.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3589.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3600.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ICI claims that there was an unlawful distinction between Union citizens not having used their rights of free movement and Union citizens having used their rights of free movement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3600.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3603.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I make two observations in this regard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3603.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3614.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the claim of ICI fails to take into account an important characteristic of the case law of the Court of Justice of the European Union.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3614.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3627.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, Union citizens who have never exercised their rights of free movement and have always resided in a member state of which there are nationals are not covered by secondary EU law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3627.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3630.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to a ruling in the case of de Russi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3630.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3636.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this may lead to what Advocate General Sharpstone calls reverse discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3636.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3642.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But under the current case law of the ECJ, this is not prohibited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3642.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3650.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And secondly, viewed from the perspective of Article 14, we submit there is no discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3650.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3664.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is for the simple reason that the principle of equal treatment requires that comparable situations must not be treated differently unless such treatment is objectively justified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3664.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3672.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Union citizens not having used their free movement rights are not comparable to Union citizens having used their rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3672.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3677.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And these are different situations and may, therefore, be treated differently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3677.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3684.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this leads me to the main question, whether any rights may be derived from Article 20 TFEU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3684.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3703.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ICI suggests, on the basis of the case law of the ECJ, that Article 20 TFEU gives rise to an unrestricted right of family life with the third country national family members of EU citizens who have not made use of their rights to free movement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3703.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3708.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in our view, ICI misinterprets the ECJ's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3708.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3714.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Zambrano case does not create a general right of family life within the EU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3714.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3724.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the contrary, as we have stated in our written observations, the Zambrano case only applies to very exceptional circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3724.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3739.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, it only applies to situations in which national measures have the effect of depriving Union citizens of their genuine enjoyment of the substance of the rights conferred by virtue of that status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3739.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3749.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the ECJ held, in Zambrano, that the genuine enjoyment of the substance of the rights conferred by the virtue of Union citizenship was at risk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3749.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3752.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And let's have a look at the facts in that case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3752.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3759.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The minor children had Belgian nationality, and their parents were both third country nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3759.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3769.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to refuse the parents a right of residence would de facto mean that the minor children would be forced to leave the territory of the EU with their parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3769.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3778.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that would lead to the denial of the genuine enjoyment of the substance of the EU rights conferred to the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3778.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3786.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, under these exceptional circumstances, the ECJ held that the parents should be given a right to stay within Belgium.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3786.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3789.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in summary, what is the Zambrano test?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3789.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3802.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a test that focuses on the question whether the Union citizen involved would be obliged to give up residence in the EU if the non-EU national were to be removed from the EU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3802.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3811.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I emphasize that obliged in this context means that the Union citizen has no other choice than to leave the territory of the EU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3811.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3819.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if the Union citizen involved is not forced to leave the EU, then there are no rights under Article 20.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3819.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3826.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, as to the role of Article 8 of the convention in this discussion, we observe the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3826.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3836.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The post-Zambrano case law makes clear that the right to protection of family life as such is not protected by Article 20 TFEU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3836.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3847.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ECJ has observed that the mere desirability of keeping a family together is not sufficient to conclude that the Union citizen is forced to leave the EU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3847.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3864.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, only where the third country national's residence is essential to ensure that the Union citizen is not forced to leave the EU must that third country national family member be granted residence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3864.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3868.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, does this mean that the right to protection of family life is irrelevant?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3868.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3870.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No, not at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3870.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3884.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ECJ has made clear that this right may play a role, but not under Article 20 TFEU, but by other national provisions or international law, such as Article 8 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3884.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3887.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this brings me back to the facts of this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3887.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3891.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is the Zambrano test satisfied in this case?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3891.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3898.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And are the children forced to leave the EU in case their mother is not granted a residence permit?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3898.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3900.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The short answer is no.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3900.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3904.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no evidence that the children are forced to leave the EU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3904.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3909.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The children have Dutch nationality and may stay in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3909.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3913.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The father has Dutch nationality and could care for them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3913.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3920.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no evidence that the children are completely dependent upon the applicant's exclusive care.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3920.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3924.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, the Zambrano exception does not come into play.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3924.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3933.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The mere desire to jointly enjoy family life within the EU does not give rights under Article 20.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3933.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3935.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, Mr. President, we would observe</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3935.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3942.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the question of a review in the light of EU law does not arise in the present proceedings before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3942.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3952.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But be that as it may, we are of the opinion that the Zambrano ruling could and should not be given a broad interpretation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3952.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3963.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Zambrano case is exceptional and does not create an unrestricted right for third country family members to claim rights of residence in the EU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3963.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3975.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A broad interpretation would have the undesirable effect that the scope of EU law would be affected and would go against the ECJ's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3975.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3985.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, lastly, with regard to the applicant's claims for just satisfaction, we would simply refer to what has been said in the written observations on this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3985.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3996.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we would only draw your attention to the applicant's submission that a short trip to Disneyland Paris would be sufficient just satisfaction for non-pecuniary damage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3996.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4008.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We find that somewhat surprising and wonder how appropriate it is to request for a trip to Disneyland in the light of the seriousness of the alleged violations as stated by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4008.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4012.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we will leave it to the court to decide upon this should that be necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4012.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4015.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4015.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4015.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4018.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4020.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mrs. Egmond.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4020.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4026.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are there any questions from the judges? Judge Power.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ann Power-Forde</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4029.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4030.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4030.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4037.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have one question for the government and one question for the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4037.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4044.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the government, you have explained and attempted to distinguish the Zambrano principle as it arises in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4044.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4053.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I would like you to comment on a submission made by the Immigrant Council of Ireland as to what effective legal protection actually requires.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4053.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4055.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Effective legal protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4055.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4064.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you will see from their submissions that they deal with this under the heading of administrative and judicial decision-making bodies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4064.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4089.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The submission is that if national authorities suggest that the family may move elsewhere in the EU or are not actually forced to leave the territory of the EU, then the law would require and would expect that the decision-making bodies adverted to this possible solution and to have adduced evidence as to its practicality, its feasibility and its proportionality for any particular member.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4089.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4109.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would ask the government, firstly, to comment on that submission, and secondly, to show where in the administrative and judicial decisions the practicality, feasibility and proportionality of a move or either within the territory has been made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4109.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4141.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would just draw attention to the fact that in the domestic decision of the court dated 8 December 2009, that's the regional court of The Hague sitting in Harlem, reference is made to EU law, but not to the possibility of moving within the territory, but rather to the fact that there's no obligation on the family, on the citizens to leave, EU citizens to leave, because the children could always stay in the Netherlands alone with their father.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4141.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4155.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if that alternative is to be submitted, is to be relied upon, then how would that not in fact result in a constructive interference with family life, with an interference in that the family would be broken up?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4155.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4158.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's the question that I would put to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4158.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4171.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the applicant, the case, as I understand it, is mainly pleaded in terms of an interference or a failure to comply with the positive obligations insofar as the applicant's family life is concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4171.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4178.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And very little is made in terms of the claim under Article 8 to private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4178.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4198.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, this court in a number of judgments has elected to examine both aspects, and I would like the applicants to comment on the private life of the applicant and to what extent identity as the mother of Dutch children forms part of the applicant's private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4198.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4205.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the applicant's identity as the mother of Dutch children, to what extent does that touch upon the applicant's private life?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4205.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4205.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4207.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4212.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Judge Power-Forde. Judge López Guerra, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4213.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4215.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4215.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4222.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'd like to make two factual questions to both the applicant and the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4222.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4231.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It seems that the reason for the denial of the residence to the applicant was the lack of a provisional residence visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4231.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4239.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This provisional residence visa has to be applied for in the country of origin of the applicant, that is in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4239.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4255.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if the regular proceedings were followed, the applicant should go back to Suriname, then apply, they should apply them for this provisional residence visa in order to be able to go back to the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4255.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4272.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now my questions are, first, if the applicant would do that, would go back to Suriname and ask for a provisional residence visa, first, what would be the criteria followed by the government to allow or not to allow this provisional visa?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4272.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4282.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, if up to the point you can answer to that, what are the perspectives of getting this permission, this provisional residence visa?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4282.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4287.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, how much time would it be needed for these proceedings?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4287.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4297.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mean, how much time would it take from asking the provisional residence visa and then to get the response by the government?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4297.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4297.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4298.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4302.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge López Guerra, Judge Ineta Ziemele.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4305.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4306.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4306.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4316.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question to the applicant and a question to the government, and it equally goes back to the facts of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4316.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4325.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties have pleaded in front of the court the principle of the best interests of the child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4325.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4369.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to the applicant, I would like to know, in the set of proceedings that the applicant has initiated in the Netherlands with the view of obtaining the residence permit, in what manner and with what arguments did the applicant reason the best interests of the child, apart from the evident fact of the Dutch nationality of the children, what other arguments were advanced as concerns the need to protect the best interests of the child, and maybe in which of the numerous proceedings?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4369.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4373.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the question to the government in the same context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4373.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4399.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government, in its observations, written observations and oral submissions, especially in paragraph 67 in your written memorial, you have mentioned several arguments showing that there was the best interests of the children have been taken into consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4399.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4403.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, a factual question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4403.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4419.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are these the government's arguments in paragraph 67, or were these exactly the words, the reasoning used by the domestic courts or the administrative authorities?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4419.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4437.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If so, could you point to the court, could you direct the court to these judgments, decisions where exactly in the same manner the best interests of the child have been assessed and balanced in the proceedings?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4437.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4437.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4438.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4443.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Ziemele and Judge Vincent De Gaetano.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Vincent A. De Gaetano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4446.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4447.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4447.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4452.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two questions to clarify certain facts, if I may.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4452.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4461.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are mainly directed towards the government, but perhaps even the counsel for the applicant can refer to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4461.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4472.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If I remember correctly, if I understood correctly, counsel for the government said that the husband's criminal record is no obstacle to him entering and settling in Suriname.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4472.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4490.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In view of the fact that, as far as I can understand, the husband has lost Surinamese nationality and the criminal record referred to something which was not really trivial, could government elaborate on that?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4490.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4511.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question is, apart from the repeated applications for residence, what exactly were the reasons or the reason why it took so long for the government to actually take action to expel applicant from Dutch territory?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4511.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4511.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4514.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4518.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge De Gaetano. Are there any... Judge Silvis?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Johannes Silvis</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4522.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4523.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4523.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4527.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question for the representative of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4527.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4539.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On page 10 of your written submissions, you state that in the context of immigration cases, children carry no responsibility for choices made by parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4539.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4545.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in order to underline this position, referral is made to three cases of our court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4545.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4559.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the Nunez case, in which deportation and exclusion orders would effectively result in a mother guilty of immigration law breaches being separated from her young children for two years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4559.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4573.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the case of Mubilanzila Mayeka and Kaniki Mitunga, which concerns detention and deportation of a five-year-old child without her family.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4573.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4576.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third, Osman versus Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4576.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4592.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You mentioned this case also in your oral submissions today, in which refusal to renew residence permit of a minor who had been sent abroad against her will is the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4592.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4602.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of these cases concern a situation in which not finding a violation would result necessarily in accepting a breach of family life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4602.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4615.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it would therefore need further explanation as to how this case law would support the applicant seeking a permanent residence in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4615.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4627.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do you think this case law is also relevant in case the refusal to give permanent residence to your client would not necessarily lead to a separation, a rupture of the family?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4629.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4630.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4630.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4632.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Silvis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4632.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4633.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Kalaydjieva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Zdravka Kalaydjieva</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4637.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4639.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4639.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4649.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question to the government, and it is related to the questions of judges and Power-Forde, and in a dissimilar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4649.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4665.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government is, as far as I understand, submitting that, first of all, acknowledging that Article 8 rights are under considerations in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4665.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4699.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are also submitting that the Dutch government have not overstepped their margin of appreciation in examining this case, and that Article 8 issues have been thoroughly considered by the national authorities, whether you refer to the courts or the minister in deciding the applicant's case appears not to be quite clear, as their reasoning in the several accounts of applications seem to vary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4699.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4749.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as a whole, from your submissions during the hearing today, it seems that you're saying that the consideration of Article 8 rights was already accepted as one involving a potential risk of alternative interference with Article 8 rights in both cases, whether the applicant should be separated from her family or whether it would result, a decision negative to the interests of the applicant would result in sending four Dutch citizens, including three children, to a country outside the territory where they were born and brought up.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4749.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4761.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do you see this as a matter of inevitable result as in view of the necessity to protect the public interests and the community interests?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4761.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4779.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like the government to provide us with more information or views whether this is the manner in which they see that the potential interference with Article 8 rights has been thoroughly considered in your opinion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4782.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4785.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Kalaydjieva, Judge Šikuta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ján Šikuta</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4789.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4791.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4791.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4797.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I do have one concrete question to the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4797.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4820.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the chronology of events list we do have at our disposal in our files, it seems that the applicant, for the very first time, applied for a tourist visa to Netherlands on 19th of February 91.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4820.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4828.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But her partner left to Netherlands at the end of October 91.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4828.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4840.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it was more than half a year before the partner left, and much more before they got married and had children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4840.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4848.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So my concrete question is, what was the reason for the applicant to apply for tourist visa in February 91?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4850.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4854.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Šikuta, Judge Gyulumyan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4858.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4861.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is for both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4861.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4876.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that time when applicant entered into Netherlands in 1997, the regulations in force did not require her to have obtained a provisional visa in Suriname before applying for a residence in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4876.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4880.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why that law is not applicable in this case?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4880.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4880.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4882.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4883.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4884.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4889.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, we will have a break now for, let's say, 15 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4890.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4896.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we will resume our hearing accordingly in the quarter to 11.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4896.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4901.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, the hearing is suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4966.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4967.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5011.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5013.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated, the hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5016.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5018.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Later, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5018.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5019.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ah.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5019.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5022.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Eertink.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5022.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5031.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5031.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5041.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In answer to the question of the Honorable Judge of Ireland, the applicant wishes to answer as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5041.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5049.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nationality can be considered part of someone's identity and therefore be part of private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5049.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5060.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Being a mother can as well form part of someone's identity and therefore as well be part of private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5060.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5075.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, the identity as a mother is therefore relevant and part of her private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5075.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5087.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In answer to the question of the Honorable Judge of Malta, the applicant wishes to answer as following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5087.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5128.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although a criminal record could in general perhaps not be an impediment to moving to Suriname, the question remains however whether access to Suriname would be obtained for this predominantly of Dutch citizens composed family with at that time no income because it has been argued by the applicant that if the whole family were to move to Suriname, this would mean that the father would lose his job and income.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5128.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5138.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In answer to the question of the Honorable Judge of the Netherlands, the applicant wishes to answer as following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5138.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5168.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case law was merely used to underline a principle which the applicant wished to put forward, this principle being the principle as also laid down in the Convention on the Rights of the Child that a child cannot be held responsible for choices made by their parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5168.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5198.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case law was merely an instruction, an illustration of this principle and in the applicant's view this principle should apply as well in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5198.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5206.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to ask my colleague Ms. Latter to answer questions that are more of a factual</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5206.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5206.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>nature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5211.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5214.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Eertink, Mrs. Later-</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5217.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5229.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I want to say something about, I think it's the Honorable Church from Latvia asked me about the rights of the child in the procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5231.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5280.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have, if we look at the procedure that started on 23rd of January, 2007, I have pleaded, all in the procedure is always a lot written about the interests of the child and I have invoked Article 9, Article 3, Article 4, Article 8 in conjunction with the Stapita case, Article 9, and there are very many different factual information in that case and also what the interests of the father are and what our advice committee for strangers cases said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5281.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5372.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And everywhere in the procedure that's going on and in the next procedure that started on 26th September, 2007, I started a very urgent request to the ministry for my clients, both parents and the children and all the arguments about people who could take care of the children, also the psychiatric background from members of the family is explicitly mentioned there and we have put the obligation, the interest of the state and the interest of the children and the family behind each other and actually since then in all the papers we have been talking about the interest of the child in where the father had to be here to provide the income and there's no possibilities of family members in the country of origin of my client, her brother who has presonile dementia and is not on one place and a sister who's not on one place and probably psychiatric problems too, there's no contact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5372.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5376.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's the background where the people would go to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5376.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5388.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the school is mentioned in the case that was pending in 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5388.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5398.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have spoken about all the different sides of the children, article two of the children's convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5402.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5407.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have done a lot concerning the interest of the child in the file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5407.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5414.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope it's so short so I haven't been able to write everything down exactly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5414.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5419.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The honorable judge from Slovakia I think asked a request about a visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5420.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5428.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My client and her now husband requested at the same time for a visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5428.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5442.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He asked a visa with his Dutch father and she asked a visa with her sister being in the Netherlands and I don't know, maybe Dutch nationality, the division between members of family after the takeover in 75.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5444.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5451.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When you do a request for a tourist visa, it takes many, many months to decide.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5451.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5461.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was about same time when her now husband got a positive decision and she got a negative decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5461.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5473.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I remember she asked a visa to stay with her sister and she asked later on a visa to stay with her father-in-law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5473.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5476.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then her father-in-law, Mr. Walden's father,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5476.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5488.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was interviewed by the police and the police wrongly wrote down that the applicant's father-in-law was a cousin or an uncle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5488.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5493.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was wrongly written down because it was her father-in-law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5493.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5502.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to answer something what the government said, we've always been discussing all these procedures around a visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5502.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5515.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In that time, in 97, if you ask for a tourist visa, as someone from Surinamese background, you came here and you applied for a residence permission, there was no problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5515.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5518.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that was very normal to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5518.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5528.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the claim that she never appealed, yeah, if you are in Suriname, it is really difficult to understand that you can appeal and where can you appeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5528.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5531.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that is...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5531.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5532.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have more?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5532.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5543.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Huh?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5543.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5546.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I've asked the question about best interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5546.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5549.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope I can say.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5549.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5550.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yeah?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5550.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5559.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Did you answer all the questions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5559.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5574.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, about, yeah, the last question about professional residence visa, I don't know whether it was a question for us, but we had this professional residence visa all the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5574.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5601.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I remember that through that jurisprudence for the law that was valuable in 82, we finally fought out in the courts that if the people were fulfilling all the conditions, then there was no reason not to get a residence permission because of the lack of a professional residence visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5601.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5609.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's why I made in my pleading note in the beginning the different arguments for a residence permission, and they fulfilled every argument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5609.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5618.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in 97, normally, if they would have looked at the case itself, there would have been granted a residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5618.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5626.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the law between 94 and 2001, the same, the aliens law, the same thing happened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5626.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5643.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Later on, under the law that's now applicable since the 1st of March, 2001, the government takes a very harsh point of view and says no, no resident, no, no professional residence visa, finish.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5643.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5657.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think that's not correct if you look at the rights of the child and Article 8 as we have been pleading here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5658.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5658.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5658.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5662.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Miss Egmond.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5667.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5669.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5669.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5672.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, I would like to go into the questions from the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5672.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5680.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then afterwards, if time permits, I have a few points in reply to the applicant's submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5680.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5691.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding Judge Power's question relating to ICI's third party intervention, we believe that ICI misinterprets ECJ's court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5691.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5704.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As stated before, the Zambrano test focuses on the question whether the EU citizen involved would be obliged to give up residence in the EU if the non-EU national were to be removed from the EU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5704.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5711.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the Zambrano test does not create a general right of family life within the EU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5711.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5719.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as to the present case, if the children have no other choice than to leave the EU territory, then they can claim rights under Article 20.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5719.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5727.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the children are not completely dependent upon the applicant, and they can stay in the Netherlands as they are Dutch nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5727.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5729.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And their father can take care of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5733.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5741.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Lopez-Guerra's question was, what are the criteria to obtain a residence permit?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5741.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5759.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in reply, we would answer that, first of all, I would like to point out that the same requirements have to be met when filing a request for a provisional residence visa in Suriname compared to filing a request for a permanent residence visa in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5759.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5770.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the requirements include an income requirement, a civic integration requirement, and a valid passport and documents regarding the marriage, for example.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5770.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5775.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then a full assessment is made of Article 8 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5775.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5780.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And a decision is taken within the statutory decision period of 90 days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5780.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5806.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, regarding the question of Judge Ziemeler, relating to the best interest of the children, the government would like to refer, firstly, to the decision of the government of the 11th of March 2009 in the fourth procedure where the applicant applied for a residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5806.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5821.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, the government refers to the decision of the 19th of December 2011, where a full assessment of whether refusal of residence permit is in accordance with Article 8 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5821.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5825.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this decision was taken in the fifth procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5825.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5840.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And lastly, we would like to refer to the court's judgment of the 17th of July 2012, where the regional court follows this full assessment made by the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5840.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5843.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge De Gaetano had two questions, actually.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5843.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5857.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His first question was, what obstacles would appear, or would there be an obstacle for the husband following his criminal conviction in the Netherlands?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5857.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5860.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, first, the applicant's husband is no longer on the blacklist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5860.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5865.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that was an obstacle because he was not able to fly, at least not from the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5865.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5872.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But second, we have no reason to assume that it would be an insurmountable obstacle, and nor has the applicant shown that it would be.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5875.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5884.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge De Gaetano's second question related to the steps taken to effectively expel the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5884.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5898.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, we do not think that it took unduly long to, at least, we do not think that we took unduly long to take the necessary steps with a view to the applicant's departure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5898.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5908.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For more than 10 years, the applicant could not be expelled because she repeatedly submitted applications and availed herself of all the available legal remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5908.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5913.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And these largely had the effect of suspending her expulsion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5913.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5922.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in the brief periods that the applicant could be expelled, practical steps were taken with a view to her departure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5922.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5936.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The steps taken went from fairly low-key, like house visits in 2000 already, and orders to present herself, to the most far-reaching power available, aliens' detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5936.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5945.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But however, the applicant failed completely to cooperate with the government, and she resisted expulsion at every turn.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5945.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5950.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Every action taken by the aliens' police was followed by letters of complaint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5950.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5959.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And she even said that she was being stalked by the aliens' police, and she complained to the ombudsman about that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5959.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5965.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides from all that, we are also dependent upon the cooperation of the Surinamese authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5965.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5968.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In conclusion, the applicant has made it very difficult to expel her.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5968.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5983.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In answer to Judge Kaladieva's question, we believe that it does not follow from the court's case law that an assessment of both different situations should be separately made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5983.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5996.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in the present case, a full assessment has been made within Article 8 of the Convention by the immigration authorities and the national courts in several proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5996.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6001.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was, as we feel at least, in conformity with the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6001.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6009.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, we reiterate that there are no exceptional circumstances and no insurmountable obstacles in this case, and hence no violation of Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6012.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6024.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, lastly, with regard to Judge Glungyun's question, the applicant herself did not pursue her first application because she did not show up in the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6024.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6029.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because she did not show up after several orders to complete her application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6029.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6034.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After several orders to complete her application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6034.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6042.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to hold a provisional residence visa is a statutory requirement since the new aliens law of 2001.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6042.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6048.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is for the purpose of preventing to put the Netherlands for a veta complete.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6048.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6054.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For her subsequent requests, the aliens act was applicable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6054.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6060.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, she had to comply with the requirement to hold a provisional residence visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6069.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6074.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I seem to have forgotten one question, which was from Judge Lopez Guerra.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6074.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6077.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is the perspective for the applicants?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6077.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6085.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, based on the case file, the applicant does not meet the requirements to obtain a residence visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6085.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6093.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I would shortly like to go into a few issues that the applicant raised in these proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6093.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6104.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first one is that the applicant has said that regarding the examples that she gave for the exemption on the basis of hardship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6104.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6112.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in the first place, the government, it is not that we could not put forward examples, because we have in our submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6112.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6122.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But there is no separate record in our electronic systems for exemptions on the provisional residence visa on the basis of hardship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6122.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6129.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the examples presented by the applicants are all very different cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6129.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6144.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And well, to give you an example of that, she has mentioned cases where serious medical conditions were at hand, or special family situations like broken family, supervision, and access arrangements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6144.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6147.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, this is not at issue in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6149.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6164.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the applicant's submission, if the applicant's children have rights to private life in the Netherlands on their own, we feel that this is a new complaint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6164.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6171.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And besides, we believe that the children's rights are incorporated and assessed within the applicant's rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6171.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6175.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicant only brought forward general interests of the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6178.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6196.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, lastly, in reply to the submissions concerning the apprehension of the applicant and in the presence of her children, the government does acknowledge that the effect of the detention of Ms. Janes on her children,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6196.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6198.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>there was an impact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6198.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6206.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government would like to stress that the measure was proportionate in the light of the earlier attempts to secure the applicant's departure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6206.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6213.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was ordered to present herself several times to the aliens police, but never appeared.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6213.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6222.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The aliens police had visited her address in the same week before the apprehension twice without finding her there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6222.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6226.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the day of the apprehension, one of her children opened the door.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6226.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6235.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we believe this was not a coincidence since, while searching the house, the aliens police found Ms. Janes hidden in a closet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6235.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6235.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6238.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6239.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6240.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6241.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Ms. Egmond.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6242.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6247.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6247.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6255.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6255.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6258.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6258.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6262.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered at a later stage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6262.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6267.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6267.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6269.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
