<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>1715311_15052013</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>26.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>26.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>70.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>71.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>76.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>85.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Vučković and others against Serbia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>85.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>98.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were lodged on the 14th of February, 2011 with a court under Article 34 of the Convention by Mr. Boban Vučković and 29 other applicants,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>98.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>101.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>all Serbian nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>101.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>110.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were allocated to the second section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the Rules of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>110.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>122.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 28th of August, 2012, a chamber of the second section joined the applications and delivered its judgment on the admissibility and merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>122.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>140.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 26th of November, 2012, the government requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention, and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on the 11th of February, 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>140.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>145.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Mr. Slavoljub</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>145.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>155.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Carić, Assistant Minister for Justice and Public Administration of the Republic of Serbia, assisted by Ms. Vanja Rodić and Mr. Nenad  Petković,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>155.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>159.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>advisors of the agent's office, and Mr. Radoslav Arsenijević</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>159.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>163.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. Slaviša Vuksanović, advisors</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>163.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>167.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from the Ministry of Defense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>167.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>172.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mr. Srđan Aleksić</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>172.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>175.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Ms. Branislava Isailović, counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>175.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>181.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Mrs. Marija Lazarević, advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>181.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>188.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>188.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>208.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome, among others, the delegations of judges from Russia, Ukraine, Montenegro, Poland, and Japan, as well as delegations from the French Senate and the High Council of Judges and Prosecutors of Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>208.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>219.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representatives of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>219.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>222.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Aleksić and Ms. Isailović for the applicants</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>222.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>228.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>will speak first, and then Mr. Carić for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>228.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>253.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting into Russian and Turkish has been authorized for the benefit of the delegation of judges from Russia and the delegation from the High Council of Judges and Prosecutors of Turkey, respectively, which are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>253.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>265.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>265.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>266.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Aleksić.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>279.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>282.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Хвала господине представнице, поштавани судије.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>282.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>299.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Шасим је да вам се као заступник 30 подносавца тужбе овом суду обратим лично и да вам укратко изнесем најважни разлоге из којих сматрамо да је већ и овога суда донело правилну одлуку 28. августа 2012. године,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>299.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>305.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>коју очекујемо да након разматрња свих наших доказа и навода потврдите.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>305.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>316.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Заједно са мном је моја колегница Бранислава Исиловић, ја овом предмету заступам 30 људи од укупно 8.500,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>316.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>331.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>који су на основу одлуке Државе Србије, тада Срба и Југославије, да прогласи ратно стање на целој своји територији, били мобилисани у марту 1999. године, а потом провели на ратишту три месеца.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>331.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>354.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>У нашој завршној речи ми ћемо се данас бавити питњама које сте нам изречито поставили, али пред свега дозволите ми да се позабавимо најпре једним фактичким питањем и то, дали су ратне дневнице исплаћене и у кому би иму и на који начин, као подносиоцима тако и остајим резервистима из 1990. године.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>354.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>363.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Не сумљиво је да је право на испаду ратних дневница имовинско право подносилаца у смислу члана 1. протокола 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>363.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>368.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>што је утврдило Вечевог суда 28. августа 2012. године.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>368.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>388.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Држава својим неоснованим наводима, прво да ратне дневнице представљају неко ново право тужелаца, а не имовинско, јер није правоснажно суски утврдђено, а потом да је то право престало јер су дневнице исплаћене доводи овај суд у заблуду.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>388.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>412.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Као доказ да су подносиоцима исплаћене ратне дневнице, држава се потрудила да суду достави хиљаду копираних страница, исплатних листа и, на жалост, ниједан оригинал. Подносиоци тврде да ови спискови нису валидни и да су специјално изфабриковани за ову прилику.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>412.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>443.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Наиме, држава је сама у првостепеном поступку тврдила да спискови не постоје јер је исплата вршена на фронту, на лицу места, да много листа недостају, а поводом своје жалбе је успела не само да пронађе све спискове, него су они више него уредни, читко потписани, као да се радило о школској учеоници, а не фронту изложеним ратним действима.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>443.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>460.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Нема поне колико је човек способан да се читко и уредно потпише када око њега лете бомбе. А још је веће чудо да сви мобилизирани резервисти, војници имају уредне рукописе, упокрос томе што једва имају основну школу.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>460.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>479.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Махом, овде говоримо о полјоприводицима и људима низке школске спреме, који, ако су запослени, онда се баве санатским пословима. Потписају су, међутим, више него академског изгледа, а основана је сумња да су многи фасификовани.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>479.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>495.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Указујемо овде и показујемо само на две случаја за које смо донели доказе људи ћији потписи на листи не одговарају наћину на коју су они потписују када се упореди списак и потписи на пунумоћу.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>495.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>505.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Више него сумљиво да овако уредне спискове држава доставља Уваженом суду тек након своје жалбе, а предходно је тврдила да спискова нема.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>505.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>521.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Далје указујемо на исплаћене износе. Овако како су наведени у списковима, види се само колико су времена појединци провели као мобилисани, али за износе се не види јединица мере по којој су рачунати.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>521.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>547.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Види се из списка да су то исто време, 40 дана, исплаћене различните дневнице, а не види се из ког је то разлога. Не зна се шта ови износи представљају, а посећам вас да је по прописима држава у обавези да ратне дневнице исплаћује у износима рачунати на бази 24 сата, не 8 или 12.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>547.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>564.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>У судским поступсима пред домачим судовима, постоје вештаћења која показују много веће износе него што је у достављеним листама наведено, што је још један доказ да предложене листе нису валидан доказ за овај суд.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>564.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>581.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Осим тога, исплате су вршене за период од неколико дана, види се из спискова да има исплата од 1. па до 9 или 15 дана. У том случају, наравно, да се нека имена ујављују више пута.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>581.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>597.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Од овие подписи се односе на 10 или више лица. Друга заблуда за коју вам, ценјени суде, обраћам пажњу је покушај државе да своју обовезу исплате ратних дневница претвори у социјалну помоћ.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>597.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>615.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Такав покушај је постојао пред домаћим судовима, који су због тога различно поступали и рачунали различне рокове за староста. Такав покушај је настављен подписијањем споразума са резервистима из 7 одаровних општа, међу које тужоци не спадају.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>615.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>633.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Социјална помоћ је категорија коју се овој ствари не ради. Исплата социјалне помоћи мора под домаћим прописима ићи у сладу са просречним примањима, сатистићким и осталим подацијима о користицима које води локална самуправа.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>633.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>660.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Покушај државе да овом суду објасни како је питање дненица решено у различним локалним срединама, олагшицама у плаћању комуналија или огрева или школовања, нит су од утицаја о овом предмету, па и позивање на пресоду одговору тужбе по тачкама 53 и 54 није од утицаја о овој ствари.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>660.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>668.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Овде се радио о имовинској обавези државе, према тужиоцима, настаоји по прописима о ратном станњу и мобилизацији.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>668.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>682.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Тужиоци траже и еднак третман са остлим резервистима, онима који су ратне дненице пријимили из средства намењених за социјалну помоћ, а која су одабрани критеријумом пребивалишта.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>682.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>690.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Сматрамо да тако поступање државе представља кршење принципа Европске конвенције о једнакости грађана.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>690.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>700.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Тачно је, како што држава тврди у тачки 55 свог одговора, да не постоје обавезе да се са неким лицем постигне споразум.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>700.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>716.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ми, као тужиоци, и то и не очекујемо, али ако је сама понудила споразум резервистима и седам општана, морала је да је исти принцип, поштујући правилој еднакости, примени за све људе који су се налазили у истој ситуацији.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>716.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>730.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Од момента када је постигла споразум 2008. године са резервистима, седам општана, њена обавеза, исплате, дненица, проширила се и на обавезу постизања споразума са свима.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>730.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>734.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Не судимо овде поштовани судије, тужиоцима ко војницима.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>734.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>752.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Они су обишни грађани који поштују прописе своје државе, као што то раде грађани у свим државама. Одазвали су се позиву на мобилизацији не зато што су хтели, већ зато што је то законска обавеза која има озбине послици уколико се прекрши.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>752.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>755.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Такву обавезу имају грађани у многим државама.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>755.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>767.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Не судимо им овде ни као ратницима. Ратна действа, као и свим другим светским сукубима, остоју посебним трибуналима у надлежност.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>767.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>776.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Овде судимо држави која не поштује обавезе која је сама прописала својим грађанима и за које она они немају альтернативу.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>776.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>786.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Говоримо о резервистима који су због мобилизације оставили своје фарме, занадске радње, оставили своје породице де се срестава за живот.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>786.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>798.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Најменје што држава може да уради је да своју обавезу према њима испуни, а не да нетачним и неоснованим наводима жалбе ово право додатно угрожава.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>798.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>808.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Није таћан навод државе да су тужиоци и остали резервисти могли да се након мобилизације повуку када су хтели.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>808.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>814.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Није и не може то бити различног броја дана које су провели под мобилизацијом.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>814.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>824.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Мобилизација је обавеза и напуштала се или попуњавала само по општим плановима мобилизације које је утврдио начальник Генералштаба.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>824.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>834.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Заступник државе би макар толико морао да зна и морао би да подкрепи доказима бројне своје наводе, али доказа, наравно, нема.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>834.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>850.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Наводи у тачкама 78 до 81 у одговору државе су с тога веома произволњи и само политички панфлект власти и немају никакво упорище у правно радавантним доказима и чинњеницама ове ствари.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>850.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>865.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Показујем на крају на још један изузетно опасан заключак државе, дату тачки 66 њеног одговора који можда и најболје илуструје осутство дубље нализе и приступа овој озбреној и комплексној ствари.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>865.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>884.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>У само једном покушају да противречи налазима Простепеног већа овога суда, у спорној тачки одговора тврди да питање пребивалишта не спада у лична својства грађена, већ како наводи, поставља питање избора сваког лица.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>884.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>897.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Даље, међутим, каже држава да пребивалиште може представљати основ за дискриминацију само када је повезано са характеристикама као што су друштвени статус и националности.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>897.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>906.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Из овога закључујемо да су људи у Срби дискриминисани по стоју друштвеног статуса и националности у зависимости од места свог пребивалишта које слободно бирају.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>906.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>925.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Што даљу пуће на закључак да место пребивалишта бирају према друштвеном статусу односно националности. Ако је то ташно, онда је то неприхватљив навод државе да је Србија гетоизирана и онда питање постајања дискриминације постоје још важније за грађене Србије.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>sr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>925.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>937.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Уколико није ташно, онда је у питању груба површност државе обраћена у Важеном суду и њена ароганција да својим обавезама одговара на правилан и демократски начин.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>944.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>957.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames, Messieurs les Juges, comme mon confrère l'a déjà dit tout à l'heure, donc on va répondre maintenant aux questions précises que vous nous avez posées.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>957.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>993.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vu que notre mémoire du 15 mars 2013 contient déjà nos arguments qui concernent l'applicabilité de l'article 14 de la Convention en connexion avec l'article 1er du protocole 1 et de l'article 1er du protocole 12, on discutera aujourd'hui devant vous les arguments du gouvernement concernant la dite question censée démontrer que les demandes des requérants ne sont pas compatibles rationne materie avec les dispositions de la Convention et du protocole 12.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>993.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1025.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pour le dire le plus simplement possible, le gouvernement CERB considère que l'obligation de l'État de payer aux requérants les indemnités per diem conformément aux dispositions des textes CERB déjà évoqués dans notre mémoire, afférents à la mobilisation en 1999, ne représente un bien au sens de l'article 1 du protocole 1 ni un autre droit prévu par la loi dont parle l'article 1er du protocole 12.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1025.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1043.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mon confrère a déjà souligné que les requérants adhèrent sans réserve aucune aux arguments de la deuxième chambre de votre cour, qui a dans son arrêt du 28 août 2012 constaté justement et à bon escient le contraire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1043.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1075.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il semble que le gouvernement s'appuie principalement sur l'opinion dissidente ou légitimant du juge Sajot, en citant votre arrêt, Raffinerie grecque stranestratis Andréa 10 du 9 décembre 1994, pour avancer qu'une créance à l'instar de celle des requérants peut être considérée comme un bien du protocole 1 uniquement si elle est susceptible d'être exécutée judiciairement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1075.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1116.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sans nous attarder sur les autres récités par le gouvernement à l'appui de la dite thèse, nous voulons attirer votre attention uniquement sur le fait que les requérants ont soulevé devant votre cour la discrimination dont ils ont fait l'objet dans l'exécution des obligations incombant à la Serbie, consistant dans le paiement des indemnités par diem aux réservistes militaires de guerre, ayant été engagé dans la défense de l'État durant l'intervention militaire des forces de l'OTAN en 1999, et non simplement la violation des droits protégés par l'article 1er du protocole 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1116.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1132.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc la question à laquelle il nous faut répondre aujourd'hui est celle de savoir si le droit dans l'exercice duquel la discrimination a été subie est suffisamment pécuniaire pour tomber sous l'empire de l'article 1er du protocole 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1132.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1137.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et la réponse ne peut être que oui.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1137.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1147.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>D'ailleurs, tout est déjà dit là-dessus dans les paragraphes 82 à 87 du jugement du 20 août 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1147.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1173.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le droit au paiement des indemnités par diem aux requérants en tant que réservistes a été prévu par les textes de portée générales adoptés en 1999, et les barèmes ont été déterminés de sorte que chaque individu éligible au paiement de cette indemnité connaisse les montants exacts de sa créance envers l'État, et par conséquent, sa nature pécuniaire ne peut être contestée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1173.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1190.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais à l'autre, et ce que le gouvernement fait semblant d'oublier, selon la jurisprudence de votre cours, bien établie depuis l'affaire linguistique belge déjà en 1968, l'interdiction de discrimination a une portée autonome.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1190.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1218.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Elle est assurée tant par l'application de l'article 14, qui fait partie intégrante de chacun des droits consacrants des droits et libertés, nous dit-on dans l'article 9 de la réprésité, que par l'application de l'article 1er du protocole 12, qui vise même les cas où la discrimination serait commise par les autorités publiques du fait de l'exercice d'un pouvoir discrétionnaire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1218.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1278.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En effet, à l'origine de la discrimination litigieuse de l'État que l'État serbe a fait subir au requérant, se trouve un texte du gouvernement adopté le 17 janvier 2008, prévoyant dans son article 2 qu'une somme de 2 milliards de dinars serait virée sur les comptes de 7 municipalités sous-développées, à savoir Kourchoum, Niablad, Sebonne, Kleb, Benégytore, Djadoljevac et Prokopie, et dans lequel il a été prévu que, et je cite, sont éligibles au paiement d'allocations tous les réservistes militaires de guerre demeurant aux municipalités mentionnées dans l'article 2, fournissant un jugement passé en force de choses jugées, suite à son désistement de l'action contre la République de Serbie, ayant pour objet le paiement de l'indemnité, ainsi qu'une déclaration écrite portant le désistement de toute future demande concernant le paiement des dites indemnités.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1278.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1281.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et aujourd'hui, nous, devant M. le Président,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1281.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1301.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>donc, on a évoqué les dossiers qui les gens de Kourchoum, Niablad et des autres municipalités étaient censés soumettre à la Commune pour être indemnisés, mais du sort de ces documents, on va trancher donc ultérieurement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1301.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1345.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les requérants ainsi que les autres réservistes militaires de guerre en dehors des municipalités mentionnées étaient exclus de l'application du texte, on entamait les protestations partout en Serbie, surtout après avoir appris de façon officieuse que même avant l'entrée en vigueur du texte du gouvernement appelé Zaklouchak, adopté le 17 janvier 2008, le gouvernement avait, le 11 janvier 2008, conclu un accord avec les comités de grévistes des réservistes militaires de guerre, demeurant en municipalité, énumérée dans le texte du gouvernement Zaklouchak du 17 janvier 2008, et le gouvernement a versé au débat, donc, même la traduction de cet accord.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1345.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1368.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il est constant que pour justifier une distinction de traitement de ces citoyens, la Serbie devrait démontrer devant vous qu'en privilégiant un groupe de réservistes au détriment d'un autre, en réglant aux uns et pas aux autres une dette ayant le même fondement et la même origine, elle avait poursuivi un but légitime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1368.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1404.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et les requérants considèrent que le comportement du gouvernement consistant à employer les méthodes déloyales dans les négociations avec ses créanciers, tels les requérants, et à essayer de cacher la vraie nature d'emploi des fonds publics provenant des privatisations des biens publics, en feignant le paiement de l'aide sociale pour masquer la discrimination des requérants et des autres réservistes, exclut toute idée que l'État ait pu poursuivre un but légitime quelconque.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1404.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1423.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le comportement des gouvernements successifs de la Serbie inspire à une personne raisonnable plutôt l'interrogation sur les vraies raisons et les vrais enjeux des pratiques aussi étrangères à un État de droit, enfermant tous les ingrédients des pratiques corruptives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1423.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1445.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le gouvernement nous dit à nouveau qu'il n'y a rien d'étrange dans le fait que pour calmer la colère de certains citoyens plus enragés que les autres, mais en même situation juridique par rapport à l'État, on les aide financièrement, et en plus nous dit que cela pourrait présenter un but légitime pour pratiquer la discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1445.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1465.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Également que la discrimination peut être justifiée par la mauvaise situation des finances étatiques qui, pour le dire en passant, payent les indemnités du réserviste à on ne sait qui, d'après les pièces versées au débat par le gouvernement lui-même, dont mon confrère vient de parler.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1465.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1474.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bien sûr, et fort heureusement, il n'en est rien, et comme les six juges de la deuxième chambre, vous ne serez pas dupes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1474.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1500.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le gouvernement essaie de nous distraire en racontant une histoire dans laquelle il se présente comme une sorte de Robin des Bois, pauvre mais juste, qui distribue à ses pauvres citoyens l'argent pour les pacifier, mais en même temps, il n'a pas assez d'argent pour rendre heureux et calmer tout le monde, et alors il est obligé de distinguer parmi ces pauvres gens et de choisir, même si cela lui brise le cœur.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1500.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1503.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et on devrait les croire sous parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1503.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1507.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Malheureusement pour les citoyens, la vérité est toute autre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1507.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1520.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans la situation où la grande majorité des citoyens serbes vit en pauvreté, la distinction des réservistes sous l'angle de résidence ou d'indigence ne peut être justifiée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1520.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1534.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et en outre, le critère de résidence d'un réserviste dans une municipalité sous-développée pour lui régler en priorité ses indemnités per diem ne peut en aucun cas servir de critère de son indigence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1534.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1539.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'indigence d'un individu ne peut être prouvée qu'in concreto.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1539.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1566.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En réalité, le gouvernement essaie de cacher le fait qu'en payant les indemnités per diem à un groupe de réservistes, à l'occurrence à ceux domiciliés dans les municipalités plus sous-développées que les autres municipalités serbes également sous-développées, allant des pays normalement développés économiquement, l'État a reconnu sa dette de nature pécuniaire et établit l'échantillé de son règlement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1566.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1598.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ceci étant constaté, l'argument du gouvernement consistant à dire que les créances des requérants envers l'État sont éteintes à cause de la prescription extinctive est inopérant dans la mesure où la reconnaissance d'une dette fait que la prescription commence à courir à nouveau, ce qui prévoit l'article 393 du Code des obligations serbes que le gouvernement cite dans les mémoires, mais pas cet article, comme par hasard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1598.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1609.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Même le paiement d'une dette éteinte par prescription est valable selon l'article 367 du même Code et ne peut pas être répété.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1609.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1637.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et l'État a été en droit de reconnaître de payer sa dette, bien sûr, même prescrite envers les réservistes, et même plus amplement que prévu dans les textes qui, nonobstant leur intitulé respectif, Andrasser, Pravil, Nicode, Louka, doivent être considérés tous comme des lois dans le sens de l'article 1er du protocole 12, car voté par le législateur en 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1637.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1673.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais l'État serbe ne pouvait, en se faisant distinguer entre les réservistes répondant aux conditions posées d'une façon générale par les textes en question, à savoir, ayant été mobilisé durant les mois mars, avril, mai, juin 1999, et ayant participé dans la défense du pays durant l'intervention militaire de l'OTAN contre l'ex-Yougoslavie, et cela donc distingué d'une façon opaque et non justifiée selon les critères bien établis par votre jurisprudence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1673.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1723.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et, au demeurant, le gouvernement lui-même a reconnu le caractère discriminatoire de son agissement envers les réservistes en adoptant le 10 avril 2008, donc trois mois après les fameux accords ESAC-DUCHAC du janvier 2008, un autre texte qui est versé au débat par le gouvernement, et seulement l'article 2, mais qui m'intéresse et traduit en anglais en tant que pièce B2, l'interprétation a contrario de cet article nous offre la preuve intrinsèque du fait que la question de paiement des indemnités dues aux réservistes n'était pas réglée d'une façon uniforme et systémique, mais en privilégiant les uns au détriment des autres réservistes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1723.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1736.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maintenant, je vais passer à la question de recevabilité qui nous a été posée tout récemment, et là, on se sent un petit peu défavorisés par rapport au gouvernement qui a mis tout ça par écrit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1736.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1743.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nous, on va se contenter de répondre oralement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1743.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1782.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ici, encore force est de constater que c'est l'opinion dissidente qui a inspiré le gouvernement, c'était son droit, qui, le gouvernement, considère, tout comme le juge Sajot, que les six juges de la deuxième chambre n'ont pas respecté suffisamment le principe de subsidiarité et de la protection des droits devant votre cour, et qu'il fallait laisser aux juridictions serbes le soin de réparer les violations des droits commises par l'État, et surtout à la coût constitutionnel serbe, érigé en une sorte de filtre entre les citoyens serbes et votre cour depuis l'arrêt Minsk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1782.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1791.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais depuis longtemps, votre cour juge que le principe de subsidiarité n'a rien d'absolu ni de sacré.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1791.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1805.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les justiciables, fort heureusement, sont dispensés de l'obligation d'épuiser les recours internes qui ne sont ni adéquats ni effectifs compte tenu des faits de leur cause.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1805.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1828.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Depuis le début, c'est-à-dire à partir du moment qu'ils avaient compris que les textes adoptés en janvier 2008 par le gouvernement ne seraient étendus à tous les réservistes, les requérants ont évoqué en substance le grief tiré de la discrimination devant tout d'abord le tribunal de première instance de Niège et ensuite devant la cour d'appel de Niège.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1828.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1842.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ils avaient demandé rien d'autre que d'être mis par le gouvernement sur un pied d'égalité avec les réservistes bénéficiant du texte du janvier 2008 et de se voir payer les mêmes indemnités perdues que ces dernières.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1842.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1862.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais, avouons-le, cela aurait coûté beaucoup d'argent à l'État, et l'occasion s'est présentée au juge serbe rescapé de la réforme judiciaire en Serbie en 2009, jugé illégal depuis, de servir les intérêts du gouvernement qui les avait épargnés du limogé sec comme les autres.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1862.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1879.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les juridictions intercités ont complètement ignoré l'objet des demandes des requérants et systématiquement jugé que les craintes des requérants et des autres réservistes étaient prescrites sans faire aucun cas de la discrimination évoquée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1879.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1915.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>S'il est vrai que les requérants n'ont pas attendu que la Cour constitutionnelle tranche sur les recours interdités le 21 janvier 2011, et ont saisi votre recours déjà le 14 février 2011, on ne pourrait pas les reprocher, surtout eu égard aux décisions citées dans les paragraphes 29, 31, 32 de l'arrêt du 28 2012, mais aussi à celles rendues par la Cour constitutionnelle serbe après le 28 2012, et surtout à la décision rendue sur le recours des requérants eux-mêmes le 5 décembre 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1915.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1945.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les six juges de votre deuxième chambre l'ont déjà dit le 28 2012, mais aujourd'hui, au vu des décisions rendues par la Cour constitutionnelle dans les dossiers des réservistes évoquant la discrimination après cette date, il ne subsiste aucun doute que le recours dit ou Stellenjalba s'est avéré purement théorique dans le système juridique de la Serbie, étant donné le contexte juridique et politique dans lequel il se situe, ainsi que la situation personnelle des réservistes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1945.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1968.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La décision du 5 décembre 2012 versée au débat renvoie pour les motifs à une autre décision, à savoir celle rendue le 7 novembre 2012, dans un dossier où Stellenjalba, 20 ans 56 11, dans lequel les demandaires ont sollicité la protection de la discrimination qu'ils avaient subie de la part de l'État.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1968.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1988.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tout comme les requérants dans le dossier devant vous, ces individus ont versé au débat devant la Cour constitutionnelle les textes de nature discriminatoire adoptés par le gouvernement serbe en janvier 2008, ayant pour effet de payer les indemnités per diem à un groupe de réservistes arbitrairement désigné par l'État.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1988.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2021.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous verrez dans les motifs de ces décisions que la Cour constitutionnelle s'est contente de dire qu'il n'y a pas de prêve de discrimination évoquée et que pour décider ainsi, elle prenait en compte l'arrêt Vucicovic et autres du 28 novembre 2012, mais comme la Cour européenne a jugé que l'État avait violé l'interdiction de discrimination sur le fondement qui diffère de celui du présent recours, elle rejette la partie du recours fondé sur la discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2021.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2044.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans une décision postérieure, à savoir Oustama Njaalba 43, 2011, rendue le 21 mars 2013, la Cour constitutionnelle adopte la même méthodologie que dans l'affaire concernant les requérants et renvoie pour les motifs à une autre décision, à savoir Oustama Njaalba 2886, 2010, du 4 octobre 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2044.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2058.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans cette dernière décision, vous trouverez copiée, collée, la même formule que dans la décision précitée Oustama Njaalba 2156, 2011, pour rejeter la demande fondée sur la discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2058.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2070.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La même formule se trouve également dans les décisions Oustama Njaalba 649 et les deux de 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2070.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2082.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et on peut espérer malheureusement qu'on trouverait cette formule magique dans toutes les décisions de la Cour constitutionnelle concernant les réservistes, si nous nous trouvons dans la même situation que nos clients.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2082.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2094.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il est évident que les décisions de la Cour constitutionnelle ne redressent en rien les greffes évoquées par les requérants devant vous.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2094.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2116.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Un recours effectif, à la différence de celui que les requérants et les autres réservistes discriminés avaient pu exercer devant la Cour constitutionnelle, leur aurait permis de se trouver dans la même situation que les réservistes auxquels l'État a payé les indemnités per diem en vertu des textes du janvier 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2116.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2132.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, il est clair que la Cour constitutionnelle, même dans les cas où elle constate les différences dans les traitements respectifs des justiciables, en l'occurrence des réservistes, ordonne comme réparation la publication de l'arrêt dans le journal officiel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2132.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2154.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Au demeurant, on peut légitimement se demander si la Cour constitutionnelle aurait du tout abordé le greffe tiré de la discrimination évoquée devant elle par les réservistes, si votre Cour n'avait pas jugé l'affaire de nos clients et si elle n'avait pas constaté la violation de l'interdiction de la discrimination commise par le gouvernement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2154.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2207.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>À mon sens, la production accélérée des décisions en majorité, sans motif et avec des formules toutes faites par la Cour constitutionnelle, n'est qu'une preuve de plus que cette juridiction se comporte trop souvent comme un bras prolongé de l'exécutif au lieu de protéger les droits fondamentaux des citoyens serbes et que le recours dit « oust en Ajaba » n'est pas un recours effectif, pour le moins dans les affaires sensibles, où l'exécutif tente, comme ici, de s'exonérer de ses obligations pécuniaires envers les citoyens ou dans d'autres affaires pendantes également devant votre cours, de s'égérer illégalement dans l'exercice des droits des citoyens serbes protégés par la Convention européenne sur les droits de l'homme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2208.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2214.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Carić.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2219.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2221.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2221.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2227.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, respondents for all submissions will tackle three issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2227.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2230.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Background of the case, the admissibility, and merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2230.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2233.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me start with a short introduction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2233.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2242.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This dispute derives from the applicant's dissatisfaction with the manner in which the government resolved the position of war veterans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2242.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2253.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the still applicable regulation in the Republic of Serbia, certain benefits have been recognized to war veterans only in cases they have the status of war-desailed persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2253.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2259.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It must be admitted, the state had indeed partially resolved the status of war veterans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2259.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2269.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Certain rights have been recognized at various levels and mostly in certain territory related to social benefits at the level of local self-governments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2269.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2279.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of this causes cumulative dissatisfaction of a large number of persons who have been engaged in military operations on the occasion of tragic events in the 19th of last century.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2279.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2304.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On this occasion, the respondent would like to present the events which had initiated the dispute, expressing its regret for the occurrence and reminding that the circumstances concerning the status of war reservists have been slowly settling down, as well as that it has been actively working on establishing systemic solutions to govern the status of war veterans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2304.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2319.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this sense, in cooperation with the veterans and their associations, a new law on care for participants in war has been in the process of adoption, which will recognize the rights to all those who have participated in the war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2319.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2325.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The NATO bombing of Yugoslavia in 1999 was a military operation during the war in Kosovo and Matochia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2325.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2331.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The strikes lasted precisely for 78 days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2331.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2339.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the purpose of defense in the territory of Yugoslavia, including Montenegro, the army has drafted civilians to military service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2339.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2352.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the data provided by the Ministry of Defense, over 200,000 people were drafted to military service in the territory of the Republic of Serbia from March to June 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2352.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2357.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The relevant per diems for military assignments were not originally prescribed by law for reservists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2357.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2362.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were established during the war according to the decision of the military headquarters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2362.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2373.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The concrete amount of per diems slightly varied in the given period, and it amounted, on average, to 10 German marks daily.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2373.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2387.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Payments of relevant per diems were affected during the war and later because, pursuant to the decision of the government and due to the lack of funds, a part of payments was paid off in six installments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2387.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2396.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As from 1st August 1999, all per diems were affected in the course of 1999 and 2000.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2396.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2403.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent has submitted evidence for each of 30 applicants regarding the payment of per diems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2403.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2418.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The report of the Ministry of Defense contains the data on payment of the amount of nowadays over 340 million euros on the account of paid per diems in regard of against during the 1919 war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2418.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2434.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Records of payment of per diems were kept under aggravating conditions because of the state of war and large number of people in the field, very often in inaccessible areas without possibility to leave military position they were assigned to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2434.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2443.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Payments were affected in different ways, as possible under the given circumstances, sometimes via mediator, sometimes with delay.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2443.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2452.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the reason of minor irregularities in respect of evidence of payments to the applicants and serious difficulties in gathering the evidences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2452.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2458.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the respondent has submitted evidence on affected payments to all 30 applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2458.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2462.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there is no doubt they have all received payments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2462.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2467.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We underline that is not here about partial payments of per diems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2467.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2469.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have been paid in full.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2469.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2475.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is only difficult in some cases to evidence every individual payment for objective reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2475.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2483.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Realizing this failure together with all other objective difficulties, we refer to force majeure as the reason to justify some omissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2483.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2496.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if there were any conflict in Europe for the last 50 years to be an excuse for precise enforcement of administration, it is by all means the conflict in the course of 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2496.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2504.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both the relevant reports and the claims by some reservists proved that the payment had indeed been affected in full.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2504.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2514.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To contribute to this, we are kindly asking honorable judges to view one of attachments provided by the applicants in their submissions to the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2514.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2534.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a press clipping in which one of the leaders of the reservists says that per diems had indeed been paid, and that the problem was with the domestic courts and their practice of avoiding certain amounts of money, what implies the problem concerning Article 6.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2534.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2545.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, let me remind you that the court declared the application inadmissible by its judgment of August 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2545.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2552.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have translated parts of material concern into English and submitted them for review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2552.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2559.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is important to say that this evidence was provided by the opposing party.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2559.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2577.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent has not been able to establish exactly how many days each of 30 applicants stayed at the front line, and therefore how many per diems they have earned without the number of military service records for each individual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2577.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2591.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Copies of the military service history of the applicants were not available because they were submitted by applicants only with their latest observation, and even then partially not for all of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2591.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2601.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is important to note the military service records were signed only for the whole period during which the mobilization lasted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2601.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2605.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no evidence of absences for weekends and days off.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2605.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2615.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such evidence was kept only in the war diaries by the officers of particular military unit for each of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2615.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2625.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A necessary condition for daily compensation was the presence in the unit for 24 hours, as the opposing party said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2625.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2633.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is assumed that the most of the reservists had some leave, which is standard practice because they are civilians, mainly family people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2633.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2644.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, at this point, it cannot be determined to how many of war per diems exactly each of the applicants had the right to, and therefore any, regularities in payments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2644.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2648.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, this should be a question for domestic courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2648.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2655.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent is of the opinion that all per diems are paid to all reservists by the Ministry of Defense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2655.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2665.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a logical question to ask now, how did the dispute concerning so-called per diems arise then?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2665.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2676.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the respondent's opinion, the motive of the reservist dissatisfaction is quite realistic, as the state did not succeed in finding a model to satisfy adequately the person's concern.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2676.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2690.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the cause of protest presents an abuse of rights by some individuals to receive a large amount of material benefits by enforced payments, abusing judicial procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2690.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2704.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some courts have even avoided compensation for participation in the war conflicts in very high amounts, which naturally caused envy with their war colleagues, encouraging them to request the same for themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2704.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2711.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Ministry of Defense initiated proceedings against those who had collected double per diems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2711.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2720.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, the documentation submitted by the applicants includes the judgments confirming the claims of the respondent on abuse of court proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2720.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2736.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, on January 2013, the Basic Court in Valjeva adopted a default judgment due to absence against the state based on the plaintiff's claim that he had not been paid per diems for 95 days of his participation in the 1990 war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2736.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2744.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is an interesting detail, since the war conflict concern lasted for 78 days exactly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2744.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2751.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any case, this first instant judgment may not represent the domestic case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2751.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2762.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is just an example of abuse of procedural legal powers to collect ill-founded payments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2762.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2769.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The representative of the Ministry of Defense had not appeared before the courts referring to the objection on absolute statute of limitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2769.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2775.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The role of Ministry of Defense in the negotiation with the strike committees was clear from the beginning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2775.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2778.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They always claimed that the per diems were paid off.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2778.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2782.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They neither signed the agreement nor affected any payments on this ground.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2782.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2795.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants' claim on acknowledgment of the debt by the establishment of the working group and the government's conclusion on 17 January 2008 are arbitrary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2795.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2798.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no explicit statement of the officials.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2798.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2806.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Other acts of direct or indirect actions that can prove the government had acknowledged the debt on per diems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2806.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2814.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that the government wanted to examine these reservist claims could not be taken as a recognition of the debt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2814.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2823.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the 2008 agreement, financial support was granted to the municipalities, which are among the least developed areas in the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2823.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2843.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the data of the Department for Statistics, the average salary in 2008, as well as in 2012, in the municipalities covered by the agreement was lower than the national average and the average for the regions of southern and eastern Serbia, generally the poorest regions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2843.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2849.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The evidences are presented with the government's submissions of 19 April.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2849.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2860.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Madam and Mr. Judge,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2860.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2883.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>these are based on four reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2883.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2900.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government had already stated this reason as a reason for the lack of accountability in the request to the House of Commons, after having made it clear the implementation of the payment of the per diem indemnity of the claimant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2900.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2905.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The claimant's claim is based on the claim of debt for the per diem indemnity in P.A.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2905.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2913.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In their request, they insist on the fact that it is a debt in P.A. or a use of the debt</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2913.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2917.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the internal procedure, respectively.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2917.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2923.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is from this claim that the other demands on discrimination are based in front of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2923.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2931.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these written observations, the government states that the per diem indemnities were paid to the claimant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2931.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2947.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was difficult to register each individual payment, but the fact that the per diem indemnities were paid to all the reservists in the territory of Serbia under the same conditions is unquestionable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2947.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2960.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reservist payments in some municipalities in accordance with the 2008 agreement may not be per diem indemnities, but by their nature, if already paid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2960.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2972.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relation to the agreement, the claimant claims the right to what does not belong to them, which is not prescribed by the law or by a court order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2972.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2985.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their claim of property rights, also mentioned in the court order, which were contested, are based on a debt resulting from their per diem indemnity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2985.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3001.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is obvious that the claimant did not inform the Court of Bonafide on the fact concerning the payment of per diem indemnities, namely that the payments could not remain unknown to the claimant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3001.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3009.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that the per diem indemnities were paid by the government deprives the claimant of the status of a victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3009.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3013.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the claim must be rejected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3013.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3034.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the report addressed to the House and in response to the additional question of the Court, the government has stated that the claimant did not comply with all the internal recourse laws which were at their disposal in terms of protection against discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3034.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3057.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In regard to the internal procedure, the claimants have filed a case concerning the debt before the municipal court, which has been rejected as unacceptable due to the prescription, since the delay prescribed by the law of three and five years had expired before the claimant was addressed to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3057.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3062.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This decision was confirmed by the Court of the Second Instance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3062.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3067.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The courts did not examine this claim and it was deemed unacceptable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3067.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3078.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In regard to constitutional protection, the constitutional recourse of the claimant corresponds well to Article 6 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3078.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3100.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition to the decision of the Constitutional Court, the courts have contested the constitutional rights of the claimant to equal protection in virtue of Article 36, paragraph 1 of the Constitution and have determined that it was a matter of fair satisfaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3100.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3110.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the question of discrimination was not considered in this decision because it was not even discussed in the recourse of the claimant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3110.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3124.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The principle of juranovic curia does not apply to the procedure before the Constitutional Court because in virtue of Article 36, paragraph 1.7 of the Constitutional Court Law,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3124.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3134.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Constitutional Court examines only the violations of constitutional rights alleged in the constitutional recourse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3134.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3166.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just as they have demanded the Commissioner's opinion on the protection of equality, the claimant could have filed a discrimination action in the context of civil proceedings and, in accordance with Article 43 of the Law against Discrimination, seek to overcome the consequences of discriminatory treatment, to demand compensation for the material and moral damage inflicted, etc.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3166.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3169.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The law provides for these possibilities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3169.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3180.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An action concerning discrimination, apart from the claimant, could also be filed by the Commissioner or the Association of War Reservists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3180.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3189.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In accordance with the law, this procedure is urgent and the appeal to the Supreme Court is always authorized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3189.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3199.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, no one has filed an action on this basis, although this possibility is always at their disposal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3199.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3207.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have said that the claimants have not used all the internal recourse laws to the research protection of discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3207.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3230.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The claimants have made their observations in the Grand Chamber, in paragraph 25, in the absence of arguments corroborated by the evidence on the non-payment of claims of lost indemnity, that the courts have served their corrupt dependent and political leaders of the moment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3230.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3233.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This position is contradictory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3233.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3237.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Governments certainly do not corrupt the courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3237.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3253.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to support the allegations concerning the compatibility of the material and moral damage inflicted with the Convention, governments must remind that the following arguments suggest that the payment to the courts was not considered as lost indemnity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3253.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3259.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the position of the Ministry of Defence regarding the internal procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3259.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3265.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Ministry relied on the fact that these claims were obsolete.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3265.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3279.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, given the circumstances, all have valid proof of payment in the form of a pay bulletin for each claimant, eight or nine years after the payment was made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3279.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3293.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is not a task that it would be reasonable to expect from the Ministry of Defence in such a short time and for such a large number of claimants at the same time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3293.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3296.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the procedures before the National Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3296.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3317.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Governments have presented evidence in the form of a bulletin from the Court indicating that there was payment of lost indemnity, which indisputably demonstrates the payment of war indemnity, contrary to the claims of claimants that it had not been paid at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3317.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3321.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, the two amounts do not correspond.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3321.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3331.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The amount paid to the reservists in the affected municipalities does not correspond to the amount of daily allocations planned for the reservists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3331.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3337.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first amount is a few times higher than the amount that followed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3337.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3349.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why would the government lose a higher amount than it should if we assume that it recognizes the debt and intends to repay it?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3349.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3355.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why is this debt not paid by the Department of Defence?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3355.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3360.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why is it a third party's obligation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3360.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3368.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some arguments show that the payment under the agreement could be considered as social allocation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3368.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3381.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is a law on social assistance for the allocation of a single aid in the extreme case of a threat to the standard of living for a large number of citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3381.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3393.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This represents the type of social assistance for a group when each individual is not obliged to pay a proof of indigence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3393.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3405.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Governments, in cooperation with the municipalities, can decide, according to their financial capacity, to establish other rights within the framework of social protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3405.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3419.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the case in the event of a natural disaster in a particular region, or in regions that face problems arising from multi-ethnic and poverty-stricken areas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3419.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3433.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the one hand, the municipalities that received this assistance are among the most underdeveloped, poor and specific in the sense of their geographical location and current geopolitical events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3433.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3443.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, there is a specific situation that applies to the consequences of war on these territories, as well as security problems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3443.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3449.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not all parts of the state's territory are as important as they are in terms of security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3449.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3457.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>States have a margin of appreciation in order to define priorities in the field of security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3457.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3469.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Governments have explained in detail why the claim of the Requiem does not correspond to a violation of Article 1 of Protocol No. 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3469.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3482.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By observing the court's jurisprudence, we find a case with certain similarities where the court has faced the violation of Article 1 of Protocol No. 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3482.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3486.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the case of the LAS against Croatia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3486.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3496.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the case of a claim for compensation for the work of a military soldier.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3496.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3503.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Between our case and the mentioned cases, we can make a clear distinction between the two cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3503.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3509.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The payment of compensation and the recognition of the debt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3509.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3524.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In certain circumstances, it is understood that Serbia could not be held more responsible at an international level, and the request is therefore also irrevocable in terms of the matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3524.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3536.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honourable Judges, With regard to the merits of the case, the ultimate question in this case relates to Protocol 12 and general prohibition of discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3536.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3562.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Respondent will try to complement its previous statements that even if the facts of the case fall inside the scope of the Convention provisions, there is still no discrimination because there are no grounds for such a claim and there is an objective justification for measures taken by the Government towards the reservists in the underdeveloped municipalities that pursue a legitimate aim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3562.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3570.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are very clear reasons leading the Government to a conclusion of the 2008 Agreement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3570.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3579.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it was explained in detail in paragraph 68 of the written observation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3579.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3585.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, the reservists are not professional soldiers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3585.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3592.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They just spend some time performing military service and their rights could only derive from that fact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3592.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3601.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the basis for unjustified distinction may only be sought in connection with the exercise of their rights in relation to military engagement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3601.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3607.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the war per diems had been paid, there is no basis for claims of discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3607.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3633.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The arguments of the Commissioner for Protection of Equality upheld in the Chamber's judgment that the payments under the Agreement were clear war per diems because of requirement waiver of claims for unpaid per diems and the protesters were not required to submit any evidence in favour of their financial status, are contrary to the evidence presented.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3633.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3640.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, the Agreement was a kind of settlement of disputes between the strike committees and the Government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3640.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3650.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Waiving of claims was part of the deal, not because the Government acknowledged the debt, but to avoid further proceedings due to double payments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3650.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3665.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the financial ad was aimed to improve economic position of citizens in certain municipalities, not as an individual social right to each indigent person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3665.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3683.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, the Convention and the protocols thereto place no restriction on the contracting state's freedom to decide whether or not to have in place any form of social security scheme, or to choose the type or amount of benefits to provide under any such scheme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3683.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3696.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In cases concerning a complaint on discrimination in conjunction with property right that has been denied, the relevant test is whether they would have had a right enforceable under domestic law to receive the benefit in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3696.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3704.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the principle established in the case Stek, in the Grand Chamber judgment E.B. versus France,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3704.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3708.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Carson and others versus the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3708.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3714.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in the present case, there is no enforceable right denied to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3714.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3728.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the understanding of Protocol 12 implies that any case of discrimination must still relate to the enjoyment of any right set forth by law in order to be justiciable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3728.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3735.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the opinion of the respondent, the right under the agreement is not a right set forth by law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3735.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3741.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is an agreement between the Government and the strike committees in order to provide aid to certain municipalities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3741.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3745.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The agreement did not create an enforceable right for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3745.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3772.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As stated in explanatory report on Protocol 12, paragraph 16, the fact that there are certain groups or categories of person who are disadvantaged, or the existence of de facto inequalities, may constitute justification for adopting measures providing for specific disadvantages in order to promote equality, provided that the proportionality principle is respected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3772.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3785.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that the protocol does certainly leave the member state with sufficient leeway to adopt measures of positive action or preferential treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3785.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3796.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In regards of place of residence as a ground for alleged discrimination, the Court has examined under Article 14 various cases with the distinction drawn.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3796.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3804.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent repeats that only the case of McGee versus the United Kingdom treats the issue of regional differences as personal characteristics.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3804.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3813.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Court held in paragraph 50 of this judgment, such a difference does not amount to discriminatory treatment within the meaning of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3813.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3823.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following the same logic in the present case, the applicants' claims for discrimination on the basis of residence in different municipalities is manifestly ill-founded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3823.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3843.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, no property rights of the applicants have been violated in the sense of non-payment of per diems, for they stay on the front line in 1999, and they have not been placed in an equal situation based on agreement, because their position were not similar and it is groundless.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3843.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3850.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They identify themselves with those who had been granted aid according to the agreement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3850.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3857.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What we got here are not 30 reservists who had lodged this application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3857.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3875.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are talking, as also deemed by the Court in its judgment of 2 August 2012, in paragraph 96, about the right of all those entitled reservists in Serbia who had not received per diems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3875.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3899.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is undisputable that they all have the right to sort their rights before the courts or to negotiate with the government better position for themselves and to request better living conditions, but the claims about non-equal payment of per diems are manifestly ill-founded for all the above-mentioned reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3899.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3917.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lastly, the government would like to reiterate that it deeply regrets for the conflict with its citizens who participated in the 1919 war and will do everything in its power to improve the situation of these people and provide adequate solutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3917.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3934.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, it does not want to accept the responsibility for violations of human rights of a large number of its citizens in the case that is not clearly based on the facts as they are presented in the judgment of the Court from last August.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3934.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3952.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the Respondent proposed to Honourable Grand Chamber to render a new judgment in accordance with the submitted evidences and findings in this hearing and to hold the Republic of Serbia not responsible for human rights violations in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3952.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3964.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honourable Judges, thank you for your attention and we remain to the Honourable Court for any further clarification and questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3964.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3964.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3967.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3968.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your interventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3968.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3977.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would now like to invite the judges of the Grand Chamber to put any questions they may have to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3977.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3977.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Villiger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Mark Villiger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3983.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3985.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3985.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3988.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would wish to put a question to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3988.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3992.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It concerns the per diem allowance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3992.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4004.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to know more about the nature and the purpose of the per diem allowances paid to soldiers, reservists, in the Serb army.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4004.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4013.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are the per diem allowances of a salarial nature, or are they intended more as a compensation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4013.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4017.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, a compensation for what?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4017.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4017.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4019.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4024.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Hirvelä, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4026.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4028.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4028.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4033.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a clarifying question, I put the question to the both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4033.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4037.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is actually the legal basis for the requested per diem?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4037.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4051.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it the rules on travel and other expenses in the Yugoslav army and decision adopted by the chief of staff of the Yugoslav army?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4051.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4058.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or is it the agreement which was concluded in 11th January 2008?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4062.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4064.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that's my question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4064.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4073.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if the answer is that they are both, so which was the legal basis for the agreement?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4074.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4076.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Were these two rules?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4078.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4079.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a clarification, thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4079.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4079.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4080.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4082.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Ziemele.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4084.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4086.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4086.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4101.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To follow up on Judge Hirvelä's questions, we heard also now in the submissions, especially of the government, if the applicants could try systematically to answer to the following questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4101.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4111.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, are you maintaining that the per diems in 1999 were not paid to you?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4111.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4124.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why, if they were not paid at that time, why did you choose to go to the first instance court only in 2008?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4124.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4149.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, are you saying that 2008 agreement recognized that debt in payment of the per diems, or are you saying that this is a new or additional financial aid to which you should also be entitled to?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4149.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4169.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And a sort of a small question, do you actually agree that the municipalities that are part of the agreement are of a particular need in financial aid, are indeed those that are particularly poor in Serbia?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4169.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4169.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4171.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4172.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Popović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Dragoljub Popović</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4177.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4179.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4179.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4182.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, I have a question to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4182.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4193.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Could the applicants specify the number of days spent in the army during the critical period, that is for each and every one of them?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4193.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4200.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I have a question to the government and another one which occurred to me during the oral hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4202.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4217.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question is, could the government provide evidence on the exact dates and amounts of the transfers from the state budget to the municipalities enumerated in the agreement of January 2008?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4218.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4239.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question is, and I'm provoked by the intervention of the government agent because he put forward the idea of providing adequate solutions from the government to the reservists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4239.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4252.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I kindly ask the government agent to specify what way and manner would they be satisfied and what sort of solution is envisaged by the government?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4252.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4252.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4253.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4256.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4256.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4262.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moi, également, j'ai une question à poser aux deux parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4262.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4271.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nous avons dans le dossier 3 arrêts de la Cour constitutionnelle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4272.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4285.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nous avons notamment l'arrêt qui a été rendu par la Cour constitutionnelle après l'arrêt de Chambre, c'est-à-dire l'arrêt de la Cour constitutionnelle du 5 décembre 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4287.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4299.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans cet arrêt, la Cour constitutionnelle rappelle que les requérants ont invoqué l'article 36 de la Constitution, n'est-ce pas?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4300.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4334.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans un arrêt qui a été rendu antérieurement à cet arrêt de décembre 2012, à savoir en date du 17 février 2011, la Cour constitutionnelle se prononce sur l'article 21 de la Constitution en rappelant que cette disposition de l'article 21 n'est pas autonome et qu'elle doit être combinée avec une autre disposition de la Constitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4334.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4363.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ouvrant la Constitution, on constate que, indépendamment des dispositions concernant le principe de non-discrimination, je pense aux articles 32, 36 et 21 de la Constitution, d'autres dispositions consacrent des droits analogues à ceux protégés par la Convention et par le protocole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4363.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4375.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et je me réfère notamment à l'article 58 de la Constitution, le droit de propriété, ou l'article 69 de la Constitution, le droit à la protection sociale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4377.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4378.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ma question est très simple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4379.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4386.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce que les requérants ont invoqué, dans la présente affaire, l'article 21 de la Constitution?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4387.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4400.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et je voudrais que les deux parties se prononcent sur la portée de l'arrêt de la Cour constitutionnelle qui a été rendue après l'arrêt de Chambre, et notamment dans le contexte de l'épuisement des voies de recours internes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4400.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4402.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4404.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4408.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there are no other questions from my colleagues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4408.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4428.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to inform you that the Court will now rise for 20 minutes, following which the parties will return for a second round of short pleadings to respond to the submissions in the first round and to the judges' questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4428.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4429.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'audience est levée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4498.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4499.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4541.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4542.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4542.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4547.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is now resumed. I call Mr. Aleksić or Mrs. Isailović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4547.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4552.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maître vous avez la parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4552.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4554.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Oui, merci, M. le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4554.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4603.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On va essayer de vraiment rapidement aller en besoin, mais tout d'abord, je souhaiterais apporter quelques réponses, répliques plutôt, à ce qui a été dit aujourd'hui devant vous par le gouvernement, qui nous parlait ici, encore une fois, des abus, des schémas d'abus, donc, toutes sortes de complots contre le gouvernement et ses fonds, mais il faut rappeler, encore une fois, qu'on ne peut pas reprocher quand même aux requérants, qui sont des simples citoyens, de ne pas mieux organiser les paiements sur place par un Etat qui a décidé, donc, d'aller en guerre contre l'OTAN.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4603.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4627.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ils étaient simples soldats, simples, disons, des gens qui ont quitté leur domicile pour aller combattre contre l'OTAN pour son pays, pour leur pays, et donc, on ne peut pas les reprocher aujourd'hui de ne pas mieux organiser le paiement des indemnisations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4627.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4645.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Encore devant vous et dans votre dossier, on nous a versé une pièce 21, donc, il devrait, selon les dires du gouvernement, représenter une preuve sérieuse sur les motifs des protestations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4645.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4658.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, on nous offre ici une interview d'on ne sait pas qui, de la presse, et on nous offre une traduction rapide de quelques phrases choisies par le gouvernement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4658.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4665.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je pense que tout ça, vraiment, n'est pas sérieux vu le problème qui est devant vous aujourd'hui.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4667.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4670.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et encore, donc, mais cela va...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4671.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4680.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ca se reproche à une question qui a été posée concernant, donc, les jugements de la Cour constitutionnelle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4680.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4697.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et encore, donc, nous, on maintient, donc, l'exception qui concerne, donc, les listes de paiement versées au débat par le gouvernement très tardivement, parce que ce n'était pas versé devant la Première chambre, on peut se demander pourquoi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4698.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4705.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et mon confrère, devant vous, est largement, je pense, expliqué quels peuvent être les motifs, parce que nous, on n'en sait rien.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4705.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4720.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, on représente les requérants, les simples citoyens, et c'est l'Etat qui, dans ce cas, a toutes les listes, a toutes les preuves, et nous verse, petit à petit, donc, devant la Première chambre, des preuves complètement d'une autre nature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4720.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4738.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Après, il nous verse les listes de paiement, donc, et attend qu'on leur croie sur parole que vraiment, c'était ces listes, donc, et nos clients contestent les signatures, contestent les montants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4739.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4752.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ils ne contestent pas qu'ils n'étaient pas du tout payés mais les listes du gouvernement étaient préparées et nous, on les soutient pour vous et pour les verser aussi tardivement dans les débats.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4753.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4774.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et maintenant, donc, je vais commencer, tout d'abord, toute seule, et peut-être que j'aurai besoin de quelques éclaircissements de la part de mon confrère, qui était avocat des requérants devant les juridictions internes, parce qu'il y a quand même des questions qui touchent un petit peu cette procédure interne.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4774.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4782.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, la 1re question de M. le juge Marc Villiger,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4783.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4796.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>qui concernait, donc, la nature, si je ne me trompe, donc, la nature de ce paiement, si c'est un salaire, vu qu'il combattait sur...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4796.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4801.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>donc, en vertu de la loi sur la mobilisation, ou d'une compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4802.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4836.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, on ne peut pas aujourd'hui, parce qu'on a les textes dans le dossier qui prévoyaient, donc, le paiement, mais, logiquement, il ne peut s'agir que d'une compensation, vu que c'était les gens qui étaient levés, disons, pour la défense du pays contre l'intervention de l'OTAN, et donc, pris dans leur bureau, sur leurs champs, dans leurs usines qui marchaient à cette époque en Serbie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4836.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4854.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et, naturellement, donc, ils avaient droit à une compensation, comme dans tous les pays, si on fait quelque chose qui vous éloigne de vos sources de vie, de vos revenus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4854.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4859.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concernant... Je vais essayer vraiment</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4859.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4863.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>de reproduire les questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4863.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4877.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, la 2e question était posée sur le fondement juridique des demandes devant les juridictions internes, et donc, par la suite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4877.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4885.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et c'était, donc, posé par le juge Agiel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4887.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4893.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Justement, il y avait des deux, et on a essayé d'expliquer ça dans nos écritures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4894.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4907.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il y avait ce règlement qui prévoyait, donc, le paiement des compensations, mais, après, il y avait l'accord.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4907.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4916.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et un des juges nous a posé la question qui se recoupe un petit peu avec celle-ci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4916.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4922.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pourquoi, donc, on les a assignées seulement en 2010?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4923.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4998.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je pense que c'était la 3e intervention des juges qui se recoupe un petit peu, et qui, pour se placer dans l'histoire, donc, il y avait l'intervention de l'OTAN, il y avait une catastrophe dans le pays, il y avait, donc, le changement du gouvernement Milosevic à l'époque, donc, une sorte, comme aujourd'hui, la révolution arabe, c'était une révolution contre Milosevic, entre guillemets, et, après, donc, la constitution des nouvelles autorités, qui, pour le dire clairement, s'est posée un petit peu avec, parce que les soldats qui étaient répondus présents étaient considérés un petit peu comme, si vous voulez, les gens de Milosevic qui étaient prêts à combattre l'OTAN, donc, il y avait toutes sortes de problèmes pour avoir ces indemnités payées, et, de toute façon, il y avait toujours, comme aujourd'hui en Serbie, des problèmes financiers, donc, qui ne sont pas étrangères, maintenant, aux États beaucoup plus puissants que la Serbie, et, justement, donc, les pourparlers duraient presque tout le temps à partir de 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4998.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5035.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>De 2004, donc, on a entamé les pourparlers avec les réservistes qui étaient restés impayés, et, aujourd'hui, ça peut nous sembler, donc, naïf de leur part, mais il faut comprendre les gens qui ont quelque chose dans les mains, donc, une créance contre l'État, mais, en quelque sorte, donc, ils ne peuvent pas s'opposer très fermement à cet État parce qu'on connaît, donc, toujours, entre créanciers et débitaires, donc, il y a ce rapport de force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5036.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5046.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et, là, vraiment, le gouvernement a eu toutes les forces dans ses mains, et les citoyens, comme les citoyens, donc, n'avaient rien du tout.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5046.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5099.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, donc, ils décidaient de mener ces pourparlers, et, justement, au mois de janvier 2008, parce qu'avant, il y avait des protestations qui avaient vraiment une ampleur, donc, sérieuse, le gouvernement, comme je l'ai dit tout à l'heure devant vous, donc, il a choisi, il l'a dit aussi dans le mémoire, de choisir, donc, les plus combatifs, c'était apparemment les gens de ces, soi-disant, municipalités sous-développées, qui étaient les plus combatifs, et il s'imposait à l'État, selon les dires de l'État, de calmer, donc, c'était l'intérêt public de les calmer en négociant plus avec eux qu'avec les autres réservistes qui étaient aussi impayés que les premiers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5099.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5114.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et là, donc, on a cet accord, et nos clients, d'une façon officieuse, ont pris la signature, et ont entamé à nouveau les protestations pour avoir les mêmes droits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5114.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5150.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, il est clair aussi, dans les demandes devant les juridictions internes, qu'ils se basent, et sur les textes de 1999, qui prévoyaient le paiement des compensations des indemnités, et aussi sur les accords, parce qu'à notre vie juridiquement, la discrimination, justement, repose sur cela, parce qu'on a deux groupes qui sont traités différemment, mais qui sont strictement en même position par rapport à l'État.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5151.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5156.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et c'est pour cela, donc, qu'on a choisi les deux fondements juridiques pour les demandes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5156.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5158.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Après aussi, on nous a...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5159.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5166.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Peut-être que ce n'était pas vraiment à l'ordre, mais les deux questions se rapprochaient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5168.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5170.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Après, donc, M. le juge Popovit,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5170.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5179.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>justement, de la Serbie, qui connaît cette situation mieux, peut-être, que les autres, parce qu'il a vécu quelques années...</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5179.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5188.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maître, maître s'il vous plaît, je vous signale que votre temps de réplique de dix minutes est déjà expiré. Je vous demanderai de répondre aux questions et de conclure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5188.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5190.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Non, non, non, je réponds aux questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5193.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5206.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maître, en dénant le temps qui vous est imparti, c'est-à-dire 10 minutes, et je vous signale que le temps est déjà expiré, donc je vous prie de répondre aux questions dans un temps qui ne devrait pas dépasser 2 minutes, s'il vous plaît.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5207.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5216.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ah oui, mais il me reste 4e question du juge pour vous, combien ils étaient payés pour épargner votre temps aujourd'hui.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5216.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5236.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, j'ai la liste exacte de paiements, mais c'est dans votre dossier, parce que c'est le jugement de première instance de niche qui a justement mis pour chacun des requérants les dates exactes de participation dans les combats contre l'OTAN.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5236.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5241.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et votre question, M. le Président,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5241.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5246.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>par rapport à la Constitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5246.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5255.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Malheureusement, donc, le maître Aleksis n'a pas évoqué l'article 21 dans sa demande devant le...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5255.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5270.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais peu importe, dans la décision que j'ai citée déjà, c'est Oustamne Jalba, 20 ans 56, 2011, qui était rédigé aussi par M. Aleksis</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5270.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5281.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>pour un autre groupe de réservistes, donc qui était strictement la même, donc le même texte que pour les requérants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5281.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5302.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans la décision de la Cour constitutionnelle, on peut trouver que, et c'est pas exact, donc c'est aussi une réplique par rapport à ce qui a été dit par le gouvernement, c'est pas vrai que la Cour constitutionnelle ne peut pas se saisir d'une question si elle a dans son dossier les éléments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5302.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5317.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, dans ce dossier que je viens de citer, la Cour constitutionnelle s'est saisie de la question de la discrimination et justement, il a répondu de la façon que j'ai déjà citée devant vous.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5317.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5324.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais l'article 21 n'était pas cité dans la Jalba des requérants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5324.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5327.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est juste, je pense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5328.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5330.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Ms. Isailović, I call Mr. Carić.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5335.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5338.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5338.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5345.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, let me answer the questions put by the distinguished court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5345.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5350.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Honorable Judge Villiger asked</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5350.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5356.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>concerning the salary nature of compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5356.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5374.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, per diems were originally compensation for temporary living separately from their families, for the officers and professional soldiers, as prescribed by army rules cited in paragraph 7 of written observation annex 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5374.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5399.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By decision of the chief of headquarters of 3rd April 1999, which was adopted during the 1919 war, the right to per diems was also extended to reservists who performed assignments in units under particular difficult conditions and of particularly psychophysical conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5399.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5407.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the beginning of the answer to the second question put by the distinguished Judge Steiner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5407.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5416.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I will also answer the question concerning the legal basis for agreement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5416.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5419.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The agreement is based on the decision of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5419.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5433.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Stemming from the Social Security Act, prescribing a grant of social aid to group persons in certain territories as the result of the negotiations with the strike committees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5433.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5455.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regard to the question concerning evidences put by the distinguished Judge Popovic, the government could provide evidence on the exact amounts of payments of funds transferred to each of seven municipalities from the budget.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5455.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5474.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The municipalities further distributed the funds concerned according to the criteria regulated by commission consisting of representatives of the strike committees and local self-government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5474.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5502.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning the question also put by Judge Popovic concerning the adequacy of measures, the government intends to resolve dissatisfaction of war veterans by adopting laws in cooperation with them, which will also include the right of those who had not been declared war-desailed persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5502.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5517.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The right to benefits is now only exercised by those who had certain disability, and the main request of the Resolves is to grant this right to all participants in the war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5521.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5534.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also concerning a question made by the President of the Court, Mr. Spilman, the applicant did not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5534.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5546.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>rely on Article 21 of the Constitution, and they referred to Article 36 of the Constitution, which concerned equal protection before courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5546.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5554.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Article 422, paragraph 1.11 of Civil</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5554.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5570.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Proceedings Act, a process that is finished with the final decision of the court may be reopened upon request of the party if before the constitutional court violation of human rights in civil proceedings has been found.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5570.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5592.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The provision of Article 87 of the Constitutional Court Act provides that if the human rights of a number of people are violated and some of them have filed a constitutional complaint, the decision of the constitutional court refers also to a person who did not file a constitutional appeal if they are in the same legal situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5592.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5611.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the above, it follows that the applicants had the opportunity to apply for reopening of the proceedings, not only when the constitutional court ruled proceedings on constitutional complaints filed by them, but after the constitutional court ruled concerning on appeal of claimants who were in the same legal situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5611.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5623.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any case, after the constitutional court's decision of 7 November 2012, this is the case Labu-Nikolic and others, the applicants were able to use this legal way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5623.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5635.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This conclusion is confirmed by the decision of the Supreme Court of Cassation concerning the possibility for reopening the proceedings in accordance with the above-mentioned provisions of the Civil Proceedings Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5635.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5645.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a revision decision of 9 November 2011 and 3 November 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5645.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5658.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I would like to say something about the allegations made by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5658.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5677.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the allegation of the applicants on precisely listed names and amounts of per diems being forced by the government, they are absolutely groundless because military operations do not last for 20 hours every day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5677.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5691.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government may submit certified copies of these lists to prove they had not been forged if the court insists on this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5691.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5712.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also, in this 10 minutes observations to the questions put by the court, the attorney of the applicant mentioned regime of Milosevic and the status of veterans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5712.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5717.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is untrue because three political structures were changed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5717.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5727.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the government did not recognize that in any way, as we elaborated in our previous statements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5727.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5736.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would like to thank the distinguished court for the attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5736.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5743.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And with this, we concluded our responses to the questions put by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5743.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5743.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5745.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5749.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5749.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5755.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5755.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5758.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5758.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5765.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later and the parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5765.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5767.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
