<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>1722411_31082016</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>10.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>10.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>77.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>88.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Medžlis Islamske Zajednice Brčko and others versus Bosnia and Herzegovina.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>88.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>126.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on 21st January 2011 under Article 34 of the Convention by a religious community, Brčko branch of the Islamic community of Bosnia and Herzegovina, and three non-governmental organizations from the Brčko district of Bosnia and Herzegovina, the Bošnjak Cultural Society Preporod, the Bošnjak Charity Association Merhamet, and the Council of Bošnjak Intellectuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>126.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>136.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the fourth section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52.1 of the Rules of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>136.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>145.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 13th October 2015, a chamber constituted within that section delivered a judgment in the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>145.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>163.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 8th January 2016, the applicants requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention, and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on 14th March 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>163.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>187.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On June 16th 2016, the President of the Grand Chamber granted leave to the Centre de Recherche d'Etudes sur les Droits Fondamentaux, CREDOF, and a blueprint for free speech to submit written comments as a third party by virtue of Rule 44.3 of the Rules of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>187.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>192.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by the agent, Mrs. Monika Mijić,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>192.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>196.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Mrs. Sandra Malešić, assistant agent,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>196.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>203.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and by Mr. Peđa  Đurasović and Mrs. Dragana Tešić, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>203.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>209.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mr. Osman Mulahalilović,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>209.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>216.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>lawyer practicing in Bričko, who is assisted by Mrs. Lejla Murselović,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>216.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>223.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Ibrahim Šadić, and Mr. Emir Fazlić, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>223.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>229.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Sabahudin Ravkić, on behalf of the first applicant, is also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>229.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>234.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>234.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>244.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to welcome a visiting delegation of judges from the Constitutional Court of Bosnia and Herzegovina.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>244.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>261.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages in the Court, English and French, interpreting into Bosnian has been authorized for the benefit of the delegation from Bosnia and Herzegovina.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>261.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>272.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpretation is not arranged by the Court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>272.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>283.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>283.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>288.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Murselović, for the applicants, will speak first.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>288.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>293.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then, Mrs. Mijić, for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>293.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>295.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mrs. Murselović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>295.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>295.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>299.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>310.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable President of the Chamber, Honorable Judges, Honorable Members of the team of Bosnia and Herzegovina, Honorable Interveners and other present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>310.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>314.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We will present our submission in four parts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>314.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>318.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Part one, circumstances of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>318.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>326.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We fully maintain the claims presented in the application and all submissions delivered to this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>326.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>335.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Brsko district of B&amp;H is a small local community with population of approximately 80,000.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>335.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>348.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This local community has its assembly, which passes all laws except those which are under the exclusive jurisdiction of Bosnia and Herzegovina, as in line with the constitution of Bosnia and Herzegovina.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>348.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>352.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Brsko district has a local government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>352.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>357.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The local government does not have a department in charge of judiciary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>357.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>383.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Laws in field of judiciary are proposed by the judicial commission, the members of which are the president of the basic court, the president of the appellate court, the chief prosecutor of the Brsko district prosecutor's office, the Brsko district public attorney, the head of the legal aid office, a judge of the constitutional court of Bosnia and Herzegovina and two citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>383.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>392.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, presidents of courts, judges, propose laws by which they judge after laws are adopted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>392.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>404.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judicial authorities are comprised of the basic court of Brsko as the first instance court and the appellate court of Brsko as the second and third instance court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>404.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>414.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the disputable period, Brsko was under the international supervision established on the basis of the Dayton Peace Accords for Bosnia and Herzegovina.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>414.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>420.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A panel for selection of director of the radio Brsko was set up in Brsko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>420.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>423.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Mara Zivkovic was proposed to the panel</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>423.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>426.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as a candidate for the director of the radio Brsko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>426.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>439.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant sent a letter of limited and confidential extent to the mayor of Brsko, the president of the assembly of Brsko district and to the supervisor of Brsko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>439.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>446.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In their letter, they opposed to the proposal for the selection of Mrs. Zivkovic as the director.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>446.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>450.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Zivkovic filed a lawsuit against the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>450.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>457.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In her lawsuit, she claimed that the applicants had issued a public statement in form of a letter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>457.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>468.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She requested by the defamation lawsuit to be paid the sum amounting to 50,000 convertible marks, approximately 25,000 euros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>468.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>472.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And she requested the judgment to be published in media.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>472.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>495.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In her statement before the basic court of Brsko as the first instance court, she stated that she had applied for the director, as well as that the mayor of the Brsko district annulled the vacancy notice after the disputable letter appeared and that she does not know who delivered the information from the disputable letter to the public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>495.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>498.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The basic court of Brsko rejected the lawsuit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>498.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>505.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The appellate court of Brsko as the second instance court adopted the appeal of Mrs. Zivkovic,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>505.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>508.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>opened a hearing, and examined evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>508.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>516.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court also examined the evidence which was not proposed by the parties in the proceeding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>516.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>536.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The appellate court of Brsko adopted the lawsuit for defamation compensation amounting to 2,500 convertible marks, which is approximately 1,250 euros, and ordered publishing of the judgment in media.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>536.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>547.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Based on the written evidence in the court file of the appellate court of Brsko, it can be clearly established that Mrs. Zivkovic did not apply for the position</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>547.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>548.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the director.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>548.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>555.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The mayor did not annul the vacancy notice because of the disputable letter of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>555.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>559.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants did not make the disputable letter public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>559.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>564.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They delivered the letter to the said institutions in a private correspondence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>564.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>569.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The appellate court of Brsko arbitrarily assessed the evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>569.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>577.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As in line with domestic laws, no appeal or revision can be presented against this decision of the appellate court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>577.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>587.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only legal remedy is the appeal with the Constitutional Court of Bosnia and Herzegovina as an alternative legal remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>587.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>608.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Constitutional Court of Bosnia and Herzegovina, as according to the Constitution of Bosnia and Herzegovina, has no authority to examine whether facts were arbitrarily established before the appellate court of Brsko district or whether provisions of material and procedural laws were arbitrarily applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>608.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>612.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bosnia and Herzegovina, by its constitution, is a complex state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>612.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>621.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It consisted of two entities, the Federation of Bosnia and Herzegovina and the Republic of Srpska, and of the Brsko district.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>621.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>634.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Brsko district has the basic court as the first instance court of general jurisdiction in all criminal proceedings, including even war crimes, all civil lawsuits, and administrative lawsuits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>634.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>644.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The appellate court is solely a second instance court which decides on appeals against the decisions of the first instance court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>644.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>653.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The appellate court, as a third instance court, decides on revisions against its own decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>653.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>666.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the disputable period of time, the appellate court had two judges for domain of criminal law, four judges for domain of civil and administrative lawsuits, and president of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>666.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>677.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Amendment 1 to the Constitution of Bosnia and Herzegovina, the Brsko district is under exclusive sovereignty of Bosnia and Herzegovina.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>677.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>681.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The entities have the supreme courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>681.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>686.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The supreme courts of the entities have no jurisdiction over courts in Brsko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>686.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>692.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bosnia and Herzegovina does not have a supreme court as the court of general jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>692.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>703.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bosnia and Herzegovina has the court of Bosnia and Herzegovina as a specialized criminal court and court of a very limited jurisdiction in litigation proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>703.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>711.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court of Bosnia and Herzegovina does not have the authority to reassess decisions of the appellate court of Brsko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>711.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>720.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, Bosnia and Herzegovina is not performing the judicial authorities over courts in the Brsko district.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>720.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>728.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Part 2, violation of right to fair trial under Article 6 of European Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>728.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>735.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant cited violations of the right to fair trial in their application and submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>735.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>745.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that the appellate court of the Brsko district of Bosnia and Herzegovina arbitrarily assessed the written evidence in the disputable judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>745.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>752.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The appellate court of Brsko, page 5, paragraph 3, stated that Mrs. Zivkovic applied</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>752.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>754.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for the position of the director.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>754.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>767.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Based on the letter of the Brsko district government from September 28, 2005, and attachments to that letter, the court could have established that Mrs. Zivkovic did not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>767.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>770.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>apply for the position of the director.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>770.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>781.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The letter from September 28, 2005 was in the court file of the appellate court of Brsko at the time the disputable judgment was made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>781.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>789.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The appellate court of Brsko has in its file written evidence that Mrs. Zivkovic did not apply for the position</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>789.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>796.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the director, and the disputable judgment states that she did apply for the position of the director.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>796.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>808.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its observations to the agent of Bosnia and Herzegovina, the appellate court of Brsko stated that it also assessed the disputable letter of the applicants from the aspect of the right of Mrs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>808.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>814.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Zivkovic to apply for the post for the director of the radio Brsko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>814.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>824.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Brsko district mayor, in his letter from June 13, 2016, did not state that he had annulled the vacancy notice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>824.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>833.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A letter of the government from September 28, 2005 also did not state that the vacancy notice had been annulled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>833.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>842.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants opposed the court to examine evidence ex officio during the proceeding before the appellate court of Brsko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>842.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>851.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are of the view that an unbiased tribunal should only assess proposed and examined evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>851.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>855.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The appellate court of Brsko examined evidence ex officio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>855.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>869.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the appellate court of Brsko examines evidence ex officio, then why hasn't the appellate court of Brsko acquire data on whether the vacancy notice was annulled?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>869.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>879.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It seems as if the appellate court ex officio selectively examines and acquires evidence which is in favor of Mrs. Zivkovic and does not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>879.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>884.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>acquire evidence ex officio which would be to her detriment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>884.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>892.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the explanation of the judgment, the court simply neglects written evidence which is detrimental to Mrs. Zivkovic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>892.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>904.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants believe that in this way, the appellate court of Brsko displayed biasness in passing of the judgment and arbitrarily assessed the evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>904.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>929.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would like to point out to the court the court practice in judgments Ravensburg versus Sweden from March 23, 1994, Bullut versus Austria from February 22, 1996, and Tejedor-Gracia versus Spain from December 16, 1997.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>929.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>940.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A court can review the assessment of evidence only if decisions passed by domestic courts were arbitrary or obviously unreasonable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>940.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>945.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we propose that the violation of the right to fair trial is established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>950.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>959.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Part three, violation of the right to freedom of expression under Article 10 of European Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>959.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>980.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In democratic societies, a court cannot limit the possibility of addressing by a citizen or access to institutions through private correspondence with the goal to point at social problems and irregularities in the work of certain bodies as necessary need in a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>980.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>988.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, this would result in discouragement of citizens to solve their problems in the social community.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>988.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>996.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no doubt that the state interfered with the freedom of expression by the disputed decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>996.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1004.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants believe that interference with the right to freedom of expression was not stipulated by laws.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1004.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1011.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This provision of the provision of the Article 6 of the Defamation Act is not precise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1011.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1023.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The set provision does not stipulate that one who addressed state bodies and reported irregularities cannot be held responsible for defamation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1023.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1033.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants could not reasonably expect to be punished for alleged defamation because they reported irregularities in someone's work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1033.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1046.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The provision of the Article 2 of the Defamation Act of the Brsko District protects the right to freedom of expression, which can be offensive, embittering, or disturbing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1046.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1053.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because of this, the applicants could not have reasonably expected to be punished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1053.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1066.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See Reckoning versus Hungary, application number AP35390-94 from May 20, 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1066.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1072.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants did not cause damage because they did not make the letter public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1072.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1091.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants reasonably expected that the mayor will deliver the disputable letter to the police in order to possibly check whether the information contained in the letter is correct to establish whether, for example, it is necessary to investigate if Mrs. Zivkovic had committed</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1091.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1101.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>an offense or, for example, a criminal act of provoking ethnic, racial, or religious hatred or intolerance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1101.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1113.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Verification of claims on whether an offense or criminal act has been committed is under the jurisdiction of the police or competent prosecutor's office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1113.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1118.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants had neither this authority nor capacity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1118.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1129.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are neither the police nor a prosecutor to be able to check claims on whether an offense or a criminal act has been committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1129.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1132.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are not supposed to carry out investigations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1132.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1148.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After all, the applicants noted at the end of the disputable letter that, quote, should there be no reaction by your side, end of quote, then they expect competent institutions to verify the claims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1148.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1157.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead of having the claims from the letter checked, for example, by the police, the letter was delivered to Mrs. Zivkovic, most probably</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1157.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1163.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by the mayor's office, so that she can file the lawsuit against the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1163.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1170.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Interference of the state by the said judgment is not proportional with the legitimate cause.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1170.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1181.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In democratic societies, the freedom of expression is always given an advantage before possible protection of honor and reputation of a natural person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1181.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1192.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that proportionality between the right to the freedom of expression of the applicants and the right of Mrs. Zivkovic to protection of honor</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1192.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1195.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and reputation was infringed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1195.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1221.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See Castles versus Spain judgment number AP-111798-85 from March 24, 1992, and Dalban versus Romania judgment number AP-128114-95 from September 28, 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1221.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1227.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants find that this interference was not necessary in a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1227.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1236.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are of the view that they informed persons in the authorities in public interest by the disputable letter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1236.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1243.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not proven, and the applicants did not deliver the disputable letter to media.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1243.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1253.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Does this mean that in matters of public interest, one should be silent out of fear that the information might leak to public?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1253.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1265.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the applicant's opinion, one should not be silent on matters of public interest out of fear that the information might leak to public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1265.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1276.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would especially like to point out that there is no law in the Brsko district that would protect whistleblowers who report on corruption or irregularities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1276.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1283.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants believe that checking of claims from the letter would have been in the public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1283.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1289.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The letter was private, sent to the mayor, the president of the assembly, and the supervisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1289.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1300.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case Lesnik versus Slovakia, application number 35640-97, is not compatible with this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1300.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1305.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Lesnik's case, he admitted that he gave the information to a journalist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1305.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1309.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, the applicants did not give the letter to media.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1309.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1312.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, Mrs. Zivkovic did not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1312.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1319.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>suffer any damage because of the letter since she did not apply for the position of the director.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1319.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1322.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No investigation on claims against Mrs. Zivkovic</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1322.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1329.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>has been carried out in the context of establishing whether she committed an offense or criminal act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1329.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1335.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, the claims from the letter have not been checked by the police or prosecutor's office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1335.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1341.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The investigation in Lesnik's case has been conducted and suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1341.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1367.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case is compatible with the case Syrik versus Ukraine, number AP-6428-07 from March 12, 2011, and Zakharov versus Russia, application number 47143-06 from December 4, 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1367.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1381.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In case this application is rejected, then how will this court render its judgment if, for example, the following case appears before the court?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1381.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1390.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A conscientious citizen reports on a corruption case to a mayor as the head of the executive authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1390.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1395.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same report is sent to a president of the assembly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1395.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1401.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The mayor fails to notify a chief of the police on the corruption report.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1401.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1408.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The assembly president fails to establish an ad hoc commission to investigate the corruption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1408.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1413.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No investigation is carried out after the corruption is reported.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1413.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1418.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The report leaks from their offices to media.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1418.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1424.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reported person sues the conscientious citizen for defamation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1424.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1432.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Will this court protect the person reported for corruption or the conscientious citizen?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1432.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1443.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Will this court decide, as the small chamber did in this case, or will it establish that the Article 10 of the European Convention was violated?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1443.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1458.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If this application is adopted, then citizens will be encouraged to address bodies of authorities with their reports on irregularities and corruption, and they will be certain that they will not be punished because of it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1458.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1468.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the application is not adopted, then citizens will be discouraged to report on corruption and irregularities out of fear that they will be punished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1468.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1477.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A public person is a subject to criticism and expression which can be embittering or disturbing is allowed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1477.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1487.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the practice of the European Court in case Hendryside versus United Kingdom from 1976.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1487.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1492.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We propose that the violation of the right to freedom of expression is established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1498.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1507.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Part four, violation of right to effective legal remedy under Article 13 of the European Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1507.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1514.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The right to effective legal remedy is one of key provisions of the European Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1514.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1523.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By facilitating this legal remedy, the volume of work of the European Court in Strasbourg will be reduced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1523.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1544.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The recommendation of the Committee of Ministers from 2004-6 on improvement of domestic legal remedies, the introduction of an effective domestic legal remedy represent a continuous effort of the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1544.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1549.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the declarations from Interlaken, Izmir, and Brighton.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1549.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1562.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Brighton declaration expressed determination of member states, among other things, to consider the introduction of new domestic legal remedies if necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1562.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1575.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application and petition explained the way in which the appellate court of Brcko merged the role of the first, second, and third instance courts in the contested judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1575.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1581.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the applicants had no right to an effective legal remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1581.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1603.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has been already explained that the appeal before the Constitutional Court of Bosnia and Herzegovina is not an effective legal remedy, and that the Constitutional Court has no authority to examine whether the facts have been properly established and whether procedural and material laws have been properly applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1603.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1616.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the applicants had no right to an effective legal remedy because they did not have the right to an appeal and revision following the disputable judgment of the appellate court of Brcko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1616.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1623.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nobody has examined the merits of the judgment of the appellate court of Brcko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1623.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1636.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants had no right to an effective legal remedy because this effective legal remedy, as according to domestic legislation, was neither available nor sufficient to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1636.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1644.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was already explained in the introduction in which way judges propose laws by which they judge later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1644.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1650.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Practically, judges create laws by which cases are judged.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1650.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1663.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The provision of the Article 14, item H of the law on the Judicial Commission of Brcko District of B&amp;H reads, quote, the commission performs the following duties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1663.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1685.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>H, prepares and delivers to the assembly the laws related to the organization and work of the appellate and basic court, prosecutor's office of the Brcko District, public attorney's office, and also related to regulation of work of lawyers and notaries in the district, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1685.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1694.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It seems that judges created a law which excludes the right to an effective legal remedy in the above described way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1694.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1705.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, there is no division between judicial and executive authorities in the Brcko District and as in other democratic societies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1705.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1723.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact the appellate court of Brcko in a certain way holds competencies of the constitutional court because it examines and assesses if all legal acts of the Brcko District are in line with the statute and constitution is yet another question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1723.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1738.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regards to the right to an effective legal remedy, please see the practice McFarland versus Ireland, application number 3133 slash 06 from September 10, 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1738.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1750.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>NSS versus Belgium and Greece, application number 30696 slash 09, judgment from January 21, 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1750.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1760.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Holford versus United Kingdom, application number 20605 slash 92.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1760.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1774.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Does this mean that if no effective legal remedy is provided in domestic laws and before domestic courts, then every case from the Brcko District should end up before this court?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1774.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1787.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As according to domestic laws, no court was in position to examine arbitrary findings in the judgment of the appellate court of Brcko as it was previously explained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1787.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1793.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no guarantee of rights from the European Convention if there is no Supreme Court in the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1793.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1805.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such court would enable use of effective legal remedies, ones that are meritorious, sufficient, and available in domestic legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1805.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1810.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this way, the truth in court decision would certainly be reached.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1810.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1817.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We propose that the violation of the right to an effective legal remedy is established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1817.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1828.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We propose that the court establishes violation of the rights under Articles 6, 10, and 13 of the European Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1828.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1828.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1831.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1833.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Madam Murselović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1833.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1838.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to call the representative of the government, Mrs. Mijić, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1841.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1844.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1844.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1854.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, applicants in the present case are for Bosniak non-governmental organizations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1854.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1868.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They argue that their right to freedom of expression was violated as a result of judicial decisions in civil defamation proceedings, which had been brought against them by Ms. Ms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1868.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1872.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At a material time, Ms. Ms. was a public servant,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1872.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1878.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the entertainment editor at the Brcko District Public Radio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1878.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1897.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In May 2003, the applicants wrote a letter to the international supervisor, to the president of the assembly, and to the governor of the Brcko District concerning the appointment of a director of the Brcko District Public Radio station.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1897.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1907.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this letter, which was published in the media shortly after being sent, the applicants made false factual allegations regarding Ms. Ms.,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1907.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1915.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a candidate from the Serb people for the position of a director, which labeled her as a nationalist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1915.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1923.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to protect her reputation, which falls within the ambit of the right to respect for private life, Ms. Ms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1923.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1933.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>filed a lawsuit claiming non-concurrent damage for mental anguish she sustained as a result of the harm to her reputation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1933.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1949.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the opium letter, the applicants, among other things, alleged that in an interview published in Neen Weekly magazine discussing the destruction of mosques in Brcko, Ms. Ms. said that Muslims were not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1949.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1959.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>people, that they did not possess culture, and that accordingly, destroying mosques could not be seen as a destruction of cultural monuments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1959.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1963.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They also alleged that Ms. Ms. on radio's premises</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1963.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1996.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>made a point of removing from the wall and tore to pieces the calendar with a schedule for religious services during the month Ramadan, that on the radio's premises, she covered the coat of arms of Bosnia-Herzegovina with coat of arms of Republic of Srpska, and that as the editor of the entertainment program, she banned broadcasting of Sevdalinga song, arguing that that type of song had no cultural or musical value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1996.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2012.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In a post-conflict and multicultural society as that of Bosnia-Herzegovina, such allegations about a public servant of a different ethnic background carry a particular weight and seriousness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2012.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2017.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These false allegations caused Ms. Ms. mental anguish,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2017.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2028.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for which she was treated by a psychiatrist, as established based on medical documentation in the Brcko District Appellate Court judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2028.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2031.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the proceedings brought by Ms. Ms.,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2031.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2047.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the appellate court distinguished, in accordance with the case law and the principles of the European Court of Human Rights, between value judgments and statements of facts that the applicants made in the impugned letter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2047.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2066.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Relying on the statements of witnesses and other evidence, the appellate court even found that the wording of the letter evidently did not convey what the witness had said to one of the applicants about Ms. Ms. and her conduct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2066.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2078.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these proceedings, the applicants had a full and unimpeded opportunity to prove factual allegations that they had conveyed to a third person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2078.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2081.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, they failed in it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2081.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2102.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the proceeding before the appellate court, the applicants argued that they could not be responsible for defamation, as they had not sent the letter to the media, nor had they issued a press release, but rather they addressed the letter to specific institutions only.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2102.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2124.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, Article VI of the Defamation Act clearly provides that any person who causes damage to the reputation of another by ascertaining or disseminating a falsehood in relation to that person, and by identifying that person to another, shall be liable for defamation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2124.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2138.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, to entail liability, defamation need not be made by public announcement or through media, as the appellate court clearly observed in its judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2138.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2152.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In accordance with the Defamation Act, the appellate court found that by sending the letter to the aforementioned institutions, the applicant harmed the honor and reputation of Ms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2152.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2156.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. and ordered them to retract the impugned letter</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2156.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2170.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>or to pay jointly and severally 2,500 Bosnian marks to the plaintiff in respect of non-peculiar damage, as well as to send the judgment for publication at their own expense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2170.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2177.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thereafter, the applicants lodged an appeal with the Constitutional Court of Bosnia-Herzegovina.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2177.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2197.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Constitutional Court of Bosnia-Herzegovina found that the interference with the freedom of expression in this case was in accordance with the law, namely the Defamation Act, and that the interference pursued a legitimate aim of the protection of the reputation or rights of others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2197.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2210.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Constitutional Court agreed with the appellate court that the impugned letter contained factual allegations that had to be proved, which the applicants failed to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2210.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2218.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Specifically, they did not make a reasonable effort to verify the impugned statements beforehand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2218.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2238.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its decision, the Constitutional Court underlined that public interest, which allows the raising of an issue of a potentially unlawful conduct of public servants, could not be defended by undisputedly false facts which constitute an attack on their reputation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2238.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2257.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Constitutional Court, guided by the case law and the principles of the European Court of Human Rights, examined in detail all the aspects of this case and concluded that the applicant's right to freedom of expression had not been violated in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2257.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2265.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court, sitting as a chamber, also found that there had been no violation of Article 10 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2265.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2284.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its judgment of 13 of October 2015, this court held, in the overall circumstances of the instant case, the court finds the solution of the domestic court strike a fair balance between the competing interests of the climate and those of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2284.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2294.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the reasons given to justify their decisions were relevant and sufficient and met a pressing social need.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2294.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2311.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the court does not see any serious reason to substitute its own assessment for that of the Constitutional Court, which examined the question at issue with care and in line with the principle laid down by the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2311.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2331.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We consider the decisions of domestic courts in this case to be a school example of proper application of all principles laid down by the case law of the European Court of Human Rights in cases where a fair balance needs to be struck between competing rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2331.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2343.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The essence of this case lies in the fact that the applicants acted with utter negligence when reporting the alleged improper conduct of Ms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2343.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2350.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Not only that they failed to make a reasonable effort</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2350.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2363.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to verify the information they had received and then transmitted it in the impugned letter, but they also made factual allegations that had not even been conveyed to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2363.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2374.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Specifically, based on direct evidence given by two witnesses, the domestic courts found that the information about Ms. Ms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2374.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2384.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>conveyed to the applicants by these two persons were clearly inconsistent with what was written in the letter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2384.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2389.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We recall that the freedom of expression is not absolute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2389.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2416.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In accordance with paragraph 2 of Article 10 of the Convention, freedom of expression includes duties and responsibilities and may be subject to such formalities, conditions, restrictions, or penalties as are prescribed by law and are necessary in democratic society in the interest of, among other things, the protection of the reputation or rights of others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2416.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2442.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Obviously, the applicants in the present case have completely disregarded these duties and responsibilities related to the exercise of the freedom of expression, as well as the provisions of the Deformation Act, which are sufficiently clear and precise and the applicants could have reasonably anticipated their application in the given circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2442.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2464.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, when it comes to duties and responsibilities related to freedom of expression, noteworthy is the fact that the applicants in the present case are four reputable Bosniak non-governmental organizations whose members are intellectuals, respectable citizens of Brcko district.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2464.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2481.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would have been quite reasonable to expect from these organizations to at least verify the facts alleged in the impugned letter before passing them on to the highest authorities of the Brcko district.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2481.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2492.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, not only that the applicants failed to do that, but they even failed to convey authentically the information they had received.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2492.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2527.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At least a minimum verification of the truthfulness of grave accusations whose content is in connection with religious and ethnic background of another person, public servant of a different ethnic and religious background than that of the applicants, is particularly important in an after war multi-ethnic society, such as the Society of Bosnia and Herzegovina, composed of members of the former warring parties, which today are three constituent peoples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2527.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2538.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason for this lie in the fact that the ultimate public interest in Bosnia-Herzegovina is to maintain peace and build mutual confidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2538.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2574.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, it cannot be argued that the applicants in the present case acted as whistleblowers, concerning that according to the 2014 committee of ministers recommendation on the protection of whistleblowers, a whistleblower is defined as a person who reports or discloses information on a threat or harm to the public interest in the context of their work based relationship, whether it be in the public or private sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2574.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2591.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Information that the applicants reported to the authorities of Brcko district were not reported in the context of their work based relationship, considering that they are not employees, but non-governmental organizations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2591.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2618.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is quite evident that the applicants, as Bosniak non-governmental organizations representing the interests of Bosniaks, in the present case acted as lobbyists of the candidate of the Bosniak people for the position of a director of the radio by reporting the family information against the candidate from the Serb people to the highest authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2618.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2628.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The impugned letter represents a specific political pressure in relation to the appointment of a director of the radio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2628.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2644.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is exactly because of undue political pressure and outvoting that the commission for the selection of a director of the radio could not decide between two candidates, one being from the Serb people, namely Ms. Ms.,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2644.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2649.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the other one from the Bosniak people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2649.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2661.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the commission proposed that the mandate of then acting director of the radio be extended until the final appointment of a director.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2661.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2680.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the domestic court found the applicants liable for defamation only on account of passing on false factual allegations in the letters sent to the authorities, one should not disregard the fact that the letter was subsequently published in the media as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2680.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2684.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the letter, applicants clearly stressed as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2684.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2694.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the absence of any action on your part, we will be forced to contact the media, as well as the other competent national and international bodies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2694.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2703.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This evidently indicates that the applicant's letter was indeed intended for general publication.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2703.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2714.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The publication of the letter in a daily newspaper evidently aggravated the harm to the reputation of Ms. Ms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2714.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2721.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not difficult to imagine how Ms. Ms. must have felt when false information</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2721.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2740.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>about her conduct and actions leaked to the public, the false information whose contents are offensive to all her friends, neighbors, and co-workers who are members of Bosniak people in the multi-ethnic community of Vrčko district of Bosnia and Herzegovina.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2740.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2750.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relation to this, we recall the case of Lesnik versus Slovakia, which also concerned freedom of expression.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2750.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2760.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, an individual who made defamatory statements about a public prosecutor was convicted in a criminal trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2760.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2768.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, the applicant Lesnik did not publish the letter himself, but it was done by a third person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2768.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2779.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the court noted the importance of the fact that the letter had been published whereby the harm to the aggrieved person had been aggravated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2779.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2798.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, in Lesnik versus Slovakia, the sanction imposed on the applicant, four months imprisonment suspended for a probationary period of one year, is far more severe than the one imposed on the applicants in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2798.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2810.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, despite the criminal conviction and rather severe sanction imposed on the applicant in the Lesnik case, the court found no violation of Article 10 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2810.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2825.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the court ordered the applicants, four applicants, to either retract the letter or pay the amount of approximately 1,300 euros for defamatory statements they made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2825.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2838.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unlike the criminal sanction imposed in the Lesnik case, these alternative orders constitute a merely symbolic satisfaction for the mental anguish of Ms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2838.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2842.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. caused by the defamation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2842.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2858.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite the fact that they failed to prove the truthfulness of their allegations, the applicants did not retract the impugned letter, although they had been given this option instead of payment of the awarded amount.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2858.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2876.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The responded party fully supports the applicants' argument that the possibility for citizens to address the competent authorities and bring to their attention potentially unlawful or inappropriate conduct of public servants should be protected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2876.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2884.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, it is citizens' duty to act in this manner, and it should be encouraged as such.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2884.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2902.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is disputable and unacceptable in the present case, however, is the fact that the applicants made very serious accusations against the public servants without even trying to verify them beforehand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2902.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2907.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such a conduct shows the lack of social responsibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2907.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2932.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also recall that the court, in its case law, frequently noted that civil servants must enjoy public confidence in conditions free of undue perturbation if they are to be successful in performing their tasks, and it may therefore prove necessary to protect them from offensive and abusive verbal attacks when on duty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2932.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2946.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Building of public confidence in the institutions and public servants working in them is of particular importance in a multi-ethnic post-conflict society like that of Bosnia-Herzegovina.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2946.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2968.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the purpose of building and preserving mutual trust, all citizens of Bosnia-Herzegovina should refrain from negligent and notably from intentional presentation of unverified or false information, especially those relating to ethnic and or religious affiliation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2968.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2984.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants cannot enjoy absolute protection of their freedom of expression only because they intended to inform the authorities of the alleged unlawful or inappropriate conduct of a public servant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2984.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2995.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was their duty and responsibility to make a reasonable effort to verify the facts alleged in the letter, which they failed to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2995.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3006.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we consider that the chamber of this court properly found that there had been no violation of Article 10 of the Convention in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3006.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3022.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A different decision of this court would deprive the defamation act in Bosnia-Herzegovina of any meaning and effect, while individuals would lose any legal protection of their private life and reputation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3022.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A different decision of this court would give protection to negligent dissemination of utterly unverified and false information, jeopardizing the rights of the others, which is certainly not the purpose and the meaning of Article 10 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mrs. Mora.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Ms. Usba.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Jar life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Ms. progression.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Ms. CONSTANTINE.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have deferred $90 million in unverified information which has served You immune symptoms for the last 60 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please remember this monument in our hearts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3047.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3056.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very muc, May I ask the members of the grand chamber to ask questions if they feel it necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3056.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3064.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Nußberger first.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3066.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3070.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. I would have a question to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3070.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3076.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I quote the judgment of the appeal court of 16th May 2005.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3076.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3101.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There it's written on the basis, I quote, on the basis of SC's statement, the court establishes that at the meeting that preceded the preparation of the letter, a distinguished member of a defendant had informed those attending the meeting that the plaintiff had given a statement to the newspaper which was identical to the content stated in the letter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3101.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3112.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then it continues, upon a subsequent verification, SC established that such a text had been published, but that the plaintiff had not been the author.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3112.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3119.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So here it's just written in the court's judgment, upon a subsequent verification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3119.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3124.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to know when has this subsequent verification taken place?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3124.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3131.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was it before the letter was sent to the authorities or was it afterwards?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3131.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3137.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it was afterwards, why was it not done before?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3137.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3147.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And why was it not, if it was afterwards, why was the letter then not verified as it was known that she was not the author?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3147.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3147.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3148.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3149.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3150.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3156.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Next to ask questions is Judge Stéphanie Mourou-Vikström.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3156.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3157.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Stéphanie Mourou-Vikström</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3160.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3167.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>qui rejoint de très près la question qui vient d'être posée et qui s'adresse également aux requérantes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3167.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3172.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bien évidemment, l'autre partie peut se prononcer si elle a des informations à nous communiquer sur ce sujet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3173.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3184.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je voudrais en effet savoir à quel moment précis vous avez appris que Mme S. n'était pas l'auteur de l'interview au journal Nînes, le journal serbe Nînes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3184.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3190.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>1re question, le moment précis, je pense que c'est quelque chose d'important dans la compréhension du dossier.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3190.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3207.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et la 2e question qui rejoint aussi la question qui vient d'être posée, lorsque vous l'avez su, lorsque vous l'avez appris, pourquoi n'êtes-vous pas allés immédiatement démentir cette information auprès des autorités, des hautes autorités auprès desquelles elles avaient été dénoncées?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3207.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3208.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Voilà, je vous remercie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3210.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3212.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci. Judge Vehabović, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Faris Vehabović</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3214.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3217.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3217.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3220.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3223.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3229.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Did you make any inquiry as to the content of the letter received by the applicant?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3232.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3233.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's the first question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3233.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3258.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And second question, what steps you have taken in order to find out if the content of the letter was disseminated by some body of Brčko district to which letter was addressed, or by its staff?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3258.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3264.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Have you performed any internal inquiry as to these circumstances?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3264.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3275.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if yes, then if you could provide us with some piece of evidence, I would appreciate very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3275.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3275.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3276.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3281.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Judge Vehabović. Yes, Judge Kūris please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3284.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3286.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3286.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3292.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question goes to the representative of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3292.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3302.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as I understood, your position was that before sending a letter, the applicants had to make a reasonable effort to verify the rest of the allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3302.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3312.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Could you please specify what could have been that reasonable effort to be satisfactory and how it could have been made?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3312.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3312.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3313.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3314.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3314.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3319.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I see, yes, Judge Keller, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Helen Keller</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3323.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3329.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a small factual question to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3329.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3350.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Did you qualify your letter as confidential, either, for example, on the envelope or in the heading of the letter, so that the addressee were fully aware that the content was confidential?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3350.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3350.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3354.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3357.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any further questions from the Grand Chamber?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3360.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3367.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to ask, following the question of Judge Keller, the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3367.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3378.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What are the expectations of privacy of a communication like the present one addressed to official authorities?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3378.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3389.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So once again, what is expected in the practice of Bosnia-Herzegovina if such a letter is sent?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3389.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3395.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it considered in practice, as a matter of practice, confidential?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3395.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3404.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or are there any specific judicial decisions in this regard?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3404.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3424.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, again, concerning the legal practice, the representative of the government mentioned that the fact of the publication aggravated the harm to the plaintiff in the domestic proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3424.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3432.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is this a matter that is generally taken into consideration in a board of damages?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3432.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3436.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is this a precondition for damages?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3436.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3441.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And was this a consideration in the present judgment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3445.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3451.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On this, I would like to allow you 18 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3451.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3455.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We will resume at 10.30.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3455.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3461.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is suspended for 18 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3616.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3617.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3674.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3679.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to call the representative of the applicant to answer the questions, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3683.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3691.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Question number one was asked by Miss Angelica Nisberger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3691.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3696.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer is, the lawsuit was filed in May 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3696.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3702.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The lawsuit claims that the applicants issued a public statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3702.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3704.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is not true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3704.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3712.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The contents of the letter were first leaked to the public and then the lawsuit was filed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3712.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3719.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Answer to the question number two, asked by Mr. Andrej Potocki.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3719.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3731.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As in line with regulations valid at the time, the mayor, as the head of executive authorities, had the obligation to request the police to verify the claims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3731.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3749.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, the applicants even stated at the end of their letter that they, that should fail to react, end of quote, indicating that they expected the mayor and competent bodies to react.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3749.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3761.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Question number three by Egidijus Kuris from Lithuania about qualifying the letter as confidential.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3761.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3770.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants did not qualify it explicitly as confidential, but it was clearly stated to whom the letter should be delivered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3770.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3775.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was mentioned attention off.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3775.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3788.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The questions asked by the president, what are the expectations regarding the correspondence in practice of Bosnia and Herzegovina?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3788.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3796.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The practice is that the letter is delivered directly to a person with note attention off.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3796.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3804.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And such correspondence does not go through protocol room.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3804.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3808.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question number two about the legal practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3808.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3815.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, Mrs. Zivkovic did not suffer the damage because she did not apply to the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3815.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3817.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>vacancy notice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3817.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3822.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this fact was just established before the grand chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3822.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3822.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3824.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3829.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. I call Mrs. Mijić, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3829.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3832.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3832.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3840.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I recall, the first question was, when did Ms. Enes give this interview?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3840.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3848.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Apparently, she never gave this interview in NIN Weekly magazine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3848.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3851.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was established by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3851.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3858.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The legal representative of first applicant was heard before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3858.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3872.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And he, as a witness, he stated before Appellate Court of Burtko District that they subsequently checked this information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3872.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3875.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they established that Ms. Enes was not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3875.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3882.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the author of this interview in Weekly magazine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3882.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3893.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it was stated by legal representative of the first applicant before Appellate Court of Burtko District.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3893.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3903.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it was established before the court that Ms. Enes never gave an interview with this content.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3903.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3921.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to the, I think, first question for the government, I think Judge Viharbovic posed this question about investigation about the content of this letter by authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3921.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3949.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to this question, I would like to emphasize that neither institution, neither supervisor, international supervisor, neither governor of Burtko District, neither president of the assembly of Burtko District, they are not competent to investigate any complaints concerning selection of the director for public radio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3949.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3961.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only body competent to consider and to these kind of complaints is managing board of the radio district Burtko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3961.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3977.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So these institutions to which the letter has been sent are not competent at all to deal with any complaints concerning any candidate for the position of the public radio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3977.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4014.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the content of the letter and the factual allegations made in this letter was considered and was investigated before domestic courts, before Appellate Court of Burtko and also the case was investigated in detail by the constitutional court of Bosnia Herzegovina and constitutional court agreed completely with the findings of Appellate Court of Burtko District.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4014.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4032.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next question was, what can we accept from the applicant when we say that they should have put in reasonable effort to verify these factual allegations beforehand?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4032.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4040.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer is, first of all, they should have conveyed in the letter what they have been told.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4040.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4045.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just to convey information authentically in the letter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4045.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4057.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because applicants allegedly put in the letter information they received from the persons working at the radio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4057.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4072.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When these persons, employees at public radio were heard before Appellate Court of Burtko, they told the court something different, different information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4072.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4080.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it was established before the court that applicants did not convey information they received authentically in the letter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4080.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4089.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for the start, the first thing they should have done to convey authentically information they received.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4089.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4096.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, they should have conveyed the information they received.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4096.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4105.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, they could have just opened the newspaper weekly magazine in, just to see who is the author of the text.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4105.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4108.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have done it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4108.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4124.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But after they sent the letter, and before Appellate Court of Burtko District, they said, well, when we checked the facts, we found that Ms. M.S. was not the author of this interview.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4124.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4128.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They could have done it before they sent the letter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4128.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4142.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to the question, what could applicants expect when it comes to confidentiality of the letter, this letter was not confidential.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4142.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4145.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was sent to public authority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4145.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4150.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not even marked as confidential letter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4150.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4159.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So they were not able to expect any special confidentiality of this letter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4159.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4167.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is a law on confidentiality data in Bosnia-Herzegovina, but this law only applies to the official documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4167.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4176.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So when someone sends a letter to public authority, you never know what might happen to this letter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4176.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4190.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So you cannot expect a strict confidentiality of your correspondence with authorities or with anyone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4190.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4216.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to the question whether the fact that the letter was published in the newspaper was taken into consideration when deciding on damages, the amount of damages, yes, this fact that the letter was published in the newspaper was considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4216.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4224.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court took this fact into consideration when deciding on the amount for the non-material damages.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4224.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4233.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this fact, of course, as I already said, was not taken into consideration when deciding on liability for defamation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4233.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4246.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in the domestic court, applicants found liable for defamation only based on the fact that they conveyed, dismissed false information to a third person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4246.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4250.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A third person can be anybody, institution, other persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4250.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4257.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So these are the regulations of the Defamation Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4257.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4258.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4258.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4260.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope I answered your question correctly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4261.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4264.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4264.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4266.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4266.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4272.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their submissions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4272.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4277.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4277.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4280.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4280.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4284.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4284.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4286.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
