<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>1901007_03102012</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>18.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>19.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>68.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>68.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>76.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>83.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case of X and others against Austria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>83.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>92.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case was lodged with the court on the 24th of April, 2007, under Article 34 of the Convention by three Austrian nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>92.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>100.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the first section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>100.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>106.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on the 29th of January, 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>106.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>113.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 1st of December, 2011, the first section held a hearing on the admissibility and merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>113.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>120.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 5th of June, 2012, it decided to relinquish jurisdiction in favor of the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>120.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>130.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At their request, the following associations were granted leave to submit joint written comments as third parties under Article 36, Paragraph 2 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>130.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>155.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Federation Internationale des Ligues des Droits de l'Homme, the International Commission of Jurists, the European Region of the International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans, and Intersex Association, the British Association for Adoption and Fostering, the Network of European LGBT Families Associations, and the European Commission on Sexual Orientation Law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>155.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>164.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the following associations or institutions were also granted leave at their request to submit written comments as third parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>164.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>174.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The European Center for Law and Justice, the Attorney General for Northern Ireland, Amnesty International, and Alliance Defending Freedom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>174.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>180.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their deputy agent, Ms. Brigitte Ohms, assisted by Mr. Michael Stormann</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>180.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>184.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Ms. Anna Jankovic, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>184.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>186.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mr. Helmut Graupner,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>186.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>188.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>188.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>192.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>192.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>203.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to welcome a group of French judges from the École Nationale de la Magistrature in Paris and a delegation of European judges and prosecutors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>203.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>211.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the deputy agent of the government and the representative of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>211.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>213.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Ohms for the government will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>213.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>216.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mr. Graupner for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>216.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>217.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Ms. Ohms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>221.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>222.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>222.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>226.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>226.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>232.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the application before us contests the general principles of Austrian law of domestic relations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>232.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>244.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have the honor to present the position of the Austrian government on second-parent adoption, focusing on adoption by same-sex partners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>244.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>250.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Austrian government has already submitted detailed written observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>250.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>257.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, our explanations will be limited to the main issues of our position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>257.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>270.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to start with the facts of the present case, which are, in our view, crucial for the case, and then turn to the applicable law before I respond to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>273.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>280.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are a same-sex couple and the son of one of the two partners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>280.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>286.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have been living in a joint household for years in their desired way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>286.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>301.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The son was born out of wedlock and, in compliance with the law, was first given his mother's family name and, subsequently, by a separate legal act, the family name of his father.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>301.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>307.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His mother has sole custody of the child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>307.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>313.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The biological and legal father was living in a separate household.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>313.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>320.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was in regular contact with his child and pays alimony for him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>320.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>326.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same-sex couple had the wish to intensify the legal family ties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>326.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>342.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a first step, they asked for a transfer of custody to the mother's partner as foster mother, without success, as this legal instrument is not designed for intact families.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>342.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>348.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in our case, the family conditions were all right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>348.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>352.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then the mother's partner wanted to adopt the son.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>352.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>357.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The father did, however, refuse to agree to the adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>357.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>362.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This has to be seen against the consequence of an adoption in Austria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>362.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>373.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The father and also his parents would lose all their parental rights, such as visiting rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>373.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>396.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants asked the Austrian courts to approve the adoption agreement, while noting that the father had refused to give his consent and that the court would have to substitute his consent, as in their view, the father had failed to give valid reasons for his refusal and the adoption would be in the best interest of the child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>396.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>408.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the applicants never applied formally for the substitution of the father's consent as required by law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>408.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>410.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Austrian courts did not agree.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>410.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>427.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They stated in the ELA that according to the Austrian Civil Code, the primary aim of the adoption provisions was to secure the child's well-being in cases where the biological parents were not in a position to care for the child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>427.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>434.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, there was no need to replace one of the parents by an adoptive parent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>434.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>444.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the adoption would not lead to the effect desired by the applicants, namely to replace the father.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>444.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>467.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here I would like to mention that even the applicants do not provide any information on how their family life might have suffered any practical restrictions or undue interferences by the fact that the mother's partner wasn't allowed to adopt the son living in the family.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>467.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>478.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Austrian government is well aware of this sensitive situation of the couples and of the applicant together.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>478.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>486.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We understand the applicant's desire to intensify the legal family ties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>486.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>497.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, I once more would like to stress that the present case is a typically patchwork situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>497.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>511.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Austria, for instance, in 2010, there was an estimated number of 77,800 minors living in patchwork families.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>511.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>529.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In comparison to this number of minors, the number of all adoptions in 2011 amounted to 248 minors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>529.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>546.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From these 248 minors, 102 adoptions were initiated by the youth welfare services looking for suitable parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>546.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>551.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>551.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>560.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicants are challenging the following general principles of Austrian law of domestic relations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>560.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>572.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the Austrian law is based on the assumption that the child has one mother and one father, his and her parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>572.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>589.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Austrian law is thus guided by the biological principle that the child has one father and one mother, even if the father cannot be identified in certain cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>589.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>595.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The adoption law is also based on this parental principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>595.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>607.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Adoption pursues the aim of creating, to the extent possible and reasonable, the circumstances of a biological family.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>607.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>612.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Adoptions may be made by a couple or an individual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>612.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>622.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An adoption by more than one person is admissible only if the adopting persons are married to each other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>622.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>643.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In case of an adoption by a single person, a biological parent is replaced without any exemption by an adoptive parent of the same sex as the respective biological parent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>643.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>655.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, for example, an aunt cannot adopt a nephew or a niece if the legal family bonds with the mother continue to exist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>658.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>671.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second principle of Austrian law of domestic relations guarantees that no measure with respect to a child can take place contrary to the well-being of the child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>671.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>680.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Recently, this principle has been embodied even in Austrian constitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>680.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>732.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, adoption of a child is primarily aimed at ensuring that children who are without parents or who are undesired or children from broken families or children with parents who, for serious reasons, cannot ensure the child's proper education will find a new home with suitable and responsible persons who will provide them with education and care unless there are serious reasons affecting the child's interests and the interference with the family law relations between children and their biological parents are to be avoided as far as possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>732.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>745.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third principle says that the rights to respect for family life of a parent to be replaced must adequately be taken into account.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>745.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>760.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, a court's approval of an adoption may only be granted if the biological parent of the minor child consents to the adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>760.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>766.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The consent of the person to be deprived of his parental rights is a sine qua non.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>766.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>778.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If no consent is given by the biological parents, the court might replace the consent under clearly defined circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>778.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>806.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Replacing the consent is an extraordinary measure that will be taken into consideration only in cases of particular circumstances, especially whenever the interests of the child in the adoption clearly outweigh the interests of the biological partner or the biological parent in general, or if the grounds for refusal are not justified in moral terms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>806.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>823.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a fourth principle might be regarded that also the partner of a single-educating parent might have certain rights vis-a-vis his children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>823.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>841.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there is family life beyond legal family ties and the children are living in the same household, the partner has to undertake all reasonable measures under the given circumstances to protect the well-being of the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>841.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>855.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, these persons may ask the courts to take certain protective measures relating to the minor, for instance, to transfer custody where the minor's well-being is endangered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>859.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>869.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to a respectable press item from February this year on the situation of rainbow families in Austria, this seems to work well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>872.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>882.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So to sum up, the sexual orientation of the persons concerned is completely irrelevant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>882.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>895.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Austrian family law and the regulation on adoptions do not contain any moral value judgment or even a moral conviction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>895.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>909.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only in 2010, an explicit exclusion of second-parent adoption was introduced in the Austrian Registered Partnership Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>909.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>923.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This act, however, I would like to stress is not applicable to the present case where the last national decision was issued in 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>923.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>928.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>928.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>936.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in our view, these general principles are fully in line with the European standard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>936.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>967.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the European level, there are only two conventions on the adoption of children, and only the revised version of 2008, which entered into force in 2011, takes into account same-sex couples insofar as the states are free to extend adoptions to same-sex couples who are married or who have entered into a registered partnership.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>967.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>991.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, these instruments cannot be regarded as European standard, as the 1967 convention has been ratified by only 16 of the 47 Council of Europe member states, and the revised version only by seven states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>991.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1038.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the international level, Article 21 of the Convention on the Rights of the Child stipulates that the state parties ensure that the adoption of a child is authorized only on the basis of all pertinent and reliable information, that the adoption is permissible in view of the child's status concerning parents, relatives, and little guardians, and that, if required, the persons concerned have given their informed consent to the adoption on the basis of such counseling as may be necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1038.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1044.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's also a consent requirement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1044.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1053.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The wording of the main up-to-date specific European soft law instrument is also drafted in a very reluctant way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1053.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1086.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The recommendation of the Committee of Ministers on Measures to Combat Discrimination on Grounds of Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity, adopted in 2010, only advises that member states whose national legislation permits single individuals to adopt children should ensure that the law is applied without discrimination based on sexual orientation or gender identity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1086.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1103.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With reference to same-sex partnerships, member states should seek to ensure that the rights and obligations are equivalent to those of different sex couples in a comparable situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1103.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1131.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the latest attempt of drafting a Committee of Ministers' recommendations on the rights and legal status of children and parental responsibilities has not been successful so far against the background of the wide diversity of political and legal traditions in the member states in the area of family law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1134.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1144.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here I would like to mention, for the sake of completeness, that Austria has only ratified the 1967 Convention at the European level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1144.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1154.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And most of the other Council of Europe member states do not permit two legal fathers or two legal mothers for a child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1154.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1170.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Reportedly, only 10 member states permit adoptions by same-sex partners at all, which means that up to now, neither a European standard, nor a trend, or even tendency exists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1170.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1191.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Court's case law, this situation indicates the existence of a state's margin of appreciation in assessing whether and to what extent difference in otherwise similar situations justify a difference in treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1191.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1195.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1195.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1211.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as Article 8 of the Convention neither contains a right to adoption nor any right to other specific legal instruments for the legal recognition of existing social family ties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1211.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1221.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The states have a very wide margin of appreciation in regulating adoptions because there is no European standard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1221.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1251.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 14 does not prohibit distinctions in treatment, which are founded on an objective assessment of essentially different factual circumstances, and which, being based on public interest, strike a fair balance between the protection of the interests of the community and respect for the rights and freedoms safeguarded by the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1251.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1290.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the Austrian legislator thus gives the biological and legal parents priority when it comes to care for the child, irrespective of the sexual orientation, and permit only in exceptional cases an adoption in the interest of the child's well-being, Austria cannot be blamed for this, even if the notion of family life within the meaning of Article 8 has developed and will presumably develop also in future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1290.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1308.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since an adoption results in a loss of parental rights and obligations, and there is an interference with the right to family of the replaced parent and the adoptive child, their interest must also be adequately taken into account.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1308.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1324.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The biological parents must not be completely excluded from the child's life as long as there are no grounds justifying such a measure for the well-being of the child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1324.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1343.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Austrian agent's view, it is thus not contrary to the Convention if the consent of the replaced parent is prerequisite for an adoption without which no adoption is possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1343.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1355.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the father in our case did not give his consent to the adoption agreement and there was no reason for replacing his missing consent, a sine qua non for an adoption has not been met.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1355.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1370.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, no one, not only the applicants, no one could have adopted and can adopt the second applicant, the son.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1370.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1375.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, one cannot ignore the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1375.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1380.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The basic reproduction principle has always been the same.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1380.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1388.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It requires two individuals of different sexes, irrespective of the sexual orientation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1388.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1406.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, if the legislator uses the biological principle as a guideline for regulating the relationship between parents and children and to regulate adoptions, this cannot be regarded as discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1406.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1425.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Securing the child's well-being is certainly a legitimate aim pursued by using adequate means since the interests of all the other persons involved are adequately taken into account.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1425.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1432.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the Court, against this background,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1432.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1440.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>we would like to answer the questions raised by the Court as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1440.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1458.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When looking at the legal situation of a married couple, respectively, of an unmarried different sex couple, and the situation of the applicants, we see no room for comparison with spouses from the outset.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1458.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1463.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here, I would like to refer to the Shalkonkov judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1463.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1487.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the applicant's specific situation, above all, it has to be taken into account that the child's father had refused to give his consent, and therefore, the applicants are exactly in the same situation as a married or unmarried different sex couple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1487.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1501.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Austrian Civil Code, the consent of both biological parents is an essential precondition for any adoption, be it in same-sex couples or in different-sex couples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1501.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1511.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first applicant could not have adopted the minor even if she had a different sexual orientation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1511.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1517.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is, therefore, no difference in treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1517.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1534.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Austrian courts have examined in substance and in detail whether the existence of an exceptional case can be assumed in the present case, which would allow to replace the father's consent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1534.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1542.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this context, the Austrian courts did not doubt at all the good situation of the applicants and of the family life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1542.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1570.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, they scrutinized the well-being of the child, and in striking a fair balance between the interests involved, especially in the light of the existing relationship between father and son, the Austrian courts did not see any necessity to override the interest of the father with regard to the well-being of the child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1570.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1583.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here I would like to refer to page 11 at sequitur and page 15 of the court, of the decision of the court of second instance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1583.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1609.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a consequence, in the present case, neither a male partner, a new male partner, nor a husband of the mother could have adopted the child, since the consent of the parent to be replaced is indispensable for the court's approval of an adoption agreement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1609.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1621.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This sine qua non and this prerequisite is to be distinguished from the effects of an adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1621.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1627.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This precondition is to be distinguished very clearly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1627.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1651.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With respect of the exclusion of second parent adoption in same-sex couples, we want to reiterate that Austrian law wants to avoid in general a situation where a child, as a result of an adoption, has two mothers or two fathers in legal terms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1651.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1660.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Austrian law pursues the aim of creating, to the extent possible, as already mentioned, the legal family ties of a biological family whenever a child is adopted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1660.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1681.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Securing a child's well-being is certainly a legitimate aim in this respect, and in our view it is pursued with adequate means, since it adequately takes the interests of all other persons involved into account.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1681.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1690.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here again I would like to stress that the consent of the father was not given.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1690.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1700.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The precondition for an adoption has not been met, irrespective of the gender and sexual orientation of the persons involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1700.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1721.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if the Strasbourg court should come to the conclusion that there had been a violation of the Convention in the present case, the decision in the original case cannot come to another conclusion also in the future, as long as the father refuses to give his consent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1721.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1731.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the Court, to conclude with, in our opinion,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1731.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1744.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Austrian law, and in particular the Austrian civil code, strikes a fair balance between the protection of the interests of the various groups of persons concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1744.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1753.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to close by referring once more to the detailed written observations of the Republic of Austria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1753.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1757.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The motions contained therein are fully maintained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1757.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1757.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1760.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1762.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mrs. Ohms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1762.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1764.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I then call Mr. Graupner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1768.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1774.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1774.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1778.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm representing here today a family.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1778.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1806.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm representing a mother and her child, a boy who has been raised for 13 years now by his mother and her female partner, a boy who was nine years of age when this case has started and who is 17 years of age now, and the mother's partner, the boy's step-parent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1806.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1815.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The mother and her partner have been living together as a couple for many years, just as heterosexual couples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1815.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1819.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have bought a joint estate, which is the home of the family.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1819.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1836.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are forming a family with the son brought in from a former relationship, and the three are living an everyday life, an everyday family life, just as all the heterosexual families around them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1836.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1847.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only difference to all these families around them is the sex of the step-parent, female instead of male.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1847.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1872.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Youth Welfare Office of Vienna, when this case started, recognized that the two women are providing the son with a second applicant with a wonderful family life, and the Youth Welfare Office recommended joint custody, and it has been refused by the Austrian courts, as we have heard just before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1872.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1887.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court has stated and treated homosexual men and women as being in a relevantly similar situation as heterosexual men and women in relation to parental rights, and especially in relation to adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1887.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1894.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of Silva-Motor, Fréte, Yppi versus France, and recently Gaille Dubois.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1894.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1912.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this court stated, quote, a cohabiting same-sex couple living in a stable, de facto partnership falls within the notion of family life just as the relationship of a different sex couple in the same situation would.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1912.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1916.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Schalkenkopf, 2010, paragraph 94.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1916.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1926.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issue before this court, and this cannot be stressed enough, is not, it is not joint adoption by a couple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1926.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1930.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issue before this court today is single adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1930.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1935.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What Austria refuses to the applicants is single adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1935.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1938.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is adoption by an individual person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1938.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1947.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first applicant may adopt an Austrian law and a child of the world, with only one single exception, the second applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1947.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1971.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What Austria argues for in this case is to take away the protection this court, this great chamber has established in Yppi versus France, from the stepmother regarding the child which is most close to her and with which she has been living in the family for years, and that exclusively on the basis of her sex.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1971.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1979.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If she were a man, she would have the chance of adopting her stepchild, second applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1979.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1988.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the circumstances of the case unchanged save her sex, and there would be no discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1988.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2003.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So a relevantly similar situation, between the applicant's step-parent family on the one hand and the heterosexual step-parent family on the other hand, cannot reasonably be denied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2003.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2010.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issue before this court, and also this cannot be stressed enough, is not a privilege of marriage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2010.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2017.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this distinguishes this case most decisively from the recent case of Guy Dubois versus France.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2017.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2025.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Austria, step-parent adoption is available not just for married couples, it is also available for unmarried couples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2025.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2042.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But while in unmarried couples, in heterosexual unmarried couples, it is meaningfully possible to do so, unmarried homosexual couples are totally excluded to do such a step-parent adoption in a meaningful way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2042.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2052.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this is perfectly a Karna-like situation, a situation established in Karna versus Austria 2003 and the follow-up cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2052.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2068.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An unequal treatment between unmarried heterosexual couples on the one hand and unmarried same-sex couples on the other hand, which the Court found inadmissible in the cases Karna, Kozak, PB and GS, and JM versus UK.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2068.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2078.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the issue before this court today is just respect for the Karna case law the Court established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2078.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2102.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the intervening six NGO coalition has pointed out, only four member states of the Council of Europe, four other member states like Austria, do allow unmarried couples step-parent adoption and at the same time exclude same-sex couples. So the other 42 are sharing an overwhelming consensus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2102.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2125.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They either restrict step-parent adoption to marriage or, if they don't do so, they are treating all unmarried couples the same without making any difference based on gender or sexual orientation. 42 member states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2125.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2144.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This Court has constantly established that discrimination on the basis of sexual orientation is unacceptable, is as serious as discrimination on the ground of race, ethnic origin, religion and sex. That differentiation on the basis of sexual</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2144.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2157.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>orientation requires particularly serious reasons, convincing and weighty reasons, and the scope of the question is narrow. Distinctions must be necessary, not only</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2157.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2163.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>suitable, to realize a legitimate aim. And this Court has also stated that distinctions</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2163.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2169.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>solely based on sexual orientation are plain discrimination. There are no particularly</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2169.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2179.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>serious reasons, no convincing and weighty reasons in this case, which would render the distinction applied by Austria in this case necessary in that sense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2179.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2217.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have provided the Court with extensive studies and expert positions in our written submissions, and especially the large-scale study commissioned by the German Ministry of Justice in 2009, which show and prove a wide scientific consensus in Europe and worldwide, a consensus which establishes same-sex parents are as good parents as opposite-sex parents, and children in same-sex families, so-called rainbow families, are developing as well as in heterosexual families.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2217.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2240.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this Court, the Grand Chamber, in these proceedings, have asked the Austrian government to provide research findings proving that same-sex couples, unlike opposite-sex couples, would be incapable of providing the care and upbringing a child needs. The Austrian government provided not a single study. The intervening</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2240.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2249.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>organizations, ECLJ and ADF, provided one, the Regnero study. If you look close to</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2249.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2276.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>this one study provided, we see that the children studied, 77 to 98 percent of them lived with same-sex families less than three years, and 57 to 77 percent, so half to three quarters of the studied children, have been living with same-sex families less than four months. And then the author compares these children to children</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2276.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2282.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>raised by their mother and their father from birth until their 18th birthday.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2282.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2301.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then when you read the study, you see that the author himself, Mark Regnero, on page 764, says, and admits himself, quote, comparing the children of such parents with those who experience no union dissolution is arguably unfair, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2301.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2319.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the only thing this study shows is that breakdown of a couple is not good for the children, but it says nothing about the welfare of children raised by stable same-sex families like my clients, like we have in this case here before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2319.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2331.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ADF has cited in addition a handful of other studies without providing them to the court. We don't see them, so we cannot evaluate them. I have looked at one of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2331.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2336.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>them, the Zarantacos study, and it does not in any way say what ADF villages.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2336.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2354.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, the outcome of the study in the summary says children in married couples are more likely to do well than children of cohabiting heterosexual and homosexual couples, merely based on the assumption of teachers, to be said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2354.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2359.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the comparator in this case is not marriage. It is cohabiting heterosexual</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2359.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2364.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>couples. And according to this study, there is no difference between cohabiting</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2364.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2368.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>heterosexual and cohabiting homosexual couples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2368.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2388.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if you look further in this study, the author, Zarantacos, says, quote, on page 30, and these findings must be treated with caution before one jumps to conclusions encouraging homophobia and traditionalism, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2388.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2404.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the one single study provided to the court against the applicants, or at best a handful of studied but not presented studies, they do not even say what the third party interveners alleged they would say. And not in any way, they can't challenge the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2404.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2406.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>findings of the rest of the scientific world.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2406.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2421.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have provided the court with a long list of renowned associations which are advocating step-parent adoption in same-sex families for the best interest of the child. The American Psychological Association, the Child Welfare League of America,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2421.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2449.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the American Psychiatric Association, the North American Council on Adoptable Children, the American Academy of Pediatrics, the American Psychoanalytical Association, the American Academy of Family Physicians, the British Association of Adoption and Fostering, the Royal College of Psychiatrists, the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, the American Medical Association, the Canadian Psychological Association, et cetera, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2449.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2464.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the Inter-American Court of Human Rights recently summed it up, quote, the abilities of gay and lesbian persons as parents and the positive outcome for their children are not areas where credible scientific researchers disagree.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2464.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2469.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Case Atalava v. Chile, earlier this year, paragraph 129.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2469.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2487.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the same conclusion recently came the Bioethics Commission of the Austrian government in a report recently presented recommending same adoption rights for same-sex couples as for heterosexual couples. And the Committee of Ministers of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2487.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2513.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Council of Europe in an unanimous decision recommended equal treatment of same-sex and opposite-sex couples and recommended the decisions on parental responsibility to be taken without discrimination based on sexual orientation in the recommendation of measures to combat discrimination on grounds of sexual orientation and gender identity from March 2010. And the Commissioner</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2513.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2530.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for Human Rights of the Council of Europe in his report on discrimination on grounds of sexual orientation and gender identity from June 2011 called for same parenting rights for same-sex couples in especially the same adoption rights. As the Court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2530.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2542.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>established, the owners of proof for necessity of a distinction on the basis of sexual orientation is on a government. Has this proof been supplied? Has this proof of particularly</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2542.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2548.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>serious reasons been supplied? The Austrian government never, ever even alleged</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2548.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2559.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that children in same-sex families, in rainbow families, are not developing as well as in heterosexual families. They did not see or say that, I have to admit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2559.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2579.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, it argued that the distinction were justified because it avoids two legal mothers or two legal fathers and it, quote, uses the biological principle as a guideline. We also have heard that today. Biologically, however, also a white child</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2579.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2586.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>cannot descend from black parents. May this biological principle also be used as a</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2586.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2601.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>guideline to ban adoption of white children by persons of black color and allow racially compatible adoptions only? I doubt. And when biological parents are still</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2601.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2608.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>alive, any adopted child in Austria has already two mothers and two fathers. That</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2608.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2632.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is why Austria has made a reservation to the mentioned adoption convention from 1967, which requires that legal kinship with the biological parents be completely terminated in what Austria does not do so that any adopted child has two legal fathers or mothers. In Ebie v. France, 2008, the Court found the reasons put forward</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2632.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2644.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by the government in this case not convincing against the background of the domestic legal provisions. We have the same here. In its written observations to the Grand</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2644.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2662.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Chamber and also in the oral observations we just heard, the government heavily claimed that due to the father's refusal of consent, heterosexual couples would have been treated the same way as my client's same-sex couple. But I'm sorry I have</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2662.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2668.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to say this is absolutely not true. The Austrian courts in this case have denied</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2668.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2679.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>any inquiry and any decision on the merits of the case, on the merits of the proposed adoption. They have denied an inquiry and any decision on whether the adoption</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2679.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2697.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>proposed serves the best interest of the child and on whether the father's consent should be replaced, all of which the courts would have done in the case of a heterosexual couple. The Supreme Court stated it more than clearly, quote, given the legal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2697.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2707.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>impossibility of adoption, it is not necessary to further discuss if there are reasons for the consent, end of quote. And that is what they would have done in a heterosexual</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2707.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2713.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>case, looked into the reasons whether the father's consent should have been replaced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2713.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2718.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>EB v. France, decided by the Grand Chamber in 2008, was not about whether a child</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2718.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2723.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ever be placed by Ms. EB for adoption, but it was about automatic exclusion</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2723.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2728.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Ms. EB from even the chance of being considered as the potential adoptive</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2728.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2739.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>parent of a specific child for reasons linked to her sexual orientation, for her partnership with a woman. And that is the same in our case here. Discrimination</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2739.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2750.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>at issue in this case is not whether Austrian courts approved or not approved the adoption. That is what we are complaining about. What we are complaining</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2750.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2762.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>about and what is the issue is that my clients have been barred from having the merits of adoption be at all considered by the Austrian courts. The automatic exclusion</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2762.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2773.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Austrian courts established from any chance to meaningful adoption would have applied even if the father would be dead. It would have applied even if the father</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2773.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2785.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>would be unknown, and it would have applied even if the father would have consented to the adoption. The refusal and the automatic exclusion of my clients would have</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2785.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2791.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>applied even if the father would have consented to the adoption. The exclusion</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2791.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2810.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of my clients from step parent adoption is not connected to the consent or to the consent of the father, but to the sex and sexual orientation of the mother and her partner, the first and the third applicant. The national court stated that the aim</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2810.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2815.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the exclusion is promotion of the traditional family. However, the second applicant,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2815.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2828.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the third applicant, has to be paramount and cannot change it, and nobody stated that anyone wants to do anything about it and change it. Luckily. In Wagner v. Luxemburg</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2828.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2840.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in 2008, this Court stressed the importance of the recognition of an existing family life for the best interest of the child. And in Yppi v. France again, the Court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2840.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2847.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>showed that the child's best interest has to be paramount. The key notion, also in</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2847.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2861.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>this case, is best interest of the child and not the sex or sexual orientation of its parents. As Judge Costa, a former president of this Court, in Yppi v. France, in a</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2861.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2875.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>dissenting opinion even, put it, quote, the message sent by this Court to the state parties is clear. A person seeking to adopt cannot be prevented from doing so merely</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2875.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2885.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the ground of his or her homosexuality. I agree. And we all should agree, I think.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2885.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2905.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Children in rainbow families deserve the same right to get a chance to establish stable legal ties with their step-parents in as much as their peers in heterosexual families who do enjoy this right, even when their parents, the parent and the step-parent are not married. Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2911.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2913.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Graupner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2914.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2927.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We've therefore come to the end of the first round of pleadings, and I would like to ask at this stage whether any of the judges present would like to put some questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2927.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2928.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Potocki, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>André Potocki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2932.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2933.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci, M. le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2934.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2937.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mes questions s'adresseront à l'agent du gouvernement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2939.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2943.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ma première question est une demande de confirmation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2944.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2963.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous nous avez dit, Madame, que l'orientation sexuelle des requérantes n'était pas pertinente dans cette affaire parce que, de toute façon, l'adoption était impossible en raison du refus opposé par le père biologique.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2965.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2966.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ma question est donc la suivante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2966.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2979.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Si le père biologique avait donné son accord, la Cour doit-elle comprendre qu'alors l'adoption aurait été possible, quelle que soit l'orientation sexuelle et le sexe des requérantes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2981.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2983.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ma seconde question est la suivante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2985.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2995.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous nous avez rappelé que l'intérêt de l'enfant est un principe si important en droit autrichien qu'il a maintenant valeur constitutionnelle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2998.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3003.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Deuxième point, dans votre mémoire écrite au point 3.3,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3004.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3021.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>je lis, ma citation sera brève, des couples homosexuels peuvent être pour l'essentiel personnellement, personnellement en italique, aussi appropriés ou non que des couples hétérosexuels pour adopter des enfants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3022.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3027.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il en va de même pour l'adoption d'enfants du conjoint dans les couples homosexuels.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3028.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Troisième point, il me semble, sauf à ce que vous me corrigiez, qu'en droit autrichien, il est absolument impossible aux homosexuels d'obtenir une adoption coparentale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3059.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En rapprochant ces trois éléments, c'est à dire l'intérêt supérieur de l'enfant comme but légitime, la reconnaissance de l'aptitude éducative de certains couples homosexuels et enfin l'interdiction absolue qui leur est opposée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3059.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3065.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est ce que ne surgit pas une question de proportionnalité ou de façon encore plus précise?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3065.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3068.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et c'est sur ce point que j'aimerais avoir vos explications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3068.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3090.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ne serait-il pas plus concevable au regard de ce principe de proportionnalité que soit prévu un examen au cas par cas des requêtes pour juger précisément de l'intérêt des enfants et de l'aptitude éducative des requérants ou des demandeurs à l'adoption plutôt que de leur opposer un refus absolu et de principe?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3090.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3090.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3097.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3098.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3098.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3098.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Ziemele, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3102.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3104.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3104.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3116.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question both to the applicants' representative and to the government, and it follows the first question just exposed by Judge Potocki.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3116.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3137.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like the parties to clarify, in your submissions just now, the government said that the applicants never applied formally for a substitution of the father's lack of consent to the adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3137.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3154.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicants just argued that the Austrian courts have denied any inquiry into reasons for replacement of father's consent because the law does not allow it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3154.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3159.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I see a certain contradiction in these two submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3159.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3165.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would be very grateful to the parties for really clarifying that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3165.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3201.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And maybe for the applicant, if you would comment in your reply in relation to the regional court's decision, in which we can read the court's reasoning about the biological father having regular contacts with the child, also the fact that the child maintains a meaningful relationship, and the court's conclusion or interim conclusion in these circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3201.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3206.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, there is no need to replace either of the biological parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3206.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3219.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So would you maintain your submission in the light of the regional court's reasoning that there was no any substantive inquiry into the whole consent issue and the best interests of the child?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3219.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3219.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3222.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3223.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3223.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3228.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are there any other questions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3228.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3230.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That would be the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3230.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3237.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I propose then that we have a break of 15 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3237.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3241.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, we will meet again at 1025.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3241.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3242.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3301.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3302.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3349.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3350.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3353.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3357.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed and I give the floor to Mrs. Ohms again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3357.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3357.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, Mrs. Ohms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3361.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3366.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. President and thank you distinguished members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3368.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3377.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With your consent I would like to begin to answer the question of Miss Simile.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3381.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3399.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Austrian concerning the contradiction between the position of the Austrian government and the position of the applicants on points of facts. The Austrian law requires formal motions to replace</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3399.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3408.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>one parent's consent to adoption and such a formal motion was not taken in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3408.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3436.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If you look at the application made by the applicants, page 3, it seems that the applicant acted on the assumption that the court will do this act ex-offer. Here it is stated</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3436.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3448.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that his denial should be replaced. And in the operative part of the submission by the applicants,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3451.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3460.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>they are dealing with different objects. There they ask for the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3460.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3503.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>approval to the adoption agreement and to state at the same time that the family law relations between the biological father and the second applicant and the family members of the second applicant should not extinguish. So it's not, it's not, this operative part is not dealing</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3503.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3517.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with the replacement of the consent of the biological father at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3517.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3527.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I want to turn to the questions of Judge Potocki. In our view, the sexual orientation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3527.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3545.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was not relevant at all in this case insofar as we are dealing with a single-parent adoption where the precondition, the consent of the biological father, was not met.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3545.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3565.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the biological father had given his consent, the adoption would not have been possible but not on the grounds of sexual orientation. Also, as I have indicated earlier this morning,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3565.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3585.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>any man, like a possible new male partner of the mother or another male relative, would not have been in a position to adopt the child as long as the father did not consent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3585.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3601.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So let me turn to the next question. Whether it is impossible for the applicants or for same-sex</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3601.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3615.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>couples to adopt together. Austrian law allows the joint adoption only for married partners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3615.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3627.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only married partners can adopt jointly. But this is not the situation of our present applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3627.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3639.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are dealing now with the adoption by a single person. And there we are once again at this</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3639.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3654.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>precondition of the consent of the father. Here I want to mention that the Partnership Act of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3654.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3683.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>2010, which explicitly prohibits the adoption by same-sex partners, is not applicable for the present case because the last national judgment was given in 2006. So we have to look at the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3683.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3699.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>legal situation at that time. That's relevant. And for us, it's also very important when looking</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3699.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3711.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>or when making the proportionality test that there is no European standard at all. And we are</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3711.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3723.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the opinion with respect to the rich variety of solution within the European countries, that our solution is also proportional in this sense. Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3734.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3736.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mrs. Ohms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3736.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3738.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then I give the floor to Mr. Graupner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3744.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3749.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3749.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3757.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicants before the national courts have applied for a replacement of the consent of the father.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3757.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3762.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the representative of the Austrian government has quoted from our application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3762.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3769.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If we are saying to the court the consent of the father should be replaced, what else is it in an application?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3769.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3772.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have said to the court what we want.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3772.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3786.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it has to be noted that, as in many member states, I guess, under Austrian law, family law proceedings on these issues are not as formal proceedings as civil proceedings general.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3786.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3808.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a very informal proceeding where the law, the statutes, Austrian statutes, even state explicitly that no motion, no application, no income from any party should be rejected on any unjustified formal grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3808.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3812.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is what exactly the government wants to argue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3815.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3829.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What my client said were that the refusal of the father should be replaced as it is not justified, as he had seriously acted against the best interests of the child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3829.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3832.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was in our application to the district court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3832.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3841.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And B, that the interests of the child in the adoption supersedes his interest in objecting to it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3841.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3850.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So these are valuable, and it has not been contested grounds for replacement of consent under Austrian, under national law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3850.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3866.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So according to national law, Article 181 of the General Civil Code, the district court would have had to start an inquiry, of course, and deliver a decision on whether the consent be replaced or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3866.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3885.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have cited that in paragraphs 41, 42 of my written submissions to the Grand Chamber, that there is Supreme Court case law in Austria on this issue, that in such proceedings, the court has to give and render a separate decision on replacement of consent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3889.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3893.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No Austrian court has ever given such a separate decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3893.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3898.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have submitted this Supreme Court decision with the written observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3898.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3909.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Supreme Court says it can be combined in one document, but nevertheless, it has to be two separate decisions issued on replacement of consent and granting of adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3909.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3911.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What did the Austrian courts do?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3911.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3912.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They said, no.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3912.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3922.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dear women and their son, we cannot grant your adoption in any case, because you are two females.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3922.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3927.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are not looking into whether this adoption is of best interest for your child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3927.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3932.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do not look in whether the refusal of the father is justified or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3932.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3939.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You are of the same sex, and that's the reason why we are rejecting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3939.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3963.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No court, there were three instances, no court of any instance ever dismissed the approval of the adoption on the basis which argues the Austrian government, namely that there were not any formal requirements met or that there were no application for a replacement of consent of the father.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3963.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3970.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the question was specifically to the regional court decision, I would like to say a little bit to it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3970.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3981.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The regional court, court of second instance, starts its decision with a discussion if the child would have needed a special guardian for the court's adoption procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3981.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4012.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The appeals court concludes, I quote in my translation, we need not discuss this issue further, as this court takes the view that, as outlined below, the adoption in the present case has to be refused without further investigations that's a literal quote, without further investigations anyway, as the first instance courts did, so that a possible deficiency in lawful representation of the child is not decisive. Page 9. So it was not even necessary that the child</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4012.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4018.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>be lawfully represented in the proceedings. A representation we have to take into</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4018.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4038.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>mind, which should guarantee the best interests of the child, because establishing a guardian, a special guardian, is, of course, a measure in the best interest of the child to be adequately represented in the proceedings, not necessary, just because there are two women. And so there was no look into replacement</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4038.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4043.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the father's consent. And the court goes on saying, and I quote,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4043.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4056.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that a child, positive development, needs relations to a female and a male attachment figure. Please keep in mind, they are not saying</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4056.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4061.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a child needs relations to his or her father and mother.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4061.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4066.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are saying to a male and a female attachment figure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4066.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4089.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are saying, I quote, in opposite-sex couples, in step-parent adoption, the child, on page 13, the child keeps two parents and thus attachment figures of different sex, in heterosexual step-parent adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4089.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4105.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This situation, literally quote, which is so important, is not just a case of separation, literally quote, which is substantial for the child's development, however, could not be created by the adoption by the same-sex partner of a parent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4105.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4112.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the only issue was that they both are of the same sex and nothing else. The child</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4112.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4126.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the court says literally, the child should just be enabled to develop with constant contact with a male and a male parent. Please note, the court does not speak and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4126.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4132.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>say to develop with constant contact with his female and his male parent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4132.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4138.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are saying with a female and a male parent. So the issue for the regional</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4138.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4149.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>court was that there is a male and a female, not necessarily the biological parents. It can be adoptive parents. It can be foster parents, both not biological</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4149.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4156.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>parents. But the basic principle should be one man, one woman. And that's not connected</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4156.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4162.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the best interest of the child. That's just ideology. So the issue for also for</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4162.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4174.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the appeals court never was the consent of the father and that the legal requirements for its replacement were not fulfilled. It was exclusively based on this decision</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4174.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4185.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the child needs a female and a male attachment figure, not the biological parents, not mother and father, male and female attachment figures. And the Supreme</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4185.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4201.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Court in the court of last instance confirmed that, as I have cited it before, when the court said, given the legal impossibility of adoption, it's not necessary to have a male and a female attachment figure. So the Supreme Court confirmed</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4201.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4226.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>we are not looking into whether replacement of consent of the father and the adoption is in the best interest of the child because it's impossible based on the sex of the partners of the parents, biological parent and step-parent, and not in any way connected this refusal to go into that question on formal grounds or any other issues presented in the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4226.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4235.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issue is that my clients have been refused an inquiry and a decision on the merits. And the merits are whether it is in the best interest of the child that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4235.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4240.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the adoption be granted. And the issue and the violation of human rights is not that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4240.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4245.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the adoption has not been granted, as the government wants to put it. The issue</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4245.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4254.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the human rights violation is that there was no inquiry into the merits, into the best interest. It can be that the courts could have come to the conclusion,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4254.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4259.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>no, consent of the father should not be replaced. It's not in the best interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4259.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4268.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Like in heterosexual step-parent families, totally okay, no discrimination on sexual orientation, no discrimination on sex. But this inquiry has not been</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4268.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4272.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>made. And there is European standard. I contest it. There is European standard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4272.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4277.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have an overwhelming consensus of 42 member states. We have a European standard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4277.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4282.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Make no difference on basis of sex and sexual orientation. Make no difference</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4282.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4293.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>between unmarried heterosexual couples and unmarried homosexual couples when it comes to step-parent adoption. That share 42 member states. If this is not European</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4293.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4298.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>standard, we don't have European standard in any case. Because 100 percent you may</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4298.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4302.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>have in Northern Korea, but not in a pluralistic Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4302.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4310.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, Mr. President, dear members of the court, this court has ended the second-class</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4310.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4318.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>status of children born out of wedlock about 30 years ago. And we, my clients and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4318.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4339.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>myself, and many others in Europe concerned by this case, are respectfully submitting that you should also end the second-class status of children in rainbow families. Children living with their parents and their same-sex partners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4339.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4363.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And thereby, this court would contribute to the well-being and the pursuit of happiness of all children, regardless of the race, the ethnic origin, the color, the religion, and also on the basis of the gender and the sexual orientation of their parents. Many thanks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4366.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4370.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Graupner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4370.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4373.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4373.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4378.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to thank the parties for their interventions and their answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4378.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4383.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4383.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4389.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the court's decision and or judgment in due course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4389.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4389.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing in the case of X against Austria closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
