<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>2172211_12062012</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>19.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>19.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>52.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>55.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>55.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>65.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case of Volkov against Russia, against Ukraine, sorry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>65.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>76.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case was lodged on the 13th of March, 2011, with the court under Article 34 of the convention by Ukrainian national, Mr. Oleksandr Fedorovych Volkov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>76.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>86.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the fifth section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>86.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>94.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on the 18th of October, 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>94.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>102.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The defending government are represented by their agent, Mr. Kulchytskyy, assisted by Mr. Nasad, Mr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>102.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>107.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bem, Mr. Demchenko, Ms. Sukhova, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>107.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>110.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mr. Leach, lawyer,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>110.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>114.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Ms. Gordon and Ms. Popova, counselors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>114.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>118.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>118.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>123.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>123.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>134.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>134.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>138.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Kulchytskyy for the government will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>138.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>142.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mr. Leach for the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>142.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>144.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Kulchytskyy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>147.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>158.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable Court, the government have honored to submit their answers to additional questions put forward on an oral hearing in the case Volkov v. Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>158.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>175.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the questions of the court concerning independence and impartiality of the High Council of Justice, the government know that in their observation they submitted their entire list of legislative safeguards ensuring objective independence and impartiality of members of the Council.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>175.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>183.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant in his turn has failed to submit any concrete facts of external influence on the members of the Council.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>183.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>192.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, it's worth mentioning that the burden of proof as to alleged facts rests with the applicant and not with the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>192.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>205.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government note that the applicant complained about alleged subjective personal prejudice of three members of the Council, namely, Mr. Skivalov, Kolesnichenko, and Kuzmin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>205.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>212.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to applicant allegation concerning Mr. Skivalov, the government note that in 2007,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>212.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>224.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicant and several other judges challenged before Pechersk District Court of Kiev the Parliament's decision on a temporary procedure on election of judges to administrative position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>224.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>230.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result, Pechersk District Court suspended the effect of the Parliament's decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>230.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>238.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Subsequently, on 14 June 2007, Mr. Skivalov made an oral statement for mass media in which</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>238.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>247.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>he supposed that the judges who had been involved in submitting the mentioned claim had to be dismissed from the office for the branch of oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>247.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>258.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant in his application refers to the aforementioned statements as a proof of Mr. Skivalov's partiality in the course of subsequent proceedings of dismissal of the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>258.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>260.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>260.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>265.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The aforementioned statement of Mr. Skivalov was made more than six months prior to the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>265.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>268.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>start of events in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>268.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>278.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to this, government consider that there was no casual relationship between the statement of Mr. Skivalov and the dismissal proceeding against the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>278.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>284.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to Mr. Kolesnichenko and Kuzmin, the government called the Court's attention to the fact that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>284.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>299.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicant's complaint about their partiality were only attributable to the applicant's disagreement with the findings made by the mentioned persons in the Court of Internal Inquiry into the applicant's activity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>299.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>309.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the government's position, a mad disagreement with the findings of the above inquiries cannot serve as evidence of prejudice of the mentioned person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>309.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>315.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant further asserts that Mr. Kuzmin has initiated proceedings as to the applicant's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>315.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>318.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>dismissal on his own motion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>318.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>322.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government draws the Court's attention to the fact that Mr. Kuzmin, as a member of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>322.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>331.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Council, on behalf of the Chair of the Council, conducted an examination of the facts stated in the request of Ms. Polly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>331.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>338.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Upon the result of this examination, Mr. Kuzmin lodged with the Council a request on dismissal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>338.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>341.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>341.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>353.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government would like to answer the next question as to whether the consideration of the applicant's case by the Parliament was in conformity with the principle of separation of powers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>353.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>367.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the principle of separation of state powers in Ukraine, legislative, executive, and judicial authorities exercise the powers within the limit established by the Constitution of Ukraine and in compliance with the laws of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>367.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>379.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, Parliament is empowered to dismiss judges elected for an indefinite term from office under Article 126 of the Constitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>379.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>391.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the grounds envisaged for a branch of law, the powers to elect and dismiss judges are exercised by the Parliament through adopting a relevant resolution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>391.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>409.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, in answering the Court's question as to the influence by the members of the Judiciary Committee on the impartiality of the decision-making process, the government accepts that there was indeed an overlap between the composition of the Committee and the Council.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>409.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>415.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, three members of the Council were at the same time members of the Committee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>415.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>420.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the government notes that the Committee is a collegial body.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>420.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>434.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Decisions of the Committee are taken by simple majority vote, and the Committee itself acts within the limits of its competence, ensuring them exercised by the Parliament of its constitutional powers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>434.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>447.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Committee is not empowered to interfere in any way with the exercise by other state authorities, including the Council or Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>447.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>470.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Article 1 of the Law of Ukraine on Parliamentary Committee and Article 89 of the Constitution, Parliamentary Committee are not bodies of the state power, and their findings and recommendations are not binding on the Parliament and are of advisory character.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>470.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>498.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the question on the availability of sufficient safeguards of independence for judges of the High Administrative Court, especially with the Council, the government again refers to the position as presented in the observation of 15 February 2012, and considers that they listed a sufficient range of legislative safeguards for independence of justice at the High Administrative Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>498.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>514.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the government calls the Court's attention to the fact that the applicants never complained about alleged partiality or dependency of the judges at the High Administrative Court when the case was pending before the domestic authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>514.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>522.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, in his application to the Court, the applicant also failed to raise properly aforementioned issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>522.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>542.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having regard to the mentioned above, the government considers that the applicant has failed to adduce any evidence of the dependency of the High Administrative Court on the Council, and that they cannot accordingly be considered impartial in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>542.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>571.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In answering the Court's question whether the principle of legal certainty was respected in the proceeding during the consideration of the applicant's case at the plenary meeting of the Parliament and the voting procedure, the government would like to note that in this part the applicant complains and to uphold the position laid down in observation of 15 February 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>571.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>594.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to authenticity of the video provided by the applicant, the government note that no authority did not carry out the examination of the video record provided by the applicant, and therefore no conclusion of the competent authority as to time and place where the video was filmed as well as to the reliability of this was done.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>594.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>598.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, such evidence is inadmissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>598.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>603.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In answering the Court's question as to the legislative basis of Mr. Plosennik to occupy</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>603.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>612.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the post of judge and capability of his power with legislation, we insist on our position also laid down in our observation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>612.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>618.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, we would like to note that only upon the expiry of term of Mr. Plosennik's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>618.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>625.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>office on 22 December 2009, he was actually to be dismissed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>625.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>641.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, at that time the provision of the mentioned law that governs the procedure for dismissal of the Court's president had been declared unconstitutional, while no new legislation on that point had been adopted by the Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>641.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>651.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, there was no legally defined procedure of dismissal of a judge from an administrative position as on 22 December 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>651.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>657.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, any actions aimed at dismissing Mr. Plosennik from the position of the head</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>657.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>661.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the Court would have been contrary to valid national legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>661.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>682.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to ensure the free exercise by the person of the constitutional right to a judicial remedy, the Conference of Judges from the Administrative Courts of Ukraine decided that the duties of the President of the High Administrative Court be temporarily performed by Mr. Plosennik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>682.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>712.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the Court's question of the applicant's violation of his rights to a written judgment, as far as this part of the applicant's complaint is concerned, the applicant maintained that the High Administrative Court failed to consider his allegations that some of the members of the High Council of Justice and those of the Parliamentary Committee were partial towards him and that the decision of the Parliament on his dismissal was unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>712.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>718.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We consider that this allegation of the applicant does not conform to the truth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>718.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>725.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, the government would like to refer to the decision of the High Administrative Court of 19 October 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>725.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>743.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the mentioned decision, the Court noted that the applicant indeed alleged that three members of High Council of Justice were interested in his dismissal in view in particular of his involvement in judicial self-government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>743.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>764.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In response to those complaints, the Court, having examined the submission of the High Council of Justice, noted the circumstances of the case disclosed, the applicant's personal prejudice or bias in this â€“ in the exercise of his professional duties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>764.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>771.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The mentioned facts were in the judge's opinion indicative of his branch of office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>771.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>785.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the submission proposing to dismiss the applicant from the office had been confirmed, the Court decided that his dismissal could not have been connected with his involvement in judicial self-government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>785.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>799.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the applicant's allegation about the partiality of the Parliamentary Committee's members, the government observed that those allegations of the applicant were also considered by the High Administrative Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>799.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>808.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having examined them, the Court noted in particular that the Parliament was an authority competent to take decision on dismissal of judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>808.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>817.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, findings of the Parliamentary Committee on the judiciary were recommendatory and were not binding to the Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>817.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>825.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, each member of the Parliament participating in voting had to decide on his own.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>825.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>832.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the mentioned facts indicate that those allegations of the applicant were properly examined by the High Administrative Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>832.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>845.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the government would like to reiterate that the domestic courts is not obliged to provide a detailed analysis of all arguments of the applicants in its judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>845.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>859.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, in this present case, the applicant's allegations about the lack of partiality on the part of the Council of Justice were rather general in character and did not corroborate them with concrete facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>859.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>877.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the government considered that in order for certain allegations to be examined by the Court shortly and for the resulted findings to be set out in the Court decision, the applicant should provide detailed arguments in support of such allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>877.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>887.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, he or she must submit any specific circumstances on which an objective observer could doubt the impartiality of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>887.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>895.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As already noted above, the applicant failed to deduce sufficient arguments in support of his allegation about partiality towards him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>895.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>908.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government accordingly in the view that the arguments set out by the High Administrative Court in its decision are sufficient for resolution to be regarded as reasoned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>908.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>923.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the applicant contends that the High Administrative Court did not properly examine his complaint of the alleged unlawfulness of the Parliament's resolution on the basis of which he had been dismissed from the office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>923.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>940.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decision of the High Administrative Court of 19 October 2010 clearly states that on the applicant's initiative, the Court examined the documents with records of the individual voting held in the Parliament on 17 June 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>940.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>957.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result of the Court found that in favor of a resolution of the applicant's dismissal from the post of the judge, there were 1,200 247 votes, while 226 were required for adoption of such a decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>957.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>964.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, the Court held that the resolution of Parliament was lawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>964.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>976.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the Court noted that the applicant had been present at the motioned session and was able to express his opinion as regards the submission of the High Council of Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>976.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>987.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the government considers that the dismissal proceedings against the applicant were properly reviewed by the Court and its findings are reflected in each judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>987.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1001.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government would like also to note that the branch of establishing the Constitution of Ukraine parliamentary procedure of adopting legal acts is the reason for finding those acts unconstitutional.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1001.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1019.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Article 171, Prime 1 of the Code of Administrative Procedure of Ukraine, it doesn't belong to the competence of the High Administrative Court to adjudicate the compliance of legal acts adopted by the Parliament in the Constitution of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1019.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1025.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For this reason, the High Administrative Court doesn't consider the voting procedure in the Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1025.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1032.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The above facts were also mentioned in the Court's resolution of 19 October 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1032.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1048.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the government considers that the dismissal proceedings against the applicant were properly examined by the Court and its findings were reflected in its decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1048.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1072.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we would like to turn the Court's question concerning the alleged inability of the High Administrative Court to formally quash the decision of the High Council of Justice and the Parliament in the applicant's case and the alleged absence of rules on further conduct of the proceedings in the event of those decisions being declared unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1072.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1098.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the complaints of the applicant, the government observes that in the response of his action to set aside the resolution of the Parliament and the decision of the High Council of Justice, the High Administrative Court noted that it was only empowered under Article 171, Prime 1 of the Code of Administrative Justice to review the lawfulness of those decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1098.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1118.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, the government points to the fact that on 1 July 2011, the High Administrative Court analyzed and summarized its practice as regards proceedings brought by action challenging decision of Parliament and those of the High Council of Justice on dismissal of judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1118.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1123.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The aforementioned was clarified in the Court's letter of 1 July 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1123.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1134.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having made the mentioned analysis, the Court concluded that in cases similar to the applicant case, claimants tended to formulate their claims differently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1134.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1140.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, they often sought to have acts of Parliament set aside.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1140.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1149.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given that, the Court noted that it was only competent to declare a decision unlawful, that is, incompatible with law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1149.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1174.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In such an event, there is no need for Court to question it in order to then or to order the body to adopt or annul its decision, since the declaration of its unlawfulness means that it has not given rise to any legal consequences since the day of its adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1174.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1185.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the annulment of the decision means that it lost its effect no earlier than from the time of respective Court's decision-take effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1185.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1206.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, in its practice, the High Administrative Court has rejected actions of annulment of impugned acts, and such claims do not fall within competence, and because a finding of unlawful is also in itself to address such a claim. Also, the mentioned clarification</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1206.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1213.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was provided in July 2011. It concerns the practice that had been in place prior</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1213.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1219.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to its adoption. The mentioned practice is uniform and doesn't raise doubts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1219.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1224.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the applicant's dismissal had been declared unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1224.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1228.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He would have been treated as having not been dismissed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1228.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1239.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, he would have been entitled to obtain compensation, and in particular, the salary for period during which it not had been paid to him in view of his dismissal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1239.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1250.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In answering the Court question as to whether the applicant's dismissal was compatible with requirements of Article 8 of the Convention, the government would like to note the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1250.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1270.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The dismissal of the applicant from the post of the judge and consequently the alleged interference with his right granted by Article 8 of the Convention were effected in accordance with law in force. Those laws were publicly accessible</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1270.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1282.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and formulated with sufficient precision that enabled the applicant to foresee the consequences of his action in the capacity of judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1282.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1306.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the legislation applicable at that time envisaged disciplinary liability of a judge in the form of requirement for demotion in the qualification round, and also a specially defined liability for branch of oath dismissal of a judge from the office. The government observed that the liability for branch of oath</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1306.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1319.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was defined by the legislation separately in view of the fact that such branch in itself has a particularly negative impact on the public's confidence in the judiciary in the State.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1319.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1337.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, in the instant case, the applicant was brought to liability not for single unlawful act, but for a series of four acts, continuing branch of oath, discrediting him as a judge. For these reasons, time limits for holding the judge liability</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1337.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1343.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for branch of oath could not be applied. It's also worth mentioning that according</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1343.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1367.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the decision of Constitutional Court of Ukraine of 11 March 2011, the provisions of Article 32 of the Law of Ukraine and Higher Council of Justice, which govern the issue of dismissal of a judge for branch of oath, complied with the Constitution of Ukraine. The government therefore point out that the legal status of the judge</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1367.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1388.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>presupposed both availability of constitutional and defined guarantees of his independence and immunity in administrating justice, as well as possibility of holding him legally liable for failure to perform his duties, in particular dismissing him from office for branch of oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1388.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1400.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the last question of the Court, the government would like to observe that they adhere to their position as set out in the observation of 15 February 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1400.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1420.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, it should be noted that fighting of violation of Article 46 of Convention in cases like the instant one is in the fact to indicate necessity for the responding State to introduce relevant changes into domestic legal system in order to eliminate the exciting problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1420.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1440.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, when finding a violation of Article 46 of the Convention on the account of differences in the domestic legal system, the Court normally refers to legislation applied by the domestic authorities in the particular case of the applicant concerned. Consequently, in so far as it's concerned, a finding of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1440.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1457.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>violation disclosing the existence of a persistent problem of a systemic nature, the application of Article 46 of the Convention depends on the valuability of the legislation in question at the time of adoption decision by the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1457.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1484.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here, the government would like to call attention to the fact that since the time the applicant applied to the Court, numerous and substantial changes have been introduced into national legislation which have been applied in the course of dismissal proceeding against him and which are under examination of the Court in present case. In particular, on 7 July 2010, the law of Ukraine on High</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1484.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1489.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Council of Justice was amendment. The amendments introduced with the aim to</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1489.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1503.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ensuring the mentioned body would be more independent, consisted in a substantial increase in number of judges among the member. In particular, according to new</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1503.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1516.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>wording of the law, 11 out of 20 members of the High Council of Justice should be judges. Hence, judges constitute the majority of the compulsion of the High</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1516.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1523.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Council of Justice. According to Article 111 of the law of Ukraine on Judiciary</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1523.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1541.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Judges Status adopted on 7 July 2010, dismissal proceeding against judge elected for an identified term are to be held before the plenary session of the Parliament with no requirement for findings of parliamentary committee or any inquiries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1541.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1555.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, we would like to call the Court's attention to the fact that on 5 June 2012, the Parliament passed on a law on amendments on certain legal acts of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1555.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1569.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The mentioned law provides for measures of strengthening the guarantees of judges independence. In particular, according to Article 1 of the law, which was amended,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1569.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1587.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that inquiries in response to a request from the prosecution authorities into allegation of misconduct by the judge in conducting certain court proceedings may only be carried out if the case in question is not pending before a court of any level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1587.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1606.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, a member of High Council of Justice who holds the post of prosecutor or held at that time of his appointment may not be entrusted with concluding such inquiry. However, the Court may not assess the changes that have taken place</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1606.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1617.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in domestic legislation since the time when it was applied by the domestic authorities in present case. It follows in particular from the fact that it's not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1617.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1629.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a function to rule in abstracto in assessing domestic law in terms of its compatibility with the Convention. That is where such assessment is beyond the context of examination</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1629.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1635.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of a specific complaint about a violation by the State of any subjective right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1635.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1653.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the government considers that the Court may assess only those laws which were applied in the applicant's case and which, as he alleged, led to violation of his rights under the Convention. However, in the view of those substantial</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1653.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1672.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>changes that have taken place in domestic legislation, any analysis in terms of Article 46 of the Convention of the laws which were applied in the applicant's case and to the Court has lost its relevance. Thus, most of alleged by the applicant's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1672.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1684.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>legislation which, according to him, caused problems of systemic nature, concerned the procedure of formation of High Council of Judges. At the same time, it was above</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1684.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1691.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>procedure which became the subject of most changes in domestic legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1691.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1706.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as the government knows, the grounds for deciding on measures to address systemic problems may only raise doubt of finding a violation made in the context of existing domestic legal system. Therefore, we consider that it's impossible</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1706.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1717.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to determine from the circumstances of this particular case whether there currently exists a systemic problem in Ukrainian legal system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1717.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1733.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, in the commentaries to the government's observations, the applicant asserts that the violation of his rights resulted from presence of problems of systemic nature in Ukrainian legislation. Instead of this, in his application to</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1733.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1743.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Court, the applicant asserts that his dismissal was a result of numerous violations of national legislation. Such position of the applicant confirms in</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1743.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1754.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the government opinion the absence of the problem of systemic nature in Ukrainian legislation. Due to the aforementioned, the government considers that Article 46</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1754.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1755.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is not applicable in the instant case. Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1761.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1768.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mr Kulchytskyy. I call Mr Leach please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1772.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1779.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the dismissal of Supreme Court Judge Alexander Volkov in circumstances involving</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1779.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1791.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a flagrant denial of natural justice originates in the ongoing systemic constitutional crisis in Ukraine. It reflects the failure to respect the rule of law, undermining the principle</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1791.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1802.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the separation of powers, and demonstrating an overwhelming level of political control over the senior judiciary. This lack of independence of the judiciary in Ukraine and the blatant</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1802.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1813.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>intervention of government and parliament have been noted by this Court in previous cases such as SovtransAvto Holdings, Salove and AgroComplex. And it's been analysed and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1813.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1831.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>condemned in recent years by a host of independent international organisations, including the Venice Commission, the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe, the Commissioner for Human Rights, the OECD, the European Association of Judges, and Transparency International.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1831.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1841.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And a number of these bodies have called for constitutional reform in order to free the judiciary from political control. Mr. President, the applicant maintains each of the arguments</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1841.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1851.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>set out in his written observations, but our submissions this morning will focus on the Court's eight questions. I will respond to the first four, after which Ms. Gordon will</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1851.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1857.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>respond to questions five to eight. The first question, concerning the requirement of independence</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1857.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1864.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and impartiality. The High Council of Justice fails each of the Court's tests of independence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1864.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1876.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The manner of appointment of its members, their terms of office, the existence of guarantees against outside pressure, and whether it presents an appearance of independence. The High Council</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1876.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1881.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Justice is neither independent of the executive nor of the legislature. Both the President</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1881.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1894.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Ukraine and the legislature, the Vokovna Rada, are directly involved in the appointment of its members. At the time of these events, its composition included the Minister of Justice,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1894.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1906.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Deputy Chief of Staff of the Administration of the President of Ukraine, and three deputies of the Vokovna Rada. Indeed, as the Venice Commission has noted, 50% of the members belong</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1906.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1912.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to or were appointed by the executive or the legislature. Its composition also included</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1912.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1918.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Prosecutor General and three other senior officials from his office. This Court, of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1918.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1928.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>course, has frequently emphasised that prosecutors cannot be considered to have the status of independent and impartial actors. The judgment in merit in Ukraine confirmed that the Prosecutor</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1928.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1933.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>General is part of the executive branch of the government. And various international</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1933.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1939.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>bodies have noted the powerful position of the Procurator in Ukraine. In accordance with</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1939.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1952.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 131 of the Constitution, the Congress of Judges of Ukraine is entitled to appoint only three of the 20 members of the High Council of Justice. This contrasts sharply with this</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1952.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1968.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Court's position, as confirmed by the Lecomte and Belgium decision, that to be a strong indicator of independence and impartiality, at least half the membership of such a tribunal should be composed of judges. The Domestic Law does not specify the length of term of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1968.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1979.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>office of members of the High Council of Justice sitting on an ex officio basis, including the Minister of Justice and the Prosecutor General. The Venice Commission has highlighted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1979.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1989.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the structural deficiency of the composition of the Council and it has concluded that there are insufficient guarantees to ensure that it safeguards fundamental principles of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1989.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2004.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our submission, the High Council of Justice could not be considered to be independent of the executive or the legislature, which have a decisive level of control and influence over it. This was a body which at May 2010 had more than 140 proposals pending before</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2005.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2011.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it for the dismissal of judges for breach of oath made by its members.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2011.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2016.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn now to the question of impartiality. The proceedings against Mr. Volkov breach</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2016.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2034.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the objective impartiality requirement because various members of the High Council of Justice were directly involved in both the instigation and the consideration of the proceedings against the applicants. I refer in particular to the involvement of Mr. Kivarov, Mr. Kuzmin,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2034.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2040.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. V. M. Kolesnichenko. As a member of the Parliamentary Committee on the Judiciary,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2040.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2044.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Kivarov transmitted a complaint to the High Council of Justice against Mr. Volkov</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2044.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2051.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in early 2008, and he wrote to the High Council of Justice in December 2008 to accuse Mr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2051.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2057.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Volkov in relation to his links with Judge Baranenko. He was a member of the High Council</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2057.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2063.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Justice which made the decisions in Mr. Volkov's case in May 2010. He then presided</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2063.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2074.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as chair at the meeting of the Parliamentary Committee on the Judiciary on 16 June 2010, which recommended Mr. Volkov's dismissal. And as chair of that committee, he then reported</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2074.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2085.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the Plenary Parliament on 17 June, informing them that the committee recommended the dismissal of 12 judges, including Mr. Volkov. The papers relating to the complaint</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2085.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2091.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>lodged against Mr. Volkov in 2008 were submitted by the High Council of Justice to Mr. Kuzmin</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2091.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2096.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as first deputy prosecutor general in order for them to be investigated. Mr. Kuzmin himself</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2096.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2107.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>submitted a request to the High Council of Justice for the dismissal of the applicant for breach of oath in December 2008. Mr. Kuzmin was also a member of the High Council</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2107.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2110.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Justice which made the decision in the applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2110.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2117.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In March 2009, Mr. Kolesnichenko submitted a proposal to the High Council of Justice</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2117.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2122.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for Mr. Volkov's dismissal, which explicitly attacked his objectivity, his impartiality,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2122.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2128.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and his independence, and alleged he'd committed gross violations of the law. Mr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2128.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2139.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kolesnichenko was himself the chairman of the High Council of Justice, which made the decisions in Mr. Volkov's case. He also took the floor in the Plenary Parliament</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2139.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2144.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on 17 June 2010 to lay out the accusations against him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2144.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2149.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn to the requirement for subjective impartiality. The applicant submits that members</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2149.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2160.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the High Council of Justice were personally biased against him, in particular Mr. Kivalov and Mr. Kolesnichenko, as evidenced by their extraordinary levels of involvement</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2160.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2169.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the various stages of the proceedings against him, as I've just outlined, and the very nature and wording of their complaints. We say that no one in their position could have</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2169.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2180.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>been unaware of the fundamental breaches of natural justice caused by there being, in effect, prosecutor and judge in the same action. From this alone, their lack of subjective</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2180.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2185.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>impartiality can be inferred. This case is much clearer even than Verner and Poland,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2185.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2200.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>where the Court found that it was reasonable to accept that the judge who submitted a motion and later sat on the Court which heard it would have had an unacceptable personal conviction. But what is more, at the High Council of Justice meetings</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2200.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2205.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in 2009 and 2010, including one chaired by Mr. Kolesnichenko, the proceedings</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2205.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2210.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>concerning Mr. Volkov's dismissal were taken off the agenda by the chairman. This</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2210.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2221.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was because 14 votes were needed to ensure his dismissal, and it became clear at those meetings that the requisite votes would not be obtained. It was also intentional</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2221.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2227.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the hearing of the High Council of Justice on 26 May 2010 was conducted in Mr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2227.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2232.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Volkov's absence. And I refer to the statements of Mr. Barbara and Mr. Sofulko,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2232.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2237.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>who confirm that at that meeting, Mr. Onopenko, the President of the Supreme</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2237.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2243.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Court, informed the chairman that Mr. Volkov had valid reasons for being absent,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2243.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2248.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that he had ordered Mr. Volkov to attend to judicial business at the military</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2248.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2253.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>court of appeal in Sevastopol. Nevertheless, Mr. Kolesnichenko decided to proceed</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2253.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2258.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with the hearing in the applicant's absence, resulting in Mr. Onopenko leaving</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2258.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2263.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the hearing, but he refused to take part in a meeting that was biased against Mr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2263.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2269.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Volkov. Mr. Barbara and Mr. Sofulko both say it was clear that the majority of the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2269.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2280.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>members of the High Council of Justice who were not representative of the judiciary were personally biased against Mr. Volkov. In the same week in May 2010, Mr. Kivalov</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2280.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2291.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was quoted in the national weekly newspaper Yezhynyrdelnik 2000 speaking disparagingly of the meeting by name Mr. Volkov. The applications by the High Council of Justice</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2291.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2296.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for the dismissal of Mr. Volkov were referred to the Parliamentary Committee</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2296.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2301.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the Judiciary before being referred to the Plenary Parliament. This process was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2301.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2316.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>clearly incompatible with the principle of the separation of powers and violated the principle of the independence of the judiciary from political interference in the judiciary. The members of the High Council of Justice were also members</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2316.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2321.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the Parliamentary Committee, and indeed Mr. Kivalov was its chairman. As to the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2321.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2337.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>role of the Plenary Parliament, the 2004 Judges Election and Dismissal Act simply stated that Parliament was required to take a decision on the dismissal of a judge on the grounds that the judge had breached his oath. In reality, this amounted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2337.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2342.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the High Council of Justice and the Parliamentary Committee. As to the Higher</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2342.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2361.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Administrative Court, the Code of Administrative Justice provides that decisions of the High Council of Justice may be challenged before the Higher Administrative Court for which purpose a separate chamber is to be set up, comprising at least five judges. There are no other legislative provisions dealing with the composition</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2361.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2366.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of that separate chamber. This serious defect has been noted by the Venice</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2366.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2382.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Commission, which has stated that the composition of this chamber, because of the significance of the cases it has to decide, should be set out in an objective way in the law. Otherwise, the risks of endangering the independence and impartiality</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2382.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2392.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the judiciary increase as political interferences in the composition of the court might occur. And there was a heightened such risk in this case, first because</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2392.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2407.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the decision was being reviewed by the court, was controlled by the executive and the legislature, and second because the court was being asked to review the decisions of Parliament itself, as well as one of its committees. I turn to the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2407.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2413.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>second question, the failure to apply any time limits. No limitation period was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2413.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2417.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>applied in Mr Volkov's case, as we've heard. The Higher Administrative Court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2417.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2431.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>found that there was no basis in the domestic law for applying the limitation periods referred to in either the Status of Judges Act 1992 or the High Council of Justice Act 1998. Mr Volkov had argued that the High Council of Justice should</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2431.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2447.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>correctly have applied Article 37 of the 1998 Act, which expressly provides for the dismissal of a Supreme Court judge, in which case various procedural guarantees would have applied, including the limitation set down in Section 43. That would</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2447.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2453.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>have meant a limitation period of either six months or one year. In fact, proceedings</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2453.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2464.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>brought against Mr Volkov, which were instigated in 2008 and 2009, concerned decisions he made going back to 2006 and even 2002 to 2003. In our submission,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2464.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2476.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicable law was opaque and incoherent, and there was a total lack of clarity or consistency in its application. I turn to the third question concerning</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2476.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2481.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the proceedings before the Plenary Parliament. When the Plenary Parliament</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2481.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2486.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>considered Mr Volkov's case, both Mr Kivalov and Mr V.M. Kolesnichenko took the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2486.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2491.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>floor to present the accusations against Mr Volkov. The Plenary voted in favor of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2491.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2501.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicant's dismissal as a judge, but members of Parliament present unlawfully cast multiple votes by using votes belonging to other MPs who were not there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2501.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2511.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is established not only by statements from the applicant and four MPs, all of whom were present, but also by the video of the proceedings. That video clearly</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2511.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2521.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>shows MPs reaching across from their positions in order to press the voting buttons of their absent neighbors. And when you see the video, it's obvious why this practice</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2521.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2526.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is commonly referred to in Ukraine as playing the piano. Two hundred and forty-seven</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2526.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2531.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>MPs were recorded as having voted. Mr Volkov has said that in fact no more than</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2531.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2537.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>140 to 150 MPs were present. I turn to the fourth question. Was the applicant's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2537.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2543.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>case considered by a tribunal established by law? This Court's case law is very</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2543.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2559.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>clear that in order to merit the designation of a tribunal, a body must have full jurisdiction to examine all questions of fact and law relevant to the dispute and satisfy various requirements, including independence of the executive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2559.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2573.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant submits that neither the High Council of Justice nor the Parliamentary Committee on the Judiciary nor the Plenary Parliament can be considered a tribunal established by law. This requirement was also breached because of the manner in which</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2573.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2577.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Chamber of the Higher Administrative Court was established and composed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2577.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2587.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The High Council of Justice could not constitute a tribunal established by law as it was a binding decision. It simply referred recommendations for Mr Volkov's dismissal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2587.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2592.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the Parliamentary Committee on the Judiciary. Similarly, that committee also had</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2592.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2597.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>no power to reach a binding decision. It made a recommendation on the case to the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2597.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2602.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Plenary Parliament. And none of these bodies were independent from the executive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2602.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2613.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the Higher Administrative Court, Judge Pasyniuk was appointed by the President and Chairman for a five-year term on 22 December 2004. His term, therefore, expired</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2613.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2620.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on 22 December 2009. There was no legislative basis for him to continue beyond that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2620.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2626.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>date. However, after the expiry of his term of office, Mr Pasyniuk issued an order</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2626.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2635.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to constitute the special chamber of the Higher Administrative Court which would hear the applicant's case. Mr Volkov sought to challenge the list of judges before</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2635.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2644.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Court, contrary to what we've heard this morning, on the basis of its unlawful composition by Mr Pasyniuk. But his application was rejected as being unsubstantiated,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2644.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2649.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and there was no right of appeal against that decision. Convention case law has clarified</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2649.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2670.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the object of the term established by law is to ensure that the judicial organization in a democratic society does not depend on the discretion of the executive, but that it is regulated by laws and in Austria, and that the organization of the judicial system is not left to the discretion of the judicial authorities, Kerm and Belgium.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2670.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2686.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The term law incorporates any provision of domestic law which, if breached, would render the participation of one or more of the judges in the examination of a case irregular. And in cases such as Gurov and Moldova, the participation of a judge</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2686.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2691.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the summary of his term of office led to a finding of a violation of Article 6.1,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2691.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2696.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for the same reasons Article 6, we say, has been breached in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2696.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2700.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr President, that concludes my submissions, and Ms Gordon will now respond to questions 5 to 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2705.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2708.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Leach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2708.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2709.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Try to call Miss Gordon, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2709.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2710.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Miss Gordon, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2711.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2712.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2712.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2719.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn next to the question of whether there has been a violation of the applicant's right to a reasoned judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2719.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2722.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that there was a violation of Article 6.1</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2722.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2729.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because of the higher administrative court's failure to properly address a number of Mr. Volkow's principal grounds</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2729.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2745.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of appeal, including the allegations of personal bias of certain members of the High Council of Justice and parliamentary committee against him and the voting irregularities in Parliament resulting in an unlawful decision to dismiss him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2745.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2748.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In essence, Mr. Volkow submits that the higher administrative</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2748.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2767.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>court simply repeated the findings reached by the High Council of Justice to the effect that he had breached his judicial oath, but it failed to adequately explain the reasons why it considered his oath to have been breached or to set out the evidence it relied upon to reach this finding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2767.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2771.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the higher administrative court determined that Mr. Volkow had had a personal interest</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2771.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2774.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in a case he had dealt with as judge of the Supreme Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2774.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2778.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the court failed to identify or explain the nature of this personal interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2778.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2782.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Its decision was based on generalities and unjustified assumptions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2782.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2786.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was therefore no proper basis for its finding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2786.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2793.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the higher administrative court relied upon this unsubstantiated conclusion of Mr. Volkow's personal interest</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2793.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2802.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to dismiss in their entirety his claims regarding the personal bias of members of the High Council of Justice and the parliamentary committee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2802.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2813.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Without providing any further reasoning or justification, the court simply referred to its own finding of the applicant's bias to refute and reject Mr. Volkow's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2813.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2815.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>claims of bias against him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2815.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2831.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court thereby categorically failed to consider his allegations, which were critical to the assessment of the legality of the proceedings before the High Council of Justice and to the legitimacy of the parliamentary decision which resulted in his dismissal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2831.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2847.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Kuznetsov and others in Russia, this court found a violation of Article 6 because domestic courts failed to address submissions on key arguments, remained silent on a crucial point, and failed to explain the reasons for rejecting the evidence put forward by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2847.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2850.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same reasoning can be applied to the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2850.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2854.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The higher administrative court's failure to address Mr. Volkow's arguments regarding</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2854.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2865.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the personal bias of members of the High Council of Justice as well as the parliamentary committee and to consider the evidence relating to that allegation violated Mr. Volkow's right to a recent judgment</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2865.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2867.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>under Article 6.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2867.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2873.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We further submit that the higher administrative court failed to properly address Mr. Volkow's allegation regarding</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2873.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2877.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the unlawfulness of the parliamentary decision to dismiss him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2877.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2880.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Volkow's statement, the statements of the four MPs,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2880.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2886.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the video evidence irrefutably demonstrate that MPs present for the vote on Mr. Volkow's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2886.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2892.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>dismissal deliberately and unlawfully cast votes belonging to other MPs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2892.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2897.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet the court's consideration of the allegation of unlawful voting was perfunctory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2897.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2902.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It failed to set out the nature of the allegation made or to assess the evidence put forward.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2902.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2911.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, the court simply referred to the data roll call vote and relied upon it as an accurate record of the number of MPs present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2911.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2912.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This missed the point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2912.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2914.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The allegation made by Mr. Volkow</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2914.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2920.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was that the data roll call was deliberately manipulated by MPs with the result that the vote was unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2920.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2923.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court failed to address this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2923.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2933.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, the court held that it did not have the authority to review the constitutional compliance of a parliamentary decision and concluded the matter on this basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2933.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2935.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It thereby ignored Mr. Volkow's arguments</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2935.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2948.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the legality of the parliamentary vote, specifically that the abuse of the voting procedure violated the law of Ukraine on the status of people's deputies of Ukraine and the law of Ukraine on regulations of Parliament of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2948.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2951.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court's judgment is silent on the point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2951.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2963.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Like Prunina and Ukraine and Bokon and Ukraine, this case again demonstrates Ukrainian domestic courts ignoring specific, relevant, and important submissions concerning questions central to the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2963.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2969.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that the failure of the High Administrative Court to analyze Mr. Volkow's specific allegations regarding</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2969.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2977.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the unlawfulness of the parliamentary decision to dismiss him falls short of the requirement under Article 6.1 for judicial authorities</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2977.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2981.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to give adequate reasons for their decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2981.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2987.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I move next to the sixth question, whether there has been a violation of the applicant's right to a court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2987.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2999.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Higher Administrative Court is unable to quash acts carried out by the High Council of Justice, which it finds to be unlawful, because it is not empowered by Article 1711 of the Administrative Code to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2999.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3006.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court explicitly confirmed this legal position in its judgment of 19th of October, 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3006.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3012.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, the Higher Administrative Court is not empowered to review the constitutionality of parliamentary resolutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3012.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3020.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, the court explicitly confirmed this legal position in its judgment, stating that this falls within the remit of the Constitutional Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3020.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3027.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the proceedings in this case, the Higher Administrative Court held that Mr. Volkov's claim was satisfied in part.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3027.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3037.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court declared unlawful the decision of the High Council of Justice of 26 May, 2010, which found that Mr. Volkov violated his judicial oath</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3037.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3044.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because he concealed the fact of his familial relationship with Judge Baranenko, the brother of Mr. Volkov's wife.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3044.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3051.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court held that under the law then applicable, Mr. Volkov and Judge Baranenko were not considered relatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3051.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3059.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court found no facts indicating personal interest and concluded that there was no evidence of a violation of his judicial oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3059.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3062.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the court refused Mr. Volkov's claim</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3062.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3071.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the High Council of Justice's decision of the 26th of May and subsequent parliamentary resolution to dismiss him should be negated or canceled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3071.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3077.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court stated that it did not have the legal jurisdiction or powers to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3077.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3093.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no statutory procedure or set of rules governing the further conduct of proceedings in the event that the higher administrative court declares a decision of the High Council of Justice and its submission to Parliament to be unlawful, or it's being the consequence of such a declaration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3093.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3100.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This effectively renders, we submit, the higher administrative court's declaration meaningless.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3100.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3105.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the basis of the above, we submit there has been a violation of Mr. Volkov's right to a court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3105.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3130.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as required by Article VI, on account of, first, the insufficiency of the jurisdiction and review powers of the higher administrative court, second, its inability to formally quash the decisions of the High Council of Justice and or Parliament, and finally, the absence of rules on the further conduct of proceedings in the event that the court declares decisions of the High Council of Justice and or Parliament unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3130.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3136.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn now to question 7, whether the applicant's dismissal was compatible with Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3136.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3138.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The concept of private life under Article 8.1</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3138.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3145.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>includes moral integrity and the protection of reputation and incorporates relations in the professional sphere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3145.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3148.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Volkov was dismissed for breaching his judicial oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3148.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3159.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The High Council of Justice considered that he had discredited the reputation of the judiciary and displayed a lack of integrity in carrying out his responsibilities as a judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3159.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3163.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The higher administrative court concluded that he had demonstrated bias and personal interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3163.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3166.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no doubt, therefore, that Mr. Volkov's dismissal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3166.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3170.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>raised fundamental questions as to his moral integrity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3170.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3174.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has conceded that there has been an interference with Mr. Volkov's right</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3174.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3176.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to respect for his private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3176.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3182.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that this interference cannot be justified in accordance with Article 8.2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3182.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3192.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the applicable domestic law on the dismissal of a judge for breach of oath is too vague to comply with the in accordance with the law test.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3192.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3201.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not until 15th of May 2010 that Article 32 of the law on the High Council of Justice set out what constitutes a breach of oath by a judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3201.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3207.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even then, the article failed to precisely define the conduct which will give rise to a breach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3207.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3219.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is vague and uncertain, using such phraseology as the commission of actions which dishonor the judicial office and violation of moral and ethical principles of the judicial code of conduct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3219.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3226.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The result is that it is neither clear nor foreseeable in law what conduct gives rise to a breach of oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3226.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3234.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This legal uncertainty of the domestic law has been criticized by independent international bodies, including the OECD and the Venice Commission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3234.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3265.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its opinion of October 2010, the Venice Commission highlighted a number of serious concerns with Article 32, including its overlap with the provisions of the law and the judiciary and the status of judges, thereby creating complexity and uncertainty in relation to the disciplinary regime for judges and its inclusion of very general concepts, which the commission considered dangerous because of the possibility of using the article as a political weapon against judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3265.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3278.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our second point regarding legal uncertainty is that Article 32 of the law on the High Council of Justice sets down no time limit in relation to the disciplinary procedure for the dismissal of a judge for breach of oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3278.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3287.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that there is no finite period within which the disciplinary procedure for judicial breach of oath must be initiated or completed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3287.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3294.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This causes significant uncertainty and imposes no requirement that allegations be dealt with expeditiously.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3294.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3299.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, there is no time bar on making an allegation or finding a breach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3299.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3310.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As such cases as Kresland and France make clear, the expression in accordance with the law under Article 82 requires that a measure which interferes with an individual's private life must have some basis in domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3310.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3321.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But further, it refers to the quality of the law in question, requiring that it should be accessible to the person concerned, who must moreover be able to foresee its consequences for him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3321.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3329.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But additionally, adequate safeguards against possible abuse must be put in place, including time limits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3329.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3345.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that Ukrainian law does not indicate, with either reasonable clarity, the scope and manner of exercise of the discretion conferred on the High Council of Justice in relation to the disciplinary procedure for the dismissal of a judge for breach of oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3345.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3351.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The absence of time limits makes the discretion open-ended and arbitrary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3351.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3361.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, on Article 8, we submit that the disciplinary procedure for breach of judicial oath is disproportionate, because the only possible sanction that can be imposed is dismissal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3361.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3378.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Special Rapporteur on the Independence of Judges and Lawyers states that disciplinary measures must be in proportionality to the gravity of the infraction committed by the judge, and calls for the adoption of a well-defined scheme of available disciplinary measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3378.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3389.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, Article 126 of the Constitution and Article 32 of the law on the High Council of Justice provide that the only disciplinary sanction for breach of oath by a judge is dismissal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3389.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3400.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For other types of judicial misconduct, Article 37 of the law on the High Council of Justice sets out just two other types of sanction, reprimand or demotion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3400.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3407.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that domestic law provides an inadequate range of disciplinary sanctions to deal with judicial misconduct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3407.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3412.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, we remind the Court that in this case, Mr. Volkov was dismissed on the basis</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3412.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3419.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of one uncorroborated complaint regarding his judicial conduct in a particular commercial case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3419.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3422.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The impugned conduct related to Mr. Volkov's decision</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3422.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3428.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to institute casational proceedings and initiate a judicial review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3428.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3430.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Volkov maintains that he acted at all times</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3430.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3437.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>within his powers under the Civil Procedure Code and made judicial decisions within the limit of those powers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3437.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3444.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For this reason, we submit that domestic law on the dismissal of judges for breach of oath is neither certain nor foreseeable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3444.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3448.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, it was applied in this case in a grossly disproportionate manner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3448.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3450.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Volkov's dismissal, therefore,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3450.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3454.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>violates Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3454.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3455.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I turn to the final question</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3455.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3460.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>concerning the application of Article 46 in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3460.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3466.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant submits that this case evidences fundamental systemic problems in the Ukrainian legal system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3466.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3482.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we have already highlighted, the lack of independence of the judiciary in Ukraine and the flagrant interference by both government and parliament have been recognized by this court on a number of occasions and by a significant number of independent international organizations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3482.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3495.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In March 2010, the Venice Commission called for profound constitutional reform on the grounds that present constitutional provisions are an obstacle for an independent judiciary in line with European standards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3495.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3500.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The PACE monitoring committee has endorsed this approach, as has the OECD.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3500.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3515.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In light of the court's established practice, we submit that Article 46 should be applied in this case in order to require the government to bring forward legislative proposals within a stipulated time in order to remedy the systemic failures identified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3515.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3518.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We propose that the following laws will require amendment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3518.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3532.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the Constitution, including A, removal of those provisions giving parliament a role in the appointment and dismissal of judges, and B, provisions relating to the appointment, composition, and role of the High Council of Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3532.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3538.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the law on the High Council of Justice, including first, the composition and role of the High Council of Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3538.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3542.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the terms of office of its members and the basis for dismissal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3542.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3547.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, recusal of members from adjudicating on complaints which they have submitted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3547.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3551.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And fourth, the definition of the concept of breach of oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3551.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3559.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, the Code of Administrative Justice of Ukraine, including the jurisdiction and powers of the higher administrative court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3559.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3563.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn finally to redress for the applicant in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3563.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3566.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Volkov maintains that he is an innocent victim</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3566.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3569.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of a politically motivated campaign to dismiss him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3569.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3578.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He refers to the systemic failings in domestic law which have resulted in his unlawful dismissal and gross breaches of his human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3578.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3595.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is trite law that the effect of a judgment in which this court finds a violation of the convention is to impose a legal obligation on the respondent state to put an end to the breach and to make reparation for its consequences in such a way as to restore as far as possible the situation existing before the breach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3595.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3601.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, we submit that the only appropriate and effective remedy is reinstatement of Mr. Volkov</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3601.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3604.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as a judge of the Supreme Court of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3604.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3610.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Reinstatement is recognized as an appropriate form of restitution in international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3610.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3617.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was evidenced by principle 19 of the basic principles and guidelines on the right to a remedy and reparation 2005.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3617.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3627.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Inter-American Court of Human Rights has also held that reinstatement is an effective remedy in the case of dismissal without proper justification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3627.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3640.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Trujillo versus Venezuela, the Inter-American Court held that Venezuela had violated the right to an effective remedy when the Supreme Court refused to reinstate a judge who was unlawfully dismissed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3640.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3643.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Volkov was a judge of the Supreme Court for 16 years</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3643.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3646.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from 1994 to 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3646.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3650.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was dismissed without proper justification or due legal process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3650.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3657.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant respectively requests that the court stipulate that he be reinstated as a judge of the Supreme Court of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3657.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3660.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the court is not minded to order Mr. Volkov's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3660.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3670.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>reinstatement, we respectfully request in the alternative that the court stipulate in the operative provisions of its judgment that proceedings in this case should be reopened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3670.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3677.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has, on appropriate occasions, stipulated the reopening of proceedings on the finding of a violation of Article 6.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3677.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3692.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in the civil case of Lungoci versus Romania, this court concluded in its operative provisions a direction to the state to ensure that if the applicant so desired, the proceeding for reopen within six months of the judgment becoming final.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3692.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3711.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the 2010 grand chamber case of Kudak and Lithuania, the majority of the grand chamber noted that a retrial or the reopening proceedings would be an appropriate response by the authorities in a case concerning the dismissal of an employee following her claim of sexual harassment against another employee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3711.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3728.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In his concurring opinion in that case, Judge Malinverni, supported by four other judges, argued that this point should have been included in the operative provisions of the judgment on the basis that the applicant had first and foremost sought a decision to the effect that her dismissal had been unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3728.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3733.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, only the reopening of the proceedings would provide full satisfaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3733.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3736.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same reasoning applies to the current case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3736.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3751.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to the systemic failings of the judicial disciplinary process as set down in domestic law and the gravity of the violations in this case, the applicant submits that his only effective remedy is for proceedings in his case to be reopened and reviewed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3751.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3753.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, that concludes the applicants' oral</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3753.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>OK.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I'll get the vote on that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Shall I do that?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>OK.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well then, I'll see you next week.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Goodbye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Goodbye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Take care.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bye.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>you</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3758.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3760.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Ms. Gordon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3760.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3765.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the judges. Judge Yudkivska, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ganna Yudkivska</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3771.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3777.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President. I have four questions which I would like to address to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3777.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3791.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first question concerns Judge P's power as the President of the High Administrative Court. According to section 41, paragraph 5 of the Judicial System Act of 2002, in the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3791.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3803.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>absence of the President of the High Specialized Court, his duties shall be performed by the first Deputy President. I would like to ask the parties to specify the term absence. In</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3803.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3821.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>particular, if a judge's terms of office as President of a court has expired, does it mean that a President is absent as of that day, or he or she is not considered to be absent until a relevant decision on his or her dismissal is adopted?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3821.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3829.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, what was the exact scope of review of Mr. Volkov's case in the Parliament during</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3829.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3837.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the plenary meeting of the Parliament, given also the very limited time the Parliament had to hear the parties?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3837.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3849.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, the government's submission on compatibility of the applicant's dismissal with Article 8 of the Convention were concentrated on issues of legality of this measure. I would like</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3849.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3872.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to ask the parties to specify whether or not the High Administrative Court is entitled, under applicable legislation, to examine proportionality of the measure at issue and to set aside the impugned decision or to declare it unlawful if it considers it to be disproportionate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3872.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3882.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, does absence of any time limit for proceedings on breach of judicial oaths pursue any legitimate aim, and is it justified in the state's legal system?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3889.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3893.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Yudkivska.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3893.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3894.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge NuÃŸberger, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Angelika NuÃŸberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3896.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3898.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3898.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3903.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also have four questions to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3903.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3908.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the first question is, the applicant was dismissed for breach of oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3908.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3917.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were several reproaches in the beginning, and two were declared unlawful by the higher administrative court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3917.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3929.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the review of decisions of a relative was not seen as a breach of oath, and also the reproach that he had not seeked the withdrawal of another judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3929.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3935.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What remained was the reproach of gross procedural violations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3935.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3941.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have just heard now that he had instituted cassational procedures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3941.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3954.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I want to know, if that's considered to be the wrong application of procedural law, why is just the wrong application of the law already considered a breach of the oath?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3954.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3967.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Has there to be any extra element, or is whatever breach of procedural law a wrong application of procedural law already considered as breach of the oath?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3967.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3982.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second question, the government stated that the consequences of the decision of the higher administrative court is to say that it's unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3982.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3992.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The consequence would be, in the end, that the judge would be reinstated and compensated for the period during which he was dismissed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3992.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4000.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do you have any concrete example of a reinstatement after such a declaration of unlawfulness, first?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4000.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4006.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And second, in this case, it was declared only partially unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4006.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4008.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the first reproaches were seen to be unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4008.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4011.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, there were no consequences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4011.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4024.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Would it not have been logical, then, to restart the procedure, at least in the parliament, as it was based on partial unlawful reproaches?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4024.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4031.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third question concerns the voting in the parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4031.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4036.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was the video, and the applicant referred to the video.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4036.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4046.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has stated that there was no examination of this video, and there was no conclusion of a competent authority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4046.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4051.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do the government argue that this video does not show reality?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4051.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4055.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So does it not mirror what has really happened?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4055.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4058.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, does it mean that it's falsified?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4058.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4063.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or what is exactly the argumentation of the government?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4063.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4071.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And last question that's a little bit refers to the second question of Judge Yudkivska.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4071.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4075.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the parliament, there was a vote on the dismissal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4075.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4078.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And actually, was it a legal or a political vote?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4078.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4085.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because I understand that the parliament, they are not lawyers, or not only lawyers in any case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4085.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4089.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was a legal question if there was a breach of oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4089.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4092.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So what is the function of the parliamentarians?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4092.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4095.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What can they say to this legal question?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4095.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4095.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4097.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4102.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge NuÃŸberger. Are there any other questions? Judge ZupanÄiÄ, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>BoÅ¡tjan M. ZupanÄiÄ</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4105.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4108.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4108.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4131.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have really more of a comment than a question, because when looking at the applicant's brief, I found that the claim for just satisfaction, according to Article 41, was about how much we said?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4131.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4141.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>1,100,000 euros for the projection of the lost salary in the future, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4141.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4150.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What has pleasantly surprised me in Mrs. Gordon's statement</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4150.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4168.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>now is that she maintains, and I assume both representatives of the applicant maintain, that the only proper remedy in this kind of case is reinstatement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4168.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4176.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because under a different terminology, we're talking about an impeachment of a judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4176.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4191.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When the impeachment procedure itself is problematic, it is clear that the reinstatement is the proper remedy, exactly as has been pointed out by Mrs. Gordon, or at least secondarily,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4191.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4205.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>perhaps, the repeat of the procedure, the retrial of the impeachment procedure, rather than 1,100,000 euros for a period projected up to 1,022.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4205.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4232.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, since this is apparently a surprise coming from the applicant based on international sources of international law, I would appreciate more buffering, not buffering, more substantiation in this respect, because our own case law goes back to Scozzari and Giunta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4232.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4235.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It goes back to Assanidze.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4235.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4257.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It goes back to Broniowski, the three triangle of cases which have initiated restitutio in integrum, restitution as a proper remedy under Article 41 in conjunction with 4619, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4257.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4273.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, what I'm saying is, yes, I'm â€“ I am surprised presently with this consultation on the part of the applicant as far as remedies are concerned, but I don't see that in the brief.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4273.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4288.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So either you may submit that â€“ depends on the decision of the President â€“ either you may submit that later on, substantiating your position on the reinstatement or retrial, or you explain why is it not in the brief.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4295.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4297.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any other questions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4299.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4307.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, I propose that we have a short break and we will resume at 10.30,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4307.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4307.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>so a quarter of an hour, 15 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4356.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4357.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4393.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4399.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing in the case of Volkov against Ukraine is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4400.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4406.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before I give the floor to Ms. Kulchytskyy,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4407.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4408.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>please be seated, please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4411.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4411.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4416.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4421.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the hearing is resumed and before I give the floor to Ms. Kulchytskyy,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4421.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4427.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to make the following observations in connection with Dr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4427.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4445.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ZupanÄiÄ's question concerning the articulation between Article 41 and Article 46 of the Convention if, and I insist on the if, the court would find a violation, which we will reflect upon and decide eventually.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4445.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4450.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We will see what we are going to do with this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4450.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4459.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the court does not find it necessary for the time being to file additional written observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4459.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4474.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I invite both parties to comment also upon Judge ZupanÄiÄ's question, which is also one of the questions we have put in the file for this hearing today, question number eight.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4474.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4485.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we do not want additional written observations, but you are free to comment upon this issue if you wish to do so now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4485.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4493.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So subject to this remark, I give now the floor to Mr. Kulchytskyy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4493.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4494.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4495.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4496.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4497.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4512.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As concerning first question of Judge Kiskov, end of the term of person in his post doesn't mean that he's automatically relieved from this post.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4512.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4521.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And only after official retirement of this person from his post, the post is considered vacant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4521.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4537.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And after official dismissal of the head of high administrative court, his deputy can act as the head of the court, as it's provided by Article 41 of this law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4537.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4565.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning second question of Judge Kiskov, and I believe it's first question of Judge Nussenberg, concerning Parliament and establishing of branch of oath, according to legislation acting at that time, just High Council of Justice was authorized to establish branch of oath by the judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4565.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4570.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No other state authority was authorized to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4570.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4578.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In spite of this, just Parliament can take decision on dismissal of the judge from the post for branch of oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4578.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4588.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And no other decision of any state authority was binding in the Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4588.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4602.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning third question, question of personality could be raised in case if there is possibility to use different sanctions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4602.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4610.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But according to Ukrainian legislation, branch of oath provides just one sanction, dismissal from the post.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4610.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4618.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for this reason, this question was not considered by high administrative court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4618.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4636.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According time limitation for branch of oath, there is no time limitation, since the branch of oath is the gravest violation which can be done by the judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4636.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4648.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it's by itself has a particular negative impact on the public confidence in justice in the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4648.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4657.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for this reason, the government of Ukraine believes that there could be no time limit for such violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4657.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4675.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning branch of procedure rules, and government would like to know that Judge Volkov was released not for single violation of procedure legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4675.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4681.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason of his dismissal, it was systemic violation concerning one case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4681.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4694.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was at least four violation of different procedural rules, which led to conclusions that it was his illegal activity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4694.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4703.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that led to conclusions that such action constitutes a branch of oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4703.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4725.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning video record, the government is not able to say that this video fails or it can be used, because it's, as I told earlier, it wasn't a matter for consideration before national authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4725.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4731.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I'm not able to decide whether it's relevant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4731.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4739.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And first question, I believe that's all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4739.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4767.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And concerning just satisfaction claim, I would like to know that according to Ukrainian legislation, in case when European courts find violation of Article 6 of Convention, according to Article 236 of the Code of Administrative Procedure, judgment of national courts which resulted violation of Convention should be quashed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4767.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4770.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there can be a fresh consideration on this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4770.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4777.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And government submitted the position as applicants claim for just satisfaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4777.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4789.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we believe that it's not possible to grant to the applicant amount of material claims, in case of fresh consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4789.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4792.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All this judgment can be found unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4792.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4795.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And he can act again as a judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4795.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4808.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it's not possible to pay two times to the applicant as compensation and second time as salary in case of his appearance as a judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4808.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4814.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One more question concerning concrete examples of finding some decision unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4814.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4828.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And government is ready to provide concrete examples under which after some decision of, for example, High Council of Justice, we find unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4828.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4832.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And after this, person start acting as a judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4832.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4834.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we can provide this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4834.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4836.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't have this materials with me.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4836.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4841.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in day or two, we can provide this to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4841.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4841.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4844.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4848.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Kulchytskyy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4848.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4852.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I give the floor now to Mr. Leach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4852.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4853.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Leach, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4856.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4872.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In response to Judge Judkiewska's first question, we say that section 415 of the Judicial System Act 2002 does refer to the expiry of the president's term of office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4872.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4877.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And even if it were to refer to mere absence or illness, that would mean that there's no provision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4877.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4881.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It doesn't deal with the issue where the president's term has expired.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4881.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4883.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say it's very, very clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4883.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4896.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Plaseniuk's five-year term had expired, and there was, therefore, no other provision dealing with his succession other than this principle, this provision in 415.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4896.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4902.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question from Judge Judkiewska was about the scope of the review of the plenary parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4906.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4918.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The plenary parliament, in accordance with the 2004 Judges Election Dismissal Act, was simply asked to make a decision on the dismissal of a judge on the grounds that the judge had breached his oath.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4918.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4922.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's what the law simply says and nothing else.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4922.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4930.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on that basis, on the day in question, 12 judges were dismissed by the plenary parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4930.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4950.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Judkiewska's third question in relation to Article 8, whether the higher administrative court was able to examine the question of proportionality, yes, it could, and yes, the applicant did raise proportionality, but of course, his claim was dismissed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4950.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4959.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Judkiewska's fourth question, did the absence of time limits have any legitimate aim?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4959.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4962.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say there's no legitimate aim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4962.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4964.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a question of legal certainty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4964.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4974.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on the contrary, because of the seriousness of the issues in this case, it should have been dealt with in a timely fashion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4974.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4995.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to Judge Nussberg's questions, her first question, which went to the issue of why simply a wrong application of the procedure could amount to a breach of the oath, we think that's a highly pertinent question to ask of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4995.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5000.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our position is that Mr. Volkov made appropriate decisions</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5000.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5005.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>within the limits of his powers, within the Civil Procedure Code of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5005.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5019.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And what this case is about is that, in fact, an assessment of his decision by a non-judicial body amounts to interference with judicial independence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5019.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5036.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Nussberg's second question, whether it would have been logical to review his case given the partial decision of the Higher Administrative Court, our answer would be simply, yes, it would have been logical to review, but it didn't happen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5036.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5043.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Judge Nussberg's third question was related to the government about the government's position on the video.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5043.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5048.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Did the government, were they suggesting that the video doesn't accord with reality?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5048.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5052.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, on that, we note that this point hasn't</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5052.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5053.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>been raised until now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5053.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5061.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would say it's up to the government, of course, to produce evidence if they wish to challenge the veracity of this video.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5061.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5065.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no such evidence whatsoever to challenge it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5065.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5074.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's no question before this court that it's inadmissible because of any rules that may be applicable in the Ukrainian system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5074.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5086.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we would say that the government, in the Ukrainian system, and finally, if you view the video itself, it's very clear that it refers and can only refer to the voting in Mr. Volkov's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5086.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5094.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's absolutely no basis on which the government can challenge it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5094.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5104.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Nussberg's fourth question overlaps a little bit with one of Judge Rudkiewska's questions about the role of parliamentarians.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5104.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5107.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was it a legal or political vote?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5107.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5110.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I've dealt with that already.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5110.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5116.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'd also emphasize that the decision was made in the course of just simply 10 or 15 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5116.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5122.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it dealt with, I've said, 12 judges in addition, 11 other judges as well as Mr. Volkov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5122.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5131.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We'd also remind the court that it was only on the 15th of May that the definition of the breach of oath in Article 32 was introduced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5131.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5138.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that definition was not explained at the plenary hearing before parliament on the 17th of June.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5142.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5150.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I then turn to Judge Zypandzic's question and point about Article 41 and Article 46.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5150.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5153.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we note what you've said, Mr. President,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5153.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5158.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>about not requiring written submissions at the moment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5158.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5165.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We accept and we note that the court hasn't previously made an order of reinstatement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5165.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5172.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we are aware of the claim that we're making before you today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5172.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5191.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would say, though, that the court has, for a number of years, taken off its shackles in terms of the limits of what it can do under Article 41 and Article 46, in that it is many, many years past since declaratory relief is what the court is limited to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5191.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5199.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you can see that in the cases on property, in cases like Bromerescu, where the court orders property to be returned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5199.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5211.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You can see it most starkly in the detention cases, that's Anidze and Ilascu, where the court orders a state to ensure the release of an individual using these provisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5211.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5216.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think you can also see it in the development of the use of Article 46 in the pilot judgment procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5216.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5230.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If you go to the test that is applicable, the restituto in integrum test, so far as is possible, the court is obliged to restore the position, restore the applicant's position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5230.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5239.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, and this is really why we raise it in this case, Parex Allance, his position can only be properly restored by reinstatement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5239.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5245.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's why we make the claim about reopening in the alternative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5245.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5258.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the systemic failings, the systemic problems in Ukraine that we've outlined today, we would have no confidence that if his case were reopened, it would be considered properly or within a sufficient time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5258.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5264.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is why we focus today on reinstatement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5264.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5274.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also submit that we don't we're not formally stopped at this stage from raising this at a hearing on admissibility and the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5274.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5278.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the government has raised today the possibility of reinstatement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5278.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5280.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We've heard them refer to that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5280.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5283.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They've conceded that there have been changes in the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5283.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5288.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so first and foremost, we ask for reinstatement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5288.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5293.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that doesn't mean that we drop, of course, all the damages claim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5293.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5300.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would be in the alternative in relation to the future damages claim, admittedly, but not in relation to past damages claim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5300.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5303.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think at the moment, that's all I'll say on that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5303.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5312.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the court were to decide in the future to ask for written submissions on that, we'd be very willing, of course, to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5312.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5315.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, Mr. President, if I could just</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5315.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5320.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>respond to a few points that the government made very, very briefly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5320.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5325.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government referred to a statement by Mr. Kivalov in 2007.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5325.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5335.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He made an oral statement to the mass media to the effect that judges who made the claim challenging Parliament at that time, including Mr. Volkov, should be dismissed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5335.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5344.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They suggested that because that statement was made more than six months before the dismissal proceedings were introduced, there was no causal relationship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5344.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5353.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say, on the contrary, that that supports our argument of subjective partiality by Mr. Kivalov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5353.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5362.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They've also referred again today to the supposed safeguards, the legislative safeguards relating to the higher administrative court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5362.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5368.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They simply referred back to their written pleadings, which specify nothing at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5368.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5372.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And yet again today, we've heard nothing specific on that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5372.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5375.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also said that Mr. Volkov did not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5375.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5378.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>complain about the judges of the higher administrative court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5378.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5380.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's simply wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5380.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5388.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He made a direct challenge to the legality of that court on the basis that Mr. Pasyniuk wasn't formally legally</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5388.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5389.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5389.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5392.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that application was rejected by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5400.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5403.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, that concludes the submissions</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5403.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5404.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on behalf of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5404.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5404.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5406.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5409.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Leach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5409.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5416.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Does, are there any other submissions by Ms. Gordon?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5416.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5423.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If not, I would have an additional question for you, and I will, of course, give the possibility also to Mr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5423.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5426.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kulchytskyy to respond.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5426.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5444.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the context of the Article 46 issue, you just said at the moment that you argue reinstatement as your main proposal, and in the alternative, you would suggest reopening.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5444.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5447.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Ms. Gordon, when she made her submissions earlier</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5447.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5458.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>this morning, she referred to our case law concerning the operative part of the judgment, and she referred to two cases, BrumÄƒrescu against Romania and DÅ¾iautas against Lithuania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5458.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5483.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do you also argue that if the Court finds a violation and if we would go into the direction of reinstatement, this should be made also in the operative part, or did your submission only concern the reopening issue when you elaborated on the operative part?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5483.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5488.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course, I will give Mr. Kulchytskyy the possibility to reply to what you are</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5488.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5488.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>suggesting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5488.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5506.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr President, yes, we would also request that, were the court minded to order reinstatement, that it is an order of the court and therefore it should be within the operative provisions and the development of the court's application of Article 41 and Article 46 is no bar to that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5506.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5520.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So yes, reinstatement in the operative provisions and the alternative reopening in the operative provisions, Lungokye and Kundak are two examples of the application of the use of the operative provisions in questions of reopening.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5520.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5528.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are of course many other decisions, particularly in the criminal context where the court has made similar decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5528.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5528.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5529.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5531.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Leach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5531.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5535.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Kulchytskyy, do you want to make further observations?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5535.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5536.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, certainly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5536.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5552.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government would like to know that, as I told already, there is a possibility, according to national legislation, to reopen procedure, and there is no reason to believe that government is not going to execute the obligation under the court's judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5552.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5564.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we believe that if there will be a finding of violation, this judgment will be executed in full, according to national legislation, and under supervision of the Committee of Ministers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5564.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5565.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5566.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5569.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Mr. Kulchytskyy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5569.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5572.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5572.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5578.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5578.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5583.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5583.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5586.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5586.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5591.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5591.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5592.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
