<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>2198004_06072016</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>22.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>22.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>65.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>66.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>76.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>83.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing in the case of Simeonovi versus Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>83.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>97.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on 8 June 2004 under Article 34 of the Convention by three Bulgarian nationals, Mr. Lyuben Filipov Simeonov and his parents,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>97.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>103.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Nelly Nikolova Simeonova and Mr. Filip Lyubenov Simeonov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>103.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>112.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was allocated to the fourth section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52.1 of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>112.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>132.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on 23 August 2011 after the court had rejected as inadmissible in a decision of the same date all the complaints of the second and the third applicants and some of the complaints of the first applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>132.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>138.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 20 October 2015, chamber of the fourth section rendered a judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>138.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>145.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 12 January 2016, the first applicant, Mr. Lyuben Filipov Simeonov,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>145.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>160.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted that request on the 14th of March 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>160.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>175.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 20 May 2016, the Association for the Prevention of Torture was granted leave to submit written comments as a third party by virtue of Rule 44.3 of the rules of court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>175.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>187.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agents, Mrs. Milena Kotseva and Mrs. Maria Dimitrova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>187.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>192.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mr. Jeremy Mcbride, counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>192.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>196.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mrs. Svetla Margaritova-Vuchkova, counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>196.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>202.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's mother, Mrs. Nelly Simeonova, is also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>202.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>207.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>207.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>221.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome a delegation of judges and prosecutors from the European Judicial Training Network and a delegation of state attorneys from Brazil who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>221.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>231.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agents of the government and the representatives of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>231.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>235.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Mcbride for the applicant will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>235.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>240.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mrs. Kotseva and Mrs. Dimitrova for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>240.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>240.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Mcbride.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>247.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>252.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and issues. Firstly, the material conditions during detention or remand and the prison</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>252.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>258.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>regime following conviction. Secondly, the right to assistance of a lawyer following</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>258.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>264.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>arrest. And finally, the imposition of a whole life sentence. In respect of all three issues,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>264.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>274.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it is the submission of the applicant that the requirements of the Convention have not been fulfilled, and the Court will thus be invited to find violations of the articles concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>274.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>284.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regard the issue of material conditions of detention or remand and the prison regime, the Chamber have already found a violation of Article 3 in this regard. The applicant</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>284.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>295.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>agrees with this finding and notes that the respondent government have made no observations on this matter, other than to indicate that reforms have taken place. In the circumstances,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>295.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>307.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicant does not wish to address this issue further, other than to request the Court to confirm the finding of the Chamber and to find a violation of Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>307.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>320.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the question of the assistance of a lawyer, this issue, which is something guaranteed, raises issues under Article 6.3c, together with Article 6.1 of the Convention,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>320.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>332.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is something which should never have arisen in this case, because this right is explicitly guaranteed by the Bulgarian Constitution and an array of legislative provisions. Indeed,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>332.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>342.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>not only is it guaranteed, but in a case such as the applicant's, it is a mandatory requirement given the seriousness of the offence with which the person was arrested.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>342.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>354.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But at the time of the applicant's arrest, these provisions were more honoured in the breach than in their observance. This is evident, as in cases referred to in the written observations</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>354.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>374.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>before the Bulgarian Supreme Court, but also in the report of the European Committee for the Prevention of Torture and Inhuman and Degrading Treatment, or Punishment, CPT, following its 1999 visit to Bulgaria. This failure is recognised in the written</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>374.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>396.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>observations of the Court, and unfortunately it is not simply a question of shortcomings at the time, it is something which continues, as has been made clear in subsequent reports, most recently in 2015, of the CPT. There, the report notes that invariably the person</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>396.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>408.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>would arrive at the place of detention and be interviewed, and only subsequently would have access to a lawyer. The applicant is not, however, raising a general</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>408.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>420.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>question he is concerned with, specifically with the failure to allow him to have access to a lawyer for three days following his arrest on 3 October 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>420.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>444.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant submits that following his arrest he was interrogated on the evening of 3 October, and at the time he asked for the assistance of a lawyer whom he already had been in contact with through his parents, and he was told in response that, despite giving the details of the lawyer, he had seen too many movies and that this was not Bulgaria, not America.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>444.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>456.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He repeated this request on several occasions in other places of detention, and was refused on each occasion on the basis that these requests were fanciful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>456.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>465.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was never informed of the right to be informed of the lawyer he was choosing, despite the requirement in Bulgarian law that he should do so. It is not disputed by the Respondent</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>465.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>479.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Government that he did not have the assistance of a lawyer between 3 and 6 October, and no justification has been advanced for him being prevented from having had such assistance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>479.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>486.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the Respondent Government does contest the other submissions of the applicant. It</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>486.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>492.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>suggests that he has not complained about having a lawyer during the three days. This,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>492.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>504.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for example, was very clearly a complaint made to the Supreme Court of Cassation, and it was in closure for the first letter submitted to the Court. It also suggested there was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>504.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>511.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>vagueness in his initial application and in the referral request about this request. But</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>511.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>521.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in paragraph 14 of his initial letter, the applicant stated, in violation of the rights provided in Bulgarian constitution and Article 73.1 of the CPC, I was refused to have a lawyer</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>521.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>526.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from the moment of detention and the intervention of a lawyer in the process. They denied me</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>526.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>533.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>access to my preferred lawyer. This was reaffirmed in his application, and in the request for</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>533.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>547.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>referral to the Grand Chamber, the applicant drew attention to the absence of any confidential conversations with a lawyer while in police custody and in the investigation detention centre. Thus, the applicant has been both unequivocal and consistent in complaining</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>547.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>557.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>about the fact that he was denied access to a lawyer during the relevant period, and also about his being interrogated during this period. The applicant was, of course, aware of his</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>557.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>567.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>rights, but it is precisely because he was not guaranteed these rights that he is now raising this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>567.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>581.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issue of the access to a lawyer, as I said, has not been disputed, but there is question raised as to whether or not there was proof of his interrogation. The applicant</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>581.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>598.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>would submit that there is definitely a coexistence of inferences, strong, sufficiently clear, and concordant inferences, that he was interrogated without the assistance of a lawyer during the three days following his arrest. The idea that there was no interrogation in these three</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>598.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>605.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>days would mean that only very minimal actions have been taken with respect to the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>605.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>619.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This seems a remarkably relaxed approach to the investigation, given that Colonel Botto of the National Police Directorate had been assigned to conduct the investigative actions following the applicant's arrest in Sofia. It is hardly convincing that there was no</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>619.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>628.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>interest in speaking to the applicants and seeking explanations as regards the very matter for which he had been arrested. Furthermore, this is not consistent with normal priest</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>628.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>633.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>practice, nor with the obligations arising under Article V.3 of the Convention to ensure</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>633.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>639.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that there is still a reasonable suspicion justifying the continued deprivation of liberty following a person's arrest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>639.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>660.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, it does not reflect the practice in Bulgaria, which has been well documented in the rulings of the Bulgarian Supreme Court and also in reports by the CPT and others, in which interrogation without a suspect's lawyer following his or her arrest has been found to be a frequent occurrence. Indeed, a contemporaneous illustration of the general</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>660.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>671.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>practice of interrogating suspects when they do not have the assistance of a lawyer can be seen in the handwritten statement of the applicant's co-accused, Mr. Sabev, also</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>671.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>681.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on 3 October, which is included in the investigation file as enclosure 4 to the Respondent Government's written observations. This was signed only by him and not by a lawyer, as should be the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>681.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>685.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>practice if you had the assistance of a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>685.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>703.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that there is no documentation of the interrogations in the case file is, it is submitted, much more consistent with the exercise of pressure on a suspect to confess, as the applicant has consistently maintained, is what has occurred, than with the absence of any interrogation. In addition, the applicant submits to the investigator who questioned</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>703.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>719.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>him after 6 October, that is, after the three-day period, was aware of his having omitted during his interrogation in Sofia to being involved in the robbery but not the murders, and had relied upon this in the questions which he asked him, as well as threatening to use this confession against him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>719.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>734.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the submission that the applicant was interrogated after his arrest is also the most probable explanation for his being taken first to the National Police Directorate, where Colonel Botov is based, rather than to a detention facility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>734.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>751.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, even if the applicant had not been questioned, which would be surprising given the statement made by his co-accused following his interrogation, and was simply held in custody, no explanation has been provided as to why his first contact with a lawyer was only three days later, on 6 October 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>751.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>767.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This seems very strange, given the awareness of Bulgarian constitutional legal requirements on the part of those responsible for the applicant's detention, and that this detention fell mostly in the working week, so there could not even be a supposed practical difficulty in finding a lawyer for him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>767.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>780.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also very strange, to say the least, why there should have been a need to keep the applicant in Sofia for two days without interrogation or access to a lawyer, when no steps involving him were taken to establish his supposed involvement in the offenses for which he was arrested.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>780.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>795.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, there can be no practical difficulties in securing his transfer to Burgas, where he was ultimately taken, since that is no more than four hours from Sofia, but the elapsing time was two days from when he was first arrested.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>795.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>809.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the medical examination of the applicant, although ordered on 3 October 1999, did not occur while he was in Sofia, but only in the afternoon of 5 October 1999, that is to say after his arrival in Burgas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>809.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>823.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The assessment then stated that there was no biomedical data about traumatic injuries, but the absence of these is not necessarily inconsistent with the claim made by the applicant to the doctor, that he had been kicked by the barriers with boots mainly in the belly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>823.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>835.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, it should be borne in mind that during the three days during which the applicant had no assistance from a lawyer, he also had no opportunity at all to make contact with anyone else in the outside world.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>835.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>841.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the applicant's parents were only informed about his arrest three days after this had occurred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>841.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>855.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these circumstances, the submission of the applicant that he was questioned by Colonel Bottoff and other investigators should be regarded as well-founded in the absence of any other cogent explanation for the failure to question him during his first three days of detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>855.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>872.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the fact that the applicant was not assisted by a lawyer for the first three days was not considered by the Chamber to have diminished his right to defend himself effectively in the framework of the criminal proceedings, and so it found no violation of Article 6.3c</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>872.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>877.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>taken in conjunction with Article 6.1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>877.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>880.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This finding relied upon several considerations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>880.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>890.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First it relied upon the absence of any case paper indicating the applicant had been questioned, but as I have already submitted, this is not really well-founded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>890.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>901.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are sufficiently strong, clear, and concordant inferences for concluding that he was interrogated without the absence of a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>901.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>913.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the Chamber relied upon the applicant being assisted by a lawyer of his choice when he remained silent during subsequent interrogations and when he confessed on 21 October 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>913.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>917.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant submits that reliance on these considerations is similarly unfounded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>917.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>931.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is because he had no opportunity to discuss his case in private with the lawyers who attended the first two acknowledged interrogations, that is, on 6 October with the officially appointed lawyer and on 12 October with his chosen lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>931.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>938.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There could be no such possibility because the Burgess District Investigation Service had no facilities for confidential discussions with lawyers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>938.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>948.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, the only place where the applicant could meet these lawyers was the investigator's office and that investigator remained present throughout those meetings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>948.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>960.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the applicant never had any opportunity to obtain confidential advice from either lawyer, it is submitted that no consequence should be attached to lawyers being present at the two interrogations since they could not provide any effective assistance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>960.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>971.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This equally applies to the applicant's confession on 21 October, because even then there had been no confidential discussion to retain independent advice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>971.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>979.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, it is more reasonable to conclude that any pressure that might have applied to him by the investigator to confess would still have remained effective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>979.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>989.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, it should be noted that the investigator had frequently called the applicant into his office with the explanation that as a gesture of goodwill he would allow him to smoke there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>989.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>996.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was welcome because it was the only opportunity to leave the cell since there were no exercise facilities in the detention centre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>996.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1002.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But these informal meetings also gave the investigator an opportunity to put pressure on the applicant to confess.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1002.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1012.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In doing so, the applicant submits that the investigator was aware of his previous admission during the interrogation in Sofia and had relied upon this in questioning him as well as threatening him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1012.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1020.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should also be noted that the Chamber seems to have placed emphasis on the applicant having two lawyers during these interrogations, but he only ever had one at a time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1020.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1026.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is to say, on 6 October it was Mr. Dimcho Todorov and on 12 or 21 October it was Mr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1026.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1029.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kanem Kanev.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1029.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1034.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Todorov was the lawyer appointed by the investigator and this appointment was made</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1034.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1042.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>despite, as the record of the interrogation shows, the applicant having made it clear that he would not give any explanations until my parents engage a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1042.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1045.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, he did not want this lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1045.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1050.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the decree for Mr. Todorov's appointment, signed only by him, the investigator, was made</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1050.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1054.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>without giving the applicant the list of lawyers from which he could make his choice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1054.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1061.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was also contrary to the law on the bar, as the appointment should have been made by the Bulgarian bar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1061.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1070.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Chamber also relied upon the fact that there were no investigative measures of concern to the applicant, but this finding is incorrect, as it was during this period that Mr. Ismailov,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1070.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1075.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a witness, and the applicant's co-accused were both interrogated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1075.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1084.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally the Chamber relies upon the view that the applicant's conviction was not based exclusively on his confession and that he had been able to mount his defense at the trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1084.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1093.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this, it is submitted, it is unwarranted as it focuses on the outcome of the proceedings rather than on the observance of the minimum right under Article 6.3c to defend oneself</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1093.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1096.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with the assistance of a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1096.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1106.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also entails the assumption that a lawyer's assistance at the time when the applicant was seen only by the investigators and those guarding him would have made no difference to the course of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1106.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1110.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is submitted that this is not really something which is possible for the Court to judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1110.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1116.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed any attempt to do so would be inconsistent with the fact that the Court is not a fourth instance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1116.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1136.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It of course is true that the assistance may not have led to the applicant's acquittal, but this cannot be known for sure since the applicant might have been able to provide information which would have affected the course of the investigation or the approach adopted at the trial, which could have affected the assessment of the evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1136.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1147.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was not also given the possibility of having the assistance of a lawyer to deal with the interrogation, the initial investigative actions involving his co-accused and his witness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1147.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1163.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant does not suggest that any of this would necessarily have occurred, as he no more than the Court can predict what would have happened if he had actually had a lawyer's assistance, which he repeatedly requested and which he had already made preparations to obtain during these first three days of his detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1163.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1176.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is clear is, however, that he being denied the assistance of a lawyer during the period from the 3rd to the 6th of October meant that the applicant could not discuss and determine his future conduct and position during the process that was to follow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1176.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1192.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the fact that he did not have a lawyer meant that the preparation of the case by the investigators was facilitated as a result of this, even though they did not use the confession which he made during that interrogation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1192.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1205.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, if the applicant had had a lawyer at this time, such a person would have been in a position to request the investigator's replacement for having breached the presumption of innocence through various statements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1205.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1215.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In all, as the Court made clear in the Dvorsky's case, the whole range of services specifically associated with legal assistance were denied to the applicant during this time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1215.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1221.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was denied this assistance for three days, and none of us can tell what difference it might have made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1221.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1231.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Apart from its relevance to the applicant's right to a fair trial, having a lawyer's assistance would also have safeguarded other Convention rights, such as the right to liberty and the prohibition on ill-treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1231.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1240.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, a lawyer would have been in a position to challenge the lawfulness of the applicant's detention between noon and 8 p.m. on the 4th of October, when there was no document justifying</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1240.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1243.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>his detention during this period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1243.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1254.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More significantly, the lawyer would have been in a position to act on the failure of Colonel Bottov to act on the assignment to organize a medical examination before any investigative actions took place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1254.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1256.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is to say, when he was in Sofia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1256.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1260.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As has been seen, such an examination only occurred two days later in Burgos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1260.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1268.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With the possible result, there could no longer be any trace of the beating to which the applicant alleged he had been submitted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1268.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1273.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The right to the assistance of a lawyer can certainly have a crucial bearing on the fairness of a trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1273.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1281.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it is submitted that it would not be appropriate to regard it as being inextricably and exclusively linked to the right under Article 6.1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1281.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1293.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rather than just being a right to avoid prejudice at trial, it should be seen as a right to defend oneself in the manner considered appropriate, whatever may be the eventual outcome of the proceedings concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1293.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1297.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus the question of whether or not there has been a violation of Article 6.3.C, surely</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1297.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1305.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it is submitted, be determined by the presence or absence of justified reasons for preventing a detained person from being assisted by a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1305.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1316.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Where there are no such reasons, the fact that there might have been some basis for conviction other than statements made during interrogations would certainly be relevant in determining whether or not the proceedings as a whole were fair.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1316.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1320.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, this should have no bearing on whether or not the right conferred by Article 6.3.C</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1320.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1323.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>has in fact been respected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1323.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1337.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, it is submitted that it is dangerous to link the question of whether or not there has been a violation of the right to the assistance of a lawyer to the ultimate conduct of the proceedings, as this will encourage the disregard of the right to the assistance of a lawyer at the initial stage of detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1337.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1349.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The resulting risk of this occurring has implications not only for the outcome of criminal proceedings, but also for the effective protection of the right not to be subjected to torture and inhuman and degrading treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1349.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1369.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, the continued flouting of the right to the assistance of a lawyer during the initial interrogation, which CPT reports have repeatedly underlined as a problem in Bulgaria, is a warning of the unsafe approach entailed by waiting to see the outcome of a trial before insisting on the observance of the right in Article 6.3.C of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1369.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1377.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Smona government itself acknowledges that there are instances in which the Court has found violations of Article 6.3.C, even though no use was made of statements given without</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1377.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1382.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a lawyer, but submits that these were only cases in which there existed a deficient legal framework.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1382.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1388.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it is submitted that this was precisely the situation that obtained in Bulgaria when the applicant was arrested.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1388.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1395.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although there were formal guarantees, insufficient steps had been taken to ensure that these were truly operational.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1395.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1405.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, even though improvements have since occurred, the clear implication of reports by the CPT is that the right to the assistance of a lawyer is still more theoretical and illusory than practical and effective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1405.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1410.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For all these reasons, it is submitted that there has been a violation of Article 6.3.C</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1410.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1415.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the Convention, either taken in conjunction with Article 6.1 or by itself if the linking</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1415.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1427.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the two provisions leads to account being taken of the ultimate outcome of the domestic proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1427.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1436.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the third issue, which is the question of the whole life sentence, which was imposed upon the applicant following his conviction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1436.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1444.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's complaint about this sentence was considered to be manifestly all founded in an admissibility decision taken on 23 August 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1444.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1453.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In raising it now, the applicant recognized that the court has established that the case referred to the Grand Chamber is the application as it has been declared admissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1453.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1463.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However the applicant submits that there are compelling reasons in the present case for making a limited exception to that general approach, which he does not otherwise contest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1463.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1475.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to appreciate those reasons, it is first necessary to note the evolution of the court's case law on the issue of irreducible life sentences and why the position now reached is applicable to the applicant's situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1475.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1485.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The admissibility decision in the present case was based upon the court's ruling in Yorgov in Bulgaria No. 2 in 2010, which held that the whole life imprisonment in Bulgaria</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1485.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1494.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was not to be regarded as irreducible de facto simply because no life prisoner had been granted presidential clemency by November 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1494.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1500.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This followed the relatively recent introduction of the whole life sentence penalty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1500.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1517.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This approach to whole life sentence was in turn based upon the earlier Grand Chamber ruling in Kafkaris in Cyprus that a life sentence did not become irreducible by the mere fact that it could be served in full, since it was enough that such a sentence be de jure and de facto reducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1517.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1533.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Yorgov judgment was handed down almost three years before the Grand Chamber overruled Kafkaris in Vinter and others in the United Kingdom, and almost four years before the approach in Vinter was applied to the situation in Bulgaria in Herakljev and Tolomov in Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1533.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1561.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vinter requires not only that there must be the possibility of a review subsequent to the passing of a whole life sentence to determine whether the continued detention of the prisoner concerned is still justified on legitimate penological grounds, but that he or she should not be obliged to wait and serve an indeterminate number of years of his or her sentence before being able to raise the complaint that the legal conditions attaching to his sentence failed to comply with the requirements of Article III of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1561.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1571.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was found not to be the case in the Herakljev and Tolomov case, and the applicant submits the situation in his case is the same as that in Herakljev.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1571.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1594.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, at the time of both his application to the court and the admissibility decision in his case, and until the early months of 2012, as found in Herakljev and Tolomov, the way in which the presidential power of clemency was being exercised was quite opaque, with no publicly available policy statements and no reasons whatever being provided for individual clemency decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1594.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1610.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, parliamentarians had sought reassurance that the President's discretion would not be exercised with regard to persons sentenced to whole life imprisonment, and there were no concrete examples showing that persons in the applicant's situation could hope to benefit from the exercise of that power.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1610.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1636.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the combination of the complete lack of formal or even informal safeguards surrounding the exercise of the presidential power of clemency, coupled with the absence of any examples tending to suggest that a person serving a whole life sentence would be able to obtain an adjustment to that sentence, and under what circumstances, there is no basis for concluding that between June 2001 and the beginning of 2012, the applicant's sentence was one that could be regarded as de facto reducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1636.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1649.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the Chamber's findings in this case with respect to the applicant's conditions of detention underline that he has been subjected to a highly restrictive prison regime, characterized by isolation from the rest of the prison population and insufficient activities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1649.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1670.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is submitted that the deleterious effects of such an impoverished regime, coupled with the unsatisfactory material conditions in which the applicant has been kept, must, just as in the Harakhchyiv and Ptolemyov case, have seriously weakened the possibility of his reforming himself, and thus entertaining a real hope that he might one day achieve and demonstrate his progress and obtain a reduction of sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1670.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1677.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, there has been a lack of consistent periodical assessment of the applicant's progress towards rehabilitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1677.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1689.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also as observed in the Harakhchyiv and Ptolemyov case, the national standards for the treatment of life prisoners appear to be geared towards helping life prisoners adapt to their sentence rather than work towards their rehabilitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1689.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1701.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those standards, moreover, do not make it clear whether any positive changes in life prisoners should be the result of their own efforts or of a proactive approach on the part of prison authorities, as has been recommended by the CPT.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1701.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1719.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the applicant was able, albeit unsuccessfully and without reasons being given, to make an application for pardon in 2015, this does not alter the fact that for the period beginning with the imposition of the whole life sentence on him until at least the beginning of 2012, this sentence could not be regarded as reducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1719.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1730.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result, it is submitted that, just as in the Harakhchyiv and Ptolemyov case, the applicant has been deprived for a significant period of time of any hope of release, however tenuous that hope may be.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1730.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1735.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such a deprivation thus equally entails, in his case, a breach of Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1735.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1749.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the light of these circumstances, the applicant submits that there are good reasons in the present case for making a very limited exception to the Grand Chamber's general approach of treating the case referred to as being just the application declared admissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1749.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1757.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly such an exception would be consistent with the Grand Chamber's role in resolving conflicts in the approach taken to the application and interpretation of the Convention by Chambers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1757.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1766.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, it was already established when the applicant submitted his application that an irreducible life sentence would amount to a violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1766.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1773.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The rulings in Vinter and Harakhchyiv have merely provided some clarification as to how irreducibility is to be understood.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1773.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1782.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these circumstances, the standard which high contracting parties were required to observe was an insubstance already applicable to persons in the applicant's situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1782.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1796.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To refuse to depart from the admissibility ruling in the particular circumstances of the applicant's case would thus lead to the differential application of a Convention right to persons who have been subjected contemporaneously to exactly the same treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1796.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1808.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly such an exception would not undermine the principle of legal certainty but would reinforce respect for the rule of law, a core Convention value, by ensuring that like cases are treated alike.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1808.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1817.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally the Grand Chamber has previously itself shown itself prepared to take account of pertinent case law developments occurring after a particular stage in the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1817.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1827.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, the judgment in NADA and Switzerland took account of the ruling in Al-Jadda in the United Kingdom which decided some three and a half months after the oral hearing in NADA.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1827.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1835.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both this approach and the exception now being proposed equally serve the goal of ensuring the integrity of the case law and its consistent application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1835.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1844.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant therefore submits that his complaint about the whole life sentence imposed upon him should be considered admissible notwithstanding the Chamber decision on 23 August 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1844.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1860.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the applicant submits that the Court should find that his sentence gave rise to a violation of Article 3 for the period beginning with the imposition of the whole life sentence on him until at least the beginning of 2012 as it could not during this period be regarded as reducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1860.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1871.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In conclusion, the Court has respectfully requested to find violations of Article 3 in respect to both the conditions of the applicant's detention in the prison regime and of the whole life sentence imposed on him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1871.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1876.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also invited to find a violation of Article 6.3c either alone or taken in conjunction</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1876.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1880.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with Article 6.1 as well as to grant just satisfaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1880.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1894.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards just satisfaction, the Court has requested to award the applicant 10,000 euros for non-pecuniary damage in view of the very significant suffering caused by the material conditions of his detention and remand and the prison regime following his conviction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1894.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1903.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No award of non-pecuniary damage is sought in respect of either the denial of the assistance of a lawyer or the imposition of the irreducible life sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1903.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1919.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However the applicant does request the Court, pursuant to Article 46 and as in the Kharakchev case, to indicate that the execution of its judgment requires the reform of the legal framework governing the prison regime which is applicable to persons sentenced to life imprisonment with or without parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1919.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1933.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the applicant requests the Court, pursuant to Article 46, to indicate that the execution of its judgment requires the introduction of a system of conditional release for life sentence prisoners as has already been recommended by the CPT.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1933.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1942.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally the applicant requests the Court to award him the costs and expenses that he has incurred in bringing the present application subject to any award of legal aid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1942.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1944.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr President, Members of the Court, thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1947.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1949.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. McBride.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1949.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1953.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to call Ms. Kotseva on behalf of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1958.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1961.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. President, Honourable Judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1961.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1969.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On behalf of the Government of Bulgaria, I will first briefly focus on some points raised to the Applicants' Memorial to the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1969.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1979.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning his complaint under Article 3 of the Convention, I would then give the floor to my co-agent, Ms. Maria Dimitrova, who will present to you our main submissions regarding</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1979.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1986.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the complaint under Article 6, Paragraph 3C, in relation to Article 6, Paragraph 1 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1986.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1989.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Simeonov has raised several complaints before the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1989.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2007.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In a decision of 23rd August 2011, the Grand Chamber of the Court declared inadmissible the Applicant's complaint under Article 3 of the Convention, in particular that the punishment life imprisonment without commutation constituted inhuman and degrading punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2007.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2018.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its judgment of 20 October 2015, the Chamber declared inadmissible another set of complaints under Articles 3, 6 and 13 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2018.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2026.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those decisions declaring certain complaints inadmissible have become final and are not subject to re-examination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2026.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2031.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In his Memorial to the Grand Chamber, Mr. Simeonov provides ample arguments regarding</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2031.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2039.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the alleged inconsistency of the punishment life imprisonment without commutation with the requirements of Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2039.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2053.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, the Government argues that according to the Court's settled case law, a case referred to the Grand Chamber necessarily embraces all aspects of the application previously examined by the Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2053.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2061.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The content and scope of the case referred to the Grand Chamber are therefore delimited by the Chamber's decision of the admissibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2061.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2070.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that the Grand Chamber may examine the case in its entirety insofar as it has been declared admissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2070.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2077.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It cannot, however, examine those parts of the application which have been declared inadmissible by the Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2077.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2088.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In paragraph 92 of his Memorial to the Grand Chamber, the applicant suggests that the present case involves a situation where the Court must make an exemption to this general approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2088.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2093.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the Government submits there is absolutely no reason to depart from this</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2093.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2095.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>principle in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2095.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2106.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither the Convention nor the rules of the Court envision a situation where reopening of proceedings is possible when a complaint has been declared inadmissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2106.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2112.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that in some very exceptional situations the Court has ordered reopening of such proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2112.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2118.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We refer here to the cases Omas and Omas v. Turkey and Edwards v. the United Kingdom,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2118.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2125.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>where there was a technical and manifest error in calculating the six-month time limit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2125.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2137.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the line, however, those situations are extremely exceptional and concern rectification of a technical mistake, but not issues related to the merits of the complaint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2137.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2156.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's argument that reopening is necessary for the sake of the interpretation of the Convention, for dealing with inconsistencies in the case law, or for reasons to the development of the case law, are completely misplaced and are not sufficient to overrule the principle of legal certainty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2156.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2175.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the Government invites the Court to rule that in the context of the present case, it has no jurisdiction to examine any complaint which had already been declared inadmissible, including the complaint under Article 3 concerning the punishment life imprisonment without commutation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2175.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2181.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same considerations apply to Mr. Simeonov's complaint under Article 6, paragraph</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2181.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2189.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>3c, that during his detention he was not given the opportunity to consult with his lawyer in private.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2189.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2206.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Government further notes that the case before the Grand Chamber concerns two main complaints, the complaint under Article 3 of the Convention regarding the combined effect of the special regime and the material conditions of Mr. Simeonov's detention, and the complaint</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2206.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2219.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>under Article 6, paragraph 3c, in relation to Article 6, paragraph 1, regarding the alleged lack of access to legal advice during the first three days of the applicant's detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2219.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2228.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As stated in our memorial, the Government does not intend to make any observations in respect to the applicant's complaint under Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2228.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2233.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would like only to point out that Major Reform C. Bulgarian Prison System, following</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2233.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2246.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neshkov-Pilot judgment and Kharagchyev-Tulumov judgment, are currently underway in order to improve those conditions and ensure compliance with international standards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2246.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2267.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Reform also envisions legislative amendments with respect to the special regime of detention, reduction of its term and regular examination of the need for its continuation, as well as possibilities for prisoners' inclusion in common activities based on the individual risk assessment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2267.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2276.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regard the complaint under Article 6 of the Convention, I would now give the floor to my co-agent, Ms. Maria Dimitrova, who will provide to you a brief overview of our main</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2276.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2278.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>submission on the matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2278.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2278.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2280.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2281.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Miss Kotseva, I call Miss Dimitrova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2296.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2299.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2299.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2317.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicant complained that due to lack of access to legal advice in the first three days of his detention, his right to a fair trial under Article 6, Paragraph 3C, in relation to Article 6, Paragraph 1, had been violated by the Republic of Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2317.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2342.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government underlined at the outset that in the context of access to a lawyer, this case is neither a case of field treatment nor a case of arbitrary detention, but a case concerning the right to a fair trial, and in particular, whether the absence of counsel during the first three days of the applicant's detention had irretrievably prejudiced the rights of the defense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2342.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2351.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our written submissions, we pointed out the developments in the domestic legislation regarding the protection of the right to legal advice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2351.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2362.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit in this connection that in Bulgaria, an adequate domestic legal framework has traditionally been in place guaranteeing that right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2362.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2385.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the reports of the European Committee for the Prevention of Torture and Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment, to which the applicant referred in his request to the Grand Chamber and subsequent memorial, indicate shortcomings in the implementation of the legal provisions governing access to lawyer during police detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2385.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2408.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, we claim that those findings, while a matter of concern, could not serve as grounds for an automatic conclusion that as a rule, in Bulgaria, each detainee's right to defense and to a fair trial, where such a trial subsequently unfolds, have been violated from the beginning of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2408.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2414.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, we admit that in all probability, the applicant did not have access to legal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2414.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2418.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>advice during the first three days of his detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2418.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2424.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do not dispose of an explicit proof that Mr. Semyonov had waived that right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2424.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2451.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nowadays, almost 17 years after the event, it is impossible to reconstruct with precision their sequence and to honestly support the statement that the domestic legal framework, including its most superior act, the Constitution, which provides for access to legal advice from the moment of the arrest, have been fully implemented in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2451.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2462.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having said that, however, the government maintains that the rights of the applicant under Article VI of the Convention were not violated for the following reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2462.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2474.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, we maintain that judging from all the documents in our possession and the applicant's submissions, Mr. Semyonov was not formally interrogated during the first three days of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2474.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2476.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>his detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2476.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2487.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the absence of a lawyer during the impugned period did not lead to arbitrary restrictions of the procedural rights of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2487.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2497.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even assuming that some questioning occurred, it was only oral, informal, and had no bearing on the criminal proceedings against him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2497.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2510.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, we maintain that the rights of the defense may be violated where the defendant makes statements or undertakes behavior which has impact on its trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2510.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2518.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, however, the state must be given a chance to remedy unjustified restrictions on the right to counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2518.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2537.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourth, Article VI, paragraph 3C, does not create a freestanding right of access to legal advice, and the lack of access to counsel must be viewed within the context of the criminal proceedings as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2537.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2542.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now proceed with our first submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2542.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2548.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant argues that there are inaccuracies in the statement of facts in the chamber judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2548.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2560.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His representative states in particular that, and I quote, the interrogation of the applicant began on the evening of October 3, 1999, and continued over the following days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2560.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2562.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>End of the quotation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2562.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2570.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In response to that, the government contend that the applicant was not interrogated in the course of the first three days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2570.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2582.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was indeed arrested on October 3, 1999, in Sofia on the strength of a police order issued on July 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2582.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2598.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the same day, October 3, the investigator in Burgas ordered Colonel Botubotev, a senior police officer, in writing to ensure a medical checkup of the applicant and his accomplice, Mr. Sabev.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2598.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2604.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no order and no mandate for Colonel Botubotev to interview the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2604.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2612.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no written trace that such an interview with the police or with an investigator took place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2612.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2624.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant himself admits in paragraph 43 of his memorial to the Grand Chamber that he never signed any document in connection to his questioning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2624.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2635.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On October 4, the applicant was accommodated in the Sofia investigative detention facility by virtue of a detention order of the investigator in Burgas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2635.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2638.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was transferred to Burgas on October 5.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2638.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2646.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His first interview took place on October 6 at noon in Burgas and was held in the presence of counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2646.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2665.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the light of the above, the government maintained that the time between the 3rd and the 6th of October was used by the authorities for, first, making the necessary arrangements for Mr. Semyonov's transfer to Burgas, second, his actual transfer, third, his medical checkup</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2665.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2674.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by two medical professionals in Burgas, and fourth, his accommodation in the Burgas investigative detention facility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2674.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2698.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would also like to refer to the rules governing transfer of suspects at the time submitted to the court on June 15, 2016, which require preliminary planning of any transfer, thus indicating that some technological time is necessary before transferring a suspect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2698.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2709.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our second submission is that the absence of a lawyer during the impugned period did not lead to arbitrary restrictions of the procedural rights of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2709.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2720.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government maintained that even assuming that some questioning indeed took place, as Mr. Semyonov argues, it was only oral, informal, with absolutely no bearing on the criminal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2720.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2722.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2722.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2727.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant made no incriminating or exculpatory statements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2727.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2731.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No statements were ever recorded or joined to the file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2731.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2741.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He did not point to any evidence, and his behavior was in no manner taken into account in the subsequent criminal proceedings against him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2741.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2748.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, it is possible that a conversation, even questioning, took place between the applicant</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2748.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2752.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the police officers or an investigator in Sofia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2752.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2757.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such questioning, however, was not objectified in any form.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2757.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2767.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the applicant never approached the domestic authorities with a complaint that he had to give statements under duress and in the absence of a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2767.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2774.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He never properly complained of inflicted ill treatment during his custody.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2774.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2788.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, on no occasion did the authorities make any references, inferences, conclusions, or statements based on possible submissions, testimony, or behavior of the applicant during the impugned period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2788.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2794.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The authorities never relied on any hearsay evidence obtained as a result.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2794.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2806.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In conclusion, we claim that despite the absence of a lawyer, the procedural rights of the applicant were not improperly restricted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2806.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2809.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now turn to our third submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2809.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2832.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's representative suggests in his memorial and today that the right to assistance of a lawyer is a freestanding right and the question of whether there has been a violation of it is to be determined by the presence of justified reasons for preventing a detained person to be assisted by a lawyer in the initial interrogations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2832.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2843.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such an approach, in essence, excludes an analysis of whether the restriction had any impact on the subsequent proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2843.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2857.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government does not agree with this position and maintains that the rights of the defense may be violated when the defendant makes statements or undertakes behavior which have impact on his trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2857.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2866.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, the state must be given a chance to remedy unjustified restrictions on the right to counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2866.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2869.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We base our submission on two main points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2869.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2881.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, such an approach is in line with the court's case law and second, it stems from the principle of subsidiarity and shrink in the convention system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2881.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2887.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In support of our first point, we refer to the leading judgment of Söders v. Turkey</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2887.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2904.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>where the court found in particular that first and foremost, access to a lawyer is needed in case of an interrogation and second, lawyer is indispensable where national law attaches consequences to statements made during that interrogation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2904.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2909.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither of these two conditions is present in our case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2909.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2922.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, there is case law which may be interpreted as suggesting an absolute right to legal advice without the need to look into the specific impact on the subsequent proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2922.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2927.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer here to the judgments in the cases of John Murray v. United Kingdom and of Dianon</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2927.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2930.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>v. Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2930.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2938.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, unlike the present case, in these cases, the court found deficiencies in the applicable legal rules.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2938.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2949.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the first case, due to a deficient legal framework, the applicant was confronted with an unsolvable fundamental dilemma relating to his defense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2949.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2965.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the second case, as pointed out by the Chamber, the decisive factor for the court to find a violation was the fact that at the relevant time, the Turkish legislation did not provide a toll for access to a lawyer in the first days of the detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2965.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2979.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the words of the court, a systematic restriction of this kind on the basis of the relevant statutory provisions is sufficient in itself for a violation of Article VI to be found.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2979.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2994.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would not deny that such a lack of safeguards and the correlated risk to draw inferences from silence or statements made may be taken as creating a negative impact ab initio on the subsequent criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2994.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3009.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In essence, it can put the defendant in uncertainty and confusion from the beginning of the proceedings as to what behavior to undertake, whereas any behavior will be used to his detriment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3009.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3014.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As stated before, however, this is not the situation in Mr. Simeonov's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3014.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3036.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An adequate legal framework was well in place, the applicant was not formally interrogated, and the national law did not attach any consequences to statements made before the police or an investigator which are not part of an official questioning in the course of criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3036.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3049.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In respect of our second point, the government submit that in any event, the state must be given a chance to remedy any failure to ensure lawyer during initial interrogations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3049.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3056.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such an approach is in line with the principle of subsidiarity enshrined in the convention system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3056.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3069.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has held consistently that it is fundamental to the machinery of protection established by the convention that the national systems themselves provide redress for breaches of its provisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3069.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3083.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the context of criminal proceedings, in such situations, exclusion of evidence or prohibition to draw adverse inferences seem to be a reasonable remedial action in line with the public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3083.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3099.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another remedial action that comes to mind is termination of proceedings or obligatory acquittal, but in our view, such an approach would be extreme, leading to situations where serious crimes remain unpunished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3099.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3110.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Bulgarian legislation provides for exclusion of evidence, and as stated before, no evidence potentially collected in the first three days of Mr. Simeonov's detention were ever used</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3110.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3112.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3112.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3129.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The remedial nature of the exclusionary rule is also cautiously suggested within the context of the fairness of the proceedings principle in the Directive 2013-48 of the Council and the European Parliament on the right of access to a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3129.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3142.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The leading judgment of 1966 of the United States Supreme Court in the case of Miranda v. Arizona is construed on the idea that questioning of a defendant usually happens in a police-dominated</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3142.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3151.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>atmosphere where there is a high risk that the individual may be improperly subjugated to the will of his examiner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3151.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3158.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to avoid that, the individual must properly be informed of his right to a lawyer and ensured such if requested.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3158.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3164.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, the thus collected evidence is inadmissible at trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3164.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3172.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Canadian Supreme Court has adopted the same approach in the leading case of 1994, Bar v. Bartle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3172.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3199.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we strongly underline that there seems to be a consensus among the States with similar human rights protective mechanisms, which is also in line with the principle of subsidiarity of the Convention system and with the Court's case law, that in the context of the fair trial, as a rule, restrictions on the right to counsel must have impact on the trial to be considered unjustified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3199.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3215.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, the State must be given an opportunity to undertake a remedial action, such as exclusion of evidence, but should not be compelled to terminate the proceedings or necessarily a kit in order to remedy such an omission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3215.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3233.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This brings me to our fourth and final submission, that in any event, as Article VI, paragraph 3C does not create a freestanding right of access to legal advice, its exigencies must always be viewed within the context of the proceedings as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3233.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3241.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, in the light of all the circumstances of a case and the manner in which the proceedings were conducted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3241.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3253.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This approach permits each fact, evidence and decision of the authorities to be taken into account without resort to formal and dispositive labels.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3253.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3266.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our view, it is not without reason that the fathers of the Convention decided to include the right to counsel in Article VI of the Convention as a guarantee of the right to a fair trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3266.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3270.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They did not create it in a separate provision as a freestanding right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3270.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3282.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They did not formulate it as a guarantee against still treatment or arbitrary detention, and did not even discuss such an option, judging from the Travaux Preparatoire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3282.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3298.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its case law, the Court has consistently held that the intrinsic aim of the guarantees in paragraph 3 of Article VI is to contribute to ensuring the fairness of the criminal proceedings as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3298.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3302.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But those guarantees are not a name to themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3302.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3316.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Compliance with the requirements of a fair trial must be examined in each case having regard to the development of the proceedings, and not on the basis of the isolated consideration of one particular aspect or incident.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3316.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3326.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the purpose of those guarantees is to give effect, in a practical way, to the fundamental right to a fair trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3326.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3332.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One can see the rationale behind such an approach taken by the Court in the case of Gavgen v.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3332.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3334.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Germany, for example.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3334.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3337.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Criminal proceedings are a complex matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3337.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3357.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They strive to reconcile two highly important interests, the interests of the individual to be protected from arbitrary invasions of his liberties by the authorities, and the public interest inherent in revealing and investigating crimes and securing evidence for that purpose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3357.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3365.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both interests are important, and they both may bring bearings on the effective implementation of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3365.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3378.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any temptation, albeit occasionally strong and seemingly fair, to give either of the two interests predominance may result in violations of fundamental rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3378.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3389.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The right to effective protection of life and prohibition of ill treatment under Articles 2, 3, and 4, or the right to a fair trial under Article 6 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3389.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3398.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Government of Bulgaria maintains that a fair balance between the competing interests was observed in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3398.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3416.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Chamber has found, the applicant had a fair trial, and the lack of access to a lawyer during the first three days of his detention did not entail a breach of Article 6, paragraph 3c, in relation to Article 6, paragraph 1 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3416.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3421.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honourable Judges, for all those reasons, the Government of Bulgaria</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3421.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3428.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>invite the Court to find that Mr. Semyonov's rights under Article 6 of the Convention have</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3428.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3429.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>not been violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3436.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3443.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mrs. Dimitrova, and thanks for your submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3443.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3453.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now invite the judges of the Grand Chamber wishing to do so to put their questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3453.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3461.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, the first question will be raised by Judge Serghides.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3461.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3461.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Georgios A. Serghides</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3465.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3469.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3469.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3475.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Actually, I have a couple of questions to both parties in regard to their recent observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3475.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3480.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I will start first with the government observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3480.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3496.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At paragraph 6 of your observations, you say that on October 1999, when the applicant was arrested, the authorities conducted a series of investigative measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3496.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3513.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They interviewed the applicants, accomplished witnesses, friends of the suspects, and anyone who could in some manner relate to the events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3513.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3520.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Evidential material was gathered in a systematic manner, and I underline the word systematic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3520.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3546.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In paragraph 9, you say that on 3rd of October, based on the applicant's submissions – and I don't know what submissions you mean – and the investigators' detention order of the 4th of October, he was taken to a police arrest and then to the Sofia Investigative Detention Facility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3546.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3562.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On paragraph 10, you say that on the 4th of October, the investigator in Berkas, the one in charge of the case, issued an order for the applicant's detention for 24 hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3562.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3571.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On paragraph 11, you say that the applicant was examined by the doctor and a forensic doctor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3571.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3579.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In paragraph 13, you admit that there was an investigation file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3579.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3591.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But despite the above, you say that there was no trace of any interview of the applicants during these three days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3591.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3594.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first question is, how do you explain this?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3594.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3613.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question is, in relation to this period, do you say categorically that there is no record proving that the applicant was asked any question whatsoever, even to state his name?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3613.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3629.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And how do you explain the investigator of Berkas to issue an order for detention on 4th of October without the applicant being asked any question?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3629.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3636.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in relation to – the second question refers to the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3636.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3656.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In paragraph 42 of the observations, the applicant argues that it may be that the assistance of a lawyer during the first three days of interrogation would not have resulted in his acquittal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3656.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3677.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, the government, at paragraph 38 of their observation, underline that the applicant does not argue that any particular statements made by him between the 3rd and the 6th of October were later used in the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3677.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3686.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Based on the above statements, and with a retrospective look, could the applicant be more specific?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3686.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3713.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I know that you answered the question, but could you be more specific how the lack of a lawyer between the 3rd and the 6th of October had any effect whatsoever on the subsequent proceedings before the domestic courts, on any of the applicant's substantive or procedural rights and on the fairness of the trial as a whole?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3713.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3713.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3715.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3718.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3718.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3724.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next questions will be asked by Judge Lemmens, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3728.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3729.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3729.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3734.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to ask a question to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3734.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3747.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has been argued by the applicant that when the applicant saw a lawyer on the 6th of October, that was Mr. Todorov, the appointed lawyer,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3747.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3756.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that he was not able to meet that lawyer before the interrogation by the investigator.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3756.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3774.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I quote from paragraph 33 of the submissions of the applicant, that indeed, all his meetings with lawyers during the pre-trial proceedings were conducted in the office of the investigator, with the latter always being present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3774.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3775.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>End of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3775.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3791.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to ask whether, according to the parties, this is indeed part of the complaint, because we are now on the 6th of October for the first time in interrogation with a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3791.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3805.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, whether the government has something to say about the presence of other people during the conversation between the applicant and his lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3805.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3811.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's something unclear about what this statement means in the context of the whole case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3811.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3814.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to ask the parties to clarify this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3814.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3814.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3816.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3817.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3817.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3821.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Grozev, if you'll ask the next questions, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Yonko Grozev</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3827.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3835.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is for counsel for the applicant, but the government might comment if they wish so, of course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3835.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3847.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is with respect to the argument that the right to access to a lawyer should not necessarily be linked to the overall assessment of the fairness of the trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3847.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3854.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What would then be the remedy of a finding of a violation, is my question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3854.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3871.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And more specifically, with respect to the reopening of the proceedings, what would be the possible standards in more general terms for reopening and in the specific circumstances of the present case?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3871.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3871.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3872.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3873.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3873.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3875.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>President López Guerra, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3877.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3880.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just some information from the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3880.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3884.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was arrested the 3rd of October.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3884.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3891.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He remained arrested for the 3rd, the 4th, the 5th, the 6th of October.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3891.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3893.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No lawyer was appointed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3893.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3899.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It seems that no evidence was gathered during these two or three days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3899.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3905.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No case paper shows that the applicant was questioned by the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3905.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3909.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was not involved in any other investigative measure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3909.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3918.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No investigation parade or any kind of other biological sampling or anything.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3918.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3925.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is, what was the reason for this negative situation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3925.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3933.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why the government decided, or the police decided, to have the applicant arrested?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3933.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3941.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was there any reason for not doing any kind of these investigation activities, appointing him a lawyer or something like that?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3941.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3946.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was there any reason for this lack of activity by the police?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3948.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3952.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. Judge Kucsko-Stadlmayer, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Gabriele Kucsko-Stadlmayer</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3953.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3957.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. My first question concerns the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3958.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3967.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Bulgarian legislation provides and provided already in 1999 the assistance of a lawyer from the moment of the arrest of a suspect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3967.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3977.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, as you cited, the CPT report from 2015 still notes systemic deficiencies in the implementation of these provisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3977.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3979.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How do you comment on this?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3979.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3992.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second question, if the applicant had made any confession in the first three days of arrest, as he claims, would he have had the right to challenge its admission before the Bulgarian courts?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3993.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3996.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my further question concerns the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3997.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4003.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You complain about the absence of a lawyer in the first three days of detention from 3rd to 6th of October 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4003.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4009.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why didn't you put emphasis on complaining about this at the domestic level?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4011.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4020.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And a separate further complaint concerns the de facto irreducibility of life sentence from 2001 to 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4020.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4031.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, as you know, it was declared inadmissible with the court's decision of 23rd of August 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4031.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4035.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why don't you consider to lodge a new complaint on this point?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4035.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4036.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4040.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4043.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4043.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4046.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, we have a question from Judge Vučinić, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Nebojša Vučinić</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4048.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4049.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4049.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4050.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Very short, very short question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4050.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4062.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would ask both parties to comment a submission from the end of the paragraph 29 of the observations of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4062.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4074.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When applicant asked for a lawyer first time, that Mr. Mihailov's name and the phone number</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4074.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4083.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was given to him, but was simply told in the response that he had seen too many movies and this was not America.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4083.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4089.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like short comments about concerning this part of the statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4089.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4089.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4093.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4098.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also would like to ask a question to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4098.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4116.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant raised an observation to the court of cassation regarding the absence of the lawyer, and I just wonder what was the reaction of the court of cassation to that observation concerning absence of the lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4121.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4124.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I see no further questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4124.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4139.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now withdraw for 15 minutes, following which the parties will be able to submit brief observations in reply to each other's submissions and reply to questions from the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4898.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4899.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4982.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4983.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4983.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4997.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed and I call Mr. Mcbride, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4999.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5005.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President, and thank you for the questions from the court, which I'll try to answer now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5005.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5019.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the question of whether there might have been an acquittal or not, the position of the applicant is clear that that is not something which could be determined. But what is submitted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5019.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5022.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is that it may well have affected the conduct of the proceedings. One of the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5022.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5032.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>issues which is important in this case is the question of the respective responsibility, the degree of culpability of the two accused.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5032.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5048.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is a finding in respect of the applicant which places the greater responsibility on him, but that may well not be the case if there had been a possibility to take part in or have the assistance of a lawyer at a much earlier stage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5048.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5050.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is one issue. There are other issues</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5050.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5057.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which are also relevant to the question of the role of the investigator which has been raised.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5057.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5065.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It may have also affected the attitude that the applicant took in the conduct of the proceedings. All of these will be relevant</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5065.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5067.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the conduct of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5067.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5076.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It doesn't necessarily mean that he would be acquitted, but it could be relevant to the way in which the case was dealt with.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5076.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5088.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In terms of the question of whether or not the lack of a lawyer, having meetings with a lawyer on a confidential basis, was part of the application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5088.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5090.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does not seem that it was.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5090.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5094.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In retrospect, it clearly should have been, but that's not where we are.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5094.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5111.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is important, nonetheless, in the present situation, because it was relied upon by the Chamber as the fact of having these meetings without going into the question of confidentiality was one of the considerations for suggesting that there was no violation of Article 6.3c</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5111.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5114.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>taken with Article 6.1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5114.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5121.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as the remedy is concerned, it is difficult in a case such as this where we don't know what would happen. In some cases, of course, there would be the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5121.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5124.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>possibility of a retrial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5124.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5136.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, perhaps the more appropriate remedy would, at the domestic level, would be the approach to the decisions on clemency, which might be a factor. So far,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5136.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5149.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>there has been a refusal of clemency, but perhaps some reconsideration in the light of the failings which have occurred might lead to a change in that decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5149.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5158.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issue the applicant emphasizes is that the issue of not having access was raised with the authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5158.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5166.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Supreme Court, it was raised, and the response to that was simple rejection. It should be said</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5166.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5171.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that a whole range of complaints were raised before the Supreme Cassation Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5171.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5177.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Most of them were not dealt with in substance. They were simply ignored.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5177.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5184.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, there's a question raised about why no fresh application on the question of the irreducible sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5184.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5192.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the applicant has made clear, there has been an attempt to seek clemency. There are still issues about</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5192.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5202.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the disclosure of the basis of the refusal, and it may well be that this would be the subject of a further application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5202.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5220.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issue for raising it now is that the situation before the current arrangements are in place is different, and therefore that is the reason why the present issue relates to the period up to 2012 and not afterwards. So there are two different periods involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5220.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5230.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant appreciates now that the Respondent Government have conceded there may well have been informal questioning taking place during the three days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5230.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5243.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, this seems inconceivable in any system of criminal justice that someone would be sitting for three days without being questioned in some way or other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5243.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5271.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nonetheless, there is some suggestion by the Respondent Government that the applicant might have waived his right to the assistance of a lawyer, but the position under the Convention is very clear that waiver must be unequivocal, and given that there is a total lack of record and it is inconsistent with everything else which the applicant has raised, it is suggested there is no basis for suggesting that there was a waiver in this particular case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5271.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5285.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The point about informal questioning is extremely important because anyone familiar with the operational criminal justice systems knows that this is exactly what the police like to emphasize. It is much more useful for the current investigation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5285.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5291.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>than what is conducted in a more formal basis and subject to the safeguards as provided by the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5291.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5298.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So therefore it is important to recognize that this could have had some impact on the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5298.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5316.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant would also like to point out that he did draw attention to the fact of the ill-treatment, precisely the remarks made to the doctor on his examination related to the beatings which he received, and that is recorded in the record of the medical examination, so there was no question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5316.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5321.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, then the obligation really should be for that to be investigated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5321.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5331.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that is not the issue of the complaint in this question, but it is relevant to the way in which the right to legal advice is concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5331.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5340.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant would make it clear that he is not saying necessarily that Article 6.1</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5340.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5344.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and 6.3c should be separated. There are two submissions being made in this</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5344.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5346.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5346.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5351.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Either there is a violation of Article 6.3 in conjunction with 6.1,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5351.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5355.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>or the alternative approach which has also been argued for is to treat Article 6.3c</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5355.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5359.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as a freestanding right for which some arguments have been put forward.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5359.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5368.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And indeed, the suggestion that they are necessarily linked is consistent also with the fact that Article 6.2,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5368.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5372.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for example, is separate from the question of whether someone has or has not a fair trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5372.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5378.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are, of course, connected, but it doesn't necessarily mean that they always have to be linked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5378.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5402.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But what is important as far as the situation, if there is a linkage made, is the point that the applicant has made that it is inappropriate to emphasize the outcome of the proceedings, because that is something which no one is possible really to judge in terms of what might have happened with the ability of a lawyer to provide input in the way in which the proceedings were conducted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5402.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5412.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is something which the applicant did not have, and therefore at a very crucial stage he did not have the advice of a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5412.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5430.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in those interrogations he has maintained, he made statements which were then the subject of a questioning after he supposedly had the assistance of a lawyer, albeit one without the possibility of confidential meetings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5430.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5438.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant does not consider that there is any problem of subsidiarity in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5438.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5446.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The possibility of dealing with this issue does lie within the Bulgarian state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5446.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5460.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The problem is, the reason why we are here today, is because the legislation, the constitutional guarantees which Bulgaria has adopted have not been applied and are consistently not being applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5460.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5477.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, as far as the issue of the exception which is being asked in terms of admissibility, that exception is being asked because there is nothing certainly in the Convention which precludes it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5477.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5496.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a practice of the Grand Chamber which has been adopted, that there is no prohibition on this, and more importantly by dealing with the case in the way which the applicants have submitted, this would ensure that like persons are treated in the same manner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5496.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5503.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is merely an accident of timing as far as the decision on admissibility was taken.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5503.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5520.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Had the Court not been able to dispatch some cases more speedily, it is equally possible that Mr Smiljov's case would have been heard after the Vinter case, and in those circumstances, since the case was within the Court already, he should be treated in exactly the same way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5520.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5520.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5522.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5524.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5524.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5530.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mrs. Kotseva and Mrs. Dimitrova in the order they prefer to speak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5539.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5543.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5543.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5563.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the first question of Judge Serkides about how actually the circumstances in the case unfolded in 1999, we tried to present a brief overview of them in our observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5563.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5577.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So what happened was that on July 2, an armed robbery and two murders happened in Burgas, and the applicant and another person were the main suspects in the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5577.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5584.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The authorities started collecting evidence right away about the crime committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5584.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5588.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And however, the applicant went in hiding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5588.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5591.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So he was declared wanted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5591.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5601.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was declared wanted, and even an order for his arrest was issued on July 9, although he was still in hiding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5601.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5617.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So because his permanent address was in Sofia, that's why the investigator in Burgas actually was looking for the cooperation of the authorities in Sofia, of the police in Sofia, to find him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5617.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5625.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on October 3, the applicant was arrested on the strength of the order of July 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5625.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5628.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A police order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5628.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5631.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This order was for 24 hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5631.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5639.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in order for his detention to be legal, it had to be prolonged by the investigator, and after that by the prosecutor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5639.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5648.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the period between July 2, when the crime was committed, and the applicant's arrest, a number of evidentiary material was collected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5648.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5652.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Witnesses were questioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5652.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5658.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order for the authorities to review the crime and to identify their main suspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5662.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5683.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the second question of Judge Lemans, about whether or not there is a complaint about the right to meet counsel in private, the government submit that this complaint was declared inadmissible by the chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5683.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5695.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we refer to paragraph 102 of the chamber judgment, where this complaint was found to be submitted outside the six-month time limit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5695.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5715.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next question of Judge Lopez-Guerra about why exactly the applicant was arrested on October 3, I refer to my answer to the first question, and we submit that he was arrested because he was the main suspect in the crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5717.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5738.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the question of Judge Stadmayer about the Bulgarian legislation, and the reports of the Committee for Prevention of Torture, the government submit that indeed the Bulgarian legislation contained guarantees and safeguards about the access to legal advice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5738.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5746.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the reports of the Committee for Prevention of Torture indicate shortcomings in the implementation of these provisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5749.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5761.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government takes measures continuously to improve access to lawyer, especially in the initial hours after arrest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5761.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5782.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would also, however, like to underline that it's been the court's case law that the convention does not provide for the institution of an actio popularis, and each case must be seen on its own, on its main facts, in concrete.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5782.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5795.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in the present case, we would like to submit once more that despite the lack of access to legal advice during that period, the applicant's right to a fair trial was not violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5795.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5814.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the question whether any confessions made during that period, it would be possible to challenge them at trial, we submit that such confessions made in the absence of lawyer would be inadmissible in trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5814.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5827.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the reason for that is that pursuant to the relevant domestic framework with his detention, the applicant became a suspect in the crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5827.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5832.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A suspect, this is, at the time, it was a temporary procedural figure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5832.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5838.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And actually, all the rights of the accused applied to the suspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5838.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5848.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And because the crime committed was a serious crime, which envisioned more than 10 years imprisonment, it was obligatory for the authorities to ensure a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5848.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5855.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, all the statements made would be inadmissible at trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5855.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5858.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope this answers your question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5858.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5884.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then regarding the comments about the possible conversation between the police and the applicant, we don't have any proof that such a conversation, the one claimed by the applicant, actually took place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5884.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5889.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it is difficult to comment what exactly was said and how it was said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5889.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5896.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What's important is that no statements were later used in trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5896.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5912.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I come to the last question of Judge Shayo about the fact that the applicant complained of his absence to lawyer before the court of cassation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5912.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5923.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would like to reiterate once more that the first three days of the applicant's detention were used for his transfer from Sofia to Burgas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5923.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5926.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The investigation was held in Burgas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5926.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5930.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the first three days, no evidence involving the applicant was gathered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5930.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5937.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, any submissions regarding that period are irrelevant to the trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5937.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5945.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So therefore, there was no need for the court to actually take any stance on that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5945.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5951.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So these are our answers to your questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5951.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5951.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5953.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5956.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5956.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5960.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5960.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5965.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their submissions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5965.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5968.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5968.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5972.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered at a later stage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5972.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5976.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5976.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5978.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
