<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>2245716_15012020</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>24.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>24.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>43.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>44.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>60.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>67.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je déclare ouverte l'audience publique sur le fonds de l'affaire X et autres contre Bulgarie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>67.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>81.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'affaire a été introduite devant la Cour le 16 avril 2016 par cinq ressortissants italiens, un couple et leurs trois enfants mineurs en vertu de l'article 34 de la Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>81.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>92.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Elle a été attribuée à la cinquième section de la Cour conformément à l'article 52, paragraphe 1 du règlement de la Cour.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>92.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>105.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le 5 septembre 2016, la requête a été communiquée au gouvernement sous l'angle des articles 3 et 8 de la Convention en ce qui concerne les grèves soulevées par les trois enfants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>105.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>117.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les grèves formulées par les parents ont leur nom propre ont été déclarées irrecevables en application de l'article 54, paragraphe 3 du règlement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>117.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>134.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le 17 janvier 2019, une chambre de la cinquième section a rendu un arrêt par lequel elle a déclaré le restant de la requête recevable et a conclu à l'unanimité à la non-violation des articles 3 et 8 de la Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>134.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>153.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le 12 avril 2019, les requérants ont demandé le renvoi de l'affaire devant la Grande Chambre conformément à l'article 43 de la Convention et cette demande a été acceptée par le Collège de la Grande Chambre le 24 juin 2019.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>153.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>166.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le gouvernement est représenté par ses agentes, Mme Raya Nikolova et Mme Iva Stancheva-Chinova, assistée de Mme Ivana Sotirova, conseillère.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>166.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>174.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les requérants sont représentés par M. Francesco Mauceri, avocat, assisté du Dr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>174.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>176.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rose Galante et du Dr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>176.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>177.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Patricia Sarah Bach, conseillère.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>177.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>183.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je salue les comparants au nom de la Cour.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>183.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>191.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ayant consulté les agentes du gouvernement et le représentant des requérants, j'ai fixé ainsi l'ordre de parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>191.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>198.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nous entendrons successivement M. Mauceri pour les requérants, puis Mme Nikolova et</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>198.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>201.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mme Stancheva-Chinova pour le gouvernement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>201.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>204.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La parole est à M. Mauceri, M., vous avez la Parole</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>208.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>210.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>210.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>222.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you to every member of the Court for offering this hearing and demonstrating its high degree of civic mindedness, sensitivity, and solidarity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>222.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>233.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These values and feelings constitute a subject of the controversy and of responsibility of a Bulgarian state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>233.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>252.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I want to say also at once that on this painful path we have also met a beautiful face of Bulgaria, full of solidarity, love, and respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>252.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>259.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This Bulgarian nation we consider our ally and not adversary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>259.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>266.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Many voices have risen in Bulgaria in defense of the crime and minors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>266.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>278.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, I think about Stefan Stoyanov, a human rights expert operating with international organization Save the Children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>278.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>282.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think about the lawyer, Mr. Markovsky,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>282.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>289.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>who worked about and is one of the best accredited crime experts in Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>289.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>296.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With them we feel near vast majority of Bulgarian people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>296.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>300.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I hope Bulgarian state will align to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>300.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>336.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now it's not possible to summarize all the arguments and evidence that demonstrates of the state Bulgaria did not fulfill the duty they had to protect the applicants while they were guests of one Bulgarian orphanage and let them undergo an organized and constant system of violence, abuse, and torture together with the other children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>336.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>344.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I must refer to the acts and to the many documents that we offered to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>344.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>350.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I will summarize what the time will permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>350.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>366.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have many, many evidence of the fact of the tortures in human and denigrating treatments suffered by the claimants who were housed in the orphanage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>366.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>374.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I believe that any discussion must start from consideration of those tortures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>374.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>410.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the investigative reports of European journalist Fabrizio Gatti, reporting the acts of violence and abuse about which we speak, we read, it is horrible and gruesome just to imagine all this, but we have to read and to consider the silence of those in Bulgaria turning their backs on the courage of the three children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>410.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>429.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For most, those tortures and the criminal organizations operating as ---- are described with clear precision and shocking drama in the detailed reports of the narratives told by the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>429.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>445.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are video recording and minor hearing reports carefully prepared and checked by Italian juvenile courts with the help of highly qualified experts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>445.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>461.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Italian judicial authority acquired and we produced concordant and multiple expert reports provided regarding the narratives of claimant children narratives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>461.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>490.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to specifically highly and experienced experts, Italian juvenile court, which the provision used on 13 May 2014, clarified the truthfulness of the children narratives and therefore explicated the serious transgressions of the responsible Bulgarian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>490.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>500.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also have evidence about other similar cases in the same orphanages and also in others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>500.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>503.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also Bulgarian media refer many.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>503.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>522.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 4 January 2013, seven days before the publication of the report on magazine L'Espresso, an orphan, his name begin by N, N.R., I will call him, in an interview published in various</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>522.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>536.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgarian media, he was coming from ---- orphanage and he denounced to the acts of violence and abuses suffered at ---- orphanage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>536.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>551.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He said all the narratives about what is happening in the orphanages are true and there is nothing exaggerated, sexist, rotund, from the earliest childhood.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>551.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>566.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This interview was annexed, including several other documents, in request for questioning set by Italian Ministry of Justice to the Bulgarian counterpart in June 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>566.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>573.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Bulgarian government, at the request of the court, provided the request of Italia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>573.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>580.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Who knows, who knows how many other dramatic events remain lost in oblivion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>580.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>592.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Buried in the silence that in most cases fall on the victims in an attempt to take refuge from the terror and the horror they have been suffering.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>592.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>600.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He also complains, many complaints from other parents, ignorant from Bulgaria State.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>600.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>618.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria archived there, ignorant also the precise and detailed complaints coming directly from the Vice President of Italian International Adoption Commissions, as we have reported in detail in our observation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>618.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>624.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are also the investigations from Italian and European journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>624.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>632.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, Rai TV reports, Presa Diretta, we produced also it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>632.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>655.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the investigation conducted in Bulgaria by Fabrizio Gatti, published on L'Espresso, the most prestigious weekly magazine in Italy, Fabrizio Gatti is well known for his undercover and very dangerous investigations about criminal organization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>655.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>662.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He cares about mafia, drug trafficking, immigrants' exploitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>662.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>669.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He found this case the most dangerous he has seen in his life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>669.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>670.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Gatti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>670.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>679.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Great work in favor of the climate minors, of all the minors, and of human droids.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>679.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>689.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have professional reports coming from expert Italian psychologists and accredited relational therapy center in Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>689.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>695.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is advanced institutions, in particular in person of Mrs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>695.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>718.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rose Galante, who is near to me, that has charge of the children since they arrived in Italy, and also now she cares about them, using all the best scientific instruments and the state of the art techniques.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>718.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>734.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The videotaped hearings were acquired and careful with most experienced and carefully were examinated by the Italian judicial authority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>734.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>756.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judicial authority was helped by specializated judicial police, the scientific police, and other public pursuers then proceeded to carry out new hearings, also videotaped and examined in cooperation with scientific police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>756.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>779.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following a far-too specialized assessment, including child and neuropsychiatrics, a further expert opinion was prepared by the professor Sergio Kimens, the director of the Department of Child and Neuropsychiatry of local health authority of an independent region of Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>779.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>790.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Subsequently, the comprehensive documentary and their results were evaluated by a panel of five Italian judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>790.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>805.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The president is one of the best magistrate experts in this kind of cases, in this very delicate field.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>805.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>818.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no doubt by any about the children mentioned on the atrocity they had to suffer at the orphanage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>818.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>827.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The psychologists, Rose Galante and Sara Bach, are here near me and they are at disposal of the course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>827.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>872.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They could be interrogated about the children, about the terrible truth that they referred and that now have in their lacerated minds, about the terrible shenery that is in the house of the children, the parents, insecurity, anxiety, fear, scare, anger, distress, nightmares, fire of emotions, ever burning at home of the victim and obviously also of their parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>872.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>877.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have also other elements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>877.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>897.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The behavior that Bulgaria State has held and is holding about this case is another element that you have to consider at the most the responsibility about which I speak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>897.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>913.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria State didn't protect Bulgarian orphans, did not do anything to punish the delinquents, manipulates, mystifies and hides the facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>913.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>925.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only who wants to cover responsibility can ignore the evidence as the parents reports, for example, Archivites.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>925.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>949.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The State's movies with delay and insufficiency only after the publication of a journalist investigation and against the investigation as if it were an offense to the national honor and not a reason to indicate and to punish the criminals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>949.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>957.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria State investigated and asking the corporates to report regarding their very serious responsibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>957.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>964.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then it quickly closed the investigation, ignoring and hiding the tragedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>964.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>977.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The versions provided by the Bulgarian authority are inconsistent, contradictory and misleading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>977.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>985.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, while denying the facts, the Bulgarian bodies ended up by admitting them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>985.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>989.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At times, haven't explicitly and clearly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>989.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1009.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During a journalist interview published by the Bulgarian press, the orphanage director admitted that many children had reported to her regarding the abuses suffered in the orphanage, asking for help.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1009.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1018.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But she said that it had been a collective hallucination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1018.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1020.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's incredible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1020.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1031.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A few months ago, this interview disappeared from the website of the Bulgarian newspaper, Borba, that published it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1031.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1041.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now the Bulgarian government, shamelessly, haven't gone so far as to support the non-existence of the interview.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1041.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1058.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it forgets that we produced it many times, also to the attention of the court, of course, and that it's still possible to view this section in another possibility, in another media.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1058.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1063.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's now possible to see this interview.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1063.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1071.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria forgot to transmit the documentation received from Italy, Italy has requested this interview.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1071.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1088.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Bulgaria not remember to forward several of the documents that the Italian court asked to it, including the decree of juvenile court of the May 2014, about which I spoke before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1088.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1097.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Many misrepresentations were asserted in an attempt to mask the clear reality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1097.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1111.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Many of the children, if not all, had asked for help, reporting the dramatic abuses suffered to the director, the psychologist, and the social worker.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1111.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1114.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, they received no help.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1114.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1125.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quite the contrary, the children were further punished and let under their abusers who haven't handled their wicked behavior.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1125.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1138.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A version of the facts very different from that admitted by the director was subsequently entered in the institution's records.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1138.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1147.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Disappeared also the thesis of collective hallucinations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1147.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1162.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On January 2013, we had a very interesting reflection about this case from lawyer Markoski, good Bulgarian lawyer Markoski.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1162.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1176.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He wrote in a media, 24 Chasabiji, every civilized country treats the elderly, the sick, and the children with care.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1176.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1178.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria is not a civilized country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1178.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1193.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The action of the government, the state agency, and Bulgarian judicial authority is a slap in the face of many innocent victims and brings serious dishonor on the Bulgarian people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1193.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1208.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government declares that the assistance of the abusers was not proven because there are not medical certificates attesting the physical consequence of the abuses suffered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1208.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1221.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The scientific literature demonstrates that the most case, the body of children who suffered acts of violence and humiliation does not remain diminished forever.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1221.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1237.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And not all the abusers can provocate on the body some consequence, but on the mind and on the soul, ever.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1237.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1252.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the men and the children should undergo humiliation and even painful visits in order to bring a scar permanently impressed on the body as evidence is an involvement, insensitive, and immature attitude.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1252.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1262.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Civil culture studied and scientific research show that physical examination are irrelevant, are dangerous.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1262.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1268.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Recently, are dangerous for the mind of the victims, of course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1268.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1278.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Recently, Bulgarian statement tied also to transform the psychological profiles of the climbing minors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1278.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1287.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now they are quite different from those described in the children's file that were given to the climbing parents at time of adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1287.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1290.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that time, their balance was declared perfect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1290.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1294.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now the opposite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1294.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1310.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the children reports and from other elements mentioned, it emerged that the tortures they suffered did not take place in exceptional or large circumstance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1310.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1320.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, they were in a system, in an organized system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1320.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1342.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We clearly substantiate and have seen the existence of tortures that occurred within a tragic and organized system in broad daylight, perpetrated with full freedom and access for the torturers to instigate their heinous schemes both inside and outside the orphanage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1342.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1356.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The children were transported by unscrupulous criminals who acted unfettered and undisturbed within a well-organized contest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1356.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1370.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We told so help of the technological and cinematographic equipment and provide a criminal market of pornographic products, specifically market for pedophiles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1370.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1377.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What did Bulgaria and its institutions do while all this was happening?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1377.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1382.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Everyone knows that children need to be protected and supervised.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1382.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1385.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a natural law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1385.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1395.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before legal law, also animals protect and supervise their little ones.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1395.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1410.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court asked very appropriately if Bulgaria's follow the rules indicated in the International Convention on Rights of Child of 20 November, 1999 and in the Lanzarote Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1410.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1415.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are many, many and evident violations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1415.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1425.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Violated is the principle established by International Convention of Child of 20 November, 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1425.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1434.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The principle of no discrimination, the principle of the best interest of the child, Sanctioned by Section 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1434.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1438.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The best interest of the child shall be considered the first.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1438.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1446.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria didn't write to law of survival and development provided for the Section 6.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1446.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1447.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria didn't.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1447.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1455.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Violated the principle establishing the duty to heard the opinions of the child provided in the Section 12.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1455.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1457.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria didn't.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1457.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1471.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria disregarded the letter also of Lanzarote Convention of the many principles and sections I must run.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1471.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1478.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we can read the memory that we offered also for this area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1478.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1489.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Violated is Section Number 5 of the Convention that prescribes a system for selecting and check the personnel to work with minors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1489.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1491.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria didn't.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1491.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1505.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Very serious violation of Section 12 that provides Missouri's necessary to encourage any persons who want to denounce.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1505.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1508.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria didn't.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1508.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1515.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But Bulgaria didn't want any denounce.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1515.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1518.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the terrible truth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1518.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1527.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Lanzarote Convention defines sexual exploitation, abuse in the section from 18 to 23.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1527.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1546.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The contents of these sections demonstrate that it's not necessary to make any physical visit to clarify and declare if abuse were done.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1546.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1558.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Section 30 of the Conventions provide effective investigation and prosecution for the crime in accordance with this Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1558.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1564.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The alleged investigation and prosecution are proven anteriorly fictitious.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1564.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1570.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No intelligence or infiltration operations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1570.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1583.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The State Agency and the Polish Trample's Police inquired in accordance with orphanage operators, the alleged offenders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1583.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1588.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is how very abuses and they are complaints regarding the abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1588.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1596.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They examined the documentation prepared from the orphanage operators.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1596.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1606.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Bulgarian expert, Stefan Nastojanov, says only an incompetent persons or an accomplice can act in this way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1606.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1609.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the result is the same.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1609.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1620.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria prevented the policeman contacted by Fabrizio Gatti from continuing the investigative activity that he had previously.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1620.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1628.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Violated are the general protection miseries of the section 31 of the Conventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1628.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1638.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria did not inform the victims of the follow-up of their complaints, did not allow the victims, namely the parents and inclined children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1638.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1645.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have a violation of point E in this particular series.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1645.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1663.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgarian authorities revealed the personal identity and other sensitive data of the victims and of complainants, giving to the media, which resulted in a wide dissemination of information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1663.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1679.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We wrote about Bulgaria, indicated about and says that the public case implicate this possibility and there is not, that is not permitted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1679.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1687.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But Lanzarote Convention is clear about and Bulgaria violated also about this profile.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1687.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1697.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria state was the author of several retaliatory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1697.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1707.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lanzarote Convention provide a lot of measures from many risk of retaliations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1707.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1714.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria didn't provide anything but was the actor of retaliation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1714.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1726.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It asked for the parents, the minors, to be declared not able to have their children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1726.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1731.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was a retaliation, terrible retaliation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1731.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1738.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I must remind the act, times run away.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1738.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1747.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I want to remember that also section 34 that prescribe a special side of the police department was violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1747.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1760.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Section 35 about the evidence of minors, Italian authority judge followed this section, Bulgarian, nothing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1760.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1763.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1763.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1776.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I want to reiterate that obligation to protect children and their lives is a natural law and obvious prerequisite in work of any legal system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1776.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1782.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Generally this task is performed by parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1782.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1793.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Climbing parents do carry out with great love and efficiency and I want to say them here now today, publicly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1793.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1803.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time I want to declare that it's really despicable the behavior of those who attempted to question their parents' skill.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1803.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1813.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whenever the parents are missing and waiting for the goal of adoption, they state as responsibility to act as mother and father.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1813.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1815.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria didn't.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1815.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1831.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the very early life, the children were deprived of parental care and the Bulgarian state was therefore required to take their parents' place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1831.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1840.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fences were guests of orphanage which is a public institution of Bulgarian state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1840.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1844.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had no protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1844.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1856.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bulgaria didn't protect their childhood, their safety, and the most intimate values of their lives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1856.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1871.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have pointed and denounced with clarity that the children were left at mercy of a predatory criminal gang that had no qualms about stockpiling children to subject them to horrible tortures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1871.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1876.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can a state let a criminal organization acquire its orphans to torture her?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1876.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1880.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Obviously not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1880.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1889.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not it's necessary to wonder whether this happened by will or fault, in any case, Bulgaria is responsible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1889.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1903.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Responsibility has grown in the investigation and prosecution faced with the mystification and the retaliations I mentioned before, and nobody was punished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1903.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1914.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Criminals may feel free to act again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1914.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1917.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any responsible dupe remains recluded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1917.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1931.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I must refer to what I wrote about the possibility of the parents, it's obvious I think that the damage goes on the parents too.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1931.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1941.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't remember, and please forgive me, any definite providement that excludes the parents from this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1941.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1951.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have here a providement that admits the case and all five claimants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1951.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1969.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We wrote about and we hope to clarify that the parents are yet applicants in this case, and I must refer to what I wrote because I have to conclude and I know.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1969.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1985.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In concluding, I see that violated are of course section number three that doesn't permit torture and inhumane treatment, and number four of the conventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1985.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1992.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also about them I remind also of the act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1992.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1996.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What about the compensations?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1996.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2002.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no price for the values we are speaking about.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2002.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2026.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Every compensation will not give back to the claimants their life, the first time of their lives, the childhood, the happy age, the age of the games, the serenity that they have tried to have.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2026.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2036.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today fight is offering us the great opportunity to contribute to a good cause and to deal a heavy blow to heaven.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2036.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2040.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let us not miss this opportunity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2040.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2040.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2040.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2041.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2041.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2041.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2045.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2048.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup. La parole est à Madame Nikolova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2052.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2053.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2053.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2056.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2056.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2069.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on behalf of the Bulgarian government, in my pleading I will address the measures taken by the national authorities to fulfill their positive, substantive, and procedural obligations in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2069.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2084.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government submitted that in the present case, Bulgaria respected all its positive obligations arising from Articles 3 and 8 of the Convention, and took all measures which could reasonably be required or expected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2084.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2097.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the requirements laid down by the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child, we refer to the last periodic report of Bulgaria published on the website of the UN Committee on the Rights of the Child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2097.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2111.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As evident, by 2012, a number of legislative, administrative, and other measures had already been taken to prevent and tackle inhuman or degrading treatment and sexual abuse of children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2111.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2121.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, the government considered that at the material time of the present case, the head state had already fulfilled its positive obligations stemming from the UN Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2121.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2131.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning the Lanzarote Convention, the government emphasized that it entered into force for Bulgaria on 1st of April, 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2131.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2146.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, since the applicants alleged that the sexual abuse had continued for six years before 2012, the obligations under this Convention were not applicable for the almost entire period at issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2146.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2158.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should, however, be noted that the substantive and procedural measures envisaged in the Convention were implemented by Bulgaria in the period between 2009 and 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2158.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2170.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As evident from the first implementation report on the Lanzarote Convention, published in 2015, Bulgaria has fulfilled all its obligations there under.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2170.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2180.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the case at hand, the government points out that the authorities reacted promptly and initiated immediate inspections concerning the alleged facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2180.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2188.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first notification containing specific information was received on 14th of January, 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2188.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2204.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was addressed to the Ministry of Justice by the association Amici dei Bambini in reply to the request of the Ministry following the publications in Bulgarian media, which mentioned that the adoption was conducted through that association.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2204.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2214.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Ministry of Justice immediately reported informally the information to the State Agency for Child Protection, which I will refer to as the agency.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2214.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2225.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the same day, 14th of January, the agency chaired assigned an inspection at the orphanage, which was conducted in accordance with the requirements of the UN Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2225.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2236.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 28th of January, 2013, a preliminary investigation was initiated after the signal of the agency chair to the prosecutor's office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2236.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2254.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Approximately at the same time, on 17th of January, 2013, the regional prosecutor's office Veliko Tarnovo opened a preliminary investigation, and the second inspection at the orphanage was appointed with the participation of various state institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2254.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2268.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, it should be noted that the Bulgarian authorities acted with promptness and initiated two preliminary investigations on their own motion as soon as they had been apprised of the impugned facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2268.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2280.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So even in the absence of any formal complaint, once the matter came to the attention of the authorities, they made immediate and comprehensive efforts to elucidate the factual situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2280.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2286.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, they acted in compliance with Articles 30 and 32 of the Lanzarote Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2286.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2306.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The materials received later through the prosecutor's office of the Republic of Italy were separated in a different case file on 18th of February, 2013, and several days afterwards, transmitted to the district prosecutor's office, which opened a third preliminary investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2306.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2317.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fourth investigation was opened on 4th of April, 2014, with respect to the documents sent by the Italian Ministry of Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2317.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2336.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government emphasized that the adoptive parents never addressed a formal complaint to the Bulgarian authorities directly or through the competent Italian organs, except for the letter received in June, 2016, through the Bulgarian Ministry of Justice, challenging the investigation carried out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2336.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2344.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was received a year and a half after the refusal to open criminal proceedings was sent to the Italian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2344.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2354.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Bulgarian prosecutor's office, aware of the seriousness of the allegations and the sensitive character of the case, thoroughly reviewed the case files once more.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2354.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2364.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, the higher-ranking prosecutors reviewed the documentation at two more levels of internal instance control on their own motion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2364.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2375.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government underlined that throughout the inspections carried out, none of the applicants' allegations were corroborated, even indirectly, by the findings established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2375.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2381.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even so, the authorities could draw very few factual details from their statements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2381.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2385.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of them were meticulously and comprehensively verified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2385.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2399.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Divergences were detected with regard to the men employed at the institution, namely that only three staff members were men, a driver, a doorkeeper, and a heating technician, and they had no access to the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2399.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2406.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The infants were divided into different dormitories by age, and the older ones over seven by gender.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2406.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2410.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, the applicants occupied different dormitories.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2410.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2421.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The layout of those premises was such that the children could not go from one to another without passing through a room where there were staff members on duty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2421.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2425.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A person named with the initials N had never worked in the institution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2425.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2432.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the medical dossier, no sexually mature children of either gender inhabited the orphanage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2432.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2440.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only occasion on which the children attended a party outside the orphanage had been the one during the annual excursion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2440.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2447.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The tutors supervised the entire event, and the only outside visitor was the DJ.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2447.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2457.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Notwithstanding the inconsistencies found, the authorities took all reasonable measures available to them to obtain evidence relating to the alleged offense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2457.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2472.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A number of investigative acts were carried out in order to establish the objective truth, such as anonymous questioning of the staff and the children, interviews with the mayor and the doctor supervising the children, the psychologist, the social worker.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2472.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2483.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Persons mentioned in the testimonies of the applicants, such as the photographer and the electrician who occasionally had come to the orphanage, were required to submit statements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2483.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2493.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, a team of psychologists performed a crisis intervention at the orphanage from 18 to 24 of January 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2493.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2505.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No dubious or alarming facts or circumstances were found evidencing that any kind of abuse of which the authorities knew or ought to have known had taken place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2505.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2517.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government emphasized that the interviews with the children at the orphanage were carried out by specialists in compliance with good social and psychological practices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2517.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2531.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As evident from the information provided by the agency in enclosure one, there is an approved manual for performance of inspections following a signal drawn up in compliance with the UN Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2531.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2541.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the inspections at hand, the interviews with the children were conducted by experienced psychologists and social workers in the absence of any member of the staff.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2541.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2544.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The children were divided into small groups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2544.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2556.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The preparatory conversations with them gradually evolved into questionings about the relations at the home, friendships, likings, and irritating behavior.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2556.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2569.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were appropriate for the age and cognitive level of the children, sparing for their psyche, and at the same time, ensuring unambiguous answers with regard to the alleged facts and circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2569.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2577.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The interviewers observed carefully the children's reactions, levels of anxiety, calmness, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2577.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2587.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following the interviews, an anonymous questioner was filled in by the older children, who were able to read and write, again, in the absence of staff members.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2587.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2599.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The methods used by the agency in the present case have been applied during the past 15 years and have proved their effectiveness in the course of numerous inspections.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2599.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2618.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The account of events presented by the applicants was not corroborated during the interviews with the children, which, taken with the other gathered evidence, substantiated the inference that there were no data that any sexual abuse had taken place at the orphanage or during the annual excursions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2618.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2634.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In view of the above and the comprehensive investigative effects of the authorities, the government point out that the positive obligation of the state to investigate the occurrence of alleged facts should not put an excessive and disproportionate burden on the authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2634.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2640.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We refer to the case of Djordjevic versus Croatia and Dodos versus Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2640.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2647.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indisputably, in the case at hand, the applicants' allegations served as a basis for the inspections carried out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2647.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2653.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the authority did not limit their scope strictly to the allegations made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2653.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2660.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, a comprehensive inspection of the orphanage for the past seven years was conducted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2660.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2670.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular matters concerning the medical status of children, complaints submitted, and all other issues that could be of relevance to the alleged facts were scrutinized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2670.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2686.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was established that the psychologist at the orphanage worked regularly with the children on an individual basis, recorded every meeting, and prepared periodical individual reports which showed no signs of abuse or ill treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2686.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2692.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The institution was constantly supervised by the local police and social authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2692.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2704.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The measures taken to protect the children from ill treatment, namely the admission regime, the camera surveillance, a telephone helpline, and the complaint box, were specifically scrutinized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2704.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2710.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No incidents corresponding to the applicants' allegations were reported through those means.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2710.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2721.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These preventive measures were available at the orphanage at the time the applicants resided there and were in compliance with Article 19 of the UN Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2721.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2731.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Convention on Human Rights requires effective deterrence against grave effects of ill treatment, and the children in particular are entitled to effective protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2731.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2738.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To this effect, we refer to Z and others versus the United Kingdom and MC versus Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2738.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2749.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In view of the state's obligation for prevention of abuse, the government point out that the children residing at the orphanage benefited from the necessary level of protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2749.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2756.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, they had contacts with the outside world as they went to school on a daily basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2756.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2759.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some of them were in touch with their families.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2759.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2768.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is very unlikely that all the children would prefer to remain silent and not to disclose their alleged experiences of sexual abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2768.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2785.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the children were regularly examined by a general practitioner in accordance with Article 24 of the UN Convention, and most of them were subjected to detailed medical examinations in view of the pending adoption procedures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2785.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2798.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As seen from the documents in enclosures 2, 3, and 4, the applicants also underwent full medical examinations every three months because they had been listed for international adoption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2798.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2809.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government explicitly noted that all three applicants passed a couple of psychiatric examinations in 2011 in relation to the adoption procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2809.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2818.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The psychiatrist established that there were no signs of stress, depression, anxiety, or other symptoms that could point to an abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2818.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2839.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government noted in this regard that according to Article 7, paragraph 2 of the Child Protection Act, all professionals who become aware of the existence of a child in need of protection in the course of their work, irrespective of being bound by an occupational secret, shall immediately report the case to the competent authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2839.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2845.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This obligation includes doctors, social workers, institutional staff, teachers, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2845.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2849.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the failure to abide by it is subject to sanctions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2849.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2854.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It complies with the requirements set by the UN and C conventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2854.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2860.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No incidents of the alleged kind were ever reported with regard to the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2860.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2868.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government notes that the Bulgarian authorities investigated with diligence all relevant data available to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2868.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2878.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They paid attention to all details of the allegations of sexual abuse contained in the psychological notes drawn up by the Italian psychologists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2878.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2891.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Considering that the testimony of minors should be taken with the utmost caution, the Bulgarian authorities did not disregard any part of it and scrutinized all the factual aspects that were deduced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2891.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2895.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government would like to point to some particularities of those notes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2895.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2900.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, they did not contain verbatim record of the applicant's statements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2900.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2906.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, indisputably, the applicants had a weak command of Italian at the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2906.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2914.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, the adoptive parent was present at the meetings and, I quote, translated between times for the applicant X.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2914.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2930.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourth, in the resume transcripts of the psychological sessions, the applicants Y and Z never mentioned any, I quote, playing with adult men while such information is present in the psychological notes as uttered by them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2930.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2941.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be underlined that the testimony of the applicants X and Y before the Italian prosecutor did not cast any new light on the alleged circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2941.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2946.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In view of that, no further questioning of the applicants seemed to be necessary at the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2946.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2959.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a well-known good practice that when it comes to the testimony of minors, interrogations should be reduced to the strictly necessary minimum in order to protect them from trauma and stress.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2959.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2967.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government considered that after being comprised of the impugned facts, the Bulgarian authorities were seriously concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2967.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2974.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They performed full, thorough, and objective investigations striving to shed light on the events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2974.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2987.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be pointed out that there is no obligation under Article Three of the Convention for the authorities to establish identical facts or to come to a conclusion which coincides with the applicant's account of events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2987.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2994.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, we refer to the case of MP and others versus Bulgaria and Maximov versus Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2994.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3010.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Bulgarian authorities complied with their positive obligation to look into the matter and to establish all the relevant facts by means of an appropriate investigation which required that all aspects of the applicant's allegations be examined and scrutinized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3010.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3018.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the grounds of the evidence gathered, the authorities concluded that there were no, that the allegations had not been confirmed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3018.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3033.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The investigation was effective because the prosecution authorities gathered and analyzed all the available data in terms of established findings, interviews with the children at the orphanage, interrogations, checkups, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3033.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3039.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None of the evidence gathered led to the reasonable assumption that the criminal offense had been committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3039.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3055.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In view of this and taking into account that the investigative measures did not produce sufficient evidence to establish that the alleged abuse had taken place, the conclusions of the Bulgarian authorities could not be deemed arbitrary or groundless.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3055.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3059.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I believe that the court will take into consideration the above reasoning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3059.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3061.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I give the floor to my colleague.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3061.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3061.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3067.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3069.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, Madame Iva Stancheva-Chinova, vous avez la parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3072.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3076.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable Mr. President and judges of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3076.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3087.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will address some issues concerning the developments before the agency, the proceedings in Italy, and the necessity of medical examinations in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3087.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3096.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government underlined that the adopter never approached the agency with any specific information allowing an inspection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3096.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3108.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In his email of 16th of November, 2012, he only requested a telephone number alleging unspecified abuse in an unspecified orphanage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3108.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3115.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the same day, the agency received an email by the Italian Telefono Azzurro via the Nadia Foundation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3115.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3130.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It contained a request by an anonymous Italian citizen who had adopted three Bulgarian children to receive the contact details of a competent organization in order to submit a signal for abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3130.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3139.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In reply, on the 26th of November, the agency provided a telephone number and an email to the adopter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3139.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3143.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He did not submit any further particular details.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3143.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3150.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Telefono Azzurro communication was also forwarded to the Ministry of Justice on the 29th of November.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3150.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3170.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the attached email did not allow verification in the Registry of International Adoptions maintained by the ministry as it did not contain the name of the adopter while at the relevant period there had been four adoption procedures of three siblings in Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3170.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3182.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, the government considered that at the time it was not clear either who the alleged victims were or what the nature of the abuse against them was.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3182.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3188.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the authorities could not be held accountable in this respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3188.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3206.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regard to the nature of the proceedings in Italy, as a preliminary note, the government underlined that the state's positive obligations under Articles 3 and 8 of the Convention apply only in relation to ill treatment allegedly committed within their jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3206.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3218.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows in the present circumstances that since the alleged ill treatment occurred in Bulgaria, it was undisputedly for the Bulgarian authorities to investigate the events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3218.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3223.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no such obligation on the part of the Italian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3223.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3233.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Convention does not envisage that a high contracting party should intervene with the jurisdiction of another state on the applicant's behalf.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3233.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3240.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, we refer to the Commission decisions on L versus Sweden and Doberstein versus Germany.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3240.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3246.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, there was no conflict of jurisdiction between Bulgaria and Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3246.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3268.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The letter from the Italian prosecutor's office of 15th of January, 2013, transmitting the documents from Telefono Azzurro, explicitly stated that as the alleged offense was perpetrated on foreign territory and by foreign citizens, the Italian authorities were not competent to examine it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3268.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3281.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The proceedings which took place in Italy were actually civil ones and concerned the evaluation of the parental capacity of the adopters and the adaptation of the applicants in the family.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3281.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3297.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The allegations of the applicants that they were started at the insistence of the Bulgarian authorities are untrue, which is evident from the email correspondence between the Bulgarian Vice Minister of Justice and Dr. Daniela Bacchetta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3297.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3305.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, it was the competent Italian authorities who intervened by initiating a case at the Miner's Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3305.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3318.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In view of the above, the government point out that the decision of the Miner's Court is irrelevant to the present case, as it does not and may not concern criminal matters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3318.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3323.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is why it was never communicated to the Bulgarian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3323.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3343.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regard to the applicants' allegations about the scientific veracity of the expert report prepared in the course of the civil proceedings before the Miner's Court, the government present a scientific analysis by Aldo Dvrish, a professor of applied social psychology at the University of Portsmouth, UK.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3343.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3353.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a comprehensive review of the available studies concerning the statement validity assessment, which I will refer to as SVA.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3353.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3362.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>SVA has been used for the past 30 years to assess the veracity of child witnesses' testimony in cases of sexual offenses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3362.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3382.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the established scientific theory and practice, the SVA consists of three stages, a semi-structured interview, a criteria-based content analysis, or CBCA, and an evaluation of the CBCA scores by means of a validity checklist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3382.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3392.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The method has proven to be quite controversial, mainly due to the large error rate, which reaches 30% in controlled studies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3392.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3402.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This error rate hardly puts these assessments as passing the standard of being beyond the reasonable doubt required for evidencing in criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3402.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3408.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The error rate of SVA in real life cannot be objectively measured and is yet unknown.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3408.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3420.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government point out that there is no consensus among high contracting parties as to whether they consider this method a legally valid evidence in criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3420.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3437.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if presuming that the SVA results could be regarded reliable, it remains unclear why such a method, which is used solely for the purposes of criminal investigations, was applied in the civil proceedings for evaluation of the adoption process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3437.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3448.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the expert report presented before the Miners Court was incomplete and elaborated contrary to the set rules for the following reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3448.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3455.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, no semi-structured interviews with the three applicants were ever conducted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3455.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3460.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The evidence in this case shows that all their questioning suffered from deficiencies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3460.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3464.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The FAD intervened during the psychological assessments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3464.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3468.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Applicants Y and Z were assessed together.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3468.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3473.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the prosecutor's hearings, a number of suggestive questions were put.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3473.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3477.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Applicant Z was never heard by the prosecutor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3477.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3482.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, no conclusive CBCA was performed either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3482.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3491.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In his report, the expert only numbered the CBCA criteria without any explanation as to why and which of them were covered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3491.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3499.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The stories of the applicants were never evaluated separately for each child, but in bulk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3499.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3504.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, the expert did not conduct a validity checklist analysis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3504.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3512.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The validity checklist consists of a list of external factors that might affect the CBCA scores.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3512.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3540.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It takes into account, inter alia, the appropriateness of knowledge and language, the interviewee's susceptibility to suggestion, evidence of suggestive leading or coercive questioning, and last but not least, the consistency with other evidence, for example, whether there are major elements in the statement that are contradicted by reliable physical or other concrete evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3540.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3544.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None of the above was discussed in the report at hand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3544.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3566.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Professor Vrisch commented in his analysis that there are many cases when the SVA cannot detect statements which are false, either because the interviewees may be confused about the circumstances or because they mix what they have actually experienced and what they have only imagined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3566.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3580.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He underlined that the SVA experts should present those problems and limitations in court so that legal professionals could make an informed decision about the validity of the SVA results.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3580.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3587.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the government's knowledge, the minors' court was never informed about those limitations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3587.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3595.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Next, the government will make some additional comments on the necessity of medical examinations in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3595.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3603.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the court's case law, allegations of ill-treatment must be supported by appropriate evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3603.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3619.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To assess this evidence, the court adopts the standard of proof beyond a reasonable doubt, although such proof may fall from the coexistence of sufficiently strong, clear, and concordant inferences or of similar unrebutted presumptions of fact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3619.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3626.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, we refer to Ireland versus the United Kingdom and Meduva versus Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3626.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3633.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case at hand, the applicants never presented any medical evidence in support of their claims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3633.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3641.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Undisputedly, they were not prevented from seeking medical assistance in order to acquire such evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3641.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3646.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, the government would like to make the following submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3646.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3663.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, as evident from the medical examinations presented in enclosures two, three, and four, all three applicants were meticulously examined three times between March and December 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3663.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3667.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The examinations included their private parts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3667.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3682.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For applicants Y and Z, the conclusion was that their sexual organs were, I quote, without deviations, which means in normal condition for their age and with no traces of abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3682.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3689.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For applicant X, the only deviation established was the scar from the inguinal hernia surgery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3689.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3698.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These documents were at the free disposal of the adopters as they were appended to the adoption case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3698.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3711.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, it is a medically established fact that in more than 75% of the cases during the first sexual intercourse, the anatomical integrity of the hymen is irreversibly violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3711.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3716.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The trace is remaining visible until the woman gives natural birth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3716.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3731.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having in mind applicants Y and Z's young age at the time, a medical examination would prove with a high degree of certainty whether they had experienced sexual intercourses or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3731.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3742.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, concerning the allegations that such examinations would be too traumatizing for the applicants, the government present a statement by Dr. Alexander</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3742.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Minchev, head of the Department of Forensic Medicine to the University Hospital Pirogov in Sofia, Bulgaria, and a member of the European Committee for the Prevention of Torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3759.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The statement explains in detail how such examinations are conducted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3759.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3767.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We note that they are very brief, only visual ones, and do not include any invasive methods.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3767.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3777.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, they are performed in privacy by experienced medical practitioners and are generally far more sparing than a standard examination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3777.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3792.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the statement points out that a medical examination of the applicant X could have also established with a high degree of certainty the existence of traces of sexual abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3792.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3798.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such examination would not be invasive or otherwise traumatizing either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3798.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3814.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, regarding the allegations of the applicants that the authorities tried to conceal the applicant X's surgical operation of inguinal hernia, the government point out that this information was provided to the adopters before the initiation of the adoption procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3814.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3824.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We note that during his first three years of life, X did not reside in the orphanage and the surgery had been performed in that period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3824.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3831.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government said that inguinal hernia is the most common surgically treated condition in childhood.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3831.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3835.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reasons for this condition are purely physiological.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3835.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3842.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The inguinal canal does not close on time and have nothing to do with abuse of any kind.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3842.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3856.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the light of the above, the government considered that there are no sufficient, consistent or reliable indications that during their stay at the orphanage, the applicants were subjected to any sexual abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3856.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3860.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable judges of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3860.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3881.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in conclusion the government underlined that the Bulgarian authorities took all necessary and reasonable measures to ensure adequate protection of the applicants and the other children at the orphanage and to conduct full, thorough and timely investigation of the applicants' allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3881.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3898.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In view of all considerations above, as well as the ones stated in our previous submissions, the government reckoned that the complaints under this application are manifestly ill-founded and respectfully ask you to uphold the chamber judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3898.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3898.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3902.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3905.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, merci pour vos interventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3905.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3911.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'invite maintenant les juges de la Grande Chambre qui le souhaitent à poser leurs questions au parti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3911.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3911.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le juge Sabato.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Raffaele Sabato</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3915.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3916.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3916.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3920.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have one question for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3920.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3945.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government have made reference to the prosecutor's order and that they were all finally reviewed by the prosecutor's office at the Bulgarian Supreme Court of Cassation by an order which is dated 27th of January, 2017.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3945.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3955.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think this order in order to simplify, but the government already have referred to the reasoning which is contained in most of these orders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3955.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3973.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This order finds that the full investigation and underline this concept appear to have been carried out, but it did not reveal that the applicants have been subjected to any ill treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3973.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3997.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The prosecutor then examined the applicant's statements and found the applicant's initial statement to the psychologists and their replies when they were questioned by the Italian prosecutor before the youth court had been at variance with each other and contained contradictions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3997.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4009.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore the prosecutor expressed the hypothesis that the children had seen sexual acts on television or that they had seen other persons performing them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4009.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4028.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore the conclusion was that in view of their parents' disapproval of this behavior of the children and in order to avoid upsetting the parents, the children had told the story – this is a quotation – claiming to be victims of abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4028.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4034.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question concerns this relationship between these two concepts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4034.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4054.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Full investigation, which we find in this order, and possible contradictions in the children depositions concerning abuse, which I understand these contradictions might occur in children depositions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4054.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4056.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What were the standards?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4056.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4068.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the question in the country at the time of the facts for a full investigation into sexual abuse and sexual exploitation of children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4068.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4083.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you might also want to comment how were contradictions in the declarations of children assessed in the light of standard of evidence on child abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4083.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4083.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4087.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4089.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Bošnjak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Marko Bošnjak</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4091.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4095.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4095.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4120.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me first start with the question for the government, namely, in their accounts before the Italian authorities, the applicants mentioned specifically by name several other children from the orphanage that were involved in sexual abuse, either as victims or as perpetrators or both.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4120.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4132.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It transpires from the file, and it was repeated today by the government, that the Bulgarian authorities heard several children in the course of investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4132.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4147.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first question is whether those children specifically named by the applicants in their accounts were amongst those children heard by the Bulgarian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4147.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4156.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, my second question is directed both to the applicants and to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4156.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4178.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In their pleadings today, but also in other documents submitted to the court, the government alleges deficiencies in interviews conducted with children before Italian authorities and other Italian institutions for several reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4178.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4187.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I would first invite the applicants to comment on those alleged deficiencies, as alleged by the Bulgarian government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4187.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4193.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I have a question in this respect directed to the Bulgarian government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4196.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4208.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It appears from your pleadings and from the documents in the file that the Bulgarian authorities never requested any legal assistance from the Italian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4208.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4229.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, the Bulgarian authorities did not request another hearing or a hearing of the applicants or their psychological evaluation or medical examination, although certain deficiencies are asserted by the Bulgarian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4229.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4240.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How come never such a request was forwarded to the Italian authorities in light of such deficiencies asserted by the Bulgarian authorities?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4240.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4246.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my final question is also directed to the Bulgarian government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4246.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4252.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a follow-up of the facts and the question as highlighted by my colleague Judge Sabato.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4252.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4277.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In their final conclusion, the Bulgarian prosecution authorities provided certain explanation as to why, in their view, the applicants' allegations did not correspond to the reality and why they allegedly were not reliable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4277.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4311.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wonder whether that particular hypothesis, as highlighted in that prosecutorial decision, was ever put to any expert evaluation, in the sense that any expert in Bulgaria or elsewhere would evaluate those statements, their veracity, for the purpose of Bulgarian inquiry and come up to such a conclusion as then highlighted in that particular prosecutorial decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4311.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4311.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you so much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4314.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4315.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Motoc.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4318.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4319.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, Monsieur le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4320.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4328.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, mes questions sont au gouvernement et à la partie recurrente, sont les suivantes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4328.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4348.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, les deux, en commençant par les récurrents, ils ont invoqué certaines normes internationales, notamment la Convention sur le droit des enfants, certains commentaires qui sont issus par le Comité sur le droit des enfants, notamment le commentaire 4, relative à la santé des enfants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4348.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4358.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Aussi, la Convention qui est fondamentale pour nous, la protection des enfants contre l'exploitation et l'abus sexuel, dite la Convention de l'Ansarothé.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4359.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4379.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ma question est, étant tous ces documents internationaux que je ne vais pas citer, parce que vous les connaissez autant bien que moi, est-ce que vous pensez qu'il y a des normes minimales internationales concernant l'investigation effective des abus sexuels ou des plaintes par rapport aux abus sexuels?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4380.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4393.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ma deuxième question est adressée au gouvernement, et est une question qui suit d'une certaine manière la question qui a été posée par mon collègue, le juge Sabato, et par la suite par mon collègue, le juge Bošnjak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4394.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4395.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce que vous connaissez l'affaire?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4396.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4399.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous avez invoqué beaucoup des affaires de la Cour.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4399.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4408.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce que vous connaissez l'affaire Fernandes Pedroso contre le Portugal, qui est restée définitive en septembre 2018?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4408.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4420.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce que vous pouvez commenter certaines allégations du gouvernement bulgare par rapport à certains faits qui sont mis en évidence par cette affaire?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4420.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4420.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je vous remercie, Monsieur le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4423.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4424.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, Mr. le juge Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4431.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4432.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4432.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4439.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have three questions, one for the applicants and two for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4439.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4452.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the applicants, I would like to know if there are any recent medical or psychological evaluations of the children regarding their mental well-being.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4452.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4464.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do they still show or show now signs of trauma related to the alleged events that took place at the orphanage?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4464.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4471.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the government, and these questions can also be addressed by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4471.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4475.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question relates to the policy of deinstitutionalization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4475.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4490.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is this policy, the state's policy to deinstitutionalize, which resulted in the closing of the orphanage, an indicator of systemic child abuse in Bulgarian state institutions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4490.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4494.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question refers to the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4494.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4502.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is there any indication of bias towards allegations of sexual abuse of minors in Bulgaria?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4502.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4517.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I put this question against the background of SD versus Bulgaria, which noted systemic problems with effectiveness of investigations regarding violations of Article 2 and 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4517.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4539.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I quote the court, this court, "apart from repeated findings of failure to carry out necessary investigative measures in certain cases, the court noted that the competent authorities had not taken account of certain evidence and had not sought to sustain certain factual circumstances or the involvement of certain individuals in the criminal offense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4539.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4552.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then the court concludes, this non-exhaustive list of the various flaws found in a large number of cases reveals the existence of a systemic problem concerning the ineffectiveness of investigations in Bulgaria".</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4552.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4557.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this refers to Article 2 and 3 complaints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4557.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4582.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also take into account, as a background, the committee on the Rights of Children report of 2018, which states at the concluding observations that it is concerned, the committee is concerned, and I quote, with the sexual abuse among and against children living in institutional care homes in Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4582.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4592.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So is there a problem with the effectiveness, a systemic problem with the effectiveness of investigations regarding these type of crimes?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4592.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4594.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the question put to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4594.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4594.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4597.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4599.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Elósegui.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>María Elósegui</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4603.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4605.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4605.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4611.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have one question for the government and another for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4611.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4623.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Starting with the first one, I would like to know more about the research or investigation in the orphanage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4623.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4643.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concretely, you have said that these interviews were done by psychologists and social workers, now in the hearing, but I read also in the files that some of the research was done by the police directly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4643.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4662.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then I want to know if the police did the interview to the children and also if the people, the workers from the orphanage, were there present in this research or in this investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4662.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4665.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How was it done?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4665.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4668.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's all for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4668.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4716.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then going to the applicants, I would like to have more information about the way you have used to denounce these facts and why you go to the media first or to some journalist instead of to, I don't say to the Bulgarian authorities, but why don't go to the official domestic institutions in Italy, even if they have no jurisdiction and so on, but just to go to the prosecutor or also to civil domestic national Italian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4716.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4721.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why was that done in another way or what was the way?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4721.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4721.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4725.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4727.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Turković.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4729.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4731.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4731.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4737.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have extensively criticized the method that was used in Italy in questioning the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4737.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4749.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to know what kind of method were Bulgarian authorities using interviewing the children and why this method was better, if some method was used.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4749.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4762.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then what kind of follow up Bulgarian authorities are doing when children are adopted or when they get the information that some problems might exist?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4762.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4772.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More concretely, did you contact and follow up what was happening with the children coming from the same orphanage who were adopted approximately at the same time?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4772.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4779.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then the area that was not at all addressed is the issue that interests me, and these are preventive measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4779.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4792.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have heard a number of preventive measures that have been taken in terms of the possibility of adults to come to the orphanage and to have access to the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4792.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4808.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What kind of preventive measures Bulgarian authorities have in institutions like this one to prevent possible sexual abuse among or between children themselves?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4808.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4815.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And at what age sexual education of children in Bulgaria starts?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4815.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4819.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it is there at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4819.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4819.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4822.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4824.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4825.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4837.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La cour va maintenant se retirer pour 30 minutes, après quoi les partis pourront présenter de brèves observations en réponse aux plaidoiries adverses et répondre aux questions des juges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4837.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4837.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'audience est suspendue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4918.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4919.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4960.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4961.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4972.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4974.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La parole est à Maître Mauceri, vous avez la parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4976.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4978.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4978.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4992.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will shortly reply and answer, and I will ask the permit to let also to the expert to give some answer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4992.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5007.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>About what we listen from the government, I note and I see that Bulgaria continues in the path of mystification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5007.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5011.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nothing did exist, nothing happened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5011.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5017.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we listen that the orphanage now is closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5017.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5022.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maybe it's interesting to know why it was closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5022.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5026.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they keep pretending that it doesn't exist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5026.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5032.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But they admit that there were any investigations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5032.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5046.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the convention prescribes, were not collaboration between authority judicial Bulgarian and Italian judicial Bulgarian.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5046.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5049.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were not recorded hearings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5049.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5058.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were not also the measures that the convention specifies prescribes for this kind of investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5058.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5062.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I agreed and appreciated the questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5062.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5086.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And about the medical, legal examination, I want to remark again that the typical, the best scientific medical, legal examination is not the physic visit of a gynecologist, but is the psychologic report.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5086.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5096.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we produced the psychologic reports that in this case were acquired from Italian judicial authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5096.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5103.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we referred the way to verify them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5103.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5108.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they were made with all the criterias of the chance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5108.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5116.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I ask about them to let answer the experts near me, Mrs. Bacchengalante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5116.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5129.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I only have to answer now to the questions about the time of the denounce to Italian authority and to the press.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5129.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5151.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were, when as notice of this terrible case, were immediately to telephone Azzurro Company, who operate in Italy in accordance with judge Italian authority, and concorded with them to go to the procura of Tribunal of Milano.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5151.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5168.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then they asked the two agency of the state of Bulgaria to help them, to indicate some authority to care of this case in 16 November 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5168.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5173.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first denounce to TelefonAzzurro was in 5 October 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5173.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5183.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 22 November 2012, the applicants went to the Ministry of Justice of Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5183.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5192.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only then, and then they went also to the police, the Postal Police Italiana, Polizia Postale Italiana.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5192.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5202.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only then, listening that Fabrizio Gatti was working about this kind of problems, they met him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5202.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5204.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they spoke with him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5204.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5207.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only them, only with Fabrizio Gatti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5207.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5217.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then he wanted to investigate, but without saying which orphanage was implicated in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5217.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5223.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If you permit, I will give the words to the expert.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5223.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5234.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I hope that the court will recall Bulgaria's state and bring it back to the path of love and human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5234.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5234.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5241.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5247.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Acting as council, the council can take the floor on the basis of the rules, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5259.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5273.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it pleases the court, I should like to address the question of the assessment that was used, the criterion-based content analysis, and why this was chosen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5273.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5285.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is an internationally recognized, well-validated statement of veracity of a witness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5285.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5306.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has been initially construed and written together and experimented because they had to prove the validity of this instrument, and following this, which was used in child abuse cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5306.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5311.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this is unlike many instruments that we use in psychology.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5311.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5321.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It actually originated as an instrument to ascertain the veracity of a child victim of sexual abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5324.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5330.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is not an inventory, nor is it a checklist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5330.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5344.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a series of interviews, semi-structured interviews, which are videotaped and subsequently evaluated according to particular criteria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5344.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5346.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have here the criteria before me.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5346.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5347.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I could read them to you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5347.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5350.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are 18 criteria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5350.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5376.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following the 18 criteria, the assessor and subsequent assessors examine the reporting style, the display insecurities, the reasons for lack of memory in certain situations, cliches and repetitions in the narrative of the individual reporting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5376.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5381.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that I can also cite several studies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5381.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5393.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My colleague, Rij, who was mentioned earlier from 2005, has subsequently written several papers on this subject.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5393.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5404.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I also have a paper here from 2015 on the inter-rater reliability of this particular analysis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5404.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5429.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was chosen by Professor Kimnitz as a validated tool to assess the veracity of the children's statements following a long series of questions which had been posed by the psychologists and medical examiners as well as law authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5429.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5434.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is what their children saying true?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5434.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5452.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that a very young child may not be plausible, and they may have been incapable of communicating what has happened as a 12 or 13-year-old can attest to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5452.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5464.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that my colleague is going to discuss further ways of assessing the veracity and the validity of the child's narrative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5464.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5467.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I'm hoping that this perhaps answers some questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5467.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5486.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I'm more than willing to submit this list of validated assessments and examinations and printed papers published in recognized medical legal journals of the use of this instrument, CBCA.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5486.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5486.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5489.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5490.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5494.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5512.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, I would like to thank the judges for their questions, because it has been rare in my long career, I've been working 40 years in this field, to have such pertinent questions by people who are not psychiatrists or psychologists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5512.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5514.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have three points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5514.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5516.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm trying to put them together because of the limits of time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5516.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5522.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But if the answers are too brief, please ask me, and I will elaborate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5522.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5524.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to cover three points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5524.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5527.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One is the hallucinations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5527.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5543.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I beg the court to realize that we are not so incompetent that after so many years of work, we cannot tell the difference between a hallucination and a real event that is, however, a traumatizing event.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5543.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5556.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so it is remembered in a very disjointed, non-chronical way so that the events are not told in the timeline in which they happened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5556.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5559.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The events are never told the same way twice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5559.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5566.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The events are told with varying degrees of emotion, at times with no emotion at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5566.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5574.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are a series of indications of when it is a hallucination and when it is a real event.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5574.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5580.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And one has to be incredibly incompetent to mistake the two.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5580.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5595.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second thing that was brought up was that the father who was present during just the first interview I had with ____, I had been working with these children for seven years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5595.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5597.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the beginning, it was very intense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5597.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5599.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I saw them at least once a week.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5599.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5602.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And over the years, it has slowed down.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5602.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5604.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was then every other week, then every three weeks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5604.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5609.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now it's every four weeks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5609.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5616.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They, in the very first interview, it is true, ____ spoke Italian poorly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5616.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5635.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that a couple of times, the father intervened to tell me that he had learned that the Bulgarian word that ____ was using means such and such because he'd been very close to the children since they had arrived, as had the mother, their wonderful parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5635.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5647.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At any rate, when I saw this difficulty, I went and got the anatomical dolls I have for people who are foreigners or who are very young and have difficulty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5649.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5653.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I remind you that you are here acting as an advisor to the delegation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5653.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5655.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You are not acting as an expert.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5655.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5658.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You are acting as an advisor to the delegation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5658.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5658.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5661.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5665.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Speak about what I see, the trauma that I see in the children today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5665.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5666.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is that pertinent?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5669.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5670.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because somebody asked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5670.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5672.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More of an expertise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5672.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5676.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not acting as a true advisor of the applicants here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5676.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5679.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not your role to do that here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5679.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5681.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Okay, what can I say?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5683.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5687.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is, you have submitted those evidence in your written pleading, so it's okay.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5687.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5693.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the council wants to expand on this in replying the question of the judges, he can.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5693.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5697.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But you are not acting as an expert here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5697.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5697.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5700.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5704.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I can speak about how traumatized the children are still today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5706.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5707.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Okay.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5709.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5710.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5710.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5713.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>has...</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5715.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5717.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please don't use the names.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5717.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5719.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, I was just reminded of that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5719.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5723.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm sorry, I made a mistake.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5723.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5734.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The oldest boy has incredible difficulty with relations with other people outside the family.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5734.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5742.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fortunately, the parents have a large group of extended family, and so he has relationships with them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5742.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5747.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He has trust of very few people in the world.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5747.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5750.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He sees things in a very rigid way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5750.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5755.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He thinks that everybody should always be punished for everything.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5755.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5762.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He has no flexibility, and therefore he has no friends.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5762.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5771.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I said, the family has been compensating for the lack of social relationships that he has with other people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5771.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5775.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And having a large family, this is a great help.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5775.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5785.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But he has never made friends at school, has never gone out with boys, and is always extremely suspicious.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5785.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5798.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second child, who is a girl, has at times totally repressed any memory of anything to do with Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5798.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5800.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She doesn't remember the language.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5800.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5801.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She doesn't remember the places.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5801.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5804.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She doesn't remember the institute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5804.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5816.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then at other times, she has flashes, which is typical of post-traumatic stress syndrome, of events that took place and gets very disturbed, and then they're repressed within a few days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5816.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5822.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is also a typical reaction of long-term chronic sexual abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5822.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5825.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I saw the children a few weeks after they arrived.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5825.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5837.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no time for these symptoms to have been developed in that short time period, because they're typical of chronic long-term abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5837.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5847.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The youngest one, another girl, has phobic reactions to a series of stimuli.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5847.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5852.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is also typical of post-traumatic stress symptoms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5852.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5864.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She is afraid when her mother leaves the house to go do something, and has put severe restrictions on the movement of the mother, who tries to reassure her.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5867.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5873.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She's never made any friends, and she tries to hide her face.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5873.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5877.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She combs her hair so that you can't see her eyes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5877.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5882.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She has difficulty responding verbally to the teachers at school.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5882.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5886.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the teachers have offered to let her write her answers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5886.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5894.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And even here, she has difficulty, although she's an extremely bright, intelligent girl.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5894.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5896.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Seven years have gone by.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5896.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5902.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I've worked very hard, and I see some progress.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5902.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5910.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But then, if there is a stimulus that reminds them of what they've been through, they regress, and then you have to start all over again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5910.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5914.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the children have been severely damaged and severely traumatized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5914.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5914.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5918.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5919.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5919.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5920.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mrs. Nikolova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5923.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5924.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5924.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5930.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will respond some of the questions and my colleague will address the others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5930.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5951.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the criminal procedure code, pretrial proceedings are instituted only if sufficient data are available and where reasonable assumption can be made that a crime, criminal offense, had been committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5951.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5956.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, those requirements were not fulfilled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5957.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5971.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The authorities collected all relevant data and they checked the orphanage, interviewed the children, and the staff who could have had a direct knowledge of the impugned facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5976.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5991.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regard to the contradictions in the testimonies in the hearing before the Italian prosecutor, this was the only verbatim record that were at the disposal of the Bulgarian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5991.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6000.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And when evaluating them, the prosecutor was aware that they should be evaluated very carefully.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6000.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6016.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the data contained did not correspond to the facts and circumstances already established and did not shed new light on the impugned facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6016.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6037.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As concerned the children questioned, only one children was required to submit written statements because at the time when the investigation was held, the other children did not reside already at the orphanage, as the children mentioned in their testimonies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6037.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6056.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As concerns the third questions, none of the investigative steps taken by the authorities revealed any data that would corroborate the applicant's allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6056.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6070.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The authorities' choice not to request legal assistance, again, was not arbitrary or unreasonable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6070.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6085.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As concerns the preventive measures, the adverse party have not really put whatever evidence as to what should have been in place in terms of safeguards preventing any risk of ill-treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6085.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6100.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the Bulgarian authorities had undertaken very measures in terms of complaint box, telephone helpline, in order to prevent such an abuse to take place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6100.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6100.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6103.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6107.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup. Nous en arrivons au terme de l'audience, je vous remercie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6107.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6115.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You want to continue, please go ahead.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6117.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6128.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regard to the fourth question, the government at present is not able to comment the Fernando Perez versus Portugal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6128.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6134.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, we could make additional written comments if this is necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6134.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6159.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning the question about the process of deinstitutionalization in Bulgaria, the government point out that this process is connected with the overall transition of the Bulgarian state from a socialist system to democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6159.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6168.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a very big process and has nothing to do with the systematic abuses of these institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6168.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6173.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that there were some cases of this kind.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6175.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6178.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some of them even reached the present court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6178.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6191.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the process of deinstitutionalization started in the beginning of this century and it approaches its end already.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6191.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6208.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By 2015, all institutions for children with disabilities were already closed and the children were moved to residential homes and to foster families.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6208.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6221.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regard to the children deprived of parental care, currently there are less than 50 such institutions in Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6221.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6226.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We could provide the particular statistics about this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6226.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6247.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning the next question about SZ versus Bulgaria, the government point out that first SZ is a very different case from the current one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6247.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6270.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was approved rape there by medical documents and the violation found concerned the lack of reasonable and adequate action taken by the Bulgarian investigative authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6270.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6282.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, this judgment of the court is currently being executed and a lot of legislative and other measures have already been taken.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6282.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6292.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The criminal procedure code that acted while the SZ facts occurred, it doesn't act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6298.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6304.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is a new criminal procedure code and the rules are different.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6304.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6321.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next question concerning the police interviews with the children, only one child was interviewed by the police and it was in the presence of a psychologist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6321.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6343.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next question about the methods that are used by Bulgarian authorities for interrogations, the government point out that interrogations in Bulgaria are conducted in the form of semi-structured interviews.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6343.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6353.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Usually the witness is left to give his own account with his own words and he's not interrupted by the prosecutor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6353.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6374.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only questions that are put to the witness are not suggestive or coercive and this can be seen from all records of interrogations that are produced in our legal system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6374.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6402.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning the next question about whether we follow up the adoption procedures when they are in a foreign country, yes, the central organ which is the Ministry of Justice follows up the adoption process for two years after the children are adopted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6402.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6411.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the central organs of the different countries maintain relations between them and exchange information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6414.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6429.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next question about the preventive measures that were taken with regard to the children, we refer to our previous submissions, we also refer to our pleading from today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6429.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6435.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The children were kept in different dormitories by gender.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6435.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6440.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were not allowed to go to the next dormitory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6440.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6445.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had to pass through the tutor on duty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6445.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6450.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there were a number of measures in this regard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6451.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6489.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maybe we should point out once more that at the time the applicants were at the orphanage, they had at their disposal a telephone helpline, a complaint box, and also they had contacts with the outside world not only by going to school, but also they used social services such as speech tutor, psychologist, which can be seen from the documents in enclosures two, three, and four.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6489.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6504.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning the question about when does sexual education start in Bulgaria, it starts in pre-school preparatory classes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6504.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6536.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The notion about sexual abuse and forbidden touches and themes of this kind should be, just a moment, should be learned by the children by the end of their basic education, which is the fourth grade, which is 11 years old.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6536.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6536.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6541.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6542.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6542.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6545.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, nous arrivons effectivement au terme de l'audience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6546.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6552.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je remercie les comparants qui ont assisté à la Cour par leurs interventions et leurs réponses à ces questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6553.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6555.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour va maintenant délibérer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6556.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6558.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'arrêt sera rendu ultérieurement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6559.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6562.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les partis seront informés de la date du prononcé de l'arrêt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6562.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6562.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'audience est levée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
