<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>2570311_21012015</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>48.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>51.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>51.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>58.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Dvorski against Croatia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>58.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>68.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged on the 16th of April, 2011, with the court under Article 34 of the Convention by a Croatian national, Mr. Ivan Dvorski.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>68.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>75.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the first section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>75.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>80.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was communicated to the government on the 28th of June, 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>80.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>97.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 28th of November, 2013, a chamber of that section declared the application partly admissible and delivered a judgment in which it held that Article 6, paragraph 1, and 3C of the Convention had not been violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>97.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>113.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 26th of February, 2014, the applicant requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention, and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on the 14th of April, 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>113.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>117.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Mrs. Štefica</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>117.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>122.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Stažnik, assisted by Mrs. Nikolina Katić, Mrs. Morana</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>122.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>127.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Briški, Mrs. Sonja Raguž, and Mr. Zlatko Budimir, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>127.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>131.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mrs. Snježana Maroševac-Čapko</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>131.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>132.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>132.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>136.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>136.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>142.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome a group of judges from Croatia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>142.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>149.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>152.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>154.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Maroševac-Čapko for the applicant</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>154.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>158.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>will speak first, and then Mrs. Stažnik for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>158.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>171.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting from Croatian has been authorized for the benefit of the applicant's representative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>171.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>181.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although that interpreting is arranged by the court, no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>181.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>182.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mrs. Maroševac-Čapko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>187.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>189.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will talk on the Croatian.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>191.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>232.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poštovani predsjedniče i članovi viječa, kolegice i kolege, s obzirom da uputama stoji da se ne bi trebala ponavljati vezano za sam predmet o onome što je već bila iznošeno tijekom postupka, pokušavat ću se ograničiti na naše očitovanje na podnesak Republike Hrvatske od dana 29. ruina 2014. godine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>232.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>263.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naime, navedeni podnesak je prepun neistina i pokušaja tumačenja problematike na nelogičan način u nastojanju da se pod bilo koju cijenu nastoji opravdati postupak države u trenutku privođenja i uhičenja mog branjenika, odnosno podnositelja zahtjeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>263.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>279.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pa tako država polemizira o tome kada su i kako roditelji uopće mogli angažirati kolegu branitelja, odnosno odvjetnika G.M.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>279.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>291.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>s obzirom da je majka podnositelja zahtjeva bila u to vrijeme u Italiji, dok je otac bio u Hrvatskoj, odnosno u Rijeci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>291.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>303.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Činjenica je da je odvjetnik G.M. opunomoćen od strane majke putem telefona.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>303.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>315.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Išto me je zatim dao i pisan upunomoć otac podnositelja zahtjeva, kako je danas pokoljnik D.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>315.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>323.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Međutim, u cijeloj toj priči bitno je istaći da kolega, odnosno odvjetnik G.M.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>323.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>338.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>nije došao u treću policijsku postaju iz vlastitog Hira, odnosno da nije imao pametnijeg posla pa se malo prošetao do treće policijske postaje.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>338.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>349.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I je doista bio angažiran od roditelja podnositelja zahtjeva i na sve načine je pokušao pristupiti svom branjeniku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>349.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>361.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Navodi države da odvjetnik G.M. nije mogao pristupiti u ranijim jutarnjim satima,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>361.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>365.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>odnosno u razdobju od 10.45 do 10.50,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>365.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>374.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>iz razloga što da je otac podnositelja zahtjeva bio obaviješten tek u 14.00,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>374.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>380.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>nije točno, odnosno više nego absurdno, iz sljedećih razloga.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>380.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>395.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naime, podnositelj zahtjeva je priveden u policijsku postaju, treću policijsku postaju Rijeka, u 13.00, 13.00. 2007. godine,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>395.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>401.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>uhićen je 14.00. 2007. godine u 9.50 minuta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>401.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>414.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dakle, podnositelj zahtjeva je bio u prostorijama policije gotovo 24 sata prije nego što je uhićen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>414.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>429.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tako da je otac podnositelja zahtjeva znao gdje se njegov sin nalazi i znao je, kad već nije sljedeće jutro došao kući, da će angažirati odvjetnika, pa je to isti i napravio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>429.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>443.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nadalje, netočni su i navodi države, da bi podnositelj zahtjeva tvrdio da su mu roditelji angažirali odvjetnika DM još 13.00. 2007. godine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>443.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>448.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naime, mi cijelo vrijeme tvrdimo da je to bilo 14.00. 2007.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>448.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>460.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>i da je tad on bio angažiran i nastojao pristupiti svom branjeniku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>460.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>472.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Također istićemo da podnositelj zahtjeva nije imao nikakvo kontakta sa vanjskim svijetom, dakle, od 13.00. 2007. u 13 sati</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>472.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>478.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>do 14.00. 2007. u 19 sati 45 minuta,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>478.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>491.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>kada mu je bio pristupio odvjetnik MR, a koji je pristupio u prostorije treće policijske postaje na poziv policije.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>491.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>516.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moj branjenik, odnosno podnositelj zahtjeva, nije bio upoznat da je u prostorije treće policijske postaje u rijeci pristupio odvjetnik DM i nije bio upoznat da bi ga on zastupao u davanju, eventualnom davanju ili obrani šutnjom pred djelatnicima policije.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>522.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>553.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naime, u podnesku o kojem se očitujemo, dokazuje se da država tvrdi da policija nije bila niti dužna upoznati podnositelja zahtjeva da je u prostoriji treće policijske postaje pristupio odvjetnik DM, budući da podnositelj zahtjeva nije niti iskazao želju niti volju da mu se angažira branitelj.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>553.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>570.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Međutim, takav navod je potpuno u suprotnosti s odredbom članka 6.3.C EUKZLTP,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>570.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>589.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>budući je policija bila dužna upozoriti i upoznati podnositelja zahtjeva da mu je pristupio branitelj u policijsku postaju, da je podnositelj zahtjeva imao pravo se očitovati da li želi da ga on zastupa ili ne želi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>592.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>606.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nadalje, država navodi na strani podnositelja zahtjeva da se radi o osobi koja ima loš karakter, odnosno da ima kriminalnu prošlost, dok je bio maloljetnik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>606.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>616.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Međutim, da je to i tako, to je činjenica koja ne bi smijela utjecati na njegova ljudska prava.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>616.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>631.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naime, EUKZLTP je upravo istvorena da se primijeni upravo prema svima, a ne samo prema nekim odabranim ljudima.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>631.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>644.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I svakoga treba tretirati na način da se poštuje njegovo ljudsko dostojanstvo kao i njegova osoba u cijelosti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>644.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>648.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kako je to propisano navedenom konvencijom?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>648.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>662.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nadalje, država polemizira i o tome da bi podnositelj zahtjeva bio osoba koja je u svakom svom kaznenom postupku angažirala drugog odvjetnika.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>662.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>682.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Međutim, uz navedeni podnesak, država dostavlja presudu Općinskog suda u Rijeci pod poslovnim brojem KSM 151 kroz 06 od 13. veljače 2007. godine, iz koje je razvjedno da ga je</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>682.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>688.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>u svakom postupku zastupao odvjetnik DM.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>688.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>696.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Znači da njihov navod i dokaz kojeg su priložili je kontradiktoran.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>696.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>713.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>S obzirom na tu činjenicu, logično je i životno da su roditelji upravo angažirali istog odvjetnika DM da ga zastupa pred policijom na trećoj policijskoj postaji.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>713.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>736.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Budući su isti, već imali percepciju o radu istog i bili su zadovoljni kakvom kvalitetom njegovog zastupanja, tako i sa znanjem da će isti obaviti savjesno i pošteno svoj rad, jer su već imali izgrađeno povjerenje prema njemu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>736.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>761.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unatoč s tim navodima o tome da li je odvjetnik DM pristupio u prostorije policijske postaje putem punomoći majke ili oca, su u konačnici i nebitne s obzirom da je konačnici njega trebao opunomočiti sam podnositelj zahtjeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>761.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>781.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To je mogao učiniti samo u trenutku da je odvjetnik DM pristupio u treću policijsku postaju i da je bio doveden u prostoriju sa svojim branjenikom. Pa se onda isti tad mogao izjasniti</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>781.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>787.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>da li želi da ga zastupa ili ne želi da ga zastupa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>787.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>818.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sadalje također imamo i nelogičnost da se tvrdi da podnositelj zahtjeva nije želio angažirati branitelja, međutim iz prijepornog zapisnika o ispitivanju podnositelja zahtjeva u svojstvu osumičenika proizlazi da ga je branitelj ipak zastupao, ali ne onaj kojeg je on želio, odnosno kojeg su ovi roditelji angažirali, nego drugi. Pa se postavlja pitanje</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>818.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>849.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>zašto policija nije obavijestila odvjetnika DM da je sada podnositelj zahtjeva želio da mu se postavi branitelja s obzirom da su isti bili upoznati da je odvjetnik DM u više navrata nastojao doprijeti do svog branjenika, odnosno podnositelja zahtjeva. Tim prije što iz daljnjeg kaznenog</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>849.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>874.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>postupka koji se vodio pred županijskim sudom u Rijeci proizlazi da je podnositelj zahtjeva angažirao odvjetnika DM da ga zastupa u daljem postupku i u tom smislu mu je potpisao i punom oču. A to je učinio čim je bio pušten iz prostorija</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>874.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>879.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>treće policijske postaje. Pa bi to bio i odgovor na pitanje</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>879.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>896.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>kojeg je postavio sud, odnosno da podnositelj zahtjeva nije imao slobodnu volju angažirati branitelja kojeg je doista želio da ga zastupa dana 14. ožnjika 2007. godine,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>896.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>907.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>već je isti bio prisiljen pristati da ga zastupa odvjetnik MR kojeg je pozvala policija. Što se tiče navoda države,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>907.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>926.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>da bi u vrijeme kada je podnositelj zahtjeva bio ispitivan pred organima policije na trećoj policijskoj postaji u Rijeci, postojale liste odvjetnika, pa da je on na temelju tih lista i mogao izabrati nekoga od njih, to nije točno.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>926.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>932.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naime, država nije dostavila popis odvjetnika iz 2007. godine</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>932.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>943.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>pod izlikom da se navedeni popis ne čuva, odnosno da policija ne čuva takve popise u svojim arhivama. Naime, da bi čuvali</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>943.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>947.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>tako nešto, oni prvo to moraju imati. A kako nisu to nijimali,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>947.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>953.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>tako to nisu mogli niti čuvati. To govorim također i iz vlastite prakse,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>953.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>962.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>jer i ja sam u svom radu bila suočena sa sličnim problemima ne u jednom, nego u bezbroj slučajeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>962.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>980.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dakle, odgovor na sljedeće pitanje koje je sud postavio, podnositelj zahtjeva nije dobio prigodu odabrati branitelja s popisa branitelja, jer mu navedeni popis nikada nije bio predođen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>980.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>996.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>S obzirom da smo u više navrata istekli činjenicu da je odvjetnik koji je zastupao podnositelja zahtjeva pred redarstvenim vlastima, odnosno u policijskoj postaji 3. PP, bio mrl i dostavili smo</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>996.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1015.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>i dokaze u tom smislu, a i država je u konačnici u tom svom zadnjim podnesku na koje se mi sad očitujemo, dostavila, odnosno priznala da doista je navedeni odvjetnik bio načelnik policijske uprave PDŽ Rijeka.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1015.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1038.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Međutim, to što je on bio po funkciji ne bi bilo toliko bitno da isti nije postupao isključivo u namjeri da se dobije iskaz od podnositelja zahtjeva, a kako bi se mogao zaključiti predmet, odnosno dovršiti predistražna radnja.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1038.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1073.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naime, ono što upučuje na to da kolega, odnosno odvjetnik MR, nije postupao u skladu sa kodeksom odvjetničke etike niti sa zakonom o odvjetništu, je činjenica da je pristupio u treću policijsku postaju ne na poziv podnositelja zahtjeva, nego na poziv policije. Da je se isti sa podnositeljem</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1073.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1096.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>zahtjeva unatoč težini inkriminacija zadržao u vrlo kratkom razgovoru, koji po slobodnoj proceni je iznosio oko 20 minuta. Da nije vodio računa o samom vremenu</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1096.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1131.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ispitivanju podnositelja zahtjeva, jer je podnositelj zahtjeva bio ispitivan, odnosno nastavljeno njegovo ispitivanje i nakon proteka zakonskih rokova u kojima se je osumnjičenik smio ispitivati, naime, iz zapisnika o saslušanju osumnjičenika proizlazi da je ispitivanje završeno u 23 sata, međutim, prema zakonu o policiji osumnjičenici su se mogli ispitivati najkasnije do 22 sata, te sljedeće jutro od 6 sati pa do 22.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1131.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1147.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Zatim, odjetnik NRL nije vodio računa o tome u kakvom stanju je podnositelj zahtjeva bio. Naime, podnositelj zahtjeva</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1147.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1160.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>se u više navrata požalio na postupanje policije, međutim, on o tome nije reagirao, niti je takvu primjedbu podnositelja zahtjeva tražio da se unese u zapisnik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1160.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1203.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naime, da podnositelj zahtjeva nije bio u dobrom stanju u trenutku davanja iskaza pred policijom na trećoj policijskoj postaji proizlazi iz kasnijeg postupka, kada je isti bio vještačen i kada je utvrđivano da li je bio sposoban, odnosno kada je utvrđivana njegova psihička sposobnost, prilikom počinjenja, navodnog počinjenja kaznenog dijela, gdje su psihijatri, kao vještaci, utvrdili da je isti bio bitno smanjeno u broji.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1203.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1232.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naime, prema samom iskazu koji prileži policiji proizlazi da je podnositelj zahtjeva, tempore criminis, bio pod snažnim utjecajem alkohola i droga i što mu je u konačnici valorizirano u samom medicinskom nalazu vještaka prilikom prosuđivanja njegove ubrojivosti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1232.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1246.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dobro bih htjeli ukazati da odvjetnik MR nikada za svoje zastupanje pred trećom policijskom postajom nije ispostavio račun podnositelju zahtjeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1246.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1252.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nikada nije tražio od njega da mu plati zastupanje.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1252.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1353.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Svega toga proizlazi kako odvjetnik MR nije brino za dobrobit svog branjenika, odnosno podnositelja zahtjeva, jer da je tome bilo tako, tada podnositelj zahtjeva ne bi tražio novog odvjetnika, a sve to postupanje policije prema odvjetniku MR, odnosno prema odvjetniku GM, je bilo prijavljeno na gotova sve državne institucije, o čemu smo mi također dostavili dokaze u spis, u pravo suđu, vrhovnom sudu Republike Hrvatske, državnoj odvjetničkoj komori, državnom odvjetništvu Republike Hrvatske, gdje se tražilo izuzeće državnog odvjetnika Primorsko-Goranske županije, u to vrijeme Dorisa Hrasta, gdje se tražilo izuzeće svih ostalih državnih odvjetnika, iz razloga što je državni odvjetnik Primorsko-Goranske županije, Doris Hrast, odnosno županijski državni odvjetnik, dopustio takvo postupanje policije prema odvjetniku GM na način da je isti bio nazočan prilikom ispitivanja osumnjičenika, odnosno podnositelja zahtjeva, a da ništa nije poduzeo kako bi omogućio pristup odvjetnika GM svom branjeniku, niti zaštitio njegovi dignitet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1353.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1368.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Povodom navedenog događaja je pred Općinskim sudom u Rijeci, odnosno prema spisima Prvožupanijskom sudu u Rijeci, bila odnesena i tužba radi otklanjanja nezakonite radnje.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1368.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1386.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dakle, zaključak svega da usluge odvjetnika MR, koji je zastupao podnositelja zahtjeva tijekom policijskog ispitivanja, nije ispunjavala zahtjeve dobre obrane.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1386.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1400.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nadalje, s obzirom da smo već naveli da je podnositelj zahtjeva bio priveden u prostorije treće policijske posta je Rijeka 13. ožuka 2007. godine u 13 sati,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1400.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1405.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a Uhićen tek 14. ožuka 2007. godine u 9.50 sati,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1405.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1411.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>dok je odvjetnik MR pristupio u policijske prostorije tek u 19.45 sati,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1411.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1427.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>i da se ta činjenica, nažalost, nastojala prikriti tijekom kaznanog postupka s obzirom da je spis u tom dijelu oštećen, odnosno ti dokumenti nisu više sastavni dio spisa, jednostavno ih nema.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1427.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1431.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Da li su slučajno ili namjerno izvedeni spisa, ja ne mogu tvrditi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1431.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1447.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To je, znači, govorimo o spisu Županijskog suda u Rijeci, postavni broj K71 kroz 07, o čemu smo mi više puta isticali, ne samo u ovom postupku, nego i u postupku pred Vrhovnim sudom Republike Hrvatske.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1447.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1471.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dakle, to sve upućuje da je pristup podnositelju zahtjeva bio potpuno onemogućen do dolazka odvjetnika MR, a što opet upućuje da je tu bilo prvenstveno namjera da se podnositelj zahtjeva prisili da da svoj iskaz, prisili da da svoje priznanje.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1471.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1484.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jer ja moram napomenuti da podnositelj zahtjeva u tih 29 sati ili koliko već nije imao humanne uvjete prilikom zadržavanja.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1484.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1511.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naime, istom je bila uskraćena hrana, uskraćena voda, isti je bio oddjeljen od sanitarnog čvora, zaključanim vratima, isti je bio u mraku čitavo vrijeme, jer tvrdnje države da u toj prostori postoje prozori i da se prozori kad se otvore ima svjetla, a ima i umjetno svjetlo, naime moram istaći da to nije tako.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1511.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1523.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naime, prozori postoje, većudin prozori imaju umjesto stakla drvo na sebi i potpuno su neprozirni. Prozori se ne otvaraju s obzirom da rešetke na prozorima</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1523.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1535.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>su razvaljene i kada bi se prozor otvorio, onda bi osumnjičenik koji se zadržava u tim prostorijama mogao lako pobjeći jer to ne bi bilo prvi put.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1535.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1577.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Što se tiče umjetnog svjetla, to svjetlo nije bilo uključeno, nego je podnositi zahtjeva bio prepušten, izolaciji, zatvoren od svih, njemu se nije pristupalo, a upravo iz razloga što i iz medicinske dokumentacije proizlazi, da podnositi zahtjeva osoba labilnog psihičkog stanja pod utjecajem alkohola i droge, da je isti u mraku, bez ikakvog kontakta bio izgubljen, izoliran i da kao takav je bio daleko podobniji davati nekakvo priznanje nego da se prema njemu postupalo na način kako bi se inače trebalo postupati prema osumnjičenicima.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1581.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1599.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dakle, zaključak, odnosno odgovor na sljedeće pitanje Suda, podnositelju zahtjeva nije poštivano njegovo pravo na slobodu od samo obtuživanja tijekom policijskog ispitivanja. Istin, nije bio upoznan s time da ako bi dao neko priznanje,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1599.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1618.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>da bi se to isto priznanje upotrijebilo protiv njega, a s time da nije upoznao niti njegov branitelj tada angažiran, a niti bilo tko od osoba koja su sudjelovali u njegovom ispitivanju.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1618.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1667.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Što se tiče navoda države, da samim time što bi netko dao svoje priznanje na policiji uz nazočnost odvjetnika, da bi to bilo potkrijepljeno i nekakvim drugim dokazima, pa da bi se onda uvažilo takvo priznanje, sudska praksa u Republici Hrvatskoj u to vrijeme, koja se na sreću sada izmijenila donošenjem novog zakona o kazenom postupku, je bila takva da bi takvo priznanje bilo apsolutni temelj za njegovu osudu, odnosno vrlo često je u postupcima jedini dokaz protiv okrljenika bio upravo njegovo vlastito priznanje, a drugi dokazi se nisu ni provodili.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1667.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1695.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>U tom smislu smo mi dostavili i sudsku praksu iz koje se je razvidno da bi priznanje osumnjičenika prilikom ispitivanja na policiji uz nazočnog odjetnika bilo neuborivo i osnov za njegovo samoobtuženje.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1695.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1717.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pa prema tome i odgovor na posljednje pitanje suda, prava podnositelja zahtjeva na obranu tijekom suđenja i zanadno su prejoducirana njegovom izjavom danom na policiji. Ovime bih ja u kratko završila sa svojim izlaganjem</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1717.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1756.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>te bi se pozvala na sve dokaze da se napravi uvid u sve dokaze koje smo priložili u ovaj spis i samo bi još ukazala na sudsku praksu ovog suda u presudi Josipa Madžera protiv Republike Hrvatske gdje smo imali sličnu situaciju prilikom njegovog ispitivanja u policijskoj postaji ali 2004. godine</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1756.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1806.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>mi predložili, odnosno predlažemo sudu da zahtjev pod brojem 25703 kroz 11 proglasi dopuštenim prema članku 35 stavka 1 EUKZLTP i dodatnih protokola te da donese presudu kojem se proglašava da su izvršene povrede članka 3 i članka 6 stavka 3 točaka C i D EUKZLTP i dodatnih protokola iz razloga navedenih kako u zahtjevu tako i cijelom tijekom ovog postupka.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1806.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1813.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mi smo također u slučaju da bi sud uvažio ovaj zahtjev priložili i naš troškovnik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1813.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1816.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ja ga naravno ovdje neću sada iščitavati s obzirom da je podnesen u pisanom obliku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1816.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1816.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hvala vam lijepa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1828.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1833.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mrs. Maroševac-Čapko. I call Mrs. Stažnik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1836.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1838.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1838.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1841.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the members of the Grand Chamber of the Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1841.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1845.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it is an honor for me to represent the government at today's hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1845.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1850.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will outline the relevant facts and summarize the government's main legal submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1850.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1857.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My colleagues and I will deal with questions asked by the court and reply to the applicants' submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1857.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1867.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the court already established, the right to a fair trial is a basic principle of the rule of law in democratic societies, securing the right to a proper administration of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1867.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1873.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The right to legal assistance and rights of defense are specific rights to the right of a fair trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1873.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1878.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They must be taken into account in evaluation of the criminal proceedings as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1878.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1899.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, the court set up the standard that compliance with these requirements of a fair trial must be examined in each case having regard to the development of the proceedings as a whole and not on the basis of an isolated consideration of one particular aspect or incident therein.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1899.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1910.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the court concluded in its chamber judgment of 28th November, 2013, the criminal proceedings in this case complied with the requirements set forth in the Article 6 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1910.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1921.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government fully endorses the chamber's findings and deems that overall assessment of the fairness of the criminal proceedings against the applicant should not be questioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1921.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1929.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The central issue of this case is not whether the applicant had a lawyer during the police questioning, because he had one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1929.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1934.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not the issue whether the applicant received effective legal advice, because he did.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1934.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1947.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only question raised by the applicant before the grand chamber is what would be the impact of his access to a particular lawyer during police custody on the ensuing proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1947.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1960.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it enough to put in doubt the fairness of the proceedings as a whole and to declare that the existence of all provided guarantees was not sufficient to protect the applicant's rights?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1960.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1974.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges of grand chamber, the purpose of the procedural guarantees is not to secure the applicant's acquittal, but to ensure that all of the applicant's defense rights are respected, regardless of the outcome of the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1974.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2003.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the government will stress all the facts which demonstrate that the applicant had a good defense during police questioning, that he had a real and fully informed opportunity to choose a lawyer who represented him, why the applicant's rights against self-incrimination wasn't violated, and why his statement given to the police wasn't of such quality to irretrievably hinder his defense rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2003.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2020.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The purpose of legal assistance at the initial stages of criminal proceedings is to provide the suspect with technical skills to exercise his right in the proceedings, since the suspect is usually a person not fully aware of his rights and lacks skills in exercising them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2020.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2026.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Legal assistance is a guarantee that the principle of equality of arms will be respected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2026.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2031.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The role of a counsel is, therefore, to explain to suspect his rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2031.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2037.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His assistance serves as a procedural guarantee of the privilege against self-incrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2037.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2048.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, a counsel performs supervision of the activities of the authorities, and his presence serves as a guarantee against the ill treatment of the suspect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2048.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2062.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If we apply these requirements to the present case, we can conclude that the applicant's counsel, who was present during the police questioning, entirely satisfied all requirements of good legal assistance and good defense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2062.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2077.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Undisputed facts of this case clearly show that upon his arrest, the applicant was informed of his right to hire a lawyer, the right not to incriminate himself, and the right to remain silent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2077.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2081.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He used all these rights at various points during proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2081.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2092.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the document provided, it is evident that the applicant at first refused to hire a lawyer and chose to remain silent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2092.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2095.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This applicant's choice was fully respected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2095.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2099.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Police took full account of all the applicant's procedural rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2099.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2106.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It never even attempted to take his statement without the presence of the lawyer of the applicant's choosing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2106.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2114.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When the applicant eventually decided to hire a lawyer and to actively present his defense, his decision was respected again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2114.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2121.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And he was given the opportunity to choose a lawyer who was then called to the police station.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2121.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2138.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to clear all doubts on this issue, it should be pointed out that the police has no authority to appoint a lawyer to a suspect during police questioning, nor is it the police in charge to secure legal aid to suspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2138.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2147.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Suspects themselves choose and hire a lawyer by signing him or her the written power of attorney.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2147.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2151.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was given the opportunity to choose a lawyer and have him present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2151.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2161.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was given an opportunity to consult his lawyer in private without any time limit for these consultations being set.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2161.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2165.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant and his lawyer consulted for 20 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2165.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2176.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After consultations, the applicant said that he was ready to give his statement, in which he confessed triple murder and arson of a skyscraper.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2176.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2184.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be stressed that the applicant obviously did not make the decision to confess during 20 minutes consultation with his lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2184.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2194.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that point, he has been under arrest for eight hours, during which he had ample opportunity and relevant information to make such a decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2194.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2205.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nothing indicates that during that period, anyone influenced the applicant's decision to confess, either by coercion or otherwise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2205.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2215.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The period of 20 minutes was not long enough to persuade the applicant to confess, if that wasn't his true will.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2215.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2220.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nor was it enough to change the applicant's mind once he made such a decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2220.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2236.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, 20 minutes was enough time to provide the applicant with sufficient information on his rights, to give him legal advice, and acquaint him with the details on how the interrogation will proceed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2236.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2251.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government draws the Grand Chamber's attention to the fact that no time limit existed for those consultations, and that the applicant at no point objected that time he spent with his lawyer was too short.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2251.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2264.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For these reasons, one can only conclude that the purpose of the legal assistance during the police questioning was completely fulfilled through the effective legal advice provided by lawyer Mirko Ružić.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2264.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2279.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following those conclusions, the only matter left is to consider whether Mirko Ružić was the lawyer of the applicant's genuine choice, and whether this was of any influence on the applicant's defense rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2279.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2291.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges of the court, in its written pleading, the government already analyzed in detail all relevant and sustainable facts which demonstrate who was the lawyer of the applicant's choosing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2291.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2294.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The facts can be summarized as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2294.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2302.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, at the time of these events, the applicant was an adult with full legal capacity and considerable criminal record.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2302.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2308.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During four previous criminal proceedings, he was represented by various lawyers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2308.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2318.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Immediately upon his arrest in the morning on 14 March 2007, the applicant refused assistance of any lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2318.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2323.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant requested police to inform his father about his arrest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2323.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2327.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The father was informed of this fact around 2 PM on the same day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2327.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2331.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's mother was in Italy at the time of these events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2331.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2345.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was impossible for her to sign the power of attorney to lawyer Mr. Marjanović on the day of the applicant's arrest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2345.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2360.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lawyer Marjanović didn't have an undisputed written power of attorney to represent the applicant on March 14, 2007, the day of the applicant's arrest, signed by either of the applicant's parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2360.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2370.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there was no legal ground to enable him contact with the applicant, who was then still refusing any legal assistance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2370.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2375.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that point, the applicant was arrested as suspect of a serious crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2375.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2389.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allowing contact of the applicant with anyone other by the lawyer who had a valid entitlement to represent him would be extremely dangerous and could have damaged criminal investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2389.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2407.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once the applicant asked for legal assistance, around 6 PM on the same day, he never asked to be represented by lawyer Marjanović, although his name was also on the list of lawyers presented to the applicant by the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2407.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2419.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lawyer Marjanović gave various versions of his alleged attempts to contact the applicant, which are contradictory, illogical, and even impossible to some extent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2419.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2425.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lawyer Marjanović wasn't at the police station at the time when the applicant requested legal assistance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2425.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2429.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant signed written power of attorney to lawyer Mirko Ružić.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2429.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2439.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And at the beginning of his statement to the police, he pointed out that exactly lawyer Ružić was the lawyer of his choice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2439.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2449.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant gave the statement to the police in the presence of the lawyer of his own choice and duly signed the statement, not adding any remarks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2449.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2454.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even though the applicant chose Mr. Marjanović as his lawyer,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2454.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2465.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the next day on hearing before investigative judge, it is evident that the applicant stated that he did not choose Mr. Ružić as his lawyer, only answering</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2465.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2470.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to leading questions of Mr. Marjanović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2470.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2484.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, lawyer Marjanović did not make any objection to the investigative judge in this regard, nor did he request the exclusion of the applicant's statement from the case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2484.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2499.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only a day later, the applicant and his lawyer had another opportunity to contest the validity of the applicant's statement given to the police as the evidence in the appeal against the decision to open criminal investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2499.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2504.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, they have never filed such an appeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2504.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2526.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, these applicant's statements made in form of answers to his lawyer leading questions in circumstances where he exercised his right to remain silent cannot be considered as credible assertions, especially if we know that they were not followed by appropriate legal action which would be reasonably expected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2526.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2539.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, these statements were proven untrue before national courts and before the chamber, and thus can only be seen as the applicant's defense tactics.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2539.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2541.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These are facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2541.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2548.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Everything else is pure speculation, which comes from unsustainable line of events presented by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2548.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2559.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of the applicant's allegations which contradicted these facts were properly considered and dismissed by domestic courts in their recent decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2559.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2574.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be also kept in mind, as the chamber already noted, that two other perpetrators of this crime never made any complaint about ill treatment or coercion in general or in respect of a choice of lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2574.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2577.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All three of them were arrested at about the same time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2577.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2587.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The records show that other two suspects, upon their arrest, decided to hire lawyers of their choosing, who were then immediately called to the police station.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2587.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2592.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Eventually, they decided not to present their defense before the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2592.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2594.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their decisions were respected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2594.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2600.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is not any logical explanation why would police treat the applicant differently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2600.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2607.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, denied him the access to a lawyer he specifically asked for, as the applicant alleges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2607.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2624.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, the government dismisses the applicant's continuous allegations that lawyer Ružič was forcibly appointed to him by the police and that this lawyer secured the applicant's confession because of his former occupation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2624.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2636.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, there was never a complaint against lawyer Ružič by any of his clients that he used his former occupation to their disadvantage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2636.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2644.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, but not less important, there is no logical explanation why would Mr. Ružič, who is now making a living as a lawyer</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2644.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2652.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and who was dismissed from his position at the police against his will, assist the police against his client.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2652.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2664.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having in mind just mentioned under these circumstances the applicant's choice of Mirko Ružič as his lawyer can be seen from another angle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2664.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2678.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is quite possible that the applicant chose him precisely because he was a former police officer and expected him to have best knowledge of police tactics and routine and who could give him the best advice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2678.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2683.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The name of Mr. Ružič and his former position in the police</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2683.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2686.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was surely well known to the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2686.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2689.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was the only name standing out from the list of lawyers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2689.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2704.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And looking from the applicant's position at that point, it was the only name which could secure him legal assistance, but also an insider advice which would assure him better chances in the criminal proceedings following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2704.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2719.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the light of these findings, one can only conclude that the applicant introduced complaints against admission of his confession as the valid evidence in the moment when he realized that he didn't have any other argument in his defense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2719.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2727.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only thing left for the applicant at this point was the attempt to contest the legality of his own confession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2727.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2741.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, this attempt of the applicant's defense, duly considered with all other sustainable facts that prove otherwise, cannot be sufficient to rise any questions under Article VI of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2741.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2758.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the respect of the applicant's right against self-incrimination, the government firstly notes that active presentation of defense by way of confession is a legitimate defense and does not automatically contradict rights guaranteed in the Article VI.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2758.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2767.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant in this case was an adult with previous vast experience of being questioned by the police and being accused in the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2767.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2782.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Upon his arrest, and once again, immediately before giving his statement, and in the presence of his lawyer, he was informed of his right not to incriminate himself and to remain silent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2782.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2791.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant stated in the minutes of the questioning and confirmed with his signature that he fully understood these rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2791.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2804.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His ability to understand all the circumstances he was in and to be aware of his actions was established by a psychiatric expertise done for only a day before the questioning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2804.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2813.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the government already explained in detail in its written submissions, the applicant was not held at the police station for 29 hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2813.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2818.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was free to leave the police station any time prior to his arrest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2818.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2830.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, all allegations that because of his prolonged stay at the police station, it was easy for the police to pressure him to give his statement are completely misleading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2830.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2842.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, it is to be pointed out that the applicant never substantiated his allegations of ill treatment during the police custody, as it was established in the proceedings before the chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2842.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2849.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's complaints in this respect were declared inadmissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2849.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2863.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the applicant did not introduce any new evidence or substantiate any of his complaints, the government invites the grand chamber to fully endorse findings of the chamber in this respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2863.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2877.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government notes that the applicant also complains to the court that his confession was a result of coercive environment created by the fact that he was forced to hire a lawyer called by the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2877.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2894.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the government already addressed the issue of the applicant's choice of lawyer in this pleading, it would note here that the applicant never advanced specific explanation to the court as to why the lawyer Marjanovic enjoyed his special trust.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2894.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2902.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that lawyer Marjanovic represented the applicant in one of four criminal proceedings against him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2902.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2909.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these proceedings, the applicant pleaded guilty and was sentenced to 10 months of imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2909.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2915.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such previous relationship is quite insufficient to conclude that Mr. Marjanovic was a lawyer of the applicant's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2915.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2927.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>particular confidence and to presume that the presence of any other lawyer would create a coercive environment leading to the applicant's confession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2927.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2938.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, if we further analyze their relationship, it should be borne in mind that after the applicant signed him the power of attorney in this case, Mr. Marjanovic failed to submit appeals</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2938.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2948.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>against three crucial decisions at the initial stage of criminal proceedings against the applicant and canceled the applicant's representation only 13 days later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2948.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2960.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These facts also endorse a conclusion that there are no sufficient grounds to assume that the applicant had any particular bond with this particular lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2960.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2967.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, nothing in the applicant's behavior at the time displays that he was in an environment which he found coercive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2967.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2983.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His detailed and thorough statement and his attitude during the proceedings before domestic authorities point that he was neither unstable, frightened, intimidated, nor susceptible to influence by the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2983.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2993.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be noted that the applicant is the person who was released from detention only a month before the impugned police questioning took place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2993.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3010.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was detained during the proceedings in which he was charged for the physical assault and heavy bodily harm against the police officer on duty for which he was finally sentenced to 10 months imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3010.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3027.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If we link this information with the fact that this was the applicant's 23rd stay at the police station and with his aggressive behavior in general, the government deems these circumstances relevant to the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3027.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3035.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sorry, the government deems that these circumstances reveal that the applicant felt no particular fear, intimidation, or respect towards the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3041.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3056.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given his previous criminal record, number of arrests, and previous police questionings, it can reasonably be presumed that the applicant wasn't susceptible to any kind of pressure or extortion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3056.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3075.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges of the Grand Chamber, not only do we claim that there wasn't any form of coercion against the applicant to incriminate himself, we claim that it is only reasonable to conclude that precisely because the applicant has already made a decision to confess, he decided to hire a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3075.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3087.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that point, the applicant was aware of the fact that the police had arrested his accomplices and that police could place him at a crime scene based on the statement of a witness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3087.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3093.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These were the circumstances in which the applicant made the decision to present his defense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3093.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3099.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No one in this courtroom knows what the exact content of the applicant's discussion with his lawyer was.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3099.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3111.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We can only read and rely on the record of the applicant's questioning, the content of which the applicant validated with his signature in the presence of his lawyer and state attorney.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3111.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3117.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it is not only the signature on the record that shows that the applicant's own true will was to confess.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3117.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3133.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's entire statement doesn't give the impression that it was given by someone who was intimidated or coerced to confess, nor that this person was eager to give the police the information they wanted just to be alone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3133.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3149.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His narrative statement was given over the course of several hours, during which time the applicant comprehensively and in detail described not only the actual crime, but also his movements during the whole day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3149.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3154.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He spoke of his mood and thoughts and gave motives for the crime committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3154.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3160.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It can even be noticed that he put emphasis on his regret for the crime committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3160.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3170.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this can also be regarded as a motive for his decision to confess once he became aware that the police had enough evidence against him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3170.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3185.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not less important to know that the applicant never revealed what he did with the material evidence which would indisputably connect him with a crime, such as a bloodied jacket, sneakers, gun, bullets, and sword.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3185.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3200.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We can only agree that in that phase of the police investigation, those information would have been the most important to the police, because under domestic law, even after a full confession, the authorities have to confirm the confession itself with other evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3200.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3214.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, police never made any pressure on the applicant to reveal this information, which is the fact of great significance showing the respect for the applicant's right against self-incrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3214.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3230.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the question whether the applicant's defense rights were irretrievably prejudiced by his statement given to the police, domestic law provides various procedural safeguards when a confession of the accused is used as the evidence in criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3230.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3238.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This detailed legislative framework setting the right to effective legal advice was fully respected in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3238.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3245.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the statement given to the police by the accused cannot be used as evidence if the lawyer wasn't present at questioning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3245.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3250.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the confession of the accused cannot be taken for granted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3250.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3252.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has to be supported by other evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3252.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3266.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's confession was not the central platform of the prosecution's case, and the trial court relied on his statement, interpreting it in the light of a complex body of evidence assessed by national courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3266.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3286.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Specifically, when convicting the applicant, the trial court relied on the statements of a number of witnesses cross-examined during the trial, numerous expert reports, and the records of the crime scene investigations, searches and seizures, as well as relevant photographs and other physical evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3286.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3292.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of these documents and evidences have been provided to the court as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3292.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3301.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, the accused can challenge the legality of any evidence, including his confession during police questioning at any stage of proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3301.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3310.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant made use of this possibility when he, at one point of the trial proceedings, started to claim that his rights were violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3310.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3324.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, after considering his objections, the national courts gave thoroughly reasoned explanations for their decisions to maintain the applicant's statement as the legally obtained evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3324.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3342.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Throughout the court proceedings, the applicant had the benefit of effective legal advice, and the trial court afforded him an adequate opportunity to participate in the proceedings and to put forward his arguments in respect of charges and all the relevant evidence adduced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3342.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3345.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His arguments were duly taken into account.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3345.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3382.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To conclude, the government calls the members of the Grand Chamber to bear in mind, whilst delivering this case, that the applicant is a person sentenced to maximum imprisonment for one of the most hideous crimes in Croatia in the last 20 years, and that the attempt to discredit the validity of the confession is the only line of the defense left for the applicant, that all the applicant's objections were carefully examined by domestic courts and proven untrue, and that sustainable facts of the evidence clearly show that the events happened as presented by the government before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3382.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3391.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To refer to the applicant's argument that he was not provided by the good defense because Mr. Ružić did not ask for the hearing</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3391.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3395.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>before the police to be adjourned after 10 p.m.,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3395.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3405.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and that the applicant could have not been questioned before the police after 10 p.m., it should be noticed</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3405.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3413.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that Article 32 of the Police Act prescribes that suspects cannot be brought to the police station between 10 p.m. and 6 a.m.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3413.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3422.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, Paragraph 5 of the same article prescribes that there is an exception of this rule if undertaking of police duties cannot be postponed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3422.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3442.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government stresses that these provisions primarily refer to bringing a person to the police station based on the competent court's arrest warrant, which then will be executed in the period between 10 p.m. and 6 a.m. unless ordered otherwise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3442.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3455.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The aim of this provision is to secure that the family or the neighbors of the person who is to be brought to the police station are not disturbed during the night unless it is absolutely necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3455.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3463.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, this provision does not apply to the crime investigation over the person which is already brought to the police station before 10 p.m.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3463.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3471.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, the government emphasizes that these provisions, not even by analogy, apply to the applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3471.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3485.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was questioned before the police based on Article 177, Paragraph 5 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, which provision does not prescribe the time limit in which the questioning should be done, nor the time when the questioning can start.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3485.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3495.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After the investigation, again, the applicant was officially opened before the first instant court, the applicant was questioned based on Article 252 of the Court of Criminal Proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3495.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3503.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This provision also does not prescribe the time limit for the questioning, nor the time limit when the questioning should start.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3503.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3508.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges of the Grand Chamber, I thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3515.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3527.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Ms. Stažnik, I would now like to invite the judges of the Grand Chamber to put any questions they may have to the parties, Judge Griţco.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Valeriu Griţco</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3530.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3531.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3531.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3533.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3533.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3534.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3538.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3557.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In paragraph 33 of written submissions dated 29 September 2014, the government states that it cannot submit to the court the list of lawyers that was made available to the applicant on 14 March 2007.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3557.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3575.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, the court was provided with another list of lawyers which, as is mentioned in the government submissions, I quote, contains the same data and information that was on the list which was given to the applicant on 14 March 2007.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3575.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3588.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in this list, next to the name of the lawyer M.R., there is a note indicating that he is no longer active.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3588.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3590.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please explain this misstatement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3590.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3590.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3595.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3598.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Luis López Guerra.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3601.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3602.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3602.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3606.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's only a question to both parties, but mostly to the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3606.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3619.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We know that the 14th of March of 2007, the applicant made a statement before the police at the police station, making a confession of the facts for what he was later sentenced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3619.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3625.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then, at this time, the 14th of March, he was with assistance of the lawyer, M.R.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3628.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3634.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the following day, the 15th of March, he was brought before the investigating judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3635.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3646.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not clear whether or not he had the assistance of any lawyer, and he made some declarations, complaining that he had never hired the lawyer, M.R.,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3648.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3651.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>but that's more or less we know.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3651.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3658.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then, the following day, the 16th of March, he was brought again before the investigating judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3658.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3663.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, he was assisted by the lawyer, G.M.,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3663.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3676.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and we know that in this case, he remained silent, and he didn't refuse to answer any questions put to him by the investigating judge or the prosecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3676.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3681.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, my question is, how did the applicant make the confession?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3681.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3705.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, my question is that we know that he made a confession before the police at the police station, but then, did he repeat it, or did he confirm the context of this confession at any time before any judicial authority, either the investigating judge or the trial court, because we know they had the confession before the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3705.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3708.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was any confirmation of this confession?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3708.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3709.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3709.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3711.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Vehabović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Faris Vehabović</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3715.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3717.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3717.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3724.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have one question for the applicant's representative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3724.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3737.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We heard from the government that no proceeding was ever initiated against the lawyer M.R.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3737.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3769.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is, have you ever initiated any kind of proceeding against M.R. or any steps you took against lawyer M.R. for his behavior in representation of the applicant, including disciplinary proceeding before the Croatian Bar Association or any kind of proceeding?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3769.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3769.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3770.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3772.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Hirvelä.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3774.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3775.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3775.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3783.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It appeared in the submissions today that the applicant was not for the first time in the police station, at that police station.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3783.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3795.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Have the parties any information whether the applicant knew during the interrogation that the lawyer was the former chief of the police?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3796.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3799.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3801.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3805.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3805.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3809.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question goes to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3809.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3823.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Article 32, paragraph 4 of the Police Act, a person shall not be brought in the period from 6 a.m. to 10 p.m. to a police station.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3823.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3833.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now we heard today that there is a difference of interpretation between the parties on this provision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3833.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3844.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the applicant, from this provision it can be drawn that a person should not have been questioned after 10 p.m.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3844.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3847.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the government, there is no limit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3847.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3851.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no limit even for the duration of the interrogation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3851.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3853.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It can go on and on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3853.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3859.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It can last five, three, six, seven hours during the whole night.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3859.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3862.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If I understood correctly, the position of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3862.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3870.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I would like to know what is the practice, what is the case law of Croatia on this particular point?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3870.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3886.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because we have heard the position of the parties, but we have not heard about the case law of the Croatian courts on this particular topic, which is an interesting feature of this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3886.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3886.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3887.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3888.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, George Zupančič.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Boštjan M. Zupančič</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3891.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3892.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3892.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3898.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions to both parties, I guess.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3898.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3908.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first question is, this is a typical case for the constitutional court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3908.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3932.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because in terms of the rights of the defendant in criminal procedure, in terms of establishing the precedence in this area, in terms of resolving the problems such as we are now faced with, this would be the competence of the constitutional court par excellence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3932.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3941.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I did not find in the file, correct me if I'm wrong, any reference to the position of the constitutional court, one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3941.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3953.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And two, I would like to know whether that decision, if there was a substantive decision on the part of constitutional court, was a unanimous one or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3953.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3958.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question goes beyond the case the way it's now discussed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3958.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3961.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I don't want to prejudge it, obviously.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3961.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3974.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the real question, if we were, I emphasize the hypothetical aspect of this question, if we were to find a violation, what would be the legal consequences in Croatia?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3974.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3977.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This goes primarily to the defense, I guess.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3977.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3989.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because the mere finding of the violation or the monetary reward in case we were to find a violation is not the obvious remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3989.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4002.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The obvious remedy, and I assume it is described in the Code of Criminal Procedure of Croatia, would be a retrial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4002.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4009.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I trust this is in the Code of Criminal Procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4009.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4009.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4009.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4031.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two, the next question, of course, is if there were to be a retrial, the evidence, the contaminated evidence obtained via the questioning of the police, if we were to find a violation, would have to be expunged, would have to be extirpated, would have to be thrown out of the file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4031.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4047.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And a new court, in my opinion, would have to be appointed or designated to deal with the issue without having been burdened by the findings of the previous court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4047.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4051.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would be very grateful for the answer from both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4051.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4051.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4052.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4053.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, judge Kalaydjieva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Zdravka Kalaydjieva</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4056.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4058.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4058.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4062.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I note that my question is to both parties to these proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4062.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4079.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I note that paragraph 5 of article 177 of the Code of Criminal Procedure speaks of allowing the suspect to appoint a lawyer from the list of lawyers on duty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4079.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4093.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And at the same time, it is submitted that the applicant was never requested to pay the fees for the services of the lawyer appointed under this procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4093.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4101.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And at the same time, it does not seem that he was required to do so under the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4101.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4110.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is interesting for me to know, were these services paid at all, or were they provided pro bono?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4110.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4120.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And how does this compare to the wording of paragraph 3.C</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4120.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4138.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of article 6, which speaks of defense through legal assistance of his own choosing, or free assistance when the interests of justice so require?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4138.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4158.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How would you define the requirements of article 177 as services of own choice of a lawyer of the choosing of the applicant, or services provided for free when the interests of justice so required?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4158.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4158.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4159.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4161.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Šikuta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ján Šikuta</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4164.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4166.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4166.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4188.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is linked close to the question of Judge Kalaydjieva, and this is directed to both parties, but mainly to the government, because during government pleadings today, my attention was attracted by a statement that I couldn't find in the file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4188.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4222.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I simply did not see that, but you said, the government, that M.R., the lawyer, that he was dismissed from the police, and you related it to the potential fact that that was the reason why the applicant chose his representation, because he is aware of the structures in the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4222.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4232.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is whether it is true that he was dismissed from his position in the police, and if yes, that when?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4232.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4232.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4233.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4237.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4237.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4250.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now the court will now rise for 15 minutes, following which the parties will return for a second round of short pleadings to respond to the submissions in the first round and the judges' questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4303.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4304.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4342.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4344.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4344.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4346.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is now resumed and I call Mrs. Maroševac-Čapko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4355.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4372.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poštovani predsjedniče članovi vijeća, kolege i kolegice, na pitanja koja su postavljena zastupniku podnositelja zahtjeva mogu samo sljedeće reći.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4375.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4390.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Što se tiče izlaganja same države danas na ovom saslušanju, naime isti su samo ponovili ono što su podnijeli u svom podnisku 29. rujna 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4390.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4398.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>tako da smo se mi već na to očitovali i nemamo nikakvih daljnjih očitovanja, jer bi se sad samo ponavljali.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4400.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4420.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Što se tiče pitenja suda, da li je podnositelj zahtjeva ikad potvrdio svoje priznanje koje je ishođeno u prostorijama treće policijske postaje u Rijeci?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4420.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4422.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moram reći, nije.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4424.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4429.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On to priznanje nikada nije ponovio i nikada nije potvrdio, niti u jednom kasnijem stadiju.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4429.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4433.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Da pače, poricao je i branio se šutnjom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4438.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4481.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Što se tiče pitanja da li je protiv odjetnika Mirka Ružića ikad pokrenut bilo kakav postupak vezano za njegovo postupanje pred policijskom postajom u Rijeci, da li je meni poznato podnijete samo primjedba i prijava Hrvatskoj odjetničkoj komori od strane odjetnika Gorana Marjanovića prema postupanju, odnosno zbog postupanja treće policijske postaje prema njemu u sklopu kojeg je onda obrazloženo cijela situacija i vezano za Mirka Ružića.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4481.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4485.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>O tom prigodom što pokrenuto protiv istoga meni nije poznato.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4491.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4527.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Na pitanje da li je podnositelj zahtjeva u trenutku davanja iskaza znao da li je odjetnik Mirko Ružić bio policijski načelnik prije toga, ja o tome ne mogu se izjasniti iz razloga što o tome nisam razgovarala, ali ono što znam, a to je da podnositelj zahtjeva, moj branjenik, nikada nije želio da ga on zastupa jer u njega nije imao povjerenja.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4527.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4577.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Što se tiče sudske prakse u Republici Hrvatskoj u to vrijeme, a u svezi ispitivanja osumnjičenika pred policijom uz nazočnost odjetnika, odnosno o trajanju vremena ispitivanja, koliko je meni poznato, ispitivanja osumnjičenika su se u pravilu vršila u okviru zakonskih ograničenja, a da li je bilo i prekoračenja, takvih situacija vjerujem da je, i koliko mi je poznato, takvi slučajevi su bili procesuirani putem Ustavnog suda.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4577.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4593.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mislim da je upravo jedan od takvih slučajeva bio i slučaj na kojeg smo se pozvali, a to je Mađer protiv Republike Hrvatske, u likom njegovog ispitivanja na policiji.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4600.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4641.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Što se tiče prakse Ustavnog suda u odnosu na tretiranje ispitivanja osumnjičenika i politiciju uz nazočnost odjetnika, naime moram prigovoriti na rad Ustavnog suda Republike Hrvatske, zbog toga ima jako puno postupaka pred vašim sudom, što taj sud zapravo u velikoj mjeri ne zauzima nikakav stav, odnosno u velikoj mjeri odbacuje ustavne tužbe, dolazeći u meritum. Tako da njihov stav vezano za to je teško komentirati.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4641.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4673.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Što se tiče posljedica osude, ukoliko bi ovaj sud prihvatio zahtjeva podnositelja, zahtjeva da se radi o povredi ljudskih prava, naravno da bi to utjecalo na postupak u Republike Hrvatskoj, da bi to dovelo do toga da se ovo njegovo priznanje pod navodnicima dalje koristi kao dokaz, da bi se obnovio postupak i da bi se tad koristili samo dokazi koji se nalaze u spisu u odnosu na materialne dokaze.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4673.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4695.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ja moram reći što se tiče tih materialnih dokaza, naravno to je moj stav, da veliki dio tih materialnih dokaza uopće ne ukazuje na podnositelja zahtjeva kao počinitelja kaznjenih dijela, nego da se radi u velikom dijelu o indicijama.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4695.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4711.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I nadam se da sam odgovorila na to pitanje sudca Zupančića, ako ne, možete mi je eventualno postaviti naklonno pitanje.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4711.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4742.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Na pitanje, da li je odvjetnik, u ovom slučaju Mirko Ružić, da li je on mogao raditi probono, u ovom slučaju moram reći da zakonski nije predviđeno da bi odvjetnik zastupao besplatno, odnosno probono, na saslušanju pred policijom, s obzirom da onda je to spadalo u predisrežni postupak, a u ovom zakonu o kaznenom postupku su vrijedila drugačije pravila.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4742.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4765.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Inače, za kazneni postupak nikada pa ni sad ne postoji mogućnost rada probono, nego postoji rad po službenoj dužnosti, što znači da postoji poseban tarifnik, odnosno pravilnik o radu odvjetnika, gdje je onda troškove obrane snose država.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4765.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4774.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To je mogućnost izabranog odvjetnika gdje je onda stranka plaća svog odvjetnika, ali probono u kaznenom postupku ne postoji.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4774.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4802.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Probono kao rad postoji samo u građanskom postupku, u slučajima kada stranka zbog teških imovinskih prilika kaži oslobađanje plaćanja troškova od strane državne uprave.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4802.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4808.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To je, predpostavljam, pitanje za državu, ali evo možda i ja mogu odgovoriti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4808.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4833.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kada je Mirko Ružić otpušten iz policije, odnosno da li kada, on je u svakom slučaju nedugo prije ovog događaja prestao biti načelnikom Policijske uprave Primorsko-Goranske županije i tada je otvorio svoj odvjetnički ured.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4833.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4851.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dok je bio načelnik Policijske uprave, o njemu se jako puno pisalo u novinama, zauzirom da je osoba koja je dosta sklona skandalima, izazivanju prometnih nezgoda i bježenja sa lica mjesta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4851.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4865.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>U tom smislu smo i dostavili novinski članak, gdje je i nakon što je prestao biti policijski načelnik, nastavio sa takvim ponašanjem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4865.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4873.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Zbog toga to sad i govorim, inače ne bih to spominjala, da to nije bilo u javnim glasilima.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4873.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4878.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ja sam nadam da sam odgovorila na sva vaše pitanja, ali ne slobodno me pitajte. Hvala lijepa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4881.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4883.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Ms. Stažnik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4887.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4891.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. President. First question, my colleague Mrs. Small.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4895.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4904.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honourable judges of the court, I would like to address the question of the judge Gritko concerning the list of lawyers which was submitted to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4904.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4915.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If you take a look at the list, it can be seen that it was printed out on 24th September 2014 from the Registry of Lawyers of Croatian Bar Association.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4915.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4924.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 24th September 2014, Mirko Ružić was no longer a lawyer because in the meantime he has been nominated the public notary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4924.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4927.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is why the list now shows the remark deleted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4927.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4933.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, in 2007 he was listed without the remark deleted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4933.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4935.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This answers your question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4940.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4949.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges of the Grand Chamber, I would like to refer to the second question made by Judge Lopez Guerra.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4949.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4955.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In reference, did the applicant confirm his confession before any judicial authority?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4955.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4970.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government would like to answer to this question that the applicant did not explicitly confirm his confession given to the police, before the police, since he exercised his rights to remain silent throughout the subsequent court proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4970.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4996.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, his confession was confirmed by large number of evidence collected regardless of the confession, mostly through the statements made by other two suspects who showed that there were no material evidence, where the material evidence were thrown, and that he was a number of expertise and documents made before the first instance proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4996.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5024.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, the government would like to note that in his closing argument before the trial court, the applicant, through his representative, presented the confession he had given to the police while represented by lawyer Ružić as a proof of his sincere regret for the crimes committed, in order for it to be taken into account while deliberating on the sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5024.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5032.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government deems that this was a form of confirmation of this confession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5036.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5041.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards third, fourth and fifth question, I would like to address them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5041.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5053.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, third question about any action taken against lawyer Ružić.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5053.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5063.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to say that there was no action or any application to the Croatian Bar Association as regards lawyer Ružić.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5063.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5068.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that Mr. Marjanović filed an action against unlawful act before Rijeka Municipal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5068.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5076.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Court claiming that the police officers unlawfully denied him access to the applicant while he was at the police station.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5076.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5083.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be borne in mind that this act was filed in the name of the applicant's mother and the lawyer Marjanović himself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5083.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5089.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Marjanović never proved the complaints made in this action as regards Mr. Ružić</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5089.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5094.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because the action was subsequently withdrawn for the reasons unknown to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5094.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5102.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We think that actually the representative, that Mrs. Čapko, withdrawn this application</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5102.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5107.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>if I'm not mistaken.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5107.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5111.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards fourth question addressed by Judge Vihavović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5111.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5129.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, as the applicant's representative today also said, lawyer Ružić, before he became a lawyer, when he was a head of the police district, was well known in Rijeka.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5129.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5142.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rijeka is a town of 300 inhabitants and he was a public person, so especially he was known to those who came to police station quite often.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5142.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5161.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards fifth question and the difference between the Court of Criminal Procedure and the Police Act that deals with bringing a person to the police station and questioning a person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5161.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5172.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Actually we would like to say that provisions about bringing a person to police station does not apply to the question of the suspect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5172.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5177.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they are prescribed by the Police Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5177.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5191.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And by this Police Act it is prescribed that suspects cannot be brought to the police station between 10 p.m. and 6 a.m. exactly for the reason that the family or the neighbors of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5191.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5201.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the person who is to be brought to the police station will not be disturbed during the night unless it is absolutely necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5201.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5211.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I said, this provision does not apply to the crim investigation over the person which is already brought to the police station before 10 p.m.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5211.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5215.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was the case with the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5215.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5225.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When we are talking about the questioning of a suspect, the provisions of Court of Criminal Procedure apply.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5225.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5236.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And by provisions, these provisions does not prescribe any time limit in which the questioning should be done, nor the time when the questioning can start.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5236.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5240.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope I answered your question, Maris.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5240.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5240.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5245.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5246.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5246.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5249.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5249.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5250.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So do you want to add something?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5248.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5251.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sorry, do you want to add something?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5251.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5255.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No, we would like to answer following questions, 6, 7, 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5255.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5256.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>OK, please, go on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5258.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5271.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, in respect of the questions made by Judge Zupancic, I would like to answer that the Constitutional Court brought unanimous decision in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5271.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5287.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that, as said by the Applicant's Council, if the court finds violation in this case, according to the provisions of CCP, the case would be open for a retrial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5287.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5304.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the statement given, if the court establishes that the statement given to the police by the applicant is even valid evidence, the new indictment will be filed based on other evidence collected irrespective of the statement given to the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5304.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5309.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the new trial will be following afterwards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5309.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5309.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5312.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5327.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to take the question of the Honorable Judge Hirvella about the laws on duty as prescribed in the Article 177, Paragraph 8 of the Code of Criminal Procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5330.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5338.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This article prescribed that there will be a list of laws on duty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5338.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5344.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The purpose of such a list was to provide information which lawyers on which day and time would be on duty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5344.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5349.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If they were on duty, they had to be available to come to the police station if they were called.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5349.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5355.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Applicant's Council already confirmed, these are not legal aid lawyers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5355.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5357.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These are privately hired lawyers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5357.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5372.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, Mirko Ružić could have charged the applicant for his services, and the government has no information whether he charged him, considering this is a private relationship between the lawyer and the client.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5372.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5381.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for that matter, we don't have the information whether Goran Marjanović also charged the applicant for his subsequent services when he represented.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5386.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5433.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, to answer the court's last question, whether Mirko Ružić was dismissed from the police and when, the government would like to clear this up with the document, if needed, we will provide it to the court's case file, that Mirko Ružić was the police, working at the police from 19th of July, 1993, and on 1st of August, 1997, he became head of police district, Primorsko-Goransko, that is the Rijeka County district, and his position, he was dismissed from this position on 7th of March, 2000.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5433.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5440.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He used his yearly leave, and he finally was dismissed on 26th of May, 2000, from the police station.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5440.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5443.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5447.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5452.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. Do you want to make closing remarks or have you finished?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5452.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5453.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, finished. Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5453.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5456.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5456.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5461.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5461.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5466.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits and the judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5466.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5469.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5469.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5469.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
