<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>2849215_20012021</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>10.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>11.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>16.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>29.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Good morning to all participants in the public hearing organized by the European Court of Human Rights with the use of video conferencing technology which has been made necessary due to the COVID-19 health crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>29.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>42.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wish to begin by thanking the applicants and the respondent government for their cooperation in preparing this hearing on the remerits in the case of Khasanov and Rakhmanov versus Russia which I now declare open.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>42.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>51.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should note before proceeding that this hearing is being recorded in its entirety and will be webcast in order to ensure its public character.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>51.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>58.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It will be available to the public on the court's website from 1430 this afternoon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>58.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>72.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were lodged with the court on 15 June and 11 October 2015 under Article 34 of the Convention by two Kyrgyz nationals, Mr. Turdivai Urumbayevich Khasanov and Mr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>72.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>75.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Shavgatbek Zalizhanovich Rakhmanov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>75.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>84.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were allocated to the third section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>84.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>102.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 15 October 2019, the Chamber of the third section unanimously declared the applications admissible and held by five votes to two that there will be no violation of Article 3 of the Convention in the event of the applicant's extradition to Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>102.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>118.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 7 February 2020, the applicants requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted that request on 15 April 2020.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>118.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>124.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Mr. Mikhail Galperin, representative of the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>124.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>131.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Russian Federation at the European Court of Human Rights, assisted by Mr. Pavel Smirnov,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>131.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>139.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Olga Ocheretyanaya, Ms. Zlata Bereza, Mr. Sergey Grigorenko, Mr. Sergey Klykovskiy, Ms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>139.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>145.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Olga Zinchenko, and Ms. Kamila Dzhabbarova, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>145.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>152.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Ms. Nadezhda Yermolayeva and Mr. Kirill Zharinov, counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>152.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>157.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties in the name of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>157.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>165.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representatives of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>165.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>171.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Zharinov and Ms. Yermolayeva for the applicants will speak first, and then Mr. Galperin for</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>171.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>173.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>173.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>174.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Zharinov, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>182.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>185.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>185.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>197.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with your permission, I will now address the current situation in Kyrgyzstan concerning risks of ill-treatment for ethnic Uzbeks under criminal prosecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>197.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>204.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My colleague, Ms. Nadezhda Yermolaeva, will continue and cover the individual circumstances</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>204.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>209.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the applicants and their assessment by the Russian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>209.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>217.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She will also show that the diplomatic monitoring mechanism is ineffective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>217.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>230.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our written submissions to the Grand Chamber, we have already given an extensive overview of various materials on Kyrgyzstan from independent and reliable sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>230.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>240.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have demonstrated that ethnic Uzbeks are systematically discriminated, persecuted, and subjected to ill-treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>240.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>256.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The existing mechanisms of protection against torture in Kyrgyzstan, including the National Preventive Mechanism, or the NPM, created in 2012, unfortunately remain ineffective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>256.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>268.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent government contested our conclusions, claiming that the situation in Kyrgyzstan has significantly improved in the recent years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>268.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>275.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government put forward a number of arguments and cited a range of sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>275.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>283.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, at a closer look, it turns out that they presented no convincing evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>283.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>305.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, the government cited the international reports selectively, referred to the information provided by Kyrgyzstan itself instead of independent observers, or made statements not supported by any statistics at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>305.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>314.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Speaking about the selectivity of the quotations provided by the government, I would like to give just one of the examples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>314.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>343.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian authorities referred to the public statement of Amnesty International made in 2020, which, I quote, welcomed Kyrgyzstan's cooperation with the Universal Periodic Review and its acceptance of 193 out of 232 recommendations, including recommendations on eradicating torture and ill-treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>343.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>345.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Full stop.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>345.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>351.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the government failed to cite the following passage from the same statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>351.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>365.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I quote, we regret that recommendations to set up an independent body to investigate torture and other ill-treatment were merely noted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>365.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>396.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally we urge the Kyrgyzstan authorities to follow through with the implementation of recommendations from the previous cycle of its UPR to carry out full and impartial investigations into human rights violations that occurred during the June 2010 ethnic violence, with special attention to allegations made by members of the Uzbek minority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>396.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>427.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in its report for the cycle of the UPR of 2020, Amnesty International expressed its disappointment that, I quote, Kyrgyzstan rejected recommendations to adapt recruitment guidelines for the police and the security forces to increase the representation of ethnic minorities and to adopt comprehensive anti-discrimination legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>427.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>439.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moving further, the government largely relied on the reports of the working group on the UPR for Kyrgyzstan of 2015 and 2020.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>439.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>443.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The UPR, I mean the Universal Periodic Review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>443.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>459.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the first sight, the citations made by the government contain a lot of information on positive changes, even an alleged decrease in reported cases of torture and ill-treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>459.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>464.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But a careful study of the quoted reports reveals the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>464.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>471.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the extracts cited were derived not from the conclusions of any independent observers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>471.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>481.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But they were taken directly from the UPR itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>481.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>492.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We strongly doubt that any serious weight could be given to such statements in view of independent information to the contrary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>492.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>501.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also important that some of the arguments of the Russian government are not accompanied by any statistics or evidence at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>501.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>508.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For instance, in their submissions, the government mentioned the Kyrgyzstan Ombudsman Office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>508.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>514.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They emphasized that it was tasked with receiving complaints of ill-treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>514.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>520.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But no statistics was provided, even on the number of such complaints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>520.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>525.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also haven't managed to find such information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>525.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>538.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, there is no official statistics even on the number of complaints of any kind received by the Ombudsman in the last few years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>538.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>551.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, the government brought the attention to the establishment of a special monitoring center in 2014 aimed at preventing the recurrence of the ethnic conflict.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>551.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>571.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the only achievement of this center in the last six years, which the government was able to find, is, I quote, working on a digital map of sites of potential ethnic conflicts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>571.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>580.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To be fair, there are some examples where the assumptions of the Russian government are indeed accompanied by precise statistics.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>580.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>590.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For instance, the government sought to prove the effectiveness of the national preventive mechanism created in Kyrgyzstan in 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>590.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>599.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They highlighted that by 2018, it had conducted over 4,000 visits to places of detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>599.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>604.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Definitely, that is quite an impressive number.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>604.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>611.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, does it in any way prove the effectiveness of the NPM?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>611.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>618.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How many complaints of ill-treatment did the NPM receive during all these visits?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>618.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>622.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How many perpetrators were brought to liability?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>622.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>625.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How many victims got redress?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>625.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>629.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian government did not answer these questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>629.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>637.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither did the government describe what happened to the NPM after 2018.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>637.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>639.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why is it so?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>639.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>650.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maybe because in most recent years, the NPM has been paralyzed and unable to exercise its most important functions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>650.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>653.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's not just our conclusions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>653.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>663.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I am quoting the latest reports of the United Nations Subcommittee on the Prevention of Torture and even the reports of the NPM itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>663.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>676.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, in 2020, the NPM even lacked money for visits as its bank account was frozen a year before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>676.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>690.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows from the international reports that the Kyrgyzstani legislature simply lacks interest in the NPM and the NPM itself misunderstands its function.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>690.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>697.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, I will continue speaking about some other statistics provided by the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>697.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>706.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, they submitted that there is no widespread ethnic bias in the Kyrgyzstani law enforcement system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>706.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>714.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the government, it is demonstrated by, I quote, many examples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>714.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>723.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After such an ambitious statement, the government managed to refer to only three cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>723.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>736.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these cases, the ethnic Uzbeks extradited to Kyrgyzstan were either released on parole or granted amnesty, or even their criminal prosecution was discontinued.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>736.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>741.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But firstly, it is clear that such statistics is not very representative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>741.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>751.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, and most importantly, this information has nothing to do with the assessment of the risks of ill treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>751.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>764.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A person of Uzbek origin may be ill treated immediately after a forced return and afterwards, for some reason, released on parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>764.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>776.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is exactly what happened in one of the cases now pending before the court, namely KK versus Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>776.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>787.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To sum up, the government failed to provide any credible evidence that ethnic Uzbeks are no more at risk of ill treatment in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>787.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>795.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is explained by a simple fact, there is just no such information at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>795.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>802.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unfortunately, the Kyrgyzstani authorities do not do their best to improve the situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>802.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>812.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of the most striking examples of their unwillingness to stop torture is the case of Mr. Azimzhon Askarov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>812.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>817.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was a prominent human rights defender convicted to life imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>817.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>823.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The National Preventive Mechanism failed to protect Mr. Askarov to ensure his release</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>823.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>826.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>or even to monitor his situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>826.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>840.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2016, the UN Human Rights Committee found that his right not to be subjected to torture was violated and recommended his immediate release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>840.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>844.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Kyrgyzstani authorities ignored the recommendations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>844.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>851.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They also ignored numerous reports about the decline of Mr. Askarov's health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>851.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>857.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Eventually, in July 2020, Mr. Askarov died in prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>857.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>863.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His conviction and death were acknowledged to be the results of a flagrant violation of his rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>863.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>870.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in 2020, the Supreme Court of Kyrgyzstan upheld Mr. Askarov's sentence despite the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>870.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>872.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>evidence of torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>872.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>878.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Supreme Court held that all Mr. Askarov's claims were refuted by the evidence of his</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>878.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>879.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>guilt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>879.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>886.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the highest judicial authority of Kyrgyzstan, in fact, gave a carte blanche to the law enforcers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>886.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>894.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It showed that a conviction clearly based on acts of torture remains acceptable in the legal system of Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>894.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>905.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And just a week ago, Human Rights Watch, in their latest report of 2021, described the situation in Kyrgyzstan in the following way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>905.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>910.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Impunity for torture and ill-treatment remains the norm.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>910.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>920.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, let me bring the attention of the Court to the extraordinary political crisis that started in Kyrgyzstan last year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>920.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>925.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that the current instability in the country raises further concerns.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>925.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>933.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the new president of Kyrgyzstan, Mr. Sadir Jafarov, was a member of a right-wing</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>933.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>937.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>nationalist party, Ata Jurd.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>937.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>946.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He also suggested that ethnicity should be indicated in Kyrgyzstani national passports, as it used to be in the past.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>946.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>957.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We strongly doubt that the rule of law will fully dominate in Kyrgyzstan in the near future, at least in respect of the Uzbek minority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>957.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>959.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>959.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>961.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I would like to pass the floor to my colleague, Ms. Nadezhda Yermolayeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>965.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>966.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>966.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>969.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>969.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>988.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>following the description of the general situation of the Uzbek ethnic minority in Kyrgyzstan, I will address the applicants' individual circumstances and practical ineffectiveness of suggested protective mechanisms, including diplomatic assurances of the Kyrgyz Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>988.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>994.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, the situation of the applicants differs as regards official grounds of their prosecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>994.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>999.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But they definitely have in common a more significant feature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>999.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1014.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both of them are ethnic Uzbeks, and the applicants' ethnic identity makes them both members of a particularly vulnerable group, ethnic Uzbeks facing detention in Kyrgyzstan due to criminal charges of any nature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1014.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1021.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should underline the word any in my previous sentence as it aligns with the Court's thinking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1021.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1044.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the cases of Mahmud Janirgachev and Mamad Aliyev, both versus Russia, where the applicants were charged with different criminal offenses, the Court has indicated that the mere fact of Uzbek ethnicity of a person who faces detention in Kyrgyzstan is a factor creating a sustained risk of torture and maltreatment for that person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1044.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1056.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the essence of the charges referred to by the responding government is only one of the factors taken into account by the Court in combination with other significant individual circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1056.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1065.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government argue that the nature of the charges against the first applicant and his criminal prosecution has nothing to do with his ethnicity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1065.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1073.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not disputed by the parties that the applicant was a businessman in Kyrgyzstan and he is charged with misappropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1073.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1087.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant notes, however, that criminal prosecution has often been used by the Kyrgyzstan authorities as a method of pressure on relatively wealthy ethnic Uzbeks and a source of corruption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1087.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1098.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Numerous facts of deprivation of property of ethnic Uzbeks were reported by human rights organizations and the applicant maintains that he has become a victim of this practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1098.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1109.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In reply to the applicant's arguments about risk of torture for them in Kyrgyzstan, the government doubts that their stories and concerns were genuine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1109.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1112.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the first applicant, Mr. Hassanov,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1112.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1117.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the government argue that his statements in domestic proceedings were controversial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1117.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1126.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, he submitted during the refugee status interview that he had left Kyrgyzstan because of his fear to be persecuted on ethnic grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1126.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1132.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While he had not mentioned it when questioned by a prosecutor shortly after his arrest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1132.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1146.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be noted that the express questioning of a prosecutor in extradition check is conducted as soon as possible after the arrest, briefly, formally and without establishing full picture of the applicant's circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1146.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1152.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During this procedure, it is in practice impossible for a detainee to obtain assistance of a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1152.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1160.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first applicant maintains that his replies to the prosecutor's question were given in stressful situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1160.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1166.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that moment, he, for the first time, found out that he was an internationally wanted person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1166.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1172.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He could not immediately realize the underlying reasons for this criminal prosecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1172.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1184.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Later, when asked detailed and targeted questions by a competent migration authority, the first applicant was given an opportunity to substantiate his request and to describe his fears.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1184.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1188.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In respect of the second applicant, Mr. Rahmanov,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1188.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1194.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the government underlines that he left Kyrgyzstan in early 2011 for economic reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1194.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1196.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is absolutely true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1196.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1205.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since after the ethnic clashes of 2010, it was practically impossible for an ethnic Uzbek to find a job in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1205.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1214.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet, after his arrest in Russia on the basis of the Kyrgyzstani search warrant, he immediately informed the Russian authorities of his fears.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1214.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1228.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He expressly asserted that he was scared of return to Kyrgyzstan since he could be prosecuted for a crime which he had never committed and thus definitely tortured in order to extract his confession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1228.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1239.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government maintains that the applicant's arguments about alleged ill-treatment were duly considered by the national courts and authorities according to the standards of the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1239.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1245.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They refer to the recent case of ASN and others that served the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1245.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1270.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the court found there that the applicant's rights would not be violated in case of their expulsion to Afghanistan and explained that the applicants, being of Sikh ethnic origin, failed to demonstrate that their personal circumstances prevail and reveal an outrageous risk of ill-treatment in comparison with other members of already marginalized ethnic community.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1270.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1277.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court in particular underlined the extract from the interview of one of the applicants in ASN.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1277.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1282.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I quote, Why do you think that you will end up in prison or killed?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1282.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1285.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mean that we feel imprisoned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1285.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1295.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We disagree with the government's interpretation of the court's position in this case as allowing refinement of a member of a vulnerable group to the country of his or her origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1295.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1303.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that this judgment merely reasserts the limits of a group particularly vulnerable to ill-treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1303.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1317.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We maintain that there are surely additional precise personal circumstances in the present case indicating a particularly high risk of torture and attributing the applicants to such especially vulnerable group.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1317.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1331.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both applicants are ethnic Uzbeks, will definitely end up in quite a real physical prison as opposed to the applicants in the ASN case who just feel imprisoned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1331.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1341.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants in this case will be arrested in a country where both of them are suspects to the crimes against the ethnic Kyrgyz.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1341.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1345.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The main witnesses in their cases are ethnic Kyrgyz.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1345.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1349.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The majority of law enforcers are ethnic Kyrgyz.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1349.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1361.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These facts already clearly distinguish the applicants from other members of the Uzbek community in Kyrgyzstan as a whole and create particular risk for them to suffer ill-treatment in custody.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1361.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1367.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And here we come to the very important issue in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1367.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1378.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Does the national preventive mechanism in Kyrgyzstan guarantee protection of the detainees and especially of those of ethnic Uzbek origin against torture?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1378.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1384.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are the diplomatic assurances in the Kyrgyzstani authorities effective in law and in practice?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1384.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1393.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that answers to these questions will illustrate how exactly, if at all, the authorities proclaimed intentions are realized in practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1393.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1399.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today, my colleague has already described the general ineffectiveness of NPM.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1399.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1403.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition to what has already been said, I should underline the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1403.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1410.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The NPM has had practice of monitoring the rights of special categories of the detainees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1410.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1415.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mean women, minors and persons with disabilities and etc.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1415.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1426.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, no research or visits were made by the NPM officials in order to monitor the rights of the ethnic minorities in penitentiary institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1426.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1436.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It didn't happen despite the fact that the position of ethnic Uzbeks in Kyrgyzstani prisons was a matter of concern of international human rights parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1436.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1443.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the applicant's opinion, this illustrates the reluctance of the local authorities to acknowledge the existence of the problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1443.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1451.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the acknowledgement, however, is the first and the most important condition of effective dealing with human rights issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1451.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1460.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further particular attention should be paid to the diplomatic monitoring mechanism introduced by the Russian and the Kyrgyzstani governments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1460.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1465.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The diplomatic assurances of the Kyrgyzstani authorities are of general nature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1465.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1479.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Literally, the prosecutor's general office of the Kyrgyz Republic indicates that the applicants would be able to have legal representation and would be not subjected to treatment contrary to the international standards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1479.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1486.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also indicates that after the applicant's extradition, the Russian diplomats will be able to visit them in custody.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1486.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1492.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These undertakings are formulated in standard terms without precision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1492.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1499.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These general words could be of effect in practice if other additional conditions were met.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1499.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1514.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, there must be legislative or international treaties provisions which would in detail regulate the procedure of visits of the Kyrgyzstani penitentiary institutions by Russian diplomats.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1514.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1518.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And secondly, such promises might be legally binding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1518.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1521.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, this is not the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1521.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1530.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We expected that the government's memorandum would contain references to some treaties between Russia and Kyrgyzstan governing the procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1530.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1540.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet, in the absence of such treaties, the government refers to the ECHR and the Convention of 6 March 1998.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1540.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1544.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both conventions contain no provisions which would govern the issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1544.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1553.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They do not guarantee the possibility of the diplomatic staff to visit the extradited persons in custody in order to monitor their state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1553.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1562.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, the government refers to the methodological instructions for the diplomats adopted by the Russian Ministry for Foreign Affairs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1562.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1568.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is important to underline that these instructions have a unilateral nature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1568.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1576.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They contain general recommendations for the Russian diplomats in extradition cases regardless of the country of destination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1576.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1582.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were not specially drafted to regulate the monitoring activities in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1582.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1586.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither do they bind Kyrgyzstani authorities in any way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1586.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1597.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the instructions, the first step to be taken by the Russian diplomats is the receipt of written permission from the authorities of the destination country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1597.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1606.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This fact alone makes the diplomatic mechanism ineffective since it is completely dependent on the Kyrgyzstani authorities' discretion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1606.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1615.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to bring the Court's attention to the letter of the Russian Ministry for Foreign Affairs attached to the government's written submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1615.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1623.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It confirms that in 2019 such permissions were granted only after numerous requests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1623.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1636.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even negotiating the difficulties in obtaining their permission would not guarantee the possibility of a visit since there are no legal obligations on the Kyrgyzstani party to issue such a permission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1636.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1640.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Next point of concern is the frequency of such visits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1640.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1648.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it follows from the government's submission, the frequency of visits is not prescribed in any document or agreement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1648.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1651.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet, they are usually held twice a year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1651.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1657.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It definitely does not create an effective guarantee against torture in respect of extradited persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1657.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1669.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even so, according to the government's submission, the visits were allegedly held in 2014, 2015, 2018 and 2019.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1669.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1673.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, the government's argument is refuted by their own information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1673.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1689.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No visits were ever made in 2016, 2017 as well as 2020 in view of the COVID-19 health crisis and the state of emergency declared by the Kyrgyzstani government in March.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1689.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1696.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And by the moment, it is still unclear for how long such state will continue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1696.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1716.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition to this, as it follows from the letter of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, which was received by the Russian Prosecutor's General Office in late September 2020, the diplomats were never informed in advance about forthcoming extraditions from Russia to Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1716.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1734.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows from the above-mentioned letter that only in the beginning of 2020, the Russian and the Kyrgyzstani authorities managed to reach an agreement on the necessary measures to be taken to ensure granting access to the extradited persons in a timely manner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1734.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1740.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It proves that all the previous visits of Russian diplomats were belated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1740.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1749.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, they were ineffective as the risk of ill-treatment reaches its highest point in the first days after the extradition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1749.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1754.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But since 2020, there have been no visits at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1754.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1760.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It means that the monitoring mechanism has never shown any effectiveness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1760.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1766.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And last but not least is the procedure of the inspections and its results.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1766.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1781.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows from the letter of the Russian Ministry of Foreign Affairs that even the most basic requirement of such kind of inspections, the confidentiality of the visits, is hardly ensured in many cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1781.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1802.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, even if the procedure results in revealing facts of torture, it is not clear either from the government's submission or from the legislative acts or international treaties what kind of actions can be taken by the Kyrgyzstani law enforcement agencies after the Russian authorities address them through their diplomatic channels.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1802.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1811.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Anyway, the question whether the Kyrgyz party is obliged to act in reply remains without an answer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1811.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1822.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In confirmation of their position in respect of the usage of the diplomatic assurances, the government refers to the case of Mamat Kulov and Askar of Messrs. Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1822.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1833.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, they underline that the court was satisfied by the fact that Turkish diplomats visited the extradited persons in the Uzbekistani prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1833.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1843.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet more than 80 people visited Mr. Mamat Kulov and Askar of and only two of them were the officials of the Turkish embassy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1843.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1852.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The rest of the visitors represented other embassies and an independent international NGO, Helsinki Watch.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1852.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1860.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In comparison, in the present case, the government suggests that the visits of only Russian diplomatic staff would be enough.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1860.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1871.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We assert that effective functioning of a diplomatic monitoring mechanism requires involvement of independent international actors, including NGOs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1871.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1884.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, nothing in the present cases gives us even a hint that the Kyrgyzstani authorities are ready to allow presence of independent inspectors in their places of detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1884.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1891.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Summing up the applicants' arguments in the present case, I should point out the following issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1891.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1901.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the applicants belong to a particular vulnerable group, members of which face real and imminent risk of ill-treatment if extradited to Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1901.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1911.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is not only because they are ethnic Uzbeks, but because they are ethnic Uzbeks with a 100% probability of imprisonment in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1911.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1918.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Next, widespread practice of abuse and discrimination of ethnic Uzbeks still exists in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1918.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1934.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third, introduced mechanisms of control and supervision over the rights of the detainees, especially those of the Uzbek ethnic origin, do not work effectively and have no positive prospects for that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1934.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1944.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For these reasons, the applicants believe that their extradition to Kyrgyzstan will violate their rights under Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1944.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1944.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1948.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1952.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed to the applicants' representatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1952.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1958.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I just want to confirm that both audio and video were clear throughout and your submissions were noted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1958.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1960.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Galperin, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1963.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1967.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President and honorable judges of the court, good morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1968.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1979.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case is based on the applicants allegations that they could become victims of all treatment after extradition to the country of their citizenship, Kyrgyzstan for criminal prosecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1979.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1988.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicants believe that the general situation in Kyrgyzstan and their ethnic origin make the relevant risk so high.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1988.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1993.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for complete ban of their return to their motherland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1993.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1997.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we consider these allegations to be ill-founded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1997.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2013.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And under the convention and these courts practice, just the abstract fears of the applicants and the subjective views of their representative of the current political situation in Kyrgyzstan should not be essence of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2013.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2041.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The core legal issue under their consideration of the grand chamber today, as we see, that should be the monitoring mechanism, but not the NPM or the results of the recent presidential elections in Kyrgyzstan and the political party where the president of Kyrgyzstan is the member of.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2041.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2053.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is just the monitoring mechanism specially developed and maintained by the Russian government in collaboration with a non-member state in accordance with this court previous case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2053.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2073.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to mention that once again, this monitoring mechanism was specially developed as the reaction on the European Court of Human Rights case law to make sure that these precedents and these practices is duly endorsed in these cooperation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2073.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2080.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for several years, it provides effective protection for extradited person from the alleged risk of ill-treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2080.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2089.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And at the same time, it gives an opportunity for proper legal cooperation and crime fighting in the CIS region.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2089.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2104.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no examples of any actual failures, but just only potential failures as the representatives mentioned today, every actual specific failures of these monitoring mechanisms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2104.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2119.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this application to the grand chamber is actually from our point of view, is just the attempt to undermine this carefully designed diplomatic mechanism without any proper arguments and evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2119.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2133.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before elaborating on these issues in more detail, please let me recall briefly the key findings of the chamber in the case as the president highlighted in the beginning of the hearings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2133.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2145.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, chamber decided that the situation in Kyrgyzstan did not in itself show that they would be a violation of the convention if the applicants extradited there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2145.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2156.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, ethnic Uzbeks no longer constitutes a vulnerable group facing risks of all ill-treatment only in connection with their origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2156.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2169.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third, and it is important what also to the chamber have decided, that the applicants had failed to provide strong evidence that they would run a risk of ill-treatment in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2169.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2186.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Last but not least, the diplomatic assurances and the monitoring mechanism created by the Russian and Kyrgyz authorities were capable of mitigating possible risks of ill-treatment in connection with the applicants' ethnical origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2186.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2198.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we, my government, for sure support and welcome these findings of the chamber, and we hope that the grand chamber will endorse them as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2198.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2207.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now touch upon each of the findings with a special emphasis on the monitoring mechanism, as I have mentioned at the beginning of my speech.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2207.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2243.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And answering again the applicants' allegations concerning general situation with ill-treatment in Kyrgyzstan, especially in respect of persons of non-Kyrgyz ethnic origin, I recall the court's judgments in the case of Turgunov versus Russia and Madali versus Russia, where it was stated that although current human rights situation in the country was problematic, at the time there was no indication that it had ever been serious enough to call for a total ban of extradition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2243.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2262.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, it is the court's practice to evaluate human rights protection in its development, taking into account indications of improvement or deterioration of the situation in general, or in respect of a particular group or area relevant to the applicant's situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2262.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2275.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the effectiveness of the Kyrgyz authorities' efforts to combat ill-treatment has been systematically assessed by international organization and respected council of the applicants also have mentioned that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2275.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2320.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, we will address again the UN subcommittee on prevention of torture and other cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment noted the following positive changes in their reports of 2019, also including the involvement of civil society members in the functioning of the national preventive mechanisms, the decreased number of incidents of denial of access or delays in assessing places of detention, enhanced visibility of the mechanisms since most of the authorities are aware of its existence, the establishment of practice to draft reports to the competent authorities after the visit to a place of detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2320.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2341.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My respected opponents also have mentioned the Amnesty International again, that still in their public statement highlighted that Kyrgyzstan accepted most of recommendations of the working group for universal periodic review, including those eradicating torture and ill-treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2341.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2370.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And after them, again, these inter-ethnic clashes in 2010, the Kyrgyz authorities have taken a number of steps, as we know from the Kyrgyz government and from the analysis made by the Russian Minister of Foreign Affairs, to address the issues of discrimination of national minorities, including ethnic Uzbeks, both in law and practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2370.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2382.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>International observers report that the instances of ethnic discrimination have not occurred in Kyrgyzstan on any kind of massive or systematic scale in the recent years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2382.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2397.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2018, the UN Committee of Elimination of Racial Discrimination noted that the concerns in this regard have switched more to the political sphere and not to the ill-treatment in prisons and detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2397.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2409.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>European Union annual reports mark the overall human rights situation as stable and indicate consistent positive changes in combating torture in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2409.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2427.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Interestingly, and it's also some recent facts, that even the Uzbekistan itself, the Uzbekistan state authorities do not appear to be considering that ethnic Uzbeks are being systematically persecuted or ill-treated in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2427.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2443.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, we are aware in the very end of the last year of recent extradition proceedings in which the Uzbekistan authorities refused to bring charges against the Kyrgyz citizen of Uzbek origin for committing and murdering Uzbekistan itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2443.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2458.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And instead, his criminal case was forwarded by Uzbekistan authorities to Kyrgyzstan as the state of citizenship for investigation and Russia was requested to extradite him there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2458.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2469.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be noted that situation with human rights protection in Kyrgyzstan, especially in respect of combating torture and ill-treatment has improved over the last 10 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2469.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2483.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And anyway, and we should be fair, you cannot demand the same high standards of the human rights protection for the council of your country and non-member state as Kyrgyz is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2483.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2504.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We cannot rely also on the mere fact and the mere risk of possibility of torture and ill-treatment to prevent extradition between countries, especially when there are international legal obligations and mechanism mitigating such risk as in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2504.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2517.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I would turn with the permission of the court to the analysis of the individual circumstances of the applicants, also answering on my opponents' counsel's allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2517.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2533.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to these courts' case law, the mere belongings of the applicants to the vulnerable minority group due to their ethnicity is not in itself indicative that the applicants run a risk of ill-treatment in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2533.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2547.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another important issue is the nature of the charges brought against the extradited persons, and I'm not sure that my opponents have spent enough time to describe that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2547.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2567.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>General criminal nature of the charges related to violent and economic crimes normally does not lead to the conclusion that the extradited persons face a risk of ill-treatment in the request-making state as opposite to religious or political charges, which is not the case here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2567.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2571.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In light of applicable case law, Mr. Khasanov and Mr. Rahmanov</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2571.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2585.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>cannot be considered as being exposed to ill-treatment in the event of their extradition to Kyrgyzstan merely because they belong to a vulnerable minority group or due to the charges brought against them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2585.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2589.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Khasanov did allege on several occasions that criminal proceedings</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2589.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2593.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>against him were ethnically biased.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2593.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2599.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the national authorities held that these claims were unfounded due to the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2599.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2610.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the information provided by the applicant to the Russian authorities on his alleged participation in inter-ethnic clashes in 2010 was controversial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2610.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2633.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant failed to describe the extent of his participation and made only general submissions about the situation in the region and that time, and that information did not contain any specific facts demonstrating his active involvement in the events or showing that Kyrgyz authorities prosecute the applicant on respective grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2633.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2650.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, during the refugee-seeking procedure, the applicant initially confirmed that before he left Kyrgyzstan, he had been interrogated as a witness in the criminal case initiated in relation to his business activities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2650.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2660.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the nature of the charges, there had been no issue of political or ethnic persecution as such, since they were of purely economic nature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2660.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2676.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only reason advanced by the applicant, which allegedly ties his criminal prosecution in Kyrgyzstan to the inter-ethnic tension in 2010, was that it was initiated, as he said, in the wake of the clashes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2676.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2685.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This, however, does not demonstrate either the ethnical bias of the prosecution or its relation to these specific political events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2685.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2704.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As for the facts of extortion of the applicant's property, they seem to be triggered by his financial situation and professional activities rather than his ethnicity, and the applicant failed to prove that the people involved in the extortion were acting on behalf or with knowledge of the state officials.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2704.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2718.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, the applicant and his relatives had never been subjected in Kyrgyzstan to any form of cruel or derogating treatment of any ground, and we have no evidence of the contrary today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2718.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2723.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As for Mr. Rahmanov, the following facts of his case were taken into</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2723.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2733.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>account at the domestic level in Russia during the assessment of the risks of ill treatment he could possibly face in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2733.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2743.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the applicant indicated that he left Kyrgyzstan in the early 2011 in order to work in Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2743.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2753.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, it was the employment issues rather than the fear of prosecution that forced the applicant to move from Kyrgyzstan to Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2753.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2766.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, during 2011, the applicant humorously entered Russian Federation for working purposes. During the period from 2011 to 2014,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2766.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2770.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicant returned to Kyrgyzstan at least on two occasions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2770.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2778.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He had no obstacles whatsoever in entering and leaving Kyrgyzstan both times freely.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2778.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2783.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Meanwhile, Mr. Rahmanov's family, including his wife, his children,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2783.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2797.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>his grandchildren, had been residing in Kyrgyzstan, and according to the applicant, did not experience any form of discrimination or mistreatment by the authorities due to their ethnicity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2797.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2806.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, during the whole period of his presence in Russia, the applicant had never applied for refugee status in the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2806.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2817.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, according to the applicant's submissions, he has not participated in inter-ethnic clashes in 2010 and has never been prosecuted on political grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2817.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2824.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He is not a social activist or a participant to any political or religious movement either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2824.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2837.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, neither the personal circumstances of the applicant's case nor the nature of their charges prove the existence of a particular risk of ill-treatment on ethnic grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2837.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2854.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I would turn to the assessment of the quality and reliability of the legal assurances given by the Kyrgyzstan authorities and the complementing monitoring mechanism ensuring the effective application, as I have promised in the beginning of my presentation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2854.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2866.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And first, I would respectfully submit that the legal assurances given in the applicant's respect meet all requirements of this court case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2866.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2870.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, special attention should be paid to the following features.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2870.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2887.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the assurances given by the Kyrgyzstan authorities in the present case were not just diplomatic assurances, but rather confirmation of the firm legal obligations and the various legal instruments in the sphere of human rights protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2887.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2897.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the assurances were provided by the Kyrgyz prosecutor general office, which is authorized to supervise law enforcement in the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2897.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2907.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, these assurances are legal in nature, and they are not only formally abiding on the Kyrgyzstan authorities, but also practically enforceable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2907.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2922.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then the assurances are supplemented by additional guarantees, allowing Russian diplomatic staff to carry out monitoring visits to the places of an applicant's detention after they are transferred to Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2922.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2937.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under these guarantees, Russian embassy in Kyrgyzstan monitors regularly the situation with the persons transferred to Kyrgyzstan for the purpose of criminal prosecution, including minorities, and the manner in which the rights of such persons are protected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2937.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2942.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to mention that the special monitoring mechanism is a special mechanism.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2942.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2949.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It could not work to protect all Kyrgyzstan population, including minorities, from ill treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2949.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2959.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is specially designed to protect people extradited from Russia to Kyrgyzstan and to ensure that their rights are protected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2959.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2970.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In carrying out this mission, Russian embassy in Kyrgyzstan and its diplomatic staff are being governed by so-called methodological instructions, which was mentioned by my learned opponents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2970.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2981.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And these detailed instructions have been prepared by Russian Minister of Foreign Affairs, as it was mentioned, with cooperation of Russian Prosecutor General Office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2981.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2998.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they established a legal framework for performing monitoring visits of the Russian diplomatic staff to penal institutions in Kyrgyzstan, where the persons extradited from Russia are detained, awaiting criminal trial or serving criminal sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2998.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3006.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These instructions are supplemented by compilation of this court practice on the prohibition of ill treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3006.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3018.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And these materials have been regularly and officially conveyed to the Russian diplomatic staff involved in the monitoring mission, and the last occasion being in November 2020.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3018.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3028.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Diplomatic visits always involve private conversations with the detainees, performed in accessible language or with the assistance of the interpreter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3028.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3039.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those conversations concern their possible mistreatment, conditions of their detention, medical assistance, or any other irregularities visited persons could possibly face.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3039.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3056.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Particular attention is paid to possible complaints filed by the visited persons to local administration and the results of the examination, and any possible obstacles in communicating with diplomatic staff, the enjoyment of the rights to visits and the legal aid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3056.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3064.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As for the applicants' concerns of the non-binding nature of the monitoring mechanism, they are unsubstantiated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3064.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3073.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And any suspicions on mistreatment of the visited persons or the Russian authorities are requested to resolve them through diplomatic channels.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3073.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3078.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also such information will be taken into account in the future extradition proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3078.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3088.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for sure, that's really the legal nature of that assurances, since they are checked during the new extradited proceedings in Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3088.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3102.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if it will work bad, and if they will not be insured, then nobody will be extradited to Kyrgyzstan under the decisions of Russian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3102.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3127.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And however, therefore, the modalities of diplomatic cooperation based on the principle of reciprocity, and that's also the legal ground on the international law, that the reciprocity additionally contribute to the parties' adherence to the assurances as requested by these courts' case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3127.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3143.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, the respondent state could not be reasonably expected to exercise any kind of direct control over the observance by Kyrgyzstan of the given assurances and human rights law in general.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3143.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3160.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This would be contrary to the basic principles of international law prohibiting interference in sovereign states' affairs, and only monitoring is possible, and it follows from the Baffet that this has been effectively conducted by the Russian government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3160.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3167.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Monitoring missions show that in the majority of cases, the prisoners were satisfied with their treatment by the Kyrgyz authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3167.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3186.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And only on one occasion after the visit to the temporary detention facility number 5 in the city of Osh in 2015, the mission has recommended improving the provision of detainee mister imaminov with necessary medications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3186.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3194.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Detainees themselves consider this monitoring mechanism as an effective remedy capable of protecting their rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3194.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3218.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, there are several examples of cases where a Kyrgyz national extradited from Russia to Kyrgyzstan, applied to the Russian authorities, applied to the Russian embassy, and the Russian embassy have received, really received these applications, and where they asked and requested their visit under the diplomatic monitoring mechanism.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3218.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3228.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the monitoring mechanism provides an effective avenue for ensuring the compliance of the requesting state with the assurances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3228.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3243.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As for the third party's assertion that the monitoring would only be effective if conducted by an independent human rights protection organization, and my learned opponents also have mentioned that today, it doesn't follow from the court's case law, really.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3243.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3268.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the effectiveness of the state diplomatic monitoring mission could not in principle be made conditional on the assistance of some non-governmental organization, especially those registered in another state, and which state, again, is not a member state of the Council of Europe, and where these courts' power and is not belong to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3268.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3283.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any case, the applicants fail to indicate in what way the existing mechanism of visit is deficient in the absence of such assistance of non-governmental organization in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3283.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3291.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same goes to the allegation that the visiting officials need special psychological and other relevant training.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3291.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3296.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would say that our diplomats are properly trained and instructed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3296.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3300.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These additional requirements also doesn't fall from this court's case law again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3300.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3313.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in the case of Mamak Tuluf and Askarov versus Turkey, which was mentioned today, the court was satisfied with the monitoring conducted via diplomatic channels by the members of the Turkish embassy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3313.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3329.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, I would like to respectfully address dissenting opinion to the Chamber's judgment in the present case, being possible reasons for its referral to the Grand Chamber after the positive for the government, the positive decision of the Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3329.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3342.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in particular, both judges proposed that the Chamber should have examined the facts of the applicants' criminal cases to decide whether there was a violation of the applicants' rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3342.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3347.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I believe that such an approach is inappropriate with all respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3347.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3365.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It obliged this court, the Supreme Court of Human Rights, to re-evaluate not only the findings of the Russian courts and Russian authorities, which could be contrary to the principle of subsidiarity, but also those of the Kyrgyz authorities, which falls outside the court's jurisdiction at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3365.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3375.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The concept of extradition is limited in international law and always limited in international law and practiced by the strict legal conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3375.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3396.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They do not require the requesting state to go into deep, substantive analysis of the charges brought against the extradited person or to evaluate their validity, except for the clear and confirmed cases of prosecution with improper hidden motive, which is not in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3396.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3403.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The questions raised by the applicants in these proceedings have been numerously addressed in the court's jurisprudence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3403.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3411.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite these facts, the present case is different from those already resolved by this court in one important aspect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3411.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3422.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for the first time, the court has positively assessed the government's efforts to ensure compatibility of the extradition proceedings with the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3422.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3434.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I sincerely hope that the Grand Chamber will support these conclusions to give governments more willingness and desire to develop this success and to develop these legal instruments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3434.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3439.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we ask to uphold Chamber's judgment and dismiss all the applicants' complaints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3439.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3439.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I'm grateful for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3443.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3445.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Galperin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3445.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3452.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also confirm that both audio and video of your intervention was clear and satisfactory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3452.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3458.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to my fellow judges of the Grand Chamber who wish to pose questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3458.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3460.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Seibert-Fohr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Anja Seibert-Fohr</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3465.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3467.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3469.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3471.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Anja, and then Judge Sabato.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3471.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3472.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Seibert-Fohr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Anja Seibert-Fohr</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3473.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3475.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3475.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3479.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to thank the parties for their submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3479.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3493.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first question is directed to the applicants' representatives and concerns the relationship between the alleged crimes and the events of June 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3493.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3507.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, with respect to the misappropriation charges brought against the first applicant, is there any factual evidence in support of the allegation that they are based on ethnic bias?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3507.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3522.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would think that everyone accused of this kind of crime would claim insufficient evidence, but does this prove that the charges are ethnically motivated?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3522.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3532.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With respect to the second applicant, I would like to hear more about the complaint that the murder and other charges were, in fact, fabricated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3532.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3546.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it enough nowadays to claim that the charges related to the inter-ethnic clashes of 2010 in order to find a real risk of ill treatment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3546.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3554.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to emphasize that we are taking a current perspective, excellent perspective here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3554.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3571.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, assuming that the charges were indeed ethnically motivated, one might ask, why then did the applicants apply for a refugee status, one of the applicants, only several years after coming to Russia?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3571.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3590.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, I would like to know from both parties whether and why ethnic Uzbeks are at a heightened risk of ill treatment in detention in Kyrgyzstan nowadays compared to in the years after the clashes of 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3590.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3618.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I understood the applicant's representative to making this kind of claim, but I would like to have a little bit more of a clarification because so far what we've heard are allegations about the commission of torture, and this is somewhat related to the ethnic Uzbeks, but I haven't heard anything supporting this kind of allegation brought forward by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3618.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3625.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then, in this respect, the question is also asked, who has to prove this kind of aspect?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3625.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3630.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning now to the government representative, I would like to ask as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3630.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3641.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Did the domestic courts sufficiently evaluate the individual risks in light of the court's jurisprudence at the relevant time, including with respect to the assurances?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3641.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3641.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3642.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3643.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3643.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3644.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Sabato.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Raffaele Sabato</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3649.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3677.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court asked already within the framework of the general questions to the parties in preparation of today's hearing whether the assurances provided by the Kyrgyz authorities in respect of the applicants had legal effects, were binding and reliable, and met with all the other requirements set out in the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3677.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3705.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Replying to the above concerning the binding character, the government in their observations before the grand chamber, I think this is in paragraph 68, qualified the assurances as being a sort of statement of confirmation of the obligations undertaken by Kyrgyzstan under the Minsk Convention of 1993.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3705.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3711.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also other instruments are mentioned, but they are not specifically indicated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3711.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3717.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants, on the contrary, in general denied such binding effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3717.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3741.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is, can the parties, and in particular the government, clarify in which way this Minsk Convention or any other international instrument is relevant in order for the court to assess the binding effect, and especially under which specific provision?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3741.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3751.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is this provision also relied upon explicitly or implicitly in the documents we have?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3751.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3751.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3753.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3755.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Judge Yudkivska.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ganna Yudkivska</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3758.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3760.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3760.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3768.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to ask the government to clarify certain issues related to the assurances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3768.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3787.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, to what extent the assurance mechanism has changed over the past years so that the court could come to a different assessment than in Khamarokulov versus Russia judgment of 2015?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3787.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3800.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More specifically, and also to amend the question put by Judge Sabato, what is the legal basis for monitoring mechanism by the diplomatic staff?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3800.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3808.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We just heard from the applicants that there is no solid legal basis apart from the instructions referred to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3808.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3816.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, are visits scheduled for the early phase of detention, meaning after the transfer?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3816.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3825.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, what about the restrictions that according to the applicants made the mechanism fragile?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3825.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3829.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why is there is a need for prior authorization for the visits?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3829.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3836.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we heard this morning from the applicants that there is no guarantee that such a request will be granted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3836.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3853.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And why should Kyrgyz authorities be allowed to be physically present during the visits, even though they are prevented from listening to what is being said, and you have just confirmed that those visits should be private?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3853.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3853.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3854.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3856.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. I turn to Judge Hseynov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ltif Hseynov</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3859.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3861.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3861.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3867.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to follow up on the question put to my distinguished colleague, Ms. Zeibert,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3869.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3875.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on concerning the vulnerability of ethnic Uzbeks in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3878.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3891.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So my question is addressed more to the applicants, but of course the government could also answer to this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3891.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3899.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So could you give please more details concerning the practical, particular vulnerability of ethnic Uzbeks?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3902.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3916.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Information, more detailed information on to what extent they are persecuted and more particularly, they are subjected to ill treatment because of their ethnic origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3918.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3932.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And whether this real risk of being subjected to ill treatment is related to their ethnic origin or it's more related to the 2010 events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3932.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3932.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3933.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3934.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3934.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3935.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Koskelo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Pauliine Koskelo</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3938.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3939.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3939.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3954.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to pose a factual question which either party might address concerning the situation of the second applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3954.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3977.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We learned from the applicant's submissions that both charges and extradition requests against other people have been made in connection with the same events of which the second applicant has been charged with.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3977.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3993.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wonder if we have any information regarding what has happened to these other persons who have been charged with and in respect of whom extradition requests have been made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3993.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3997.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do we have any information what has happened in those cases?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3997.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3997.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3999.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4000.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4000.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4004.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No other judges have asked to pose questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4004.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4015.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We will now suspend the hearing for approximately 25 minutes until 11.30 local time, 1.30 Moscow time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4015.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4019.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we will be back at 11.30 sharp.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4019.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4019.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hearing is suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4439.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4439.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4446.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4448.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Good morning again. The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4448.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4455.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We now turn to the applicants' representatives for their replies to the questions of the judges and their rebuttal arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4455.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4455.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Zharinov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4463.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4470.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Judges, I would like to thank you for the question and I will try to answer them now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4470.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4488.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the first question of the Honorable Judge Zybert for concerning the relationship between crimes and the events, especially in the case of Tay-K and the factual evidence of ethnic bias.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4488.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4498.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, the criminal prosecution against the first applicant was initiated in the wake of the ethnic clashes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4498.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4501.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was initiated shortly after that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4501.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4508.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The clashes were in June 2010 and the criminal prosecution was initiated in September 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4508.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4526.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it concerned the facts that took place a lot earlier in 2008, but only after the clashes, one of the colleagues of the applicant initiated the criminal proceedings against him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4526.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4530.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this colleague was of Kyrgyz ethnicity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4530.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4534.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So he decided to initiate the criminal proceedings only after the clashes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4534.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4543.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although he knew about the events, he had known about them for two years, but initiated only after the clashes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4543.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4555.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hoping that tension, the whole ethnic bias against ethnic Uzbeks maybe will help to somehow oppress the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4555.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4562.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was possible only after the clashes to initiate such vague criminal charges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4562.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4572.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning the question that the applicants applied for refugee status only a few years after coming to Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4572.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4576.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, the applicants resided in Russia perfectly legally.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4576.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4583.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no risk of refoulement before they found out that they were internationally wanted persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4583.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4595.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And only after their arrest, when they found out that there was a risk of refoulement, when they fully realized that they were charged and the underlying reason of these charges, they applied for refugee status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4595.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4607.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to bring the attention of the court to the fact that the Russian law on refugees does not oblige to apply to refugee status immediately after crossing the border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4607.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4615.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those people who stay in Russia legally, only those who cross the border illegally must apply immediately.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4615.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4623.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But those who stay legally, there is no such obligation for that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4623.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4632.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Next, about the ethnic motives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4632.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4635.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No, I'm sorry. Just one moment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4635.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4644.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yeah. About the fabrication of the charges against the applicant, especially in respect to the second applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4644.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4648.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are clear indicators of the fabrication of the charges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4648.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4652.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the applicants cross the border without any problems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4652.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4662.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second applicant crossed the Russian and the Russian border and other borders from 2011 to 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4662.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4665.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is stated in our submissions in the government submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4665.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4678.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the criminal case against him was allegedly initiated in 2012, two years before he stopped his travels.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4678.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4686.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if he had really been charged, if he had been an internationally wanted person, he couldn't just freely move and cross the borders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4686.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4699.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It may lead to the conclusion that it was just backdated, that in fact the criminal charges were initiated later, not in 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4699.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4703.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's one of the indicators of the fabrication of the whole case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4703.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4723.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And another factor is that there are a lot of other people of Uzbek ethnicity who were also charged with absolutely identical charges, not just analogous, but absolutely identical, word by word.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4723.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4727.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But they are not mentioned in the applicant's criminal documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4727.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4732.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in their documents, they are mentioned only and the applicant is not mentioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4732.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4741.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there is one case with identical charges who are just used to charge this or that person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4741.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4748.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there is allegedly no connection between them, but they are all known for the Kyrgyz authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4748.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4756.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if it was a normal criminal procedure, they would be all mentioned in the criminal documents as accomplices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4756.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4759.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But what do the Kyrgyzstani authorities do?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4759.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4766.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They just change the name, change the name and the charges remain the same.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4766.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4769.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is very, very strange.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4769.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4774.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we have in detail described it in our written submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4774.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4781.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would also like to bring the attention of other, to the situations of other people of ethnic origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4781.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4789.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What happened to them when they were extradition requests from Kyrgyzstan to have them back?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4789.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4790.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What happened to them?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4790.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4798.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Most of these people, they are also charged with identical crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4798.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4805.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And most of them, they are in Russia legally staying and having temporary asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4805.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4821.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In most cases, the Russian courts, without even any interference from the European court in the recent years, the Russian court have themselves annulled the extradition requests, the extradition orders to Kyrgyzstan, expressly referring to the risk of ill treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4821.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4826.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in the cases of Mr. Hassan Bayev, also the alleged accomplice of the applicant,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4826.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4832.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Sarimshakov, Mr. Talibayev, annulled, extradition orders annulled here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4832.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4839.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the general prosecutor's office also denied extradition itself in some cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4839.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4846.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in the case of Mr. Akbarov, also an ethnic Uzbek, charged with absolutely identical crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4846.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4850.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were all granted asylum in Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4850.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4858.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that is one of the explanations why the statistics of the government concerning the extradited persons to Kyrgyzstan is not very representative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4858.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4865.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just three or eight cases of monitoring, because they are not extradited usually due to the risk of ill treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4865.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4874.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our case is just some unfortunate example where the applicants were just not lucky.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4874.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4886.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And is more an exclusion from the general practice of the Russian courts and migration authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4886.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4903.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to answer the, to say a few words in respect to the question of the Honorable Judge Sabat concerning the binding effect and on which provision does the binding effect is based relating to the diplomatic monitoring mechanism.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4903.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4907.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is there any provision in the means convention or not?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4907.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4916.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No, there are no provisions in the means convention concerning such diplomatic assurances at all, let alone their binding effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4916.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4926.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we would also like to underline that we don't understand the value of such assurances at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4926.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4932.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because what source of international law gives them a binding effect?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4932.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4937.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no treaty, as we know, there is no international custom or something.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4937.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4940.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What are these assurances?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4940.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4943.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just some unilateral voluntary acts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4943.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4951.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't understand how they can be enforced as our learned colleague from the government emphasized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4951.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4952.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is that?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4952.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4962.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But there are already treaties, there are already international customs that bind Kyrgyzstan and that obliged Kyrgyzstan not to torture people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4962.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4967.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is already guaranteed by other, by the international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4967.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4977.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So what is the value of some additional guarantees of some unclear legal nature to again emphasize that we will not torture people?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4977.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4984.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maybe it doesn't give any more trustworthiness to such assurances, maybe even more doubts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4984.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4990.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are already international treaties, why again guaranteeing that we will not torture people?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4990.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5001.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the potential value of the assurances may be found only in the diplomatic monitoring mechanism.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5001.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5005.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the diplomatic monitoring mechanism is very weakly developed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5005.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5015.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we have already elaborated on this issue in detail in our submissions and in our today's speech.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5015.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5022.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government surprisingly stated that the visits are always confidential.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5022.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5027.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this is refuted by the letter of the Russian Ministry of the Interior.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5027.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5035.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm sorry, Russian Ministry for the Internal, for Foreign Affairs of 2020.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5035.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5039.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They expressly state that not all visits were confidential.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5039.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5044.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were problems with that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5044.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5052.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Next, I'd like to say just a few words about the vulnerability of ethnic Uzbeks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5052.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5065.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is vulnerability more concerned with the criminal charges or with the ethnic ethnicity itself?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5065.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5072.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, the conflict between Kyrgyz and Uzbeks have a very long history.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5072.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5077.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And these roots are deeply in the history.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5077.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5079.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is not the first conflict in 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5079.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5084.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is high tension between those nationalities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5084.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5101.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And after the conflict, just one of the conflict of 2010, it was just one of the forms of oppression of ethnic Uzbeks to criminally prosecute them with participation in the conflict.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5101.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5111.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But there were other forms of oppression not related to the conflict itself, but to a long history of tension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5111.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5118.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The conflict was just one of the starting points and one of the way to oppress them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5118.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5137.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Other criminal charges like charges of misappropriation are also a way of persecuting one of our applicants because of his ethnicity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5137.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5151.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I suppose that's all I wanted to say.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5151.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5152.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5153.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5155.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5155.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5156.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr Galperin, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5158.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5161.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. Thank you very much, Mr. President, judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5161.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5165.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your questions, which gives us opportunity to clarify our position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5166.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5173.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, I would just to mention several things which my learned opponents have mentioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5173.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5183.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, about some repetitive cases of the prosecution, criminal prosecution, I would say that in the Rahmanov case, it was a group crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5183.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5186.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it was several persons which were involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5186.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5195.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is why the factual grounds for that could be the same, because that's a group crime and a group murder and a destroyment of the assets.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5195.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5208.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, my opponent answering the honorable judge's question mentioned that it's not all cases when the Uzbeks extradited from Russia to Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5208.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5224.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In a lot of cases, there is a refusal to do that, which really means that there is a differentiated practice which is based on the European Court of Human Rights practice and human rights considerations, which are accurately considered in each case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5224.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5235.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would say that in these two cases here, they are not just surprising or it's made by case, because both cases went through the Russian Supreme Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5235.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5244.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Russian Supreme Court in both cases have confirmed that there is the grounds for extradition or there is no grounds not to extradite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5244.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5256.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, I would object on the proposal of the opponent saying that Uzbek-Kyrgyz conflict was just started in 2010 and now it's continuing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5256.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5258.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no evidence of that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5258.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5264.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also, we see in international organization reports that there could be discrimination of Uzbeks, but it's not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5264.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5279.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It goes to some political sphere, but there is no anything which is connected with the criminal convictions, illegal criminal convictions, and ill-treatment in prisons, especially on ethnic origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5279.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5286.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I would like to respectfully answer on the questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5286.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5294.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as we understood from the judges' questions that maybe we should tell a little bit about just the scale of the problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5294.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5295.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So how many people extradited?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5295.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5298.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would say that it's not thousands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5298.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5310.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's just 12 extradited, non-ethnic original extradited from Russia to Kyrgyzstan and now in detention in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5310.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5314.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only 12 people which extradited from Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5314.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5318.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Each of them, for sure, is under special control of Russian embassy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5318.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5329.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also, in his speech, my opponent mentioned about the Askarov case as showing the discrimination and ill-treatment of Uzbeks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5329.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5333.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But Askarov has never been extradited from Russia to Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5333.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5340.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He lived in Kyrgyzstan, so it's not really have any connection with this case and the problem we are discussing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5340.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5348.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>About and answering on the question of Judge Shabat, about what are the judges about the legal framework.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5348.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5358.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would say this Article 66 of the Minsk Convention would provide for the limitation of the criminal prosecution of people extradited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5358.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5363.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And which is also more important in Article 3 of UN Convention against Torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5363.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5391.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would say that Article 3 is also referred in the decisions of the Russian courts, including the Russian court's decision on these two cases, which is in the case file, which also refer on Article 3 of UN Convention against Torture, which provides for the different measures which the country should make to make sure that extradited people should not be ill-treated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5391.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5398.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for sure, as I mentioned, it is the well-established principle of reciprocity international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5398.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5404.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for sure, as I mentioned in my speech, it is European Convention of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5404.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5417.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this court practice, which really developed and forced us to develop this practice and have legal grounds in European Court of Human Rights practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5417.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5428.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the questions of Judge Yudkivsky about the changing of this mechanism's development, I would say that's 2017.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5428.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5435.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was the year when these detailed methodological instructions were issued and developed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5435.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5440.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also, they are obligatory for all Russian embassies in the respective countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5440.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5443.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they were sent to them, so it's development there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5443.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5469.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, I would just inform that last year in 2020, it was a new agreement between the Department of Consulate of Kyrgyzstan and General Prosecution Office of Kyrgyzstan and Russian authorities about making the move fast over them, receiving and receiving the access of the diplomatic authorities to the detainees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5469.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5471.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's in the development.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5471.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5492.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, as it was mentioned in the question of Judge Yudkivsky about that we were rejected in several times, and I think it also was mentioned by the applicants councils about rejection about the access of diplomatic staff to meet these detainees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5492.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5493.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was not true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5493.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5496.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we were never rejected for that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5496.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5499.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the procedure is long.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5499.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5508.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The procedure could be long because it considers Minister of Foreign Affairs and General Prosecutor Office, but there was no any rejection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5508.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5512.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have always success if Russian Minister of Foreign Affairs ask for that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5512.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5515.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as I said, we are now working with Kyrgyz authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5515.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5522.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there are now any practical step to make this process faster to receive the access.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5522.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5536.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, as I said about the confidentiality of meetings, and it was mentioned in the question, that's for sure that's really that we work on to be as confidential.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5536.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5548.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, for sure in several occasions, that couldn't be ensured because of reconstruction, really the construction of these buildings, of old buildings of prisons in Kyrgyzstan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5548.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5550.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for sure, it could be not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5550.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5553.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It could in some occasions could not be 100% confidential.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5553.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5571.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, as we understand, in most cases, that really the conversation between Russian diplomat and the detainees in Russian, which is not the case, that's all these people know Russian, I mean the administration of the prison authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5571.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5576.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in most cases, the confidentiality is secure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5576.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5592.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, I would say, and I would like to respectfully answer the Judge Hussainov question about the prosecution and really connection between the OSH events and that prosecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5592.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5608.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like, and we have this information from the Minister of Foreign Affairs and General Prosecution Office of Kyrgyzstan, that not only Uzbeks for sure, that the people of other nationalities, including mostly the Kyrgyz nationals were prosecuted for these events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5608.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5622.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it was not really focused, this prosecution was only focused on Uzbek authorities, which mostly Uzbek nationalities, which mostly live in this region, in OSH region.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5622.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5632.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's Kyrgyz, and we have real cases of Kyrgyz nationals to be prosecuted for their murders and other crimes in that field.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5632.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5654.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, I would like to answer the first question of the Judge Saibit-Fur, who kindly also addressed it to the government, not only to applicant, regarding really how courts has developed and examined how they examined these cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5654.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5680.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would say that if you will see the decision of 2015 of Belgorod District Court on the applicant's case, it is a several pages decision which also referring and examining manifest that the practice of amnesty international, and there was a referral at the court to that, Human Rights Watch and UN Committee Against Torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5680.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5692.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there's all these referrals in the decision of Russian courts, they examined the situation in complex, including their human rights consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5692.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5697.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I once again, thank you for your attention and this hearing, thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5698.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5701.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Galperin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5701.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5706.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do any of the judges want to follow up with any of the questions posed?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5706.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5708.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I do not see so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5708.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5711.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5711.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5718.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I want to thank the parties both for their cooperation in the organization of the hearing due to the crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5718.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5720.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5720.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5727.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered at a later date, and the court will inform the parties accordingly of the delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5727.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5728.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
