<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>2876111_03122013</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>20.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>20.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>59.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>60.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>77.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>89.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the cases of Al Nashiri and Husayn Abu Zubaydah against Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>89.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>106.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first application was lodged with the court on 6 May 2011, under Article 34 of the Convention by Saudi Arabian National Mr. Abd Al Rahim Hussayn Muhammad Al Nashiri.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>107.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>122.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second application was lodged with the court on 28 January 2013, under Article 34 of the Convention by stateless Palestinian Mr. Zayn Al-Abidin Muhammad Husayn,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>122.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>125.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>also known as Abu Zubaydah.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>125.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>135.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were allocated to the fourth section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>135.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>143.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cases were assigned to a chamber of the fourth section of the court, following the Rule 52, Paragraph 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>143.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>149.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application of Mr. Al Nashiri was communicated to the government</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>149.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>152.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on 10 July 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>152.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>174.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 13 September 2012, the President of the Chamber granted leave to the Helsinki Foundation for Human Rights, Amnesty International and the International Commission of Jurists to submit written comments as third parties by virtue of Rule 44, Paragraph 3 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>174.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>180.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 8 October 2012, the court granted leave to Mr. Ben Emmerson,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>180.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>193.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the United Nations Special Rapporteur on the Promotion and Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms while Countering Terrorism, to submit written comments as third party.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>193.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>198.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application of Mr. Abu Zubaydah</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>198.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>202.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was communicated to government on 9 July 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>202.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>214.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the same date, the court decided that the cases be examined simultaneously in accordance with Rule 42, Paragraph 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>214.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>230.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 2 October 2013, the President of the Chamber granted leave to Amnesty International and the International Commission of Jurists to submit written comments as a third party by virtue of Rule 44, Paragraph 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>230.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>239.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also invited the United Nations Special Rapporteur to take part in the public hearing held in both cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>239.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>254.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 2 December 2013, the court held a fact-finding hearing under Rule A1, Paragraphs 1 and 5 of the Annex to the Rules of Court and heard evidence from experts and witnesses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>254.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>268.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the same day, it also held a hearing in camera under Rule 63, Paragraph 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>268.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>274.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the present hearing, the defending government are represented by their agent, Mr. Artur Nowak-Far,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>274.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>281.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Undersecretary of State in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, assisted by Mr. Janusz Śliwa,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>281.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>288.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Deputy Krakow Prosecutor of Appeal, Ms. Justyna Chrzanowska,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>288.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>295.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Agent of the Government before the European Court of Human Rights, Ms. Aleksandra Męźykowska,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>295.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>301.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Co-Agent of the Government before the European Court of Human Rights, and Ms. Katarzyna Górska-Łazarz,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>301.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>306.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Advisor of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>306.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>309.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Al Nashiri is represented by his counsels,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>309.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>312.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Amrit Singh,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>312.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>315.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Mikolaj Pietrzak,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>315.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>317.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Rupert Skilbeck,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>317.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>320.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Ms. Nancy Hollander.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>320.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>322.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Abu Zubaydah is represented by his counsels,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>322.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>325.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Padraig Hughes,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>325.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>328.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Bartłomiej Jankowski,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>328.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>329.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Helen Duffy,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>329.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>332.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. Joseph Margulies,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>332.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>336.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and also by Mr. Crofton Black, Advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>336.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>339.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third party, Mr. Ben Emmerson,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>339.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>354.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the United Nations Special Rapporteur on the Promotion and Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms while Countering Terrorism, is present and is assisted by Ms. Anna Katulu, Advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>354.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>360.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>360.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>372.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agents of the government, the representatives of the applicant, and the third party, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>372.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>374.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Nowak-Far for the government will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>374.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>374.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Ms. Singh for the first applicant,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>374.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>382.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Hughes for the second applicant,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>382.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>387.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and finally Mr. Ben Emmerson, the United Nations Special Rapporteur.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>387.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>394.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that the representatives of the government will proceed with their submissions in Polish.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>394.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>411.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the Court, English and French, interpreting from Polish into English and French, and from English and French into Polish has been authorized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>411.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>411.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>427.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>432.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dziękuję bardzo. Wysoki Sądzie, szanowna Pani Przewodnicząca.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>434.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>445.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Postępowanie Trybunału zmierzają do ustalenia faktów, okoliczności faktycznych, na które powołują się skarżący.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>445.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>457.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sprawdzenie tych faktów przez Trybunał jest zdaniem rządu w sprzeczności z zasadą subsydiarności formułowaną przez sam Trybunał.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>457.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>468.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Zgodnie z tą zasadą najwłaściwiej jest, aby okoliczności sprawy były badane przez organy państwa i by państwo naprawiło ewentualną szkodę.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>468.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>473.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jest to zgodne z orzeczeniem w sprawie Warnawa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>473.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>481.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W tej sprawie konkretnej nie ma przesłanek do zastępowania organów krajowych przez Trybunał.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>481.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>496.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Okoliczności sprawy są bowiem badane i mają na celu ustalenie, czy działania, o które jest toczone całe to postępowanie, miało miejsce, a jeżeli tak, to kto jest za nie odpowiedzialny.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>496.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>514.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Polska jest obecnie jednym z niewielu państw, które podjęło się szczegółowego zbadania sprawy i ma w tym zakresie zaawansowane śledztwo, o czym świadczy naszym zdaniem nagromadzony materiał dowodowy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>514.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>526.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rząd Polski w związku z tym nie podejmuje się potwierdzenia albo zaprzeczenia przed Trybunałem okoliczności, które podnoszą skarżący.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>526.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>539.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Uważa bowiem, że powinny te okoliczności być ustalone i ocenione przez Krajowy Wymiar Sprawiedliwości, który działa zgodnie z narodowymi regułami.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>539.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>556.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Wierzymy, że działania tego wymiaru pozwolą na efektywne i rzetelne rozpoznanie sprawy, na tyle, na ile pozwalają również okoliczności międzynarodowe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>556.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>578.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Trybunał nie jest w tej sprawie konfrontowany z dwiema rozbieżnymi wersjami zdarzeń i w odniesieniu do których Trybunał mógłby wziąć na siebie rolę Sądu Pierwszej Instancji ustalającego fakty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>578.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>587.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Różnicuje to tę konkretną sprawę od okoliczności, które stały u podstaw orzeczenia Trybunału w sprawie El-Masri.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>587.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>607.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Trybunał, szanując na wczorajszym posiedzeniu in camera potrzebę ochrony informacji posiadanych przez świadków o źródłach potencjalnych dowodów, naszym zdaniem powinien również ze zrozumieniem odnieść się do potrzeby ochrony tajemnicy śledztwa toczącego się w kraju.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>607.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>640.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W przeciwieństwie do sprawy El-Masri, Polska przedstawia Trybunałowi informacje na temat przebiegu krajowego postępowania przygotowawczego, zaoferował również Trybunałowi dostęp do aktego postępowania w pewnym zakresie określonym regułami polskiego prawa, a to dlatego, że materiały odnoszą się do toczącego się śledztwa, które dla jego dobra musi być objęte tajemnicą.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>640.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>650.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W odniesieniu do artykułu 38 rząd oświadcza, że jest świadomy obowiązków współpracy z Trybunałem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>650.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>657.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Podjął więc działania, które zmierzały do zapoznania Trybunału ze szczegółami prowadzonego w Polsce śledztwa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>657.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>675.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rząd Polski zdaje sobie sprawę, że istnieje również zasada subsydiarności i wie, że istnieją również własne reguły dotyczące zachowania istotnych elementów postępowania przygotowawczego w tajemnicy ze względu na dobro śledztwa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>675.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>699.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rząd Polski zdaje sobie sprawę, że materiały, o które prosił i prosi Trybunał w kontekście sprawy Al-Nasri, ale już nie Abu Zubayda, mają umożliwić mu ustalenie zakresu i zaawansowania prowadzonego w Polsce postępowania przygotowawczego, choć niekoniecznie samych z wydarzeń, które miały mieć miejsce w Polsce w latach 2003-2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>699.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>736.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Procedury Trybunału są w swojej zasadniczej logice, nastawionej na przejrzystość i upublicznienie, w pewnej sprzeczności z regułami krajowymi, które dążą do wykazania w postępowaniu prokuratorskim wszystkich okoliczności sprawy, w tym zebrania takich dowodów, które mogłyby niezbicie udowodnić czyjąkolwiek winę i umożliwić skuteczne postawienie tej osoby przed sądem oraz wymierzenie takiej osobie kary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>736.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>750.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To powoduje fundamentalną sprzeczność systemów prawnych państw w stronę konwencji z żądaniem Trybunału wtedy, gdy utrzymanie tajemnicy jest konieczne i uzasadnione.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>750.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>754.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Z taką okolicznością w naszym przekonaniu mamy w tej sprawie do czynienia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>754.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>774.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Polska starała się zapoznać Trybunał z treścią jawną akt, zaproponowała również możliwość zapoznania się z dokumentem przygotowanym specjalnie dla Trybunału przez prokuratora apelacyjnego w Krakowie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>774.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>791.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dokument ten szczegółowie informował o toczącym się postępowaniu, zawierał więc informację niejawną, co wymagałoby wskazania osób, które z nią się zapoznały i zabezpieczenia dokumentów także w trakcie postępowania prowadzonego przed Trybunałem in camera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>791.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>795.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Trybunał jednak z tej oferty nie zechciał skorzystać.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>795.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>800.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jak wspomniałem, Trybunał nie ma reguł w tym zakresie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>800.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>807.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Reguła 33 prim regulaminu Trybunału, a w tym zakresie wydaje nam się niewystarczająca.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>807.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>814.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nie jest to zapis materialnie adekwatny, a poza tym sam Trybunał jest aktem o charakterze wewnętrznym.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>814.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>824.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Decyzja przewodniczącego Trybunału o ograniczeniu dostępu do dokumentu nie jest trwała i może być zmieniona także bez zgody stron w przyszłości.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>824.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>833.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Przewóz dokumentacji w Trybunale jest dokonywany przez komercyjną firmę kurierską, a nie zastrzeżonym kurierem dyplomatycznym ad hoc.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>833.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>846.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Te zasady są bardzo inne i luźne w stosunku do procedur, które są stosowane w innych Trybunałach, które mają do czynienia ze sprawami o podobnym profilu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>846.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>854.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tutaj w szczególności chciałbym wspomnieć o bardzo w tym zakresie rozbudowanych regułach Międzynarodowego Trybunału Karnego.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>854.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>873.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rząd liczył na podjęcie przez Trybunał prac nad procedurą przekazania dokumentów, ale nie spotkał się z odzewem na przykład takim, z jakim się spotkał wtedy, gdy współdziałał z Trybunałem w procedurze wyroku pilotażowego.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>873.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>882.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Objęcie tajemnicą śledztwa w Polsce jest regułą ogólną stosującą się w każdym postępowaniu karnym w Polsce.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>882.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>893.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dotychczas Trybunał nie był skonfrontowany z tego rodzaju sytuacją, w której musiał żądać tego rodzaju dokumentów, nie chciał akta toczącego się w Polsce śledztwa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>893.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>905.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Polska nie nadużywa tajemnicy śledztwa, dlatego że tajemnica śledztwa jest nierozerwalnie związana również z poszanowaniem zasady domniemania niewinności.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>905.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>917.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dzięki tajemnicy postępowania, a sądowe postępowania prokuratorskie w Polsce nie toczą się w atmosferze publicznej nagonki i nacisku mediów na tego rodzaju postępowania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>917.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>934.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tajemnica śledztwa jest również potrzebna po to, by w ogóle nie nastąpiło udaremnienie celów, dla których śledztwo jest zaprojektowane, przeprowadzane, a dla których ma się ono skończyć znalezieniem faktów.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>934.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>944.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Obecna w Polsce praktyka jest taka, że o wynikach toczącego się postępowania opinia publiczna jest informowana dopiero na etapie wniosienia aktu oskarżenia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>944.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>964.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tajemnica wynikająca z klauzuli tajne, ściśle tajne jest bardzo ważnym elementem tej sprawy. Zdaniem rządu, ze względu na istotę zarzutów i okoliczności sprawy, śledztwo musiało objąć materię klauzulowaną.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>964.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>980.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nie ma przesłanek w tym zakresie do rozszerzenia orzeczenia w sprawie Janowiec, w tzw. sprawie katyńskiej, na którą można by się było tu ewentualnie powoływać.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>980.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>999.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dlatego, że w sprawie Janowiec rząd, do którego odnosiła się ta sprawa, zamknął śledztwo, je zakończył, umorzył postępowanie i ukrył uzasadnienie tej decyzji.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>999.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1018.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tutaj w odniesieniu do Polski takiej okoliczności nie ma, dlatego, że sprawa się nadal toczy. Reasumując, sądzę, że, jestem przekonany, że Polska nie naruszyła konwencji. Nie naruszyła jej także w zakresie stosowania artykułu 38 konwencji. Dziękuję.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1034.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1036.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Wysoki Trybunale, Pani Prezydent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1036.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1043.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Część mojego wystąpienia odnosi się przede wszystkim do kontroli skuteczności i rzetelności śledztwa prowadzonego w Polsce.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1043.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1062.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W odniesieniu do zarzutów skarżących dotyczących domniemanych tortur, tajnego pozbawienia wolności, pozbawienia kontaktów z rodzinami w czasie pozbawienia wolności oraz wydania do kraju, którym będą narażeni na ryzyko rażąco niesprawiedliwego traktowania, a także ryzyko wymierzenia im kary śmierci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1062.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1080.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W tym zakresie strona polska stoi na stanowisku, że nie odbiega to postępowanie od standardów przewidzianych dla postępowania krajowego w zakresie efektywności, sprawności, niezależności, transparentności i zapewnienia odpowiednich uprawnień systemowych dla organów prowadzących postępowanie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1080.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1098.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tu w nawiązaniu do wczorajszych zeznań świadków pragnąłbym zwrócić uwagę Trybunału na to, że oba postępowania komisji toczyły się nie jako procedury dowodowe w sensie sądowym, ale jako niesformalizowane sprawdzenie faktów.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1098.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1111.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W istocie były to działania przedprocesowe, które zmierzały do potwierdzenia udziału państw europejskich w programie prowadzonym przez agencję amerykańską, nie zajmowały się badaniem konkretnych przypadków.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1111.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1130.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Natomiast według innego schematu prowadzone jest postępowanie krajowe, w którym chodzi o zebranie dowodów na wszystkie ujawnione przestępstwa, ustalenie konkretnych sprawców i sprawdzenie materiału dowodowego pod kątem możliwości obrony oskarżenia w postępowaniu sądowym.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1130.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1150.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W pierwszym rzędzie należy przy tym zaznaczyć, iż zarówno w czasie wniesienia rozpoznawanych skarg przeciwko Polsce, jak i obecnie, wstaje w toku. Wykonywane są stale czynności dowodowe i analityczne zmierzające do umożliwienia oparcia przyszłych ustaleń i rozstrzygnięć na prawdziwych ustaleniach faktycznych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1150.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1161.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Stanowi to istotną przeszkodę dla szerszego informowania o dotychczasowych ustaleniach śledztwa oraz wynikających z nich dalszych zamierzeniach śledczych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1161.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1180.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Możliwość w ujawnianiu treści zabezpieczonych dowodów jest w pełni zgodna z obowiązującą w polskim systemie prawa zasadą tajemnicy śledztwa, znajdującą swój normatywny wymiar w treści art. 241 PKK. Mimo oczywistej opozycji wobec zasady jawności i publiczności rozprawy głównej,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1180.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1201.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>tajemnica postępowania przygotowawczego pełni ważną rolę, zarówno w odniesieniu do traktowania jej jako parawanu mającego zapewnić skuteczne ściganie sprawców przestępstw, w użyciu jej jako narzędzia ochrony m.in. dóbr osobistych, osób funkcjonujących w różnych rolach procesowych w postępowaniu karnym.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1201.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1212.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Istotny jest także walor wyłączający oddziaływanie przedwcześnie ujawnianych informacji na późniejsze procesowe relacje osób przesłuchiwanych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1212.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1227.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W nawiązaniu do wczorajszych wystąpień świadków, chciałbym zwrócić uwagę Trybunału, że w odniesieniu do zaprezentowanej metodologii prac Komisji, przed zebraniem kompletnych informacji nie ujawniano opinii publicznej bieżących ustaleń.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1227.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1243.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W tym kontekście wyraźnie widać, że tym bardziej ujawnienie informacji ze śledztwa krajowego mogłoby być kontrproduktywne, tj. wpłynąć negatywnie na osiągnięcie celów tego postępowania w zakresie dotarcia do prawdy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1243.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1260.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Trzeba pamiętać, iż ustalenia faktyczne będące punktem wyjścia dla ocen karnoprawnych są nadal czynione, co sprawia, że aktualnie nie mogą być uznane za pełne, kompletne i umożliwiające merytoryczne rozstrzygnięcie sprawy w postępowaniu krajowym.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1260.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1266.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Gdyby tak było, zostałaby już bowiem podjęta decyzja o przesunięciu procesu karnego na kolejny etap.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1266.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1281.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Miałoby to wyraz bądź w wydaniu postanowienia o umorzeniu śledztwa, co do którego zapewniona jest kontrola sądowa w drodze zaskarżenia, bądź też skierowano by akt oskarżenia do sądu, inicjując stosowną rozprawę główną.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1281.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1307.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Skoro to nie nastąpiło, trwa dążenie do zrealizowania celów postępowania przygotowawczego, którymi są przede wszystkim wytrwalenie, czy został popełniony czy zabraniony, jak wiele czynów zabranionych zostało popełnionych, czy stanowią one przestępstwo, a także wykrycie, ujęcie sprawcy, zebranie o nim danych, wyjaśnienie okoliczności sprawy, w przypadku przedstawienia zarzutów weryfikacja linii obrony.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1307.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1315.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To wszystko także w zakresie zabezpieczenia i niezbędnym zakresie utrwalenia dowodów potrzebnych dla postępowania sądowego.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1315.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1321.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W tym miejscu konieczne wydają się dwie uwagi szczegółowe dotyczące standardu dowodzenia w sprawach karnych krajowych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1321.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1334.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Postępowanie w Polsce toczy się w obliczu szeregu informacji medialnych i pod presją wielu znaczących opracowań instytucji i organizacji zajmujących się ochroną praw człowieka, tym także o charakterze międzynarodowym.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1334.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1338.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Operują one licznymi faktami, których źródła w większości pozostają anonimowe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1338.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1353.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Co więcej, metodyka opracowań tak podczynionych ustaleń w formie raportów oraz regulacje dotyczące funkcjonowania instytucji i organizacji uniemożliwiają dotarcie przez prokuratorów do osobowych źródeł informacji, jak tego wymaga polska procedura.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1353.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1368.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W tym stanie rzeczy opublikowane ustalenia są wykorzystywane oczywiście w postępowaniu krajowym, niemniej jednak mają głównie charakter źródła informacji o potencjalnych dowodach i ukierunkowują dalsze działania prokuratorów.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1368.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1378.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To jest dowod do sensu stricto, a oparcie się na nich byłoby niewystarczające dla przypisania oto działalności karnej konkretnej osobie za konkretny czyn.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1378.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1383.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cena skuteczności, rzetelności i postępowania może być dokonana w kilku aspektach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1383.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1387.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Systemowym, to jest w odniesieniu do systemu obowiązującego prawa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1387.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1392.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kontrolnym, zwłaszcza w relacji do skuteczności pozaprocesowych środków kontrolnych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1392.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1399.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I indywidualnym, to jest współwzględnieniem uwarunkowań organizacyjno-przedmiotowych konkretnego postępowania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1399.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1405.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jeżeli chodzi o aspekt systemowy, pragnąłbym podkreślić, że polska prokuratura pracuje zgodnie z zasadą legalizmu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1405.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1418.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Każde zatem polskie śledztwo swoim zakresem obejmuje wszystkie czyny zabronione, których prawdopodobieństwo popełnienia ujawniło się w jego toku, a nie tylko te, które pierwotnie opisano w decyzji o jego wszczęciu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1418.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1425.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nie sądzę kątpliwie na zakres postępowania, który w tym konkretnym przypadku jest dynamiczny.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1425.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1431.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W ramach samego postępowania funkcjonują mechanizmy prawne umożliwiające realizację uprawnień osób pokrzywdzonych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1431.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1444.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Na wstępie krótkiego omówienia tych instrumentów wskazać należy, iż zgodnie z przepisami polskiej procedury karnej szeroki zakres ma kontrola sądowa decyzji procesowych zapadłych w toku śledztwa oraz podejmowanych w trakcie jego czynności.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1444.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1458.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Polskie postępowanie przygotowawcze ma także wiele elementów o charakterze kontradyktoryjnym, takich jak prawo stron do składania wniosków dowodowych, udział w części czynności procesowych, dostęp stron do materiałów śledztwa, możliwość zaskarżenia decyzji procesowych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1458.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1466.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Katalog uprawnień jest szeroki. Aby urealnić możliwość korzystania z tych uprawnień, zasadą jest pouczanie stron o przysługujących im prawach na piśmie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1466.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1491.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To liczy zarówno podejrzanego, przy czym status ten jest związany z wydaniem określonej decyzji procesowej i ogłoszeniem jej zainteresowanemu, jak i pokrzywdzonemu, co do którego nie wydaje się formalnej decyzji dla korzystania z praw pokrzywdzonego w postępowaniu przygotowawczym wystarczającym jest poczucie pokrzywdzenia. Ten element o charakterze subiektywnym połączony z uprawdopodobnieniem,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1491.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1499.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>że zgłaszający faktycznie doznał naruszenia lub zagrożenia dobra prawnego przez przestępstwo, które jest przedmiotem postępowania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1499.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1505.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ten element ma charakter obiektywny, jest to zgodne z artykułem 49 Polskiej Procedury Karnej.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1505.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1514.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W tym miejscu przedstawione zostaną najważniejsze uprawnienia pokrzywdzonego jako strony z odniesieniem do realiów prowadzonego w Polsce postępowania krajowego.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1514.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1521.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pokrzywdzony ma możliwość korzystania z reprezentacji fachowej, a więc pomocy pełnomocnika bądź z urzędu bądź wyboru.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1521.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1532.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W niniejszej sprawie zgłosili się pełnomocnicy trzech pokrzywdzonych, ustanowieni dla nich przez osoby trzecie wobec faktu, iż bezpośrednio zainteresowani są pozbawieni wolności.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1532.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1537.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pragnę zwrócić uwagę Wysokiego Trybunału na czas zgłoszeń.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1537.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1549.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Zgłoszenie dotyczące pana Alna Sziriego miało miejsce 21 września 2010 roku, natomiast dotyczące pana Abu Zubajdy 16 grudnia 2010 roku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1549.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1556.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Zgłosił się również trzeci pokrzywdzony, miało to miejsce 14 czerwca 2013 roku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1556.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1564.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Polskie prawo przewiduje także, iż w razie śmierci pokrzywdzonego prawa, które by mu przysługiwały, mogą być wykonywane bądź przez osoby najbliższe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1564.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1571.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W przypadku braku ich lub nieujawnienia przez prokuratora działającego z urzędu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1571.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1583.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pokrzywdzony może złożyć wniosek o wyłączenie sędziego lub prokuratora, jeżeli istnieje okoliczność tego rodzaju, że mogłaby wywołać uzasadnioną wątpliwość co do jego beztronności w danej sprawie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1583.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1595.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pragnę zaznaczyć, że wniosków takich nie składano ani w okresie, kiedy postępowanie prowadzone było w Prokuraturze Apelacyjnej w Krakowie, ani wtedy, kiedy było prowadzone w Prokuraturze Apelacyjnej w Warszawie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1595.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1599.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pokrzywdzony ma prawo składać wnioski dowodowe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1599.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1609.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Przyznać należy, iż przy zgłoszeniach pełnomocników podniesiono szereg różnych wniosków dowodowych, które podlegają sukcesywnemu rozpoznawaniu bądź realizowaniu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1609.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1646.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Przykładowo podam, iż postanowieniami z dnia 9 i 14 marca 2011 roku częściowo wyrzeczono w zakresie złożonych wniosków dowodowych, że uznano, iż okoliczności wskazane we wnioskach zostały udowodnione zgodnie z twierdzeniem wnioskodawców, jak to przewiduje Polska Procedura, co do niektórych wniosków stwierdzono, że dowodów nie da się przeprowadzić, przy czym zastrzec należy, iż decyzja w zakresie oddalenia wniosków dowodowych na danym etapie postępowania nie stanowi przeszkody do ich dopuszczenia w późniejszym czasie, w szczególności, gdy zmienią się okoliczności wskazujące na zasadność podjętej decyzji.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1646.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1650.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pokrzywdzony może być dopuszczony do udziału w czynnościach procesowych śledztwa lub dochodzenia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1650.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1668.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Przykładowo można podać, iż wniosek pełnomocnika złożony w dniu 13 września 2012 roku o odebranie zeznań świadka rozpoznany został pozytywnie, tego samego dnia dokonano przesłuchania objętego wnioskiem świadka w obecności wnioskodawcy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1668.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1673.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pokrzywdzony może wnioskować o skorzystanie z dodatkowych ułatwień i zabezpieczeń przy czynnościach ze swoim udziałem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1673.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1679.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Może to dotyczyć także przesłuchania przy użyciu urządzeń technicznych umożliwiających przeprowadzenie tej czynności na odległość.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1679.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1684.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Wspominam o tym uprawnieniu, ponieważ możliwość skorzystania z tzw. przesłuchania na odległość</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1684.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1691.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>jest brana pod uwagę przy oczekiwanej współpracy strony amerykańskiej przy uwzględnieniu miejsca aktualnego pobytu pokrzywdzonych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1691.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1701.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jest bowiem priorytetem i dążeniem polskiej prokuratury do tego, aby uzyskać relacje pochodzące także bezpośrednio od pokrzywdzonych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1701.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1707.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pokrzywdzony lub jego pełnomocnik może w toku postępowania przeglądać akta i sporządzać z nich odpisy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1707.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1717.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pełnomocnicy ustanowieni w polskim postępowaniu mają nieskrępowany dostęp do akt jawnych śledztwa z materiałami niejawnymi, natomiast zapoznawali się odpowiednio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1717.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1725.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pan mecenas Pietrzak 19 stycznia 2012 roku, a w określonej części także 13 czerwca 2012 roku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1725.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1734.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pan mecenas Jan Kossk 19 stycznia 2012 roku i w analogicznej części 13 marca 2013 roku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1734.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1744.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pokrzywdzony ma prawo do zaskarżenia szeregu postanowień, w tym postanowień o odmowie, wszczęcie, umorzeniu postępowania przygodowczego, składaniu zażaleń na czynności inne niż postanowienia i zarządzenia naruszające jego prawa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1744.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1755.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W razie powtórnego wydania przez prokuratora postanowienia o odmowie, wszczęcie lub umorzeniu postępowania służy mu droga sądowa, ma możliwość wniesienia aktu oskarżenia o przestępstwo ścigane z oskarżenia publicznego.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1755.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1768.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Po wniesieniu aktu oskarżenia przez oskarżyciela publicznego może złożyć stosowne oświadczenie, iż chce występować w przewidzianej roli oskarżyciela posiłkowego, która poszerza jego uprawnienia na etapie postępowania sądowego.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1768.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1778.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dodatkowym bardzo istotnym elementem i uprawnieniem pokrzywdzonego jest możliwość złożenia skargi na naruszenie prawa strony do rozpoznania sprawy bez nieuzasadnionej zwłoki, tzw. skarga na przewlekłość.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1778.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1789.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jest ona w przypadku jej złożenia w toku śledca rozpoznawana przez sąd w składzie trzech sędziów, będący sądem przełożonym nad tym, który byłby właściwy rzeczowo do rozpoznania sprawy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1789.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1795.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Może być składana kilkukrotnie, co do zasady co 12 miesięcy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1795.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1803.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Skargę niezasadną sąd oddala, natomiast uwzględniając skargę stwierdza, że może zostać przyznana suma pieniężna tytułem odszkodowania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1803.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1820.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Odnośnie faktów z postępowania można podnieść, iż w 2011 roku pełnomocnik pana Alna Szyriego złożył skargę na przewlekłość postępowania, która została oddalona przez rozpoznający sprawę sąd apelacyjny w Białymstoku. Pełnomocnik pana Aby Zubajdy skargi takiej dotychczas nie składał.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1820.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1837.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rozpatrując z kolei aspekt kontrolny w rozumieniu także transparentności śledztwa, podkreślić należy, iż w postępowaniu towarzyszy stałe zainteresowanie opinii publicznej, mass mediów oraz organizacji pozarządowych. Informacje o biegu postępowania przekazywano</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1837.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1846.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>oddziałowi Amnesty International, Helsińskiej Fundacji Praw Człowieka, odpowiadając na ich pytania w możliwie szerokim zakresie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1846.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1859.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sprawa pozostaje także w bieżącym monitoringu Polskiego Rzecznika Praw Obywatelskich, który otrzymywał pisemne informacje o charakterze niejawnym, a w ostatnim czasie zasygnalizował także swoje zainteresowanie prokuratorowi generalnemu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1859.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1880.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W tej aspekcie, w nawiązaniu do wczorajszych wystąpień świadków, chciałbym zwrócić uwagę, że sformułowane pod adresem strony rządowej zarzuty dotyczące braku współpracy w latach 2006-2007 muszą być oceniane przez pryzmat tego, że od 2008 roku Polska była praktycznie jedynym krajem, które realnie prowadziło śledztwo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1880.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1883.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I właśnie to śledztwo jest przedmiotem postępowania przed Trybunałem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1883.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1890.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jako oskarżyciel chciałbym powiedzieć, że paradoksem byłaby jego negatywna ocena w momencie, kiedy przynosi ono pożądane skutki.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1890.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1900.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W aspekcie indywidualnym chciałbym wskazać, że śledztwo pozostaje pod nadzorem służbowym Prokuratury Generalnej, a prowadzone jest w Wydziale V Prokuratura Polacynej w Krakowie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1900.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1904.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To jest na najwyższym szczeblu, na którym prowadzone są postępowania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1904.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1918.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W sprawie towarzyszy osobiste zainteresowanie prokuratora generalnego, który uczestniczył w organizowanych naradach roboczych i otrzymuje bieżącą informację o ustaleniach i zamierzonych czynnościach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1918.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1930.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Referentem tej sprawy jest doświadczona i energiczna prokurator, która w przeszłości prowadziła także ważne śledztwa o skomplikowanym charakterze, dotyczące także wysokich rangów funkcjonariuszy publicznych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1930.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1944.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Odmawiając wczoraj rządowi możliwości zaprezentowania przygotowanego dokumentu opisującego kalendarium i przebieg śledztwa w oparciu także o materiały niejawne, nie utrudniono wykazania jego efektywności i rzetelności.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1944.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1952.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pragnę się przynajmniej odnieść do jednego z także sygnalizowanych wczoraj elementów, a mianowicie do długości trwania tego postępowania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1952.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1962.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pragnę bym zaznaczyć, iż nie jest to jedyne kryterium oceny, a na pewno nie może być uznane za kryterium decydujące przy ocenie efektywności i rzetelności postępowania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1962.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1968.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prosiłbym, aby Trybunał zechciał uwzględnić przy tej ocenie następujące czynniki.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1968.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1995.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Zareplikowane od strony merytorycznej i prawnej charakter przedmiotów sprawy, który obejmuje podejrzenie popełnienia wielu przestępstw o różnym ciężarze gatunkowym, upraszczając od przestępstw urzędniczych, aż po najważniejsze przestępstwa, które zgodnie z polskim prawem nie ulegają przedawnieniu przez szereg osób na różnych szczeblach decyzyjnych, łącznie z osobami na najwyższych stanowiskach państwowych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1995.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2007.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Zwrócenie uwagi także na bezprecedensowy brak możliwości procesowego kontaktu z pokrzywdzonymi, także celem odebrania ich zeznań oraz poznania zakresu poczucia ich krzywdy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2007.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2017.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Niebagatelne utrudnienie związane jest z międzynarodowym aspektem postępowania i ufam, że Trybunał weźmie go pod uwagę, także mając w pamięci wczorajsze zeznania świadków.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2017.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2043.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kluczowy aspekt ustaleń, które muszą zostać w sposób pełny poczynione w toku śledztwa, dotyczący domniemanego funkcjonowania na terenie Polski ośrodka odosobnienia związanego z działaniami CIA, odnosi się w sposób oczywisty do działań wywiadowczych co najmniej dwóch krajów, to jest USA i Polski, które co do zasady są ściśle chronione przez te państwa ze względów bezpieczeństwa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2043.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2054.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pewna trudność w prowadzeniu tego postępowania odnosi się także do obowiązku ochrony informacji niejawnych i stosowania właściwych procedur w tym zakresie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2054.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2064.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Podsumowując powyższe, strona polska twierdzi, iż postępowanie, które jest nadal w toku, nie daje podstaw do uznania go za nieskuteczne bądź nierzetelne.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2064.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2077.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jest w prawdzie długotrwałe, ale nie została stwierdzona jego przewlekłość, zwłaszcza jeżeli uwzględni się jego złożony i skomplikowany charakter, a także wpływające na czas trwania ograniczenie niezależne od prowadzących śledztwa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2077.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2090.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Wyglądając na przebieg śledztwa przez pryzmat elementów standardu określonego dla postępowań odnoszących się zwłaszcza do badania naruszeń praw przez funkcjonariuszy publicznych, stwierdzić należy, iż są one zachowane.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2090.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2092.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Śledztwo jest prowadzone przez niezależną prokuraturę.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2092.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2109.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Odpowiadając na pytanie, które padło wczoraj, mogę powiedzieć, że zmiana systemowa dotyczy rozdzielenia pozycji prokuratora generalnego i ministra sprawiedliwości, co niewątpliwie przyczynia się do tego, iż śledztwo może być prowadzone niezależnie od wpływów politycznych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2109.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2112.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prowadzone jest tak ze sposób obiektywny.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2112.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2121.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dotychczas brak było okoliczności wskazujących na konieczność wyłączenia któregokolwiek z prowadzących i brak procesowych wniosków w stron zmierzających w tym kierunku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2121.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2137.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Transparentnie, albo w możliwym zakresie informacje są udzielone zainteresowanym, tym także organizacjom pozarządowym, sprawnie i efektywnie, albowiem nie stwierdzono zaniedbań w prowadzonych czynnościach, które skutkowałyby utrudnieniami w dochodzeniu do prawdy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2137.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2137.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dziękuję.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2146.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2147.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Śliwa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2147.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2147.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Ms. Singh.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP4</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2154.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2170.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President and members of the court, about 160 kilometers north of Warsaw is a Polish intelligence base that was used during World War II by German intelligence officials and later by the Soviet military.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2170.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2182.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More recently, in a joint operation with the Polish authorities, the CIA secretly imprisoned Abdel Rahim al-Nashri on that base.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2182.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2206.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There, in a secluded villa hidden from sight, CIA interrogators subjected him to torture, to mock executions while he stood naked and hooded before them, to painful stress positions that nearly dislocated his arms from his shoulders, and to threats of bringing in his mother to sexually abuse her in front of him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2206.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2216.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today, this court will be the first to meaningfully address Mr. al-Nashri's torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2216.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2219.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why does this case belong before this court?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2219.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2231.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because it concerns the active participation of Poland in a practice that the court has found to be anathema to the rule of law, that is, extraordinary rendition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2231.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2238.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because Poland has failed to deliver justice and failed to conduct an effective investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2238.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2264.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And because this court's intervention is now essential for ending impunity, impunity with respect to egregious violations of the most basic rights under the European Convention, the right not to be tortured, the right not to be secretly detained, the right to a fair trial, and the right not to be subjected to the death penalty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2264.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2267.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will address the first three of the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2267.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2272.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My colleague, Mr. Piechak, will address the remainder.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2272.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2286.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yesterday, the court heard cogent, credible, and consistent expert testimony that categorically, and I repeat, categorically, concluded that Mr. al-Nashri was secretly detained in Poland</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2286.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2299.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from 5th December 2002 to 6th June 2003, and that Poland knew that the United States was secretly detaining prisoners at the Polish intelligence base at Stare Kiekuty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2299.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2302.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The expert confirmed that Mr. al-Nashri</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2302.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2308.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was subjected to the most significant abuse in the CIA program.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2308.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2319.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was subjected to unauthorized techniques, including mock executions and stress positions, specifically documented in a CIA Office of Inspector General report.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2319.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2323.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That report also admits that Mr. al-Nashri was subjected</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2323.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2330.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to enhanced interrogation techniques in the first two weeks of December 2002.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2330.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2339.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The report's descriptions make clear that the term enhanced interrogation techniques is but a euphemism for torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2339.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2352.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In light of this torture, it is no surprise that even US government doctors concede that Mr. al-Nashri suffers from post-traumatic stress syndrome.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2352.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2361.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, a United Nations report states that on 4th December 2002, the CIA transported Mr. al-Nashri on a flight registered</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2361.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2369.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as N63MU from Bangkok to Shimane Airport, which is just under an hour's drive from Stare Kiekuty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2369.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2383.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Official Polish border guard documents disclosed to the Helsinki Foundation for Human Rights and the 2007 Marti report further confirm that this flight landed on 5th December 2002 at Shimane Airport.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2383.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2385.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Zubeda's submissions, which we</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2385.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2389.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>adopt insofar as they support Mr. al-Nashri's claims,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2389.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2397.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>provide further evidence corroborating the fact that he and Mr. al-Nashri were flown from Thailand to Poland</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2397.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2399.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the same flight.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2399.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2402.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ICRC reports that Mr. al-Nashri</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2402.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2420.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>confirmed that in his third place of detention, that is in Poland, he was held naked, subjected to prolonged standing stress positions with his wrists shackled above his head to the ceiling for days at a time, and threatened with sodomy and the arrest and rape of his family.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2420.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2437.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Numerous US government documents, including the CIA OIG report, a December 2004 CIA memo, as well as US Justice Department legal memoranda, provide further details of the CIA's policy and practice of torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2437.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2445.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, an Associated Press report citing former US officials confirms that Mr. al-Nashri was detained in Poland from 5 December</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2445.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2448.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>2002 until 6 June 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2448.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2455.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once again, official Polish air navigation and Polish border guard documents disclosed to the Helsinki Foundation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2455.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2471.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The 2007 Marti report and the Center for Human Rights and Global Justice report confirm that rendition flight N379P departed from Shimane Airport on 6 June 2003 for Rabat with the assistance of Polish authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2471.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2482.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court heard expert testimony yesterday confirming how Polish officials filed false flight plans and assisted in the cover up of CIA operations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2482.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2508.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In contrast to the strong, clear, and concordant facts put forth by the applicant, the Polish government has failed to answer the court's questions on the merits, whereas here the events at issue lie wholly or in large part within the exclusive knowledge of the authorities, the burden of proof may be regarded as resting on the authorities to provide a convincing explanation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2508.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2527.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whereas here the authorities have failed to provide a convincing explanation, failed to conduct an effective investigation, and failed to furnish the court with necessary information, the court is entitled to draw inferences adverse to the authorities in favor of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2527.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2536.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, unrobotted presumptions of fact lead to the conclusion that the applicant's factual allegations are true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2536.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2556.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the government's 15 March 2013 submission concedes that, and I quote, the Polish government do not contest in the proceedings before the court the allegations submitted by the applicant's plenipotentiaries, nor does it contest the alleged facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2556.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2570.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, by granting him victim status more than three years ago in the pending investigation, the Polish prosecutor implicitly confirmed the validity of Mr. Al-Nasri's claims, because under Polish law,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2570.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2577.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the decision to grant victim status is a non-discretionary one mandated by the supporting evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2577.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2596.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That Warsaw prosecutors apparently brought charges against the former head of Polish intelligence for exceeding his powers, depriving prisoners of war of their freedom, and allowing corporal punishment further suggests that the government possesses evidence that corroborates Mr. Al-Nasri's detention</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2596.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2598.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and torture claims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2598.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2607.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court's decisions in Al-Nasri and Elaskiw make clear that this torture and secret detention can be imputed to the Polish state for two reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2607.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2615.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, these acts occurred on Polish territory with the acquiescence and connivance of Polish authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2615.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2622.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, Poland failed to fulfill its obligations to prevent these acts, despite being on notice of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2622.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2632.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The 2007 Marti reports confirms that several high-ranking Polish officials knew about and authorized Poland's role in the secret CIA prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2632.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2643.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As noted in the statement of facts, Polish prosecutors reportedly possess an agreement between the Polish intelligence agency and the CIA that was signed by Mr. Szymiutkowski, then head</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2643.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2645.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Polish intelligence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2645.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2653.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The agreement set out detailed rules for running the prison on Polish territory and a provision for what should be done if a detainee died there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2653.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2668.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prime Minister Leszek Miller and President Aleksander Kwasniewski reportedly received oral reports from Polish intelligence officials about what was going on in that CIA prison, including on the fact that the United States was detaining individuals there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2668.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2674.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These officials reportedly drafted memos after every oral report to the prime minister or president.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2674.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2686.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Polish intelligence agency reportedly transmitted documents to the Polish prosecutor that showed that the agency was cooperating with the CIA over 2002 to 2003 in relation to secret detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2686.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2697.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Senator Józef Biniur has publicly said that he has information showing that the Polish intelligence unit at Stare Kiekuty commissioned a local contractor to build a prisoner's cage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2697.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2709.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court had heard testimony yesterday that confirmed that the cage was built by a Polish company from Pruszków with specifications as to the thickness of the bars and size.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2709.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2714.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cage was supposed to be big enough to hold a grown man and a portable toilet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2714.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2725.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President, you heard expert testimony yesterday stating that it was Polish officials who entered into a secret operating agreement with the United States to convert the Polish intelligence base into a prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2725.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2731.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was Polish officials who assisted the CIA in secretly flying Mr. El-Nashry into the country</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2731.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2733.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and transporting him to the prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2733.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2739.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was Polish officials who assisted the CIA in secretly flying him out of Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2739.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2749.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As described in the 2007 Marti report, it was Polish officials who granted CIA rendition planes licenses and overflight permissions, as well as special exemptions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2749.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2760.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was Polish officials who guided the planes into land and who cleared the runway and secured the perimeter and grounds of Shimani Airport so that detainees like Mr. El-Nashry could secretly</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2760.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2763.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>be offloaded into vans bound for the secret prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2763.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2774.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court had heard expert testimony yesterday that the director of Shimani Airport provided significant information with respect to abnormal procedure allowed for rendition aircraft.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2774.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2784.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The 2007 Marti report shows that Polish officials provided extraordinary physical security by setting up buffer zones around the CIA's detainee operations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2784.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2793.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Polish Air Navigation Services Agency, Polish officials assisted in disguising the existence and exact movements of incoming CIA rendition flights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2793.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2799.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Polish border guard, they ensured that CIA flights were exempt from normal procedures for incoming foreign passengers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2799.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2805.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the National Customs Office, they resolved irregularities in the payment of fees related to CIA operations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2805.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2820.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court had heard expert testimony yesterday that after a rendition operation, the day after such an operation, Polish airport employees were paid cash at a rate far higher than the usual rate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2820.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2822.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The removal of Mr. El-Nashry from Poland</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2822.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2831.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the face of a risk of further ill treatment, arbitrary detention, a flagrantly unfair trial, and the death penalty is also imputable to the Polish state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2831.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2847.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For it was Polish officials who assisted the CIA in secretly transporting him out of Poland, despite the fact that their own involvement in the extraordinary rendition program, as well as numerous credible sources, placed the Polish government on notice of the risks at the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2847.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2853.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the court's decision in Al-Syadoun makes clear, even though Mr. El-Nashry has been transferred</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2853.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2863.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from Polish territory, Poland is under an obligation to use all available means, including diplomatic interventions, to ensure that the United States does not subject him to the death penalty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2863.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2870.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President, this case has profound implications for Mr. El-Nashry, who is now detained at Guantanamo Bay.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2870.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2885.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He is gagged from speaking publicly of his own torture in Poland, because the United States takes the remarkable position that disclosure of his own memories, observations, and experiences of what happened to him would reveal classified sources and methods.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2885.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2890.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, US regulations prevent his US lawyer, Ms. Hollander, who is also counsel in this case,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2890.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2893.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from addressing the issues before this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2893.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2899.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition to having endured years of secret detention and torture, Mr. El-Nashry now faces the prospect</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2899.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2907.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the death penalty, following an unfair trial by military commission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2907.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2915.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court's findings will be critical for his trial, which is currently scheduled to begin on 2nd September 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2915.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2933.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More generally, this case has profound implications for several Council of Europe member states, which participated in the Extraordinary Rendition Program in various ways, including by hosting secret CIA prisons for torture that the US did not see fit to conduct on its own territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2933.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2940.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Significantly, Romania and Lithuania also have cases pending in the court for hosting secret CIA prisons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2940.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2954.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President, in the face of efforts to draw a veil over these abuses, this case presents an opportunity for the court to break the conspiracy of silence, an opportunity to uphold the rule of law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2954.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2954.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2958.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2961.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I call Mr. Pietrzak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2971.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2983.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President and members of the court, Poland has failed to conduct an effective investigation or provide an effective remedy for Mr. Al-Nashry's torture,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2983.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2987.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>secret detention, and rendition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2987.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2991.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland has also failed to cooperate with the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2991.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2996.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the pending Polish investigation is not prompt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2996.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3009.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It started five years after the violations took place, even though the state agencies that cooperated with the CIA knew of these violations while Mr. Al-Nashry was held captive</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3009.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3012.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and being tortured in Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3012.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3025.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Publicly available sources indicate that the state agencies knew about violations from their beginning in 2002, since they actively took part in preparing a special building for the purpose of detention and torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3025.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3030.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet the state did nothing for five years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3030.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3043.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only under strong domestic and international pressure from bodies such as the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe did the prosecutor initiate an investigation in 2008.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3043.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3053.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To this date, no information regarding the findings of the prosecutor has been made publicly, officially available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3053.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3056.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The passage of time has undermined the effectiveness of the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3056.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3064.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is, of course, a threat that the charges which could be pursued for illegal detention and abuse of power by public officials could expire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3064.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3076.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The lengthy duration of proceedings has also made it more difficult to effectively gather evidence, interview witnesses, who will remember less now than they did several years ago.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3076.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3088.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the investigation is proceeding, it is not reflected in the non-classified files, which do not show any significant actions having been taken since the case was moved to Krakow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3088.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3095.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A comparison of the government's 5th of September 2012 response to Mr. Al-Nashry's application</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3095.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3101.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with its 16th September 2013 response to Mr. Abu Zubaydah's application</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3101.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3105.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>shows minimal progress in the investigation in the intervening year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3105.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3111.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The total number of witnesses interviewed remained stagnant at 62.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3111.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3119.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the government's own submissions, it is therefore apparent that nothing happened over that one year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3119.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3126.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It appears to be convenient for the Polish state to keep the investigation going in a suspended state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3126.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3134.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A dismissal of the investigation would be difficult in the face of public pressure to effectively hold perpetrators responsible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3134.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3138.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And an indictment would be politically inconvenient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3138.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3143.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, this indefinite investigation is the worst possible scenario for the victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3143.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3158.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He has neither the right to a full review of the case files and then an appeal against the decision to dismiss the investigation, nor the possibility of having his rights vindicated in a criminal trial against the perpetrators.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3158.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3164.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the investigation cannot be considered to be independent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3164.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3176.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The prosecutors were changed in this investigation three times at junctions important for the victim, with no specific explanation from the prosecutor general or the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3176.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3184.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Each such change required the new prosecutor to become familiar with the files, thereby delaying the investigation further.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3184.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3193.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first change actually occurred after prosecutor Jerzy Mierzewski acknowledged Mr. Al-Nashiri as a victim in the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3193.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3197.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The prosecutor was, in fact, dismissed in my presence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3197.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3200.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I came to meet with him to discuss the advancement of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3200.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3210.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And immediately after I entered his room, he received a phone call from his superior and was told that he was relieved of the case and cannot speak with me.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3210.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3214.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second set of prosecutors, led by Mr. Wladimir Martyl,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3214.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3220.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>were relieved of the case immediately after they granted me and Mr. Bartłomiej Jankowski</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3220.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3224.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>access to the classified files for a very limited time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3224.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3233.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I found out about this when I arrived to continue reading the classified files a few days later, as agreed with prosecutor Wladimir Martyl.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3233.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3244.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that the prosecutors were changed following moments of cooperation with the victim's representative suggests a non-meritorious reason behind the changes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3244.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3267.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is further supported by a statement made on public radio by the Minister of Justice, Jaroslaw Gowin, on February 5, 2013, in which he states that charges brought against Zbigniew Szymiankowski were too hasty and that the charges against Szymiankowski proved to be insufficiently founded once the investigation was transferred to the prosecutor in Kraków.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3267.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3283.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The independence of the investigation requires that the Minister of Justice, independent from the prosecutor general, should not be commenting on decisions made by the prosecutor where the prosecutor himself has made no public statement concerning the charges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3283.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3291.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Helsinki Foundation for Human Rights complained to the National Prosecutors' Council regarding the unusual transfers of the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3291.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3301.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The council indicated in its report, which the government submitted to this court, that it found no grounds to state that the transfer was politically dictated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3301.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3312.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the council reached this conclusion based on the fact that none of the prosecutors involved in the investigation had filed a formal complaint to the council regarding the transfer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3312.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3319.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is not a sufficient explanation for extraordinary transfers in such a politically sensitive case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3319.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3327.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To my best knowledge, the National Prosecutors' Council did not have access to any of the case files in this investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3327.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3333.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were therefore not in a position to judge whether the transfers were legitimate or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3333.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3349.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The council, however, indicates in its report that such a decision to transfer an investigation, I quote, can only be dictated by the interest of the proceedings and be based on findings of improper conduct or oversight of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3349.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3363.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet neither the observations of the government nor the letter of the National Prosecutors' Council makes any mention of improper conduct or oversight that could possibly justify three changes of the prosecutors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3363.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3369.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, I cannot properly represent the interests of Mr. al-Nashry in the domestic proceedings</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3369.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3374.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because I have not had sufficient access to the files of the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3374.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3381.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I only had access to the classified files for a total of approximately three hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3381.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3389.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was grossly insufficient time to review, understand, and memorize the relevant fragments of the very broad classified files.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3389.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3393.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I was also not allowed to take notes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3393.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3398.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourthly, the investigation is not sufficiently transparent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3398.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3408.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, since it began, no meaningful information on its terms of reference or the precise scope of the investigation or its progress has been publicly disclosed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3408.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3429.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unsurprisingly, the 13th November 2013 report of the United Nations Committee Against Torture urges Poland not only to urgently complete its investigation, but to inform the public and ensure transparency into the progress of its investigation process, as well as cooperate in full with the European Court of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3429.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3433.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The state of Poland has done neither.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3433.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3439.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the secrecy of the investigation has severely hampered vindication of the applicant's rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3439.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3451.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The confidentiality which protects every investigation in Poland under Article 241 of the criminal code referred to by the prosecutor today is provided to ensure the effectiveness of the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3451.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3457.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does not prevent the prosecutor from informing the public of important information concerning the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3457.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3466.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, almost all relevant materials in this case were classified as secret or top secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3466.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3475.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government, in its letter dated November 12, 2013, justifies this classification by invoking the interests of the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3475.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3482.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But investigative secrecy is not a legal basis under Polish law for classifying documents as secret or top secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3482.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3492.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This objective is served by Article 241 of the criminal code, which prohibits the public disclosure of materials from the files of an investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3492.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3507.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The classification of documents in this investigation actually serves to protect the illegitimate interests of the agencies of the Polish state, which played a role in the illegal cooperation with the CIA and in violation of human rights and fundamental freedoms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3507.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3510.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the purpose of the classification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3510.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3526.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result of this over-classification, I am handicapped in presenting important information to this court, particularly since Polish law provides no mechanism for my seeking judicial review of the grounds for classification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3526.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3532.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With respect to the issue of effective remedies, Mr. Al-Nashiri should have had access</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3532.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3538.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to all effective and practical remedies capable of leading to the identification and punishment of those responsible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3541.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3546.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Civil remedies alone are insufficient under this court's jurisprudence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3546.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3563.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relation to his rights under Article 2 and Article 1 of Protocol Number 6, the applicant was entitled under Polish law to judicial review of his transfer outside of Poland, which would have been barred in the face of substantial risk of the death penalty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3563.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3574.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following his transfer, the Polish government has been under a continuing obligation to use all available means, including diplomatic interventions, to preclude the death penalty in his case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3574.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3586.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, had the Polish government conducted an effective investigation, the applicant could have used information derived from it to mitigate against the death penalty in his military commission trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3586.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3591.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By failing to provide any of these remedies, the Polish government has violated Mr. Al-Nashiri's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3591.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3595.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>rights under Article 13 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3595.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3606.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As indicated in our written observations, the government has also violated Article 38 of the convention by failing to furnish all necessary facilities to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3606.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3621.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite the court's guarantee of confidentiality of information conveyed by the state to the court, the government did not supply any meaningful information in response to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3621.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3634.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the government has provided no reasonable and solid grounds, as required under Janowicz and others, to justify the treatment of most of the relevant documents in the investigation as a secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3634.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3661.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, it did not even indicate which specific regulation of the Act on Protection of Classified Information was the legal basis for secrecy of the files of the investigation, or which agency issued the decision to classify the documents, or why entire volumes of the documents remain classified in their entirety instead of being released in the form of redacted versions of documents to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3661.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3675.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is in contrast to the approach of the Polish government in Janowicz, in which it argued that the Russian government had not produced a reasoned decision on the classification of relevant documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3675.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3692.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, Janowicz makes clear that a mere reference to the structural deficiency of the domestic law, which rendered impossible communication of sensitive documents to international bodies, is an insufficient explanation to justify the withholding of information requested by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3692.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3702.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Invoking limitations under Polish law regarding the classification of documents cannot justify a failure to cooperate with the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3702.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3712.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also failed to comply in a timely manner with the court's two procedural orders directing the production of an extract from the investigation files.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3712.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3723.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As such, the government has failed to abide by the standards reiterated in Janowicz, and the court is entitled to draw adverse inferences from such conduct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3723.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3730.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President, the Polish state failed to cooperate with the Marti inquiry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3730.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3733.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It failed to cooperate with the Fava inquiry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3733.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3738.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now it has failed to cooperate with the European Court of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3738.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3745.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only organization that the Polish state did cooperate with in this matter was the CIA.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3745.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President, members of the court, I urge the court to hold Poland accountable for its joint operation with the CIA in the violation of Mr. Al-Nasri's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3756.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>rights and freedoms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3756.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3756.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3761.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3762.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Pietrzak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3762.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3763.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Hughes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3777.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3781.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Madam President, members of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3781.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3787.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case concerns abduction, secret detention, torture and the practice of extraordinary rendition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3787.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3804.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Described by this Court as the extrajudicial transfer of persons from one jurisdiction or state to another for the purpose of detention and interrogation outside the normal legal system, where there was a real risk of torture or cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3804.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3815.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 5 December 2002, Abu Zubaydah, a victim of this practice, was transferred to Poland from CIA Blackside in Thailand as part of the CIA High Value Detainee Program.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3815.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3824.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He spent over nine months in incommunicado detention in a secret prison in Poland before being moved again to another secret prison outside of Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3824.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3828.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Abu Zubaydah is now imprisoned in Guantanamo Bay.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3828.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3836.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Throughout his decade-long detention he has never been charged with a crime and there has never been any judicial review of his detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3836.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3842.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result of his ill-treatment he now suffers from serious and debilitating physical and mental conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3842.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3852.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He is prevented from communicating with the outside world, including this Court, and his US counsel are precluded from disclosing to this Court any information he conveys to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3852.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3855.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case presents extraordinary challenges for the victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3855.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3869.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It involves the commission of crimes on Polish territory by state agents acting in secret and making determined efforts to cover up and conceal evidence relating to the operation of a CIA detention centre on Polish territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3869.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3876.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland's failure to carry out an effective investigation and its consistently secretive approach to this case heightened those challenges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3876.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3894.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet there is overwhelming evidence that Poland hosted a CIA secret prison in north-eastern Poland, that it assisted in and supported the running of that secret prison, and that it facilitated the transfer of Abu Zubaydah into and out of Poland to face the risk of further torture and inhuman treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3894.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3902.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite this evidence, Poland refuses to publicly acknowledge its role in rendition, detention and torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3902.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3913.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This Court has on many occasions identified the object and purpose of the Convention as the protection of individual human rights and the maintenance and promotion of the ideals and values of a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3913.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3933.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to be effective, the Convention must protect individuals from violations of their human rights, especially where those rights are violated by state agents operating under a policy of deliberate secrecy and concealment, and where the state relies on a completely ineffective domestic investigation in order to avoid proper scrutiny of its acts and omissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3933.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3941.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no doubt that the practice of extraordinary rendition was carried out within the territory of the Council of Europe and with the complicity of Member States.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3941.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3948.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is beyond dispute that those States have failed to ensure protection for the victims of this practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3948.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3960.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will set out the evidence which demonstrates that Poland hosted the CIA secret prison and Abu Zubaydah was detained incommunicado there from 5 December 2002 until 22 September 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3960.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3965.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will then demonstrate why Poland is responsible for specific violations of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3965.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3985.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr Jankowski will show that the pretrial criminal investigation initiated by the Government over five years ago is ineffective, that no effective remedy was available to the applicant, and that Poland, throughout these proceedings before this Court, has failed to comply with its duty under the Convention to furnish all necessary facilities for the Court's examination of this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3985.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3996.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The CIA secret prison in Poland was deliberately established in order to allow incommunicado detention of prisoners take place outside any legal, political or public scrutiny.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3996.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4008.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dr Marti, in his Council of Europe 2007 report, highlights the existence of bilateral agreements between the Polish Government and the CIA allowing this secret prison to operate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4008.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4025.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Polish politician and Member of the European Parliament Józef Pinior, in his affidavit, gives evidence of an agreement drawn up for the purpose of regulating the existence of this prison and of documents that illustrate the provision of practical logistical support and servicing of the prison site by Polish authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4025.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4029.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>NGOs have identified Poland as having hosted a secret prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4029.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4043.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Authoritative press reports citing numerous Government officials and private contractors have also referred to the existence of an agreement allowing CIA planes to land at Ziminy Airport and detention of prisoners suspected of terrorism at the secret prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4043.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4051.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The head of the Polish intelligence agency in the relevant period has confirmed the landing of CIA flights in Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4051.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4058.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even the President at the time, Kwaśniewski, has publicly acknowledged that Poland hosted a CIA-run secret prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4058.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4064.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is now proven beyond a reasonable doubt that Abu Zubaydah was transferred into Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4064.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4072.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also now clear beyond any credible dispute that Abu Zubaydah was imprisoned at a CIA secret prison in Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4072.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4084.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Senator Marti, in his 2007 report, states that CIA sources have confirmed to him that Abu Zubaydah was held at this secret prison and was questioned while there through the use of enhanced interrogation techniques.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4084.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4091.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His presence on Polish territory is also demonstrated through the evidence already set out in detail in our written pleadings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4091.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4113.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As Expert 3 confirmed yesterday in his evidence to this Court, the declassified US Government reports, the CIA Office of Inspector General report and the Department of Justice Office of Professional Responsibility report demonstrate that Abu Zubaydah was transferred out of Thailand on 4 December and CIA operational cables show that the black site was shut down on that date.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4113.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4123.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, we have put before this Court sworn testimony from the New York Supreme Court Appellate Division, in the case of Richmond v. Sport Flights, that contracts and invoices</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4123.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4137.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>also all point to the one consistent narrative and one only, that the flight from Thailand to Poland was performed by an aircraft N63MU, specifically contracted by the US for the purpose of performing rendition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4137.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4152.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A letter from the Polish Border Guard to the Helsinki Foundation of Human Rights confirms that plane number N63MU landed in Jiminy on 5 December 2002 with eight passengers and four crew and departed on the same day with no passengers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4152.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4159.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This account of the plane's arrival is verified by a handwritten log of landings and takeoffs at Jiminy Airport.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4159.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4164.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We heard yesterday how multiple efforts were made to disguise the true route of this plane.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4164.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4178.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Information disclosed to Senator Marti in his 2007 report by Eurocontrol showed that false flight plans were filed for N63MU, omitting Jiminy from the record of the plane's movements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4178.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4197.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further evidence pointed to concerted attempts to cover up these flights provided by Senator Marti in his 2007 report, which notes that the filing of false flight plans was done so that, and I quote, their actual movements would not be tracked or recorded, either live or after the fact, by the supranational air safety agency Eurocontrol.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4197.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4205.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The system of cover-up entailed several different steps involving both American and Polish collaborators."</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4205.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4213.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Considering the totality of this evidence, it is clear that Abu Zubaydah was rendered out of Thailand on this flight and brought to Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4213.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4224.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Number three, when asked by this court yesterday whether he could say beyond a reasonable doubt that Abu Zubaydah was imprisoned in Poland during the relevant period, replied categorically yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4224.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4247.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As also demonstrated in evidence given yesterday to this court, after over nine months of secret detention on the CIA black site in Poland, Abu Zubaydah was then transferred from Poland on 22 September 2003 on airplane number N313P, a plane that was at this time flying under official state status and will be familiar to this court from its role in the El Masry case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4247.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4263.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The plane designated as N313P has been identified by the New York Times as operated by a CIA front company, while the company responsible for trip planning services, Jeppesen, was involved in a range of flights involving the transport of suspected terrorists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4263.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4270.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say that this evidence taken together clearly establishes that Abu Zubaydah was imprisoned on Polish territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4270.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4282.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The evidence we rely on is detailed, specific and consistent and concerns the entire period Abu Zubaydah spent in Poland as well as the circumstances surrounding that period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4282.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4293.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This evidence has been uncovered in the face of determined efforts by state agents and state organizations to stymie any attempt at getting to the truth of Abu Zubaydah's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4293.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4305.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland has never provided an explanation of the events we have outlined in our memorial and which I have summarized today, instead it has relied on a secretive and stalled investigation to deflect attention away from this failure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4305.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4317.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court has consistently held that where facts lie within the state's control and the state fails to provide a satisfactory and convincing explanation of events, the court can draw inferences from that failure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4317.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4329.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Similarly, adverse inferences may be drawn where the state has not provided any meaningful fact-finding process to clarify certain events and has failed to rebut the allegations made against it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4329.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4335.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is equally clear that Poland is and must be legally responsible for the torture that took place on its territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4335.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4353.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland had a positive obligation to investigate allegations of serious violations of human rights, to investigate whether anyone was held at the CIA secret detention site on its territory, and to ensure that no one was transferred from its territory to a risk of torture and flagrant denial of their fair trial rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4353.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4355.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It failed on every count.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4355.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4367.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not only did it fail to take any steps to secure the applicant's convention rights, as this court heard yesterday, it actively engaged in ensuring he was able to exercise those rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4367.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4375.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The CIA secret prison could not have operated on Polish territory without the support and assistance of the Polish government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4375.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4382.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Polish state agents facilitated the landing of planes at Chimney and the operation of the secret detention center close by.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4382.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4390.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It secured the area around the secret prison and ensured the CIA could operate free from interference on the site.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4390.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4400.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It worked from within state institutions such as PANSA, such as the Polish border guard, to ensure that normal procedures were not applied when CIA flights were arriving.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4400.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4420.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to evidence set out in the Marti report of 2007, when the CIA flight was landing, the manager of the airbase was told by Polish officials to clear the runway of all other aircraft and vehicles and to ensure that all local staff were brought into the terminal building from the vicinity of the runway and remain at a distance from the aircraft.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4420.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4435.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The UN joint expert report, as well as the media reports outlined in our application, all state that Polish intelligence agents were put at the disposal of the CIA at the relevant time to provide open-ended assistance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4435.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4443.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland's responsibility for the violations of Abu Zubaydah's Article 3, 5, 6 and 8 convention rights is clear and decisive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4443.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4454.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As Expert 3 told this court yesterday, the nature of abuse by the CIA with respect to extraordinary rendition was public knowledge in 2002 and 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4454.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4459.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is well documented in our application using both Polish and international sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4459.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4474.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet Poland authorized, organized and facilitated the applicant's arrival at Chiminey Airbase in December 2002, facilitated his subsequent detention on Polish territory for over nine months, and facilitated his departure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4474.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4480.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court in El Mazri recognized that fear and anguish arising as a consequence of extraordinary rendition amounted to torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4480.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4489.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court went on to equate rendition with enforced disappearance, a practice that other international bodies have consistently recognized as torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4489.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4506.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Senator Marti in his 2007 report, relying on multiple sources, Poland, and I quote, agreed to provide the premises in which these facilities were established the highest degrees of physical security and secrecy and steadfast guarantees of non-interference, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4506.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4516.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It knowingly and intentionally ensured that the CIA could hold Abu Zubaydah in secret detention at the site for a prolonged period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4516.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4521.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His detention by its very nature amounts to a violation of Article 3 rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4521.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4529.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Abu Zubaydah was detained as part of a rendition program deliberately designed to ensure disorientation and vulnerability.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4529.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4531.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was denied access to a lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4531.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4538.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was denied access to a court that challenged the lawfulness of his detention, and he was never told why or where he was being held.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4538.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4543.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His detention amounted to a breach of every one of the subcategories of Article 5.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4543.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4554.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, his family did not know where he was, and he was unable to make contact with them due to the absolute ban on communication with the outside world, a clear violation of his Article 8 rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4554.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4562.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Numerous state agents and state authorities at all levels of the Polish government have been involved in different ways in the secret prison system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4562.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4571.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Expert 4 told this court yesterday, and I quote, Polish authorities had full knowledge of the illegality of this operation, its breach of the Polish Constitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4571.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4579.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was clear that the Polish authorities cooperated to breach Polish law, European law, and habeas corpus, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4579.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4588.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Senator Marti's 2007 report, the former President Wazniewski was, and I quote, the foremost national authority on the high-value detainee program.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4588.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4597.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, President Wazniewski confirmed this in a newspaper interview in Poland where he stated, and again I quote, of course, everything took place with my knowledge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4597.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4604.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The President and the Prime Minister agreed to secret service cooperation with the Americans because that is what was needed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4604.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4621.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decision to cooperate with the CIA carried a risk that the Americans would use unacceptable methods, but if a CIA agent brutally treated a prisoner in a Marriott hotel in Warsaw, would you charge the directors of that hotel for the actions of that agent, end of quote?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4621.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4635.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This provides a telling insight into the Polish government's attitude to the CIA high-value detainee program and demonstrates at the highest level of government involvement in the operation of the secret prison and knowledge of the illegal methods used by the CIA.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4635.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4647.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court has on numerous occasions given particular evidentiary weight to statements from government ministers or other high officials where, and I quote, they acknowledge facts or conduct that place the authorities in an unfavorable light.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4647.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4652.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They may then be construed as a form of admission, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4652.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4663.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Other high-level officials have also been identified, and Senator Marty's 2007 report is, as having had first-hand knowledge of the operations of the secret detention program.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4663.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4671.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The conduct of such persons is an act for which the state is plainly responsible, even if that person exceeds authority or contravenes instructions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4671.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4681.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This longstanding rule of customary international law is codified in Article 7 of the ILC's Articles on State Responsibility and has been consistently recognized by this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4681.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4689.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is beyond dispute that Poland knew about the CIA's high-value detainee program on its territory and the real and immediate risk to which detainees were exposed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4689.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4700.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As Expert 3 told this court yesterday when asked about the extent of Polish awareness, and I quote, Poland not only should have known, Poland in fact did know.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4700.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4705.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The direct involvement of Polish agents entails direct knowledge of the high-value detainee program.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4705.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4718.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland had a positive obligation to take all necessary, appropriate, and feasible measures to protect Abu Zubaydah from violations of his convention rights, even where those violations were committed by non-state agents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4718.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4726.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is demonstrably the case that there were steps reasonably available to Poland to prevent these violations and offer protection to Abu Zubaydah.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4726.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4738.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not only did it fail to comply with its positive obligations, it actively aided, abetted, and facilitated his extraordinary rendition, secret and incommunicado detention and torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4738.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4751.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, and consistent with a long line of authority developed by this court since Soering, the government is responsible for exposing the applicant to a real and substantial risk of torture through actively assisting in and facilitating his removal from its territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4751.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4760.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Abu Zubaydah's transfer out of Poland to Guantanamo proceeded with the full knowledge, acquiescence, and support of the Polish authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4760.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4777.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland has been directly implicated in the removal of Abu Zubaydah to face the risk of torture, detention, and flagrant denial of his right to a fair trial by a series of credible and consistent accounts documenting in minute detail the nature and scope of the involvement of its state agents in the rendition process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4777.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4793.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court has consistently held that the removal of an individual from the territory of a contracting state engages the responsibility of that state, where there are substantial grounds for believing that the person concerned, if removed, faces a real risk of being subject to serious violations of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4793.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4805.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Polish authorities had a positive obligation to ensure there was an independent and rigorous scrutiny of that risk prior to his transfer, and that he was allowed to challenge his removal before an independent judicial body.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4805.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4807.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Abu Zubaydah was denied these fundamental rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4807.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4818.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, the Polish authorities actively and purposely assisted in his secret extrajudicial removal from the territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4818.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4827.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After leaving Poland, Abu Zubaydah continued to be subject to CIA secret detention elsewhere, ultimately being transferred to Guantanamo, where he is currently held in detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4827.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4839.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Polish authorities knew or ought to have known of the real and substantial risk that he would continue to be held in essentially the same regime of detention to which he had been subject up to that point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4839.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4845.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the moment of his transfer, information about the treatment of detainees at Guantanamo Bay was common knowledge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4845.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4856.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was well known that detainees at Guantanamo would be at substantial risk of violations of their rights under Articles 3, 5, 6 and 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4856.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4861.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Subsequent and ongoing violations of the rights of Abu Zubaydah are a direct consequence of Poland's actions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4861.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4872.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On this basis, Poland's responsibility under Articles 3, 5, 6 and 8 of the Convention is engaged in respect of the subsequent torture, detention and flagrant denial of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4872.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4887.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The evidence presented to this Court, including the compelling evidence provided by the four experts yesterday, established beyond a reasonable doubt Polish responsibility through its acts and omissions for violations of Abu Zubaydah's human rights on its territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4887.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4897.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My colleague, Mr Jankowski, will now address the Court on Poland's criminal investigation, the lack of an effective remedy and the failure of the State to provide all necessary facilities to this Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4901.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4902.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Hughes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4902.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4903.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Jankowski.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4913.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4925.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President, honorary members of the Court, all member states of the Council of Europe have a positive obligation under the Convention to investigate serious violation of human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4925.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4936.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That obligation is triggered on authorities becoming aware of credible assertions of arguable claims in cases of forced disappearance, secret detention, and torture involving state agents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4936.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4939.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That obligation is heightened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4939.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4954.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first credible assertion concerning the existence of a CIA black site in Poland were made public in the beginning of November 2005, followed by the, as expert number four described it yesterday, closed meeting of Polish parliament and government members.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4954.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4967.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet it wasn't until May 2008 that the Polish government decided to initiate an investigation in clear breach of the well-established Convention requirements of promptness and expedition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4967.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4978.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the meantime, there had been three comprehensive official reports from institutional bodies establishing that CIA black sites had operated on Polish territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4978.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5008.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This Court, in the Stamirov and Adersvie Russia at paragraph 89, found that the delay of even only a few months to open an investigation may amount to a, quote, delay that must have affected the effectiveness of the proceedings, end of quote, because that, quote, the passage of time would inevitably erode the amount and quality of the evidence available and the appearance of a lack of diligence would cast doubt on the good fate of the investigative efforts, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5008.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5018.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court is entitled to ask, what was Poland doing for over two years prior to the initiation of the pretrial criminal investigation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5018.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5024.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What has Poland been doing since 2008 once the investigation was initiated?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5024.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5030.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why has the investigation continually been extended 10 times at last count?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5030.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5046.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why were the two prosecutors removed and the investigation itself transferred from Warsaw to Krakow just before the victim lawyers were to get acquainted with additional bits, just bits, of the secret part of the investigation file?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5046.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5048.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And why?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5048.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5058.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since then, for nearly two years now, no significant development in this investigation has been disclosed to the victims' representatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5058.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5062.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Polish government has adopted a very simple approach to this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5062.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5081.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It asked this Court to find that this application is premature on the basis that it is currently carrying out an investigation into this allegation, an investigation that was opened only after years of mounting pressure and has continued for more than five years with no end in sight.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5081.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5092.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this light, the most recent statement from government that the investigation, quote, continues to conduct preparatory proceedings is an extraordinary assertion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5092.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5111.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that the proceeding has been formally initiated and is declared to be in progress and subsequently prolonged does not mean that it's actually thorough, complex, conducted in the effective way and may assure protection of rights of the victims and bring effective remedies there, too.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5111.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5126.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third evidence of its dissimulation can be found in the convenient position it has adopted that it cannot engage to the fullest extent with this case because to do so would be seen as an interference with the independence of the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5126.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5129.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet there are already serious concerns about its independence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5129.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5132.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will come back to that issue at the end of my speech.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5132.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5139.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The investigation has been delayed by the unexplained removal on two separate occasions of prosecutors assigned to lead the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5139.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5150.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland also relies on the failure of the US authorities to reply to its request for information to explain why the criminal investigation remains open.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5150.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5165.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, there should be considerable evidence available to the criminal investigation now to allow it to proceed and eventually even now bring charges against at least some individuals responsible for crimes that were committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5165.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5169.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the evidence we had yesterday leads us to that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5169.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5177.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Polish government cannot hide behind the failure of the US government to take responsibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5177.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5185.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The criminal investigation in Poland into CIA black sites began in March 2008, has since stalled and remains pending.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5185.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5187.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Its terms of reference have never been published.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5187.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5191.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do not know its exact scope.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5191.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5205.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And apart from publicly available speculations concerning one individual, a member of the intelligence services, no charges appear to have been brought against the individuals who committed the violations outlined in application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5205.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5213.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that the investigation is neither impartial nor tariff and is completely ineffective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5213.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5224.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We further submit that the applicant has not been able to access the effective remedy within the meaning of Article 13 for this complaint under Article 3, 5, 6, and 8 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5224.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5230.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An applicant is not required to exhaust domestic remedies that are ineffective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5230.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5242.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While we have actively sought to pursue a remedy through the criminal investigation, it has become absolutely clear that this investigation is completely ineffective from the perspective of protection of the victim's rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5242.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5245.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have encountered real difficulties in accessing case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5245.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5251.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have filed a number of pleadings before prosecution offices, yet there has been no real progress in the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5251.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5260.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the prosecution office did not provide us with any particularly formal written decision on the access to the classified of the case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5260.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5267.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not having such decision results actually in the lack of the possibility to challenge that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5267.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5272.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as a result, factual lack of access to the classified part of the case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5272.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5275.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no domestic remedy to challenge such behavior.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5275.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5278.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The party is simply helpless.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5278.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5293.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are unable to take part in the evidence-taking process, have not been informed of or allowed to participate in hearings of witnesses or experts, and have been consistently arbitrarily denied access to the complete file of the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5293.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5299.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There appear to have been no meaningful developments since the investigation was initiated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5299.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5311.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On March 14, 2013, I filed a motion to the prosecutor office in Krakow, asking kindly for its permission to enclose my pleadings regarding this case to the application to this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5311.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5319.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Reply dated 4 October 2013 came to my office on 8 October 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5319.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5330.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm sorry to invoke it, but it is just a tiny little example which illustrates the general feature of this investigation, showing how long does it take to obtain even minor formal decision in this proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5330.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5348.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The nature and scope of the criminal investigation, the ongoing delays, the publicly made suggestions of State interference, and the lack of any meaningful progress all clearly indicate that the government will not provide an effective remedy to the applicant and will not put right the violation complaint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5348.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5364.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relation to the alleged prematurity of this application, in relation to its unjustified delay, it should be stated that the complaint under the 2004 Act has already been filed in this reparatory proceedings and failed to produce any, in particular, the desired effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5364.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5369.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The complaint was filed by another party granted the victim status in the same proceeding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5369.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5373.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was based on the same factual state and proved to be completely ineffective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5373.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5382.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also blocked the case for over two months, as the whole case file needed to be moved to one of the courts in another end of Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5382.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5390.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should another victim apply this facade law and challenge the length of the investigation simply to fulfill the former requirement?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5390.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5393.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A formalistic answer would naturally be yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5393.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5408.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The one I kindly suggest is no, as this formally available domestic remedy, instead of serving its initial substantial goal of a victim, would not only be ineffective but actually counterproductive, causing additional, at least two or three months long, additional delay.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5408.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5415.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We kindly ask the Tribunal to observe the absolute ineffectiveness of this particular remedy in the case at hand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5415.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5423.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relation to the length of the proceedings, what we mainly challenge, however, is the investigation ineffectiveness in protecting applicants' rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5423.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5430.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The attitude of the State at the domestic level is reflected in its approach to these proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5430.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5436.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has relied on a clearly ineffective investigation in order to refuse to engage with the substance of this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5436.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5442.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has failed to address any of the questions posed by the Court in its reply to our memorial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5442.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5447.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has unsuccessfully sought to have today's hearing held behind closed doors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5447.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5459.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now it refuses to comply with this Court's request that it provide documents comprising the extract of the non-confidential part of the Krakow case file on the terms outlined by the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5459.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5468.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland claims that it cannot provide a document to the Court on the basis that the Court's rules do not indicate the way in which fragile documents are protected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5468.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5476.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It suggests alternative methods, such as but not limited to visiting its premises here in Strasbourg or attending the office of the general prosecutor in Warsaw.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5476.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5481.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no indication as to the length of the document, its content, or its complexity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5481.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5492.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no explanation as to how the applicants' legal representatives are to consider this document and whether they will be allowed to make copies or take notes in order to better understand its input.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5492.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5498.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In short, the alternatives suggested by the State are value and unsatisfactory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5498.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5512.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Notwithstanding this, the State's assertion that this Court is unable to protect sensitive information is made without foundation, and it's a clear attempt to frustrate the Court's efforts to access all relevant information to assist in its determination of its case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5512.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5529.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In cases concerning grave unlawful actions by State agents, documents from criminal investigations may be fundamental to the establishment of facts, and the absence may have the effect of prejudicing the Court's proper examination of the complaint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5529.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5536.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court has, in such cases, often drawn inferences from the failure to make disclosure of the investigation file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5536.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5544.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 38 of the Convention requires States to furnish all necessary facilities for the Court's examination of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5544.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5566.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court reiterated that where a State fails to submit information without a satisfactory explanation, this may not only give rise to the drawing of inferences as to the well-foundedness of the applicant's allegations, but may also reflect negatively on the level of compliance by a respondent State with its obligation under the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5566.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5579.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In IANOVIT, it held that the obligation to furnish all necessary facilities for its investigation is a corollary of the undertaking not to hinder the effective exercise of the right of individual application under Article 34 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5579.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5597.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has held that effective exercise of this right may be prevented by a State's failure to assist the Court in conducting an examination of all circumstances relating to the case, including in particular, but not producing evidence by which the Court considers crucial for its task.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5597.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5607.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The State's refusal to comply with the Court's production order is consistent with its attempts to avoid any scrutiny that might lead to accountability for its actions and inactions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5607.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5617.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Requests for information have continually been denied on the basis the investigation must maintain its purported independence and stages of confidentiality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5617.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5632.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application of its blanket confidentiality approach to every aspect of this case, including withholding information from the victim's party to proceedings without explanation, is unattainable in light of the evidence set out here today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5632.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5640.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The consequences for the functioning of the Court where States actively seek to prevent or disrupt proper judicial scrutiny of its actions are serious.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5640.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5646.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that this Court should take into account the conduct of the State in failing to disclose the investigation file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5646.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5656.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The State is willfully obstructing this Court from establishing the truth of this case, and the Court should, on the basis draw necessary inference from the failure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5656.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5667.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unjustified limitation of the access to the case file results with limitation of exercising certain rights by the parties, which have no influence and knowledge about the current actual status of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5667.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5678.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is well established in the case law of this Court that the obligation to conduct the effective investigation includes the obligation to provide the victim with the effective access to the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5678.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5688.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There cannot be an effective investigation where the victim has not been allowed to get meaningful access to the case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5688.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5703.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lengthy proceedings, in particular, where the one conducted for more than five years at its in-rem phase and not entering into the in-personam phase cannot be treated as effective remedy for the violation of one's rights and freedom under the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5703.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5726.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that the proceeding is repeatedly and automatically prolonged by General Prosecutor's Office means that the Appealed Prosecution Office, which is in charge of the case, is not forced to act and finish the preparatory proceeding in the reasonable time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5726.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5738.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a counsel of the victim, I was allowed to get access to the secret part of the case files only twice during the whole proceedings since 2010 when I entered it on behalf of the victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5738.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5746.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once I had access to the part of the classified part of the case files for about three hours, as was said a couple of minutes ago.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5746.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5753.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then once more for about 15 minutes to the allegedly classified document, which shouldn't even be treated like one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5753.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5764.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Denying a party access to the case files requires a formal decision in writing of the prosecutor in charge, even though the Appealed Prosecutor Office in Krakow never issued any formal decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5764.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5777.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Denying access to the case files were multiple obstacles of the factual nature that made such access impossible, such as the illustration from October 2013 mentioned earlier.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5777.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5808.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President and the honorary members of the Court, by concluding this submission, I would kindly like to ask not only to help the victims have the right to protect in the effective and just way, and to make clear that prosecutors in charge of the investigation in cases of this importance must run it effectively, professionally, and keeping it independent from all kinds of pressures they might be exposed to right now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5808.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5811.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Prosecutor Schliewa, my distinguished colleague,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5811.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5818.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>invoked certain Polish laws which allegedly guarantee him independence from political pressure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5818.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5827.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With all due respect, Poland's constitution and the European Convention on Human Rights guaranteed certain rights to my client.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5827.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5839.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I am very sorry to say that, but the Polish government didn't seem to care at the time the crimes against Abu Zubaydah were committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5839.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5843.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unfortunately, this hasn't changed much since.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5843.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5843.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5847.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5849.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Jankowski.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5849.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5853.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call the United Nations Special Rapporteur Ben Emmerson, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>ThirdParty</Role>
		<Name>TP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5864.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5890.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Madam President and members of the court, for this unprecedented invitation to address you in person in this most important of cases, and to do so on behalf of the special procedures of the Human Rights Council of the United Nations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5890.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5908.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm bound and pleased to record my thanks to the Secretary General of the United Nations, who has consented to waive the immunity attaching to my mandate in order to enable me to be here, and given his permission for that purpose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5908.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5920.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Madam President, I'm grateful also to the High Commissioner and her office for the support that they have provided in this regard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5920.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5945.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The focus of the remarks that I will convey on behalf of these institutions this morning is on the scope of the right to truth in contemporary international human rights law, and on its relationship within the architecture of the European Convention on Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5945.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5950.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My observations fall into three parts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5950.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5963.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I am not, of course, going to comment on the facts of these cases, or the adequacy of the investigations that have or have not been conducted in relation to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5963.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5992.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the first part of my submissions, I'm going to explain why it is that the United Nations Human Rights Mechanisms consider the right to truth in the context of such gross and systematic human rights violations as are alleged here to be a freestanding right vested not solely in the individual victim and his or her representatives, but also in society at large.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5992.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6008.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Next, I will move on to say a few words concerning the location of that rather unusual species of right which has both an individual and a collective aspect within the framework of this particular convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6008.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6038.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in the final part of my submissions, I'm going to update the court on some recent developments, some of them very recent, that have occurred at United Nations level, which are of relevance to the criminal conspiracy hatched and implemented by the Bush-era CIA involving rendition, torture, and secret detention of high-value detainees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6038.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6046.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I begin, then, with the scope of the right to truth as it is understood within the United Nations Human Rights System currently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6046.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6072.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I could refer, if I may, parenthetically to the amicus brief that was submitted by the High Commissioner for Human Rights in the El Masri and Macedonia case, where she drew attention to a range of international instruments negotiated at United Nations level, which now recognize the right to truth as having both an individual and a collective dimension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6072.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6106.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They include the International Convention for the Protection of All Persons from Enforced Disappearances, the Convention Against Torture, the UN Basic Principles and Guidelines on the Right to a Remedy and Reparation for Victims of Gross Violations of International Human Rights Law and Serious Violations of Humanitarian Law, and the updated set of principles for the Protection and Promotion of Human Rights through Actions to Combat Impunity, all of them instruments concerned and concerned solely with gross and systematic violations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6106.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6123.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She referred also to the repeated resolutions of the Human Rights Council itself concerning the right to truth, as well as to comparable statements from her own office, from the Committee Against Torture, and from the various of the special procedures mandate holders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6123.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6131.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We speak with one voice in our understanding of the scope and nature of this right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6131.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6136.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The contours are, we say, now well settled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6136.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6148.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in our view, they are fully reflected in the short statement of principle of the majority of the court in the El-Masri case at paragraph 191.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6148.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6167.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In that passage, the majority of the court held that the right to truth belongs not just to the individual victim, but also, and I quote, to other victims of similar crimes and the general public who had the right to know what happened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6167.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6172.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court was right to say that in the context of such systematic violations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6176.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6203.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My annual report to the Human Rights Council in March of this year, as I foreshadowed in my initial intervention letter in these proceedings, sets out what I've described as framework principles for securing accountability of public officials for gross and systematic human rights violations committed in the context of state counterterrorism initiatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6203.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6217.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are general principles concerning the right to truth and its relationship with the duty of accountability and the international law imperative to end impunity for systematic human rights violations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6217.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6220.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The document is, of course, publicly available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6220.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6225.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I have arranged for it to be formally submitted onto the record in these proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6225.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6230.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is already formally on the record in the linked proceedings brought by Mr. Al-Nashiri</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6230.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6232.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>against Romania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6232.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6238.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can I just say a word or two about it before looking at its implications on the right to truth?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6241.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6249.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The process of seeking the truth about the Bush-era conspiracy has taken a very, very considerable time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6249.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6256.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it has been gathering momentum in the past three years or so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6256.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6272.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Independent investigations have reliably established the complicity to a greater or lesser degree of the public officials of a large number of states in the CIA rendition, secret detention, and torture program.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6272.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6276.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I use the word torture without hesitation or qualification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6276.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6284.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do not recognize the notion of enhanced interrogation as practiced by the CIA as being anything other than torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6284.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6308.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is now credible evidence to show that CIA black sites were located on the territory of Lithuania, Morocco, Poland, Romania, and Thailand, and that the officials of at least 49 other states within and outside the Council of Europe allowed their airspace or airports to be used for rendition flights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6308.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6317.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite the emergence of these facts, only one state has so far brought any public official to justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6317.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6346.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 4th of November 2009, the Milan criminal tribunal convicted 22 CIA agents in absentia, including the Milan station chief of the CIA, for their role in the abduction of Hassan Mustafa Osama Nasir, a dual Egyptian-Italian national in Milan in February 2003, and his rendition to Cairo, where he was detained for 14 months and repeatedly tortured.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6346.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6357.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The CIA officials responsible were sentenced by the Italian criminal court to terms of imprisonment of between five, seven, and nine years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6357.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6363.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Claims to withhold relevant evidence were eventually rejected by the domestic courts on appeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6363.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6389.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on the 1st of February of this year, convictions were returned additionally against the Italian officials involved in the abduction and rendition, including an official as senior as the former director of the Italian military intelligence service, who was in February of this year sentenced to 10 years immediate imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6389.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6416.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The prosecutions brought in Italy in the case of Hassan Mustafa Omar are nothing more and nothing less than straightforward applications of the relevant principles of international law that are binding on every member of the United Nations, every member of the Council of Europe, and every signatory to the European Convention on Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6416.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6436.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I cannot but record, therefore, that it must be a matter of obvious regret to all of us that that remains the only instance amongst this entire international criminal conspiracy in which the perpetrators of those crimes have so far been brought to justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6440.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6457.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The experience of the past decade has shown that there are various means by which the right to truth and the principle of accountability can be and have been frustrated, perpetuating effective impunity for the public officials involved in these crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6457.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6484.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They include de facto immunities, officially authorized destruction of relevant evidence, objective obstruction or interference in independent investigations, unjustified assertions of executive secrecy, dilatoryness, interruptions in investigations, suppression, delayed publication of reports, and so on and so forth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6484.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6511.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should report, as I'm sure the Court is aware, that in March of 2009, the United States, after all, the orchestrator of this conspiracy, through its Senate Select Committee on Intelligence, began a comprehensive investigation into the secret detention and interrogation program chaired by Senator Dianne Feinstein.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6511.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6523.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under the published terms of reference, the committee is to inquire whether the CIA implemented the program, how it implemented the program, where and in what circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6523.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6541.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has obvious relevance, the report has obvious relevance to any case, including these ones, which are said to be manifestations of that program because it is the single, sole, and totally comprehensive analysis that has access to all relevant material.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6541.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6551.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In December 2011, Senator Feinstein announced that the committee had completed the report and it had been adopted by the committee as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6551.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6571.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in April of 2012, she announced that it would, quote, provide a detailed factual description of how interrogation techniques were used, the conditions under which all detainees were held and where, and the intelligence that was or was not gained from the program.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6571.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6605.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She has since indicated publicly that the majority of the committee believe that the creation of CIA black sites, of the sort that we've described in Europe, and the use of so-called enhanced interrogation techniques were, quote, terrible mistakes, unquote, and that the report would, quote, settle the debate once and for all over whether our nation should ever employ coercive interrogation techniques, such as those detailed in the report.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6605.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6613.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You will appreciate why I thought it might be of some assistance to this court to have a copy of the Feinstein report.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6613.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6633.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I called for its publication in my March report to the Human Rights Council, but I've taken the step of writing directly to the United States to ask for an updated timetable for disclosure of the report so that it might be made available to this chamber in its consideration of these proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6633.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6638.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I have asked for a response by close of play on Friday of this week.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6638.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6642.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will communicate my response as soon as I receive it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6642.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6661.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tangentially, but perhaps less directly relevantly, is the outstanding report prepared and commissioned from a group of privy councillors in the United Kingdom under the chairmanship of Sir Peter Gibson into the United Kingdom's own involvement in the CIA program.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6661.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6673.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wrote a similar letter to the United Kingdom asking for similar updated information on when this report, which has been in the possession of the Prime Minister now for well over a year, is to be published.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6673.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6680.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I am glad to be able to tell you that the information I have received is that its publication is now imminent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6680.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6685.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is measurable in a matter of days, not months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6685.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6687.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm not in a position to give you a precise date.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6687.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6689.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope to be so by Friday of this week.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6689.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6696.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that report, at least, it is anticipated to be available very, very soon indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6696.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6719.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, that is unlikely to have the same relevance to these proceedings as the Feinstein report, which is a comprehensive black box overview of a program now recognized even by those who were closest to the intelligence community in the United States to have been a grave error on their part and one which has left a stain on America's reputation throughout the world.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6719.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6724.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President, I want, if I may, just to touch on what we mean by the right to truth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6724.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6732.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because as I said, within the United Nations, we see this as a right which has two dimensions, a private dimension and a public dimension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6732.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6742.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But there are some voices that still dispute the proposition that the right has a collective dimension belonging to society as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6742.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6761.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for example, in their separate opinion in the El Masri cases, judges Cacer de Val and Lopez Guerra both state in terms that, and I quote, as far as the right to truth is concerned, it is the victim and not the general public who is entitled to this right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6761.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6768.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The human rights mechanisms of the United Nations do not share the view of those two judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6768.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6783.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is the consistent position of the UN mechanisms that where gross or systematic human rights violations are alleged to have occurred, the right to know the truth is not one that belongs solely to the immediate victim, but also to society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6783.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6791.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And whilst the two dimensions may overlap, they of course will have different procedural implications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6791.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6809.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But both need to be accommodated in cases where, such as is the position with this particular program, there has been undoubtedly a pattern of systematic and deliberate and organized human rights violation on a grand scale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6809.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6822.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The right to truth as a separate right owes its first recognition to the inter-American human rights system and was a response to the widespread disappearances in the South American dictatorships.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6822.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6835.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it's since come to be recognized within the United Nations instruments as a dual aspect right in a range of contexts where gross and systematic violations are engaged.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6835.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6838.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the reasoning behind it is simple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6838.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6845.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was explained by my colleague, the special rapporteur on the right to freedom of expression, Mr. Frank LaRue,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6845.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6854.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>just over a month ago in his most recent report to the General Assembly, which I've had added to the court file in these proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6854.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6861.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm just going to read you a short passage which summarizes why it is that this right must be seen in both dimensions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6861.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6871.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He says, the right to truth is a collective right which ensures society access to information that is essential for the workings of democratic systems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6871.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6877.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it's also a private right for relatives of victims which affords a form of compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6877.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6890.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the context of serious human rights violations, there is a particular obligation which requires states to inform not only the victims and their families, but also society as a whole of what has happened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6890.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6907.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The right to truth implies not only the clarification of the immediate circumstances of the particular violations, but also the clarification of the general context, the policies, and institutional failures and decisions that enabled their occurrence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6907.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6916.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Beyond this, the realization of the right to truth may require the dissemination of information on violations in order to restore confidence in state institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6916.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6923.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It goes really, in other words, to the heart of the very democratic principles which underlie this convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6923.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6936.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is why we say the court in El Masri, the majority, was right to link the collective aspect of the right to truth with the gravity of the allegations that were at issue in that case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6936.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6943.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If you look at paragraph 191, it is directly anchored, that statement of principle, in the seriousness of the allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6943.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6961.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not, of course, every individual violation of the convention in isolation and of a civil or political right of a different and perhaps less grave character that would carry with it a collective right for the public at large to know the full truth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6961.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6995.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But where it's established that gross or systematic violations have occurred, the right to know what happened and why are essential foundations for preventing impunity, dispelling an appearance of official tolerance, guaranteeing non-repetition, and for participatory decision making in a democracy so that the citizenry are in a position to know who did and did not do what when they are deciding who should be their government for the future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6995.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7015.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While that is an approach which may seem counterintuitive to a convention lawyer, because we are, after all, lawyers dealing with a convention that was pioneering for the very fact that it enabled individuals for the first time to be the subjects of international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7015.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7028.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And many of its provisions are crafted around the position of the individual vis-a-vis the state, including Article 1, and perhaps above all, the right of individual petition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7028.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7044.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But once it's recognized that in cases of gross or systemic violation, there's a freestanding right to truth belonging to society at large, then it follows that any individual with a legitimate interest in the truth is entitled to invoke that right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7044.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7068.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it were the right to truth to be confined to the individual who had suffered the violation or his representatives, then the exposure of grave and systematic international crimes would necessarily be dependent on the chance occurrence of there being an individual victim or relative who was able and willing to bring proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7068.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7074.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let us imagine for a moment that more of those detained as a result of this program had died.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7074.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7075.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some did, we know.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7075.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7078.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But let's assume that more had died.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7078.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7088.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And let's assume that their relatives did not want to identify themselves as individuals associated with people who had been detained, tortured for al-Qaeda purposes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7088.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7091.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Who then owns the right to truth?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7091.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7105.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Where human rights violations are sufficiently serious, and I repeat, the threshold is gross or systematic violations, then the societal interest in the truth cannot be made to depend on chance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7105.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7120.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That would be contrary to the very essence, object, and purpose of human rights law, of this convention, and of the underlying democratic principles on which it is based.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7120.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7140.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The notion that the right to truth should be seen as collective, though it was culled in the context of societies making the transition from totalitarianism to democracy, trying to come to terms collectively with their past, is by no means confined to those circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7140.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7155.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The need for accountability in that broader sense has continuing implications in this context, where we are dealing with a global conspiracy, something which was affected with 49 states involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7155.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7170.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Involving well-established democracies, then a proper recognition of the right to truth has implications going well beyond the espace juridique of this convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7170.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7199.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the perspective of my mandate, it remains vitally important to place this question in its political and security context, and to recall the relationships between the conditions that are conducive to the spread of terrorism, that is, the recruitment of terrorist ideology and violent extremism, and the measures that can be effectively used to counter that threat.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7199.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7217.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's an approach that is embodied expressly in pillars 1 and 4 of the UN Global Strategy on Counterterrorism, which most recently was readopted in June 2012, to address not just the manifestations of terrorism, but its underlying causes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7217.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7242.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the success of the international community's initiatives countering the appeal of violent extremism depends on persuading civil societies in some of the most vulnerable and unstable regions of the world that the world's democratic governments and organizations are genuinely committed to upholding the rule of law and respecting human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7242.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7269.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And two vital components, essential components, of the framework that carries that message to the place where it is needed most for international peace and stability are the collective right to truth and the duty of accountability which imposes, even under this convention, on all states a duty to conduct investigations exproprio motu without the need for a victim to initiate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7269.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7293.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is self-evident that the international community's expressed commitment to ending impunity is antithetical to the maintenance of a laissez-faire doctrine of de facto immunity through inaction for public officials who engaged in acts of torture, rendition, secret detention, and those with whom they collaborated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7293.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7297.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or putting it another way, if Italy can do it, why can't it do it for us?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7297.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7302.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If Germany can do it, why can't other states?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7302.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7318.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The continuing failure to address past crimes inevitably generates the misperception in other parts of the world that the perpetrators of those crimes remain as beneficiaries of official toleration or collusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7318.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7327.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However inaccurate some of those perceptions may be, they will endure until decisive action is taken.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7327.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7358.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is impossible to build bridges, to win hearts and minds, and to draw a line under this terrible period of our history when some of the darkest crimes were committed under the color of authority of state, whilst democratic states, including some member states of this Council of Europe, continue to demonstrate resolute indifference to the involvement of their predecessor administrations in those crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7358.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7368.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can I then just turn briefly to how and why we say that idea fits within the Convention's structure, and I'll do so in short order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7368.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7376.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question here is how best to locate a right with collective aspects within the framework of the Convention's articles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7376.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7401.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we can see from El Masri itself that there are legitimate and serious differences of view, even among the judges of this court, whether the right is to be recognized as part of the adjectival obligation attaching to Article 3, as part of the right to receive information attaching to Article 10, or as part of the right to reparation under Article 13, effective domestic remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7401.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7409.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All three views are reflected in different parts of the opinions in El Masri.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7409.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7418.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The UN human rights mechanisms adopt a holistic approach to this, one which promotes the objective of ending impunity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7418.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7436.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say that the court was right in El Masri to locate the right to truth in the adjectival obligation owed under Article 3, but that it was wrong not to make a separate finding in relation to Article 10.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7436.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7447.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is because the collective dimension of the right can only be fully reflected through the rubric of the right to receive information under Article 10.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7447.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7471.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as I said earlier, I have submitted this morning and yesterday a number of additional recent documents, including the recent report of the Special Rapporteur on the right to freedom of expression, that explains in great detail why it is that the right to receive information and the right to truth about gross and systematic human rights violations are inextricably intertwined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7471.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7485.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Putting it another way, if you locate the right to truth solely in Article 3, that presupposes that at the international level, it can only be invoked by the victim of the underlying violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7485.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7507.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But once it's recognized that it is a freestanding principle of international law, then the category of person who is entitled to invoke that right will include those who have a legitimate interest, representative interest groups, and as well as the media, who have a duty to seek the truth and to inform the public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7507.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7518.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So under the architecture of the convention, we say the appropriate place to locate the collective dimension of the right is under the right to receive information protected by Article 10.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7518.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7520.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7520.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7529.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the first concurring opinion to the decision in El Masri, there is discussion about the role of Article 13.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7529.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7541.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course, it's true that this right has its reflection in Article 3, has its reflection in Article 10, and has its reflection at a domestic level also in Article 13.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7541.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7551.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it's well established that from the perspective of an individual victim, that right, the right to an effective remedy, includes a right to the truth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7551.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7557.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You'll find that in the Law Commission's articles, but it really is a self-evident proposition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7557.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7569.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we would respectfully invite the court to pause and caution against an approach which would situate the right to truth in Article 13 alone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7569.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7586.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That may be an appropriate means to vindicate the aspect of the right which is individual, but since Article 13 is parasitic on the underlying substantive violation, it would leave the collective aspect of the right unprotected and unreflected in the convention's articles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7586.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7596.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, even as regards the individual right, there are some states that have chosen not to incorporate Article 13 into their own domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7596.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7607.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The United Kingdom is a case in point, taking the view that their domestic implementing legislation is sufficient to prescribe the scope and limit of domestic remedies available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7607.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7632.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so if the right were to be located solely in Article 13, there would be protection gaps at both level, inconsistent with the principle of subsidiarity, as well as with the guiding philosophy of the Brighton Conference, which is to devolve responsibility for human rights protection to national institutions as far as possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7632.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7632.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President, those are our submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7637.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7640.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Emmerson.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7640.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7646.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to judges if there are any questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7646.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7646.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Hirvelä.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7649.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7650.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7650.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7653.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7654.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7680.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has referred to the principle of subsidiarity and the advanced investigations carried out by the prosecutor in Poland and we can really read from the documents that there have been, for example, 62 persons who have been interrogated and 21 volumes of main files with documentary evidence that has been collected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7680.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7694.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the investigation of the allegations has been ongoing since 2008 and lasted already five years and 10 years since the alleged events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7694.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7704.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since this case has been brought before this court today, I have to ask, what has come up in the investigation so far?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7704.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7712.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Meaning, does the government challenge the allegations of the applicants or not?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7712.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7736.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my second question, which is linked to the first one, is the applicants have been granted victim status in the domestic investigation and does this indicate that there has appeared evidence that the applicants have been transferred via Poland or, or, and that they have been detained in Poland?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7736.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7736.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7738.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7740.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Hirvelä.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7740.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7740.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Wojtyczek, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7743.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7745.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Madam President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7745.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7755.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question to the government, but maybe the applicants, the counsels of the applicants may wish to comment on this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7755.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7764.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties refer to a criminal investigation carried out under the Polish Code of Criminal Procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7764.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7771.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Has there been in Poland any other kind of investigation carried out by other public authorities?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7771.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7776.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, what are the results of those investigations?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7776.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7776.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7778.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7780.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Wojtyczek, Judge De Gaetano.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Vincent A. De Gaetano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7785.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7787.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Madam President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7788.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7801.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first question to government is in connection with what was stated at the beginning of the government's submissions on rules of procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7801.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7820.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Am I correct, or would this court be correct in understanding that it is the government's view that procedural rules of this court should give way to national rules of procedure, particularly whenever confidentiality or secrecy is involved?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7820.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7838.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, is it government's contention that if a respondent government pleads confidentiality or secrecy, then the proceedings before this court stop? That is my first question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7841.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7848.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question refers to the plea of prematurity of the applications. I believe</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7850.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7854.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it was raised in respect of both applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7854.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7862.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government is asking this court to consider that the applications are premature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7862.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7888.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can the government comment at least on why the investigations in Poland, which began either in May or March, I don't remember exactly, of 2008, can the government comment at least on why the investigation was only started in 2008 and not before?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7888.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7901.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was it an ex officio investigation or was it on the complaint of an injured party or on a report by a public official?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7901.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7909.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My third question is this. Can the government comment, if at all, on the statement made</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7909.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7925.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by counsel for one of the applicants that there is no remedy at domestic law, no remedy of judicial review to challenge the classification of documents in criminal investigations?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7925.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7943.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My last question is, is the respondent government in a position to comment, if at all, on the change of prosecutors in this case? We've heard of at least the investigation having</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7943.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7950.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>passed into the hands of three prosecutors. What was the reason, if this reason can be</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7950.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7950.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>given, if at all, why there was this change of prosecutors?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7955.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7957.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge De Gaetano.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7957.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7957.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Kalaydjieva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Zdravka Kalaydjieva</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7960.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7962.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Madam President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7962.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7967.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question also goes to the respondent government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7967.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7983.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as I understand your position, you do not contest the fact that various planes landed and took off from different airports on the territory of Poland, including Szymany .</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7983.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8008.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, having been informed of the applicants' complaints before this court, have the investigation or other authorities of your country been able to check and confirm, so as to confirm or deny, the fact that the applicants have been, for certain periods of time, on the territory of Poland?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8008.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8021.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, do you maintain any border control system capable of checking the number of arriving and departing passengers, as well as their identity?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8021.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8026.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question does not go to the result of any such steps.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8026.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8030.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is whether at all such steps have been taken.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8031.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8034.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Judge Kalaydjieva, Judge Bianku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ledi Bianku</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8037.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8038.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Madam President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8038.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8044.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is somehow related to the second question of Judge Hirvela and probably to the question of Judge Kalaydjieva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8044.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8048.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will slightly expand it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8048.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8056.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Does it mean that the victim status of Mr. Al Nashiri, recognition at domestic level,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8056.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8062.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>means that to Mr. Al Nashiri is considered like being under the jurisdiction, not under</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8062.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8070.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the territory itself, but under the jurisdiction of Polish state, having in mind also the serving jurisprudence?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8073.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8075.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Judge Bianku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8075.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8091.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there are no further questions, the court will now break for 15 minutes to enable the parties to prepare their answers to the questions of the judges and the short replies to each other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8091.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8091.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court is in the break.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8122.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8123.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8155.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8155.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8164.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8167.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court resumes the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8167.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8174.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call on Mr. Nowak-Far.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8190.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8213.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Wysoki Sądzie, z uwagi na treść pytań proponuję Wysokiemu Sądowi, żebym ja odpowiedział na jedno z pytań, natomiast co do reszty, z uwagi na to, że one dotyczą aspektu prokuratorskiego, bym prosił o udzielenie głosu Panu Prokuratorowi Śliwie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8213.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8244.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ja postaram się odpowiedzieć na pytanie czwarte, to jest pytanie Pana Sędziego Gatano dotyczącego tego, czy oczekujemy, że reguły proceduralne Sądu, Trybunału powinny uwzględniać, czy stosować reguły krajowe w takim zakresie, w jakim jest to potrzebne do zachowania w tajemnicy dokumentów klauzulowanych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8244.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8260.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moja odpowiedź brzmi nie. To nie jest nasze oczekiwanie. Raczej widzimy tutaj bardzo poważny gap, brak w regulacji sądu,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8260.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8282.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>polegający na tym, że sąd powinien naszym zdaniem przyjąć własne reguły, które by zapewniały prawidłową nić współpracy pomiędzy państwami, które chciałyby udzielić Trybunałowi materiałów, które są objęte tajemnicą państwową, a samym Trybunałem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8282.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8294.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Celem takich procedur musiałoby być zapewnienie wysokiego poziomu bezpieczeństwa tych dokumentów w zakresie ich przechowywania, udzielania dostępu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8294.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8299.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A więc mówimy tutaj o fundamentalnych gwarancjach zachowania tajemnicy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8299.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8315.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To jest ta nasza odpowiedź na pytanie Pana Sędziego. Ja bym teraz za pozwoleniem sądu przechadzał głos Panu Prokuratorowi Śliwie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8315.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8330.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dodam tylko, że ten dokument, o którym wspomnieliśmy i który chcieliśmy przekazać sądowi, on zawierał zarówno materiały jawne, czy opierał się na materiałach jawnych, jak i niejawnych postępowania przygodowawczego.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8330.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8348.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Krótko mówiąc, byliśmy przekonani, że postępowanie in camera mogłoby dać sądowi sposobność, że było wręcz stworzeniem sposobności dla rządu do wypracowania tego rodzaju modelu współpracy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8348.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8348.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To jest tylko taki dodatek. Bardzo dziękuję.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8356.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8357.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Śliwa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8363.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8366.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Wysoki Trybunale, Pani Prezydent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8367.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8374.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Postaram się udzielić według mojej najlepszej wiedzy odpowiedzi na te pytania, które zostały skierowane w odniesieniu do postępowania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8376.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8383.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pragnę jednak na wstępie zaznaczyć, iż w swojej wypowiedzi nie mogę się odnosić do ustaleń faktycznych, które zostały poczynione w toku śledztwa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8385.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8390.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W pierwszym rzędzie chciałbym odnieść się do pytania związanego ze statusem pokrzywdzonego w toku polskiego śledztwa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8390.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8394.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I pytania, czy oznacza to określony poziom ustaleń faktycznych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8396.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8406.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otóż tak jak pozwoliłem sobie w wystąpieniu wskazywać, decyzja procesowa o uznaniu danej osoby za pokrzywdzonego nie zapada w polskiej procedurze.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8406.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8412.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jest ona związana z przekonaniem organu o tym, że zostały spełnione dwa elementy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8412.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8417.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Subiektywny, czyli element związany z indywidualnym odczuciem pokrzywdzenia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8417.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8427.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I dwa, jednak element obiektywizujący, dotyczący uprawdopodobnienia, że na szkodę konkretnej osoby popełnione zostało w Polsce przestępstwo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8431.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8436.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tyle mogę powiedzieć, że jest to problem związany z uprawdopodobnieniem popełnienia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8436.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8444.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I ten stopień uprawdopodobnienia jest na tyle wysoki, że polska prokuratura na podstawie zgłoszeń traktuje skarżących jako pokrzywdzonych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8444.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8453.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Między innymi ustalenia śledztwa zmierzają do tego, aby potwierdzić w jakim zakresie konkretne osoby zostały przez kogo pokrzywdzone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8453.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8467.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jeżeli chodzi o moją aktualną wiedzę, z tego co mi wiadomo, nie toczą się w Polsce inne postępowania karne dotyczące tego samego przedmiotu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8467.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8479.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ustaliliśmy, iż toczyło się jedno postępowanie na północy Polski związane z funkcjonowaniem w tym okresie portu lotniczego i rozliczeń.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8479.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8482.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ono miało charakter karnoskarbowy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8482.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8486.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Materiały tego postępowania zostały przekazane do prokuratury apelacyjnej w Krakowie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8486.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8490.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I znajdują się obecnie także w szerokich materiałach prowadzonej sprawy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8490.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8495.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Także możemy z nich korzystać.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8495.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8506.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kluczowe dla jedności, zwartości i możliwości dowodowych tego postępowania jest przede wszystkim fakt pozyskania materiałów niejawnych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8506.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8509.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Wydaje się, że one decydują o tym.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8509.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8521.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jedyne postępowanie, które może przyczynić się do wyświetlenia faktów badanych w jego toku, toczy się aktualnie właśnie w prokuraturze apelacyjnej w Krakowie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8521.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8535.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W trakcie pytania dotyczącego zawiadomienia, otóż sprawa rzeczywiście została wszczęta w 2008 roku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8535.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8541.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dokładnie 31 stycznia 2008 roku został przesłuchany pierwszy świadek.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8541.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8545.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I miał on charakter osoby zawiadamiającej o podejrzeniu popełnienia przestępstwa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8545.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8550.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Był to rzeczywiście funkcjonariusz publiczny.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8550.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8557.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W związku z czym powołał on się na konieczność zwolnienia go z obowiązku zachowania tajemnicy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8557.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8567.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mógł być uzupełniająco przesłuchany dopiero po wykonaniu formalnych czynności związanych z uchyleniem tej tajemnicy na potrzeby postępowania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8567.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8574.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Taka procedura została przeprowadzona i w konsekwencji 11 marca 2008 roku śledztwo zostało wszczęte.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8574.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8587.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I w marcu 2008 roku wystąpiono już o żądanie podstawowych dokumentów do szefa Kancelarii Sejmu RP.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8587.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8593.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Odpowiedzi na system dotyczący monitorowania osób przybywających do Polski.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8593.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8597.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Według mojej wiedzy taki system funkcjonuje.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8597.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8608.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sprawdzenia w tym zakresie, w toku śledztwa zostały podjęte dużo wcześniej, zostały wywiedzione skargi do Europejskiego Trybunału Praw Człowieka w Strasburgu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8608.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8621.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prace związane z zabezpieczeniem materiału dowodowego zostały podjęte w toku śledztwa niezwłocznie po jego wszczęciu w 2008 roku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8621.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8638.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jeżeli chodzi o kwestię związaną z możliwością zakwestionowania klasyfikacji określonych materiałów, wydaje się, że istnieje taka możliwość prawna.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8638.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8654.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Na podstawie artykułu 9 obowiązującego w Polsce prawa ustawy o ochronie informacji niejawnych, zgodnie z treścią tego zapisu, odbiorca materiału w przypadku stwierdzenia zawyżenia klauzuli może się zwrócić do osoby, która ją nadała z wnioskiem o dokonanie stosownej zmiany.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8654.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8664.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jest przewidziany tryb sporu w tym zakresie i jego rozstrzygnięcie przez najwyższe organy państwowe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8664.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8686.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Wprawdzie przepis ten nie odnosi się bezpośrednio do uprawnień osób reprezentujących w polskim śledztwie pokrzywdzonych, ale niewątpliwie taki wniosek, jeśli formalnie zostałby skierowany do prokuratora prowadzącego postępowanie, będzie rozpoznawany i procedowany.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8686.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8693.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kwestia dotycząca zmiany prokuratury prowadzącej postępowanie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8693.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8703.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jest to zgodne z polskim systemem prawnym. Uprawnienie, które zostało przypisane prokuratorowi generalnemu,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8703.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8705.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>może się nim posługiwać.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8705.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8710.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Trudno mi jest odpowiedzieć za prokuratora generalnego, który nigdy nie ujawniał powodów swojej decyzji.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8710.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8718.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mogę tylko powiedzieć, że nie jest to sytuacja bez precedensu, a precedens, na który chciałbym się powołać, jest bardzo istotny z punktu widzenia państwa polskiego.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8718.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8727.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dotyczy bowiem także przeniesienia z Warszawy do prokuratury apelacyjnej w Łodzi śledztwa dotyczącego zabójstwa generała Papały, polskiego komendanta głównego policji.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8727.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8734.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Takie przeniesienie w tej konkretnej sprawie przyczyniło się do nowego spojrzenia na zebrany dotychczas materiał dowodowy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8734.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8746.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pozwoliło na zdynamizowanie postępowania, które aktualnie się toczy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8746.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8766.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W zakresie pytań dotyczących statusu pokrzywdzonego i odpowiedniego poziomu uprawdopodobnienia, że skarżący zostali pokrzywdzeni przestępstwami popełnionymi na terytorium Polski, zdaniem delegacji łączy się to także z kwestią pozostawania w jurysdykcji i z zasadą terytorialności.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8766.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8772.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W tym zakresie uznajemy za uprawdopodobniony fakt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8772.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8779.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Natomiast końcowe działania śledcze mogą doprowadzić do jego pełnego potwierdzenia w takim zakresie, aby stało się to podstawą decyzji procesowej.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8791.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8793.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8793.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8795.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now call Ms. Singh.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8799.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8804.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With the court's permission, Madam President, I would begin the answer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8800.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8801.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Dutrych?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8801.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8803.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With the court's permission, Madam President, I would begin the answer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8803.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8803.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8805.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8807.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on behalf of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8807.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8810.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, I would like to address on behalf of Mr. Al-Nashiri</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8810.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8815.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the question posed by Judge Vojticek.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8815.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8823.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Specifically, to our best knowledge, there was another inquiry, but it cannot be said to have been anywhere near an effective inquiry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8823.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8834.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was referred to by witness number one at today's fact-finding hearing, and it was dismissed by this witness as being highly irregular and ineffective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8834.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8841.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This inquiry is also referred to in the Marti Report from 2006 under Section 252.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8841.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8845.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Marti Report also indicates the complete ineffectiveness of this inquiry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8845.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8855.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was, in fact, a closed-door hearing of a permanent commission concerning special services of the Polish Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8855.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8862.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Most of the members of this commission were, in fact, expelled from the hearing because they did not have the adequate clearance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8862.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8870.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This hearing was, to our best knowledge, a meeting between select members of this parliamentary commission and top intelligence officials.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8870.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8873.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It did nothing in terms of fact-finding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8873.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8882.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It did nothing in terms of transparency of its reasoning and published only the conclusion that it found nothing illegal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8882.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8887.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This can hardly be said to be an effective investigation and should not be treated as such.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8887.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8903.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, I would like to address a point made twice now by the government, which points out that Poland is one of the few countries to actually be conducting an investigation, and it is my understanding the government suggests that it is to be congratulated on this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8903.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8906.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, this is not sufficient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8906.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8916.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This does not mean that the investigation is effective, transparent, prompt, and independent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8916.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8936.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, by way of rebuttal, Madam President, to answer, I would like to refer to one of the questions of the court regarding the system of border control, controlling who comes into the state, who leaves the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8936.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8942.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President, one of the ways in which the Polish state violated Mr. Al-Nasri's rights</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8942.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8956.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was that the special service agents of the Polish state expressly prohibited the border guards from coming near the plane and verifying who was being brought in, who was being brought out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8956.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8963.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is, in fact, the way that the Polish state inhibited the vindication of Mr. Nasri's rights</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8963.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8965.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the protection of those rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8965.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8968.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8968.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8969.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My colleague, Ms. Singh, would like to address</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8969.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8969.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a few further issues, if possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP4</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8984.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9012.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President and members of the court, it is striking that despite repeated opportunities given to the Polish government to answer the court's questions, till this time it still has not answered those questions with respect to whether or not they contest the factual allegations set out in the applicant's submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9012.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9022.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, we submit the reason they're unable to contest these facts is because these facts are true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9022.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9040.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the court has heard overwhelming evidence, both documentary evidence as well as the testimony of expert witnesses, that confirm that the allegations in the application submissions are true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9040.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9071.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With respect to Judge Wotaczek's question as to whether there are other methods for investigating or admitting the truth of the matter beyond the criminal investigation, we respectfully submit that nothing prevents the Polish government from admitting in general terms that in fact there was a CIA prison on Polish territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9071.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9075.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because the overwhelming evidence in fact shows that that's the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9075.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9083.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, we just heard from the prosecutor that, and I quote, he says, the events are sufficiently credible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9083.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9106.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that this investigation began in 2008, more than five years after our client was detained in Poland, the fact that it has gone on for so long only demonstrates that this is just another opportunity to obscure the truth, both from the applicant and from the public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9109.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9119.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To sum up, the overwhelming evidence before this court supports the truth of Mr. Al-Nasri's application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9119.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9126.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in contrast, the government has utterly failed to rebut those allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9126.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9130.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court should therefore find that Mr. Al-Nasri has</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9130.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9132.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>established the truth of his allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9132.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9132.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9136.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9137.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Ms. Singh.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9137.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9139.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Hughes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9139.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9144.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, Mr. Jankowski, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9153.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9162.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Madam President. Very briefly, in relation to the victim status of both applicants,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9162.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9182.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think it is absolutely beyond any doubt in relation to what was said by the prosecutor representing government that both elements, subjective and objective, are met in this case. The prosecutor even today says that there is a certain level of probability that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9182.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9198.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>my client suffered from crimes committed against him in the territory or within the jurisdiction of the Polish law. I wonder why he may not say in the face of the quality of evidence</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9198.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9212.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that even yesterday was presented in front of the court that it is absolutely beyond reasonable doubt. In relation to the very specific provisions of law that were invoked</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9212.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9228.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a couple of minutes ago to challenge the decision about the classification of certain documents, there might be such procedure, one may say, completely beyond the scope of jurisdiction of this tribunal. But in order even to apply that, one needs to find</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9228.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9234.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>out what has been classified. We've only been trying to get access to the file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9234.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9251.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once seeing that, once being granted this essential right within the criminal proceedings, essential from the perspective of a victim who we represent, then we would probably might consider any such actions. But I have very strong doubts if this is in any way applicable</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9251.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9251.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to these proceedings. Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9264.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9297.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President, members of the Court, in respect of Judge Gaetano's question, the suggestion from the State today that there is some kind of lacuna or gap in the way in which this document should be dealt with by the Court is not borne out by any reasoned argumentation or reasoned grounds why the government cannot comply with an order made in time, sufficiently, and on two separate occasions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9297.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9311.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would ask the Court, based on the government's attitude to that particular issue, to draw inferences from its approach to the provision of that document to the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9311.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9333.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say in that respect that, in practical terms, consistent with its approach throughout the investigation, throughout its dealings with these proceedings, it has maintained a position of obstruction and has maintained a position of not complying with its obligations pursuant to Article 38.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9333.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9339.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In terms of the case itself, in general terms, we would say this, that this Court is not just about principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9339.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9343.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is about practical reality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9343.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9356.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is telling that in everything the government has said, both in writing and orally here today, that when it comes to practical reality, it is unwilling to engage with the evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9356.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9363.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It seeks refuge in what is nothing more than a flawed investigation, a discredited investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9363.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9367.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the strategy in response to the evidence is really quite simple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9367.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9380.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is to invoke and to rely on confidentiality of the investigation, which, in their view, absolves them of any responsibility in connection with the violations that were committed against Abu Zubaydah.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9383.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9387.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't dispute that in certain circumstances, issues may arise in the course of an investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9387.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9404.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But where the state applies a blanket confidentiality approach, we would respectfully request that the Court take into consideration its attitude with respect to both these proceedings and in respect to dealing with the applicant at domestic level in Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9404.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9410.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It relies on the non-cooperation of other states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9410.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9415.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's now hiding behind the apparent conflict between Polish law and the rules of this Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9415.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9427.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is precisely the approach that has informed the cases that are now before this Court, secrecy, confidentiality, and lack of transparency.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9427.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9442.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, it is a basic international law principle that states are not allowed to invoke domestic law to avoid international legal obligations or to justify noncompliance with international legal obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9442.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9448.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In respect of the evidence, we submit that the evidence is overwhelming.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9448.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9461.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We've had consistent and comprehensive accounts of rendition flights, of activity in Ziminy Airport, of the intransigence and obstruction of the Polish government with respect to the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9461.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9482.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There has been categorical affirmation in relation to the existence of prisons in Polish territory, in relation to government knowledge, actual knowledge of what was happening, an act of participation and facilitation in the activities that were happening between 2002 and 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9482.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9484.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The evidence is overwhelming.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9484.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9488.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has, in its reply, said that the events are sufficiently credible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9488.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9497.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would ask the Court to take into consideration everything it heard yesterday and the documentation we've submitted in respect of the application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9497.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9503.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we ask that the Court find violations in respect of Articles 3, 5, 6, and 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9503.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9503.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9508.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9511.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Hughes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9511.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9515.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9515.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9520.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the Court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9520.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9526.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9526.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9529.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9529.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9533.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9533.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9533.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
