<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>3555312_17012018</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>13.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>14.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>56.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>57.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>67.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>78.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the cases of S., V., and A. versus Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>78.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>94.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were lodged with the court on 8 June 2012 under Article 34 of the Convention by three Danish nationals, Mr. S., Mr. V., and Mr. A..</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>94.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>104.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were allocated to the second section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>104.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>112.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were communicated to the government on 7 January 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>112.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>122.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 11 July 2017, the chamber decided to relinquish jurisdiction in favor of the grand chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>122.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>138.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Mr. Tobias Elling Rehfeld, assisted by Mrs. Nina Holst-Christensen, co-agent, Mr. Christian Wegener, and Mr. Jan van Deurs advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>138.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>149.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mr. Claus Bonnez, counsel, assisted by Mr. Tobias Stadarfeld Jensen and Mrs. Hanne Ziebe, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>149.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>154.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>154.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>164.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>164.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>168.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Elling Rehfeld for the government will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>168.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>171.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mr. Bonnez for the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>171.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>173.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Elling Rehfeld.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>173.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>173.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>180.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>182.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>182.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>187.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's an honor to appear before you this morning on behalf of the Danish government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>187.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>203.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case before you concerns a matter of general public interest, interpretation of Article 5 of the European Convention on Human Rights, and the possibility of the police to use preventive detention in situations of vital public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>203.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>214.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the court is well aware, the present case concerns the preventive detention of three applicants on the 10th of October 2009 by the Copenhagen police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>214.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>222.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On that day, a high-profile football match took place in Copenhagen between Denmark and Sweden for the qualification to the World Cup.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>222.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>236.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thousands of peaceful football fans, families, and children had traveled to Copenhagen from all parts of Denmark and Sweden to celebrate their national teams and enjoy the traditionally good-humored neighboring competition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>236.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>250.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, prior to the match, the police had received information that hooligan groups intended to prey on this peaceful sport event and initiate hooligan brawls in connection with the match.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>250.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>261.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police had prepared accordingly, and 186 police officers were deployed throughout Copenhagen to maintain law and order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>261.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>268.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police observed the first major fight break out between Danish and Swedish hooligans around 3.40 PM</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>268.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>272.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the main pedestrian street in the city center of Copenhagen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>272.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>284.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As another group of Danish hooligans were heading towards this fight, the police decided to detain a small number of individuals from this group in order to prevent them from escalating the situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>284.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>287.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second and third applicants were part of that group.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>287.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>292.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the first applicant, he was detained approximately one hour later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>292.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>307.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A witness deemed highly credible by the police had contacted the police with information that he had just overheard the applicant calling other people by phone, inciting them to join him in a fight against Swedish hooligans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>307.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>329.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police released the three applicants approximately 7 and 1 half hours after they had been detained, when the police assessed that the risk of further fighting between the different hooligan groups had diminished sufficiently after a day of running clashes in Copenhagen between hooligan fractions, leading to the arrest and detention of more than 130 persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>332.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>334.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>334.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>342.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>after this very brief summary of the facts, let me now address the question of whether these detentions were lawful under Danish law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>342.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>344.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer to this question is yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>344.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>351.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The criteria for lawful detention are set out in the Danish Police Act, section 5, paragraph 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>351.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>362.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under this provision, the police may detain persons deemed to cause a risk of disturbance of public order and danger to the safety of individuals and public security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>362.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>373.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Travert Propertoire of the Police Act, a crucial point is the probability that the risk or danger will occur if the police do not intervene.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>373.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>383.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, the police may only detain a person if it is considered necessary, and if less intrusive measures are deemed insufficient to avert such a risk or danger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>383.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>386.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police must assess this in each individual case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>390.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>406.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the police had conducted the individual assessments required by the Police Act, establishing that it was indeed necessary to detain the applicants to reduce the risk of further disturbances between the Danish and Swedish hooligans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>406.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>416.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We firmly hold that under these circumstances, the police made the correct assessment by detaining the hooligans, including the second and third applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>416.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>425.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Simply giving a forewarning to the group of hooligans heading towards the fight in the city center by ordering them to leave would have been insufficient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>425.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>436.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nor would it have made sense for the police to redirect the group towards the national football stadium, as all circumstances clearly indicate that the hooligans would not have obeyed by this instruction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>436.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>441.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, one of the applicants, applicant number three, did not even have a ticket for the match.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>441.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>448.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In both situations, the hooligans involved would just have met up elsewhere to initiate or participate in the fighting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>452.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>455.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Similar arguments apply to the first applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>455.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>476.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was overheard planning and inciting others to join him in a fight against Swedish hooligans, thus creating a situation that presented a concrete and an imminent risk of disturbance of the public order, a risk that would have been insufficiently dealt with if the first applicant had just been ordered to leave his location at the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>476.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>479.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, confiscating his mobile phone would also have been insufficient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>479.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>484.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He could easily have acquired one elsewhere and continued his planning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>484.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>500.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this specific situation, it is clear to us that the police, as part of their crowd control measures on the day of the match, was left with no other option than to detain the applicants in order to avoid further escalation of the violence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>500.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>504.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, let me turn to the lawfulness of the length of their detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>504.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>513.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under section 5, paragraph 3 of the Danish Police Act, detention should not extend beyond six hours where possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>513.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>522.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, under status in the Traveau Propertoire of the Police Act, the six-hour period can be extended in special situations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>522.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>534.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were released from detention after 7 and 1 1⁄2 hours, which was as soon as the police assessed that the risk of further hooligan violence had diminished sufficiently in the city of Copenhagen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>534.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>541.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Upon release, the applicants requested a judicial review of the lawfulness of the detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>541.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>551.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A particularly easy access to such a review is available under section 469 of the Danish Administration of Justice Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>551.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>565.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During this subsequent judicial review in two instances, both the District Court of Aarhus and the High Court of Western Denmark reached the conclusion that the detention were lawful under section 5 of the Police Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>565.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>585.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Specifically, both court instances concluded that there were no basis for invalidating the correctness of the assessment made by the police with regards to the concrete and imminent risk posed by the applicants of disturbance of the public order and danger to the safety of individuals and public security on the day of the match.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>585.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>600.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Danish courts thus, in effect, reached the conclusion that the detentions of the applicants were in accordance with the procedure prescribed by international law as required by Article 5, Paragraph 1 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>600.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>604.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>604.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>610.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>allow me now to say a few general remarks about preventive detention and crowd control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>610.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>617.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Preventive detention is a vital tool for the police in situations where crowd control is necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>617.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>622.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The concept is known in many of the member states of the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>622.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>640.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Crowd control concerns situations where the police, in order to keep the peace and maintain public order, need to detain individuals during mass events, for example, in a situation of a large football match where aggressive supporters have assembled and the risk of hooligan brawls is imminent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>640.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>655.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is in these types of situations imperative for the police to have effective means available, such as preventive detention, in order for the police to be able to deflate an otherwise escalating situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>655.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>662.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having touched upon these introductory points on crowd control, I will now turn to the central question in the case at hand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>662.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>673.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was the preventive detention of the three applicants justified under Article V, paragraph 1, subparagraph B, or subparagraph C?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>673.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>682.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When analyzing the court's case law, it is clear that there has been a change in the understanding and interpretation by the court of these subparagraphs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>682.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>686.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This development took its starting point in the 60s with the court's judgment in Lawless v. Island</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>686.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>690.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No. 3 from 1961.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>690.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>697.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In that case, the court concluded that preventive detention could fall within the scope of subparagraph C.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>697.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>703.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court, however, was divided on this matter in the more recent judgment in Ostendorff v. Germany</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>703.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>709.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from 2013, a judgment from the fifth section of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>709.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>720.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Ostendorff case, the majority found that the preventive detention of a German hooligan was justified under subparagraph B, but not justified under subparagraph C.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>720.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>730.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the majority, in our view, moved away from the previous interpretation of the court in Lawless v. Island.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>730.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>747.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the court was divided on the issue with the minority in the Ostendorff case finding that the detention was indeed justified under subparagraph C, favoring a return to the interpretation in the Lawless case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>747.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>754.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This fundamental question of the applicability of Article V has also been the focus of national jurisprudence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>754.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>766.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A relevant example is the judgment of 15 of February 2017 from the United Kingdom Supreme Court, R v. Commissioner of Police for the Metropolis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>766.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>787.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In that case, the United Kingdom Supreme Court found that preventive detention should be justified under subparagraph C, even if it is clear from the outset that the deprivation of liberty is not affected for the purpose of bringing the individual concerned before the courts to decide on the merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>787.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>800.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As demonstrated, the case before the court today is an excellent opportunity for the court to revisit and articulate the understanding and interpretation by the court of subparagraph B and C in situations of preventive detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>805.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>808.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>808.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>812.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the court has asked the Danish government to answer six specific questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>812.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>820.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Danish government has submitted its answers in the written observation to which we refer as regard to questions 1, 2, and 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>820.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>823.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We will not go further into these questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>823.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>828.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today, we will instead focus on the questions 4, 5, and 6.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>828.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>832.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the first of these questions, question 4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>832.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>841.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me start by briefly mentioning the criteria for lawful detention under subparagraph B as set out in the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>841.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>855.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As stated in the Ostendorf case, the main criteria for detention under subparagraph B is that the person detained has failed to fulfill a specific and concrete obligation incumbent on him or her.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>855.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>862.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has made clear that this obligation must be very closely circumscribed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>862.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>872.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If a person is under an obligation not to commit an offense, the person must have taken clear and positive steps indicating intent of non-fulfillment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>872.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>878.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, the person must have been made aware of the offenses he or she is to refrain from committing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>878.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>885.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Danish government is of the opinion that these two criteria are met in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>885.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>898.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The three applicants were subject to a clear obligation to refrain from committing criminal offenses, such as instigating or taking part in fights and hooligan violence, which are criminal offenses under Danish law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>898.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>914.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Notwithstanding that the obligation to refrain from committing these offenses is closely circumscribed under Danish law, the applicants had taken clear and positive steps towards committing such offenses rather than indicating an intent of not committing the offenses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>914.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>927.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we mentioned earlier, the first applicant was overheard calling other individuals, trying to incite them to join him in a fight against Swedish hooligans, a situation very similar to that of the Ostendorf case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>927.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>939.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second and third applicant had specifically been observed talking to a known leader of a Danish hooligan group, as well as issuing orders to other individuals known to be part of the Danish hooligan community.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>939.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>944.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they were on their way to the ongoing fight between the different hooligan groups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>944.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>964.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the second criteria, that the person concerned must be made aware of the specific acts he or she is to refrain from committing, the Danish government recalls the current uncertain state of the interpretation of this particular criteria under subparagraph B.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>964.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>984.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The majority of the judges in the Ostendorf case found that the applicants in that case had been made aware that the police intended to avert hooligan violence, and that he was under an obligation to refrain from arranging and participating in such violence for two reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>984.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>991.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, he'd been ordered by the police to stay with his group, and he was warned that he would be arrested if he left the group.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>993.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1006.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the police had escorted the group earlier in the day, and had searched the group members for instruments typically used in hooligan brawls.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1006.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1018.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The majority of judges did, however, not discuss whether either of these two reasons separately on their own would have been sufficient to make the applicant aware of his obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1018.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1036.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the question remains whether it was sufficient under Article 5, paragraph 1, subparagraph B, that the police previously that day had escorted the group and searched them in order for the applicant to be made aware of the acts that he were to refrain from committing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1036.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1041.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Practical considerations must be included in the interpretation of this criteria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1044.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1062.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is evident that situations can arise in which a national police force may need to take immediate action to maintain law and public order, where there's no sufficient time to give a specific forewarning to the individuals concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1062.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1077.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case from the United Kingdom, the Supreme Court explicitly mentioned the example of hooligan violence, where two hooligan groups collide, and the police has no alternative but to detain ringleaders immediately and for a short period of time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1077.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1097.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The United Kingdom Supreme Court found that understanding subparagraph B as including a limitation on the police to first make the person aware of the acts they may not commit may leave the police effectively powerless in their efforts and obligations to protect the public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1097.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1104.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would argue that the circumstances of that case are very similar to those of the present case before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1108.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1125.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to crowd control in the event of hooligan brawls, requiring that the police first give a direct warning and then a way to see if the hooligans concerned follow through on the warning before the police can decide to detain them, it's simply not a viable option.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1125.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1142.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such a requirement would entail a disproportionate amount and impractical use of police resources, and more importantly, seriously hamper the ability of the police to protect persons and property in the event of hooligan disturbances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1142.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1162.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, we argue that the applicants were made aware of the concrete and specific obligations incumbent on them by the visible and long-term presence of a substantive number of uniformed police officers in close proximity of the Danish hooligans on the day of the football match.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1162.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1174.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allow me in this regard to direct the court's attention to page 11 and 15 of the applicants' memorial, where they seem to agree with the government's understanding of the criteria enshrined in subparagraph B and its application in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1177.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1189.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition to the criteria just discussed, the court in its case law has established two other criteria for lawful detention under subparagraph B. Firstly, the detention</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1189.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1199.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>must not be of a punitive character, and secondly, the basis for detention ceases to exist when the relevant obligation has been fulfilled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1199.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1211.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the first criteria, we will briefly state the obvious, namely that the applicants were detained solely for the purpose of preventing their participation in and planning of hooligan violence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1211.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1220.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Contrary to what the applicants have stated in their memorial, the detention was not in any way of a punitive character.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1220.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1234.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the other criteria, allow me once more to stress that the applicants were released as soon as practically possible based on the assessment of the situation in the city conducted by the police at regular intervals throughout the day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1234.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1241.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Danish courts in two instances have validated this ongoing assessment made by the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1241.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1265.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the basis of the arguments stated in our written observations and reiterated here today, the Danish government submits that the measures taken by the Copenhagen police were proportionate to the aim of securing the fulfillment of the applicants' obligations and that the detention was therefore justified under Article 5, paragraph 1, subparagraph C.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1265.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1269.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1269.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1279.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now turn to question 5 from the court pertaining to the question of whether the detention of the applicants were justified under subparagraph C of Article 5, paragraph 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1279.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1297.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should the court, contrary to what the Danish government anticipates, find that the detention of the applicants cannot be justified under subparagraph B, we alternatively argue that the detention would, in any circumstances, be justified under subparagraph C.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1297.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1310.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The criteria for lawful detention under subparagraph C has been examined in the court's case law referred to earlier in our submission today, namely the Lawless case and recently the Ostendorff case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1310.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1323.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Ostendorff, the court found that subparagraph C authorizes the detention of a person also when it is reasonably considered necessary to prevent his committing an offense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1323.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1337.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we have argued earlier, the Copenhagen police in the present case made an assessment very similar to that of the police in the Ostendorff case, namely to detain the applicants in order to prevent them from committing a criminal act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1337.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1349.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the police had not detained the applicants, there would have been a concrete and imminent risk that they would have committed a number of criminal acts, participating in and arranging further hooligan violence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1349.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1360.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the other criteria for detention under subparagraph C, the court in Ostendorff was divided on the interpretation of the subparagraph.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1360.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1374.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The majority found that detentions are only justified under subparagraph C if they are affected for the purpose of bringing a person before a competent legal authority in order to decide the merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1374.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1380.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, to initiate criminal proceedings against the detainee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1380.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1392.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In their dissent, the minority of two judges rightly pointed out that this interpretation unduly restricts the purpose of bringing the detainee before a judge to deciding on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1392.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1403.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The deciding judges underlined that such an understanding removes the possible purpose of bringing a person before a judge to examine whether the deprivation of liberty in itself was lawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1405.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1421.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the minority states, Ostendorff represents a shift from the court's previous understanding of subparagraph C, since in the lawless case of 61, the court clearly recognizes both these options.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1421.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1434.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allow me to recall here the previous mentioned judgment from the United Kingdom Supreme Court, in which the Supreme Court reaches a conclusion very similar to that of the dissenting judges in the Ostendorff case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1434.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1441.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Returning to our case, the applicants were detained for a very short period of time before being released again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1441.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1447.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And afterwards, they requested that their cases brought before the Danish courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1447.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1452.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here, the lawfulness of that detention was examined thoroughly in two instances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1452.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1460.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On this basis, the Danish government admit that their detention met the criteria in subparagraph C.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1460.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1476.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allow me to emphasize that such an interpretation, in the opinion of the Danish government, is necessary in order to allow the police to have sufficient and effective means for crowd control, and thereby avoiding hooligan brawls in connection with football matches.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1476.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1496.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And allow me further to stress that when interpreting Article 5, the court itself has stated, for example, in the Ostend case, that it is important not to make it impracticable for the police to fulfill their duties of maintaining order and protecting the public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1496.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1501.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is provided, of course, that individuals are protected from arbitrary detention of liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1501.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1504.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These two requirements are complementary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1504.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1508.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When balancing them, a pragmatic approach is necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1508.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1515.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the one hand, it's important to be aware of the practical implications of placing requirements that are too strict on the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1515.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1533.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the police cannot lawfully detain a person for a short period of time when necessary to avert the risk of imminent violence, it could render the police powerless when it comes to maintaining public order and security at mass events as a football game.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1533.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1542.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, it goes without saying that national law must contain clear safeguards against arbitrary deprivation of liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1542.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1558.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows that national laws allowing the police to use preventive detention as a last resort must be clear, precise, and accessible to the public, as is the case of Section 5 of the Danish Police Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1558.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1573.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, in case of a claim that the police have exceeded their powers, persons subject to preventive detention must have a quick and easy access to judicial review of the lawfulness of the detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1573.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1577.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such access is available under Danish law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1577.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1584.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If a detention is found to have been unlawful under Danish law, this, of course, warrants compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1584.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1586.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, your honors, distinguished members</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1586.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1596.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the court, getting to the end of my submission, I will now turn to answering question 6 posed by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1596.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1616.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the basis of the arguments presented by the Danish government, we maintain that the detention of the applicants were lawful under either Article 5, paragraph 1, subparagraph C, or Article 5, paragraph 1, paragraph B, or Article 5, paragraph 1, subparagraph C.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1616.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1620.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In conclusion, allow me to stress our major points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1620.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1624.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the detention of the three applicants were lawful under Danish law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1624.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1638.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Copenhagen police conducted an individual assessment with regard to each of the three applicants and found it necessary to detain each of the applicants to prevent them from participating in hooligan brawls and arranging further hooligan violence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1638.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1644.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Less intrusive measures would not have sufficed in specific circumstances of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1644.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1654.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Based upon regularly conducted assessment of the situation in the city on the day of the football match, the police also deemed it necessary to detain the applicants for more than six hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1654.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1660.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the Danish court, in two instances, have confirmed the legality of this assessment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1660.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1671.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, Article 5 of the convention should not be interpreted in such a way that makes it impossible for the police to perform the legitimate and indeed expected duties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1671.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1674.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police must have effective measures of crowd control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1674.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1692.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police must be able to take immediate action to avert an imminent risk of disturbance of the public order and security, and to ensure the safety of individuals, for example, in connection with football matches, which are likely to be disturbed by hooligan violence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1692.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1708.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government of Denmark agrees, of course, that such an interpretation of Article 5, according to which national laws may allow the police to use preventive detention, require that the national law is clear, precise, and accessible to the public in order to avoid arbitrary deprivation of liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1708.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1720.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, under such national laws, persons subject to preventive detention must have a quick and easy access to judicial review of the lawfulness of their detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1720.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1729.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On this basis, the government of Denmark respectfully requests that the court find no violation of Article 5 of the convention in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1729.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1734.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And with these remarks, the government of Denmark thereby concludes its initial submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1734.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1734.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1738.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1742.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Rehfeld, I call now Mr. Bonnez, please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1744.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1752.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. Mr. President and Honourable Judges of the Court, the applicants submit that the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1752.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1766.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>detention they have been subjected to is in breach of Article 5 in the European Convention on Human Rights. The applicants also submit that the deprivation of liberty was contrary</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1766.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1773.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the national law. In particular, they find that that part of their detention that exceeded</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1773.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1783.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the statutory six-hour limit was in breach of Article 5, as well as national law. The</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1783.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1802.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>three applicants were detained on two different locations by the police in Copenhagen on 10 October 2009, where Denmark were playing Sweden at the National Football Stadium in the World Cup qualifiers. Mr. B and Mr. A, the second and the third applicant, were detained in</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1802.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1823.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the afternoon as they were walking together with a relatively small group of people in a pedestrian street not far from Amertorps Square, where a fight between some football supporters had broken out. Mr. S, the first applicant, was arrested approximately one</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1823.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1830.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and a half hours later in another area of central Copenhagen. It is reported that a</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1830.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1837.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>total of 138 football fans were arrested during the day. It is worth mentioning that, according</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1837.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1852.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the Danish authorities and the applicants themselves, none of the three applicants are believed to have participated in any kind of unruly behaviour during the day in Copenhagen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1852.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1858.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. V and Mr. A had arrived in Copenhagen earlier in the day together with a group of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1858.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1865.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>football supporters from their own team from the city of Aarhus. The whole group had made</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1865.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1871.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>their way to a pub in central Copenhagen. After having spent some time in the pub, the group</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1871.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1877.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>had decided to move on to another pub, preferably a bigger one. After having left the pub on</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1877.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1885.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>foot, the police detained Mr. V and Mr. A, but no other members of the group. According</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1885.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1891.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to testimonies from police officers, both Mr. V and Mr. A, as well as the rest of the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1891.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1899.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>group, were quiet and behaved well in the pub and after they had left the pub. In other</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1899.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1912.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>words, according to the police, there had been no trouble on the part of the group or on the part of Mr. V and Mr. A at any time during the day. Shortly before their arrest,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1912.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1925.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the group was stopped by the police and ordered to turn around and walk back and then into a side street. The group complied with that order as they immediately turned around and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1925.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1932.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>did exactly what they were told. The arresting officers were told by the leaders in charge</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1932.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1938.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the police operation to arrest two persons from the group. The officers were further</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1938.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1953.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>told to pick the two who, in the eyes of the police officers, looked the most like ring leaders. That happened to be Mr. V and Mr. A. During the ensuing court proceedings, a</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1953.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1959.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>police officer testified in the Danish courts that he had seen Mr. V talking to a leader</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1959.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1967.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of a hooligan group from the Copenhagen area while in the pub. This policeman further testified</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1967.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1973.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that he had also heard Mr. V and Mr. A giving orders to others, albeit the policeman was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1973.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1989.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>unable to give any details about these orders, let alone if the orders were related to football hooliganism or any other subject. The first applicant, Mr. S, was detained while he was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1989.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1995.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>standing in the street together with a few other persons. A policeman who happened to</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1995.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2014.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>be in a police car parked on the opposite side of the road has testified that he was approached by a member of the public and was told by the same member of the public that he had overheard Mr. S planning a hooligan brawl on his mobile phone. The policeman could</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2014.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2021.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>see Mr. S talking on a mobile phone from his car. He immediately approached Mr. S and learned</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2021.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2028.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that Mr. S had previously been detained by the police in connection with football matches.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2028.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2035.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He then detained Mr. S. He did not secure the identity of the member of the public that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2035.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2044.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>had drawn his attention to Mr. S and presumably heard Mr. S talking on his phone. There's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2044.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2061.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>no information available that suggests that the police have examined whether calls pertinent to hooliganism had been made from Mr. S's phone. One of them had no ticket. Yes, what</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2061.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2070.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>about the two others? Also, it's not illegal to be in the city without having a city. He</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2070.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2084.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>might be to the place with a mere purpose to enjoy himself or to be together with his friends outside the football stadium. Mr. V, Mr. A and Mr. S were detained between seven</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2084.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2091.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and eight hours. Upon their release, the court trained back to all as quickly as possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2091.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2104.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All three applicants flatly denies that they had any plans to get involved in brawls during their stay in Copenhagen. All three applicants feel that they have been deprived of their</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2104.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2119.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>liberty in a wholly arbitrary fashion, which is exasperated by the fact that even simple time limits in national law were deliberately ignored by the police. In the present case,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2119.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2127.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>domestic law sets out a six-hour time limit and still does so today. Neither the wording</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2127.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2134.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of section 5.3 of the Danish Police Act nor the preparatory work allows for an extension</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2134.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2146.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of that strict time limit for other purposes than due to practical difficulties in dealing with a large number of arrests. The authorities have never advanced the view that the reason</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2146.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2159.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to extend the applicants' detention beyond six hours was due to the handling of a large number of detainees. The applicants submit that in accordance with the court's case</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2159.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2180.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>law, it is essential that the conditions for deprivation of liberty under domestic law be clearly defined and that the law itself is foreseeable in its application so that it meets the standards of lawfulness set out by and inherent in the Convention. This requires</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2180.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2192.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the law to be sufficiently precise for the individual to foresee his or her position and set a high standard to the quality of national law. The applicants argue that the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2192.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2200.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>relevant Danish law does not meet these requirements. The fact that none of the applicants at any</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2200.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2213.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>point were warned that they would be detained if they did not behave in a specific way is a particularly blatant breach of Article 5. The fact that they were not detained for the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2213.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2231.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>purpose to be brought before court also indicates that the detention does not comply with Article 5. Neither Article 5 paragraph 1 subparagraph B or subparagraph C, none of these are applicable</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2231.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2238.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for the detention of the applicants in this case. It is obvious that a comparison of the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2238.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2253.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>detention in the present case can be made with the detention carried out in the case of Ostendorf versus Germany, which was decided by the court on 7 March 2013. Mr Ostendorf</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2253.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2266.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was detained only for about four hours while he was in Frankfurt am Main to watch a football match. The police claimed that he was the leader of a hooligan group. He had arrived</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2266.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2278.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in Frankfurt am Main earlier in the day by train together with a group of persons from Bremen. They had been searched by the police and some members of the group had been found</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2278.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2285.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in possession of objects frequently used by hooligan groups. In their fights, the police</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2285.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2299.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>had ordered them to stay in a specific pub until they were ready to walk to the stadium in one single group under police surveillance. They were also told that they would be detained</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2299.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2306.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>if they attempted to leave the group. Mr Ostendorf was found hiding in the pub's ladies lavatories</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2306.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2314.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>after the group had left the pub. The display on his phone indicated he had communicated</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2314.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2321.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with a person from Frankfurt am Main, hence he was detained. None of the three applicants</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2321.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2334.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the present case had received any instructions from the authorities as to what to do in order to avoid being preventively detained. No weapons or other items relevant to hooliganism had</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2334.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2341.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>been found on them or on other members of their group for that matter. Nor had the applicants</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2341.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2354.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>or other members of their groups been involved in any disruptive behaviour during their stay in Copenhagen. Mr B and Mr A complied with the orders given by the police shortly before</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2354.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2365.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>their arrests to turn around as soon as they were told to do so. The applicants do not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2365.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2390.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>disagree with the minority's conclusion on page 28 of the Ostendorf judgement, where the minority concludes that Mr Ostendorf was detained in order to prevent him from committing specific criminal acts and regulatory offences. The minority points out that it was not for</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2390.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2402.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the mere fact that he had left his group, which was under police surveillance on the way to the stadium, that Mr Ostendorf had been detained. Strictly speaking, the minority</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2402.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2409.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is right. It was not for the mere fact that he had left the group that he was arrested.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2409.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2431.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in the applicants' view, the fact that Mr Ostendorf did try to avoid the police surveillance by leaving the group and hiding out in the women's lavatory was a predominant reason for his detention. Had he stayed with the group and not tried to hide in the women's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2431.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2437.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>lavatory, there is no reason to believe that he would have been detained whatsoever. In</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2437.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2463.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicants' view, the detention of Mr Ostendorf was triggered by the mere fact that he apparently had communicated on his phone with persons attached to the Frankfurt &amp; Main supporters and that he had left the group after having been told by the police not to do so. It is hard not to reach the conclusion that the majority in the Ostendorf case attached</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2463.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2490.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>considerable weight to the fact that Mr Ostendorf possibly had communicated with Frankfurt &amp; Main supporters and had sought hide in the women's lavatory, despite the fact that he and the rest of the group had been expressly told by the police to stay in the group if they didn't want to be detained. In paragraph 95 in the court's assessment, the majority</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2490.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2512.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>explicitly points out that the applicant by the police prior to his arrest was ordered to stay with the group of football supporters with whom he had travelled from Bremen and who were to be escorted by the police to the football stadium. If paragraph 94 is read</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2512.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2541.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in conjunction with paragraph 95, it appears that the order to stay with the group of football supporters under the police escort to the stadium was one of the requirements which the majority found necessary for the detention to be compatible with article 5, paragraph 1 subsection b. The court also found that there was no basis for detention if Mr Ostendorf</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2541.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2562.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>had not taken clear and positive steps which indicated that he would not fulfil his obligation to refrain from arranging brawls with other football supporters on the day of the match and in the location in question. The minority in Mr Ostendorf's case expressed concern</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2562.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2581.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>about the fact that the majority considerably extends the scope of the provision in article 5, paragraph 1 subparagraph b of the convention. The minority is of the opinion that the general</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2581.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2599.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>duty of obedience to the law is not a specific and concrete obligation for the purpose of article 5, subparagraph b of the convention. In the applicant's view, the majority strikes</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2599.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2622.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a fair balance between, on the one hand, the obvious need to prevent the nascent disruptive behaviour at football matches and, on the other hand, the fundamental human right to liberty and thereby avoiding opening the floodgates to arbitrary detention. The possible extension</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2622.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2655.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the scope of the provision in article 5, paragraph 1 subparagraph b seems to be counterbalanced by the fact that the majority emphasise that the obligation at issue to keep the peace by not committing criminal offences can only be considered as specific and concrete for the purpose of article 5, paragraph 1 subparagraph b if the place and time of the imminent commission of the offence and its potential victims have been sufficiently specified. This was in fact</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2655.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2661.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>not the only requirement pointed out by the majority. The majority further analysed whether</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2661.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2694.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr Ossendorf had been made aware of the specific acts which he was to refrain from committing, whether he had shown himself unwilling to refrain from committing such acts, whether he had been ordered to act in a prescribed way to avoid detention, and whether he had been warned in a sufficiently unequivocal manner about the consequences of his failure to act in the way prescribed by the authorities. Only after it was established that these requirements</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2694.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2708.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>were met by the German authorities, that the requirements were reasonable, the majority found that article 5, paragraph 1 subparagraph b of the Convention was applicable. The applicants</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2708.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2737.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>should not hesitate to express their fear that more cases of arbitrary deprivation of liberty could emerge across Europe if the Court would embark on a shift in its well-established case law and find article 5, paragraph 1c applicable in cases like Mr Ossendorf's case or this case. That would allow the authorities to detain a person if the administrative authorities</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2737.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2772.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>consider it necessary to prevent his or her committing of an offence even though the arrest is not effected for the purpose of bringing the person before a competent legal authority, or even though the person has received no further orders as to how to behave to avoid preventive internment for possible crimes that he or she have not had any intention to commit. The checks and balances that have characterised democratic societies for decades</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2772.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2781.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>would all of a sudden have been stifled. Prompt judicial review is one of the most basic and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2781.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2789.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>important safeguards people have against arbitrary detention. The slippery slope of arbitrary</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2789.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2798.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>detention has attracted the Court's attention way back in time. The repercussions on people's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2798.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2804.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>rights to liberty were thoroughly discussed by the Court in the case of Lawless v. Ireland,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2804.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2812.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>decided by the Court back in 1961, almost 60 years ago. In that case, too, it was suggested</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2812.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2831.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by the Respondent State that article 5, paragraph 1c of the Convention was applicable in a case where a person was detained for preventive reasons even though the arrest was not effected for the purpose of bringing the detainee before a competent legal authority. In paragraph</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2831.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2865.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>14, page 24 of Mr Lawless's judgement, the Court, among others, stated that this would mean that, and I quote, anyone suspected of harbouring an intent to commit an offence could be arrested and detained for an unlimited period on the strength merrily of the executive decision, without it being possible to regard his arrest or detention as a breach of the Convention. The Court's view, and I quote again, such an assumption with all its implications</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2865.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2881.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of arbitrary power would lead to conclusions repugnant to the fundamental principle of the Convention. This decision was a herald of a new Europe where mechanisms had been</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2881.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2895.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>put in place that should secure ordinary people that the agents of this State should be held accountable for their acts. A shift in the Court's interpretation of article 5, paragraph</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2895.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2902.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>1, subparagraph c, seemed to have no basis in the Convention text. The wording of article</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2902.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2925.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>5, paragraph 1, subparagraph c, read in conjunction with paragraph 3, in the Applicant's opinion, leave no room for an interpretation which allows for that subparagraph to be applicable to other cases, the criminal cases, where persons are detained for the purpose of being brought before a competent legal authority. This interpretation is fully in line with</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2925.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2966.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the case law followed up to this day and expressed by the Court in the above-mentioned lawless case, where the Court found that article 5, paragraph 1, subparagraph c, and paragraph 3, I quote, plainly entails the obligation to bring everyone arrested or detained in any of the circumstances contemplated by the provisions of paragraph 1c before a judge for the purpose of examining the question of deprivation of liberty or for the purpose of deciding on the merits. The applicants are aware of the fact that the Irish Government</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2966.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2990.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>held the view in the lawless case, that the preparatory work of the Convention lent support to the view that article 5, paragraph 1, subparagraph c, is applicable for detention of the kind at issue in the present case. Based on a comprehensive analysis of the preparatory work carried out</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2990.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3004.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>both by the Commission and by the Court, they both ruled out that the preparatory work of the Convention could be construed in the way suggested by the Irish Government. On top</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3004.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3029.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of that, the Court further added that it is a generally recognised principle that parties cannot resort to preparatory work when it comes to the interpretation of international treaties. In the view of the applicants, the minority in Mr. Ostendorf's case and the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3029.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Danish Government attach undue weight to one single sentence in paragraph 14 of the lawless judgment, thereby missing the overall meaning of the Court's reasoning in the judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3061.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In paragraph 14, the Court states that the obligation in article 5, 3, is to bring a person promptly before a judge for the purpose of examining the question of deprivation of liberty or for the purpose of deciding on the merits. When reading the context of what</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3061.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3083.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Court states in lawless, paragraph 13 to 15, the Court makes, in view of the applicants, it crystal clear that any arrest must be initiated for the purpose of bringing the individual before a competent legal authority, and reasonable suspicion of having committed a criminal offence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3083.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3104.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An arrest for other purposes than bringing the individual before a judge to decide on the continued deprivation of liberty or to decide on the merits of the charge at a trial is not justified under article 5 paragraph 1, subparagraph C.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3104.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3111.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In paragraph 68 of the Mr. Ostendorf case, the majority cites a great number of cases</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3111.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3125.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which show that subparagraph C exclusively permits deprivation of liberty only in connection with criminal proceedings, that it governs pretrial detention. The majority finds that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3125.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3136.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>this is apparent from its wording, which must be read in conjunction both with subparagraph A and with paragraph 3, which form a whole with it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3136.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3169.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the applicants' view, there is no compelling reason to suggest that the advent of football hooliganism has necessitated that the Europeans should surrender one of our most fundamental human rights, the right to a speedy judicial hearing of the administrative authorities, if the administrative authorities such as the police make encroachments on our right to liberty. On the one hand, it is understandable if the national authorities, including the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3169.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3183.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>police, once and again find the possible short-term gain of arbitrary detention, for example, of people regarded to be possible football hooligans tantalising. On the other hand,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3183.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3198.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the European countries have demonstrated for decades that a culture that gives high priority to fundamental human rights and places the authorities under strict scrutiny prospers in the long run.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3198.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3220.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Danish government points out on page 29, paragraph 4 of their memorial of 19 October 2017, that the requirements set forth by the majority in Ossendorff's case may in reality render the police powerless when it comes to protecting the public in certain situations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3220.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3231.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They argue that there may not be sufficient time to make members of the public specifically aware of the criminal offences that they must refrain from committing. A similar view is</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3231.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3246.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>put forward by Lord Toulson in the judgment given on 15 February 2017 by the Supreme Court of the United Kingdom in the Higgs case. In paragraph 40 it is pointed out that the requirements</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3246.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3259.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>set forth by the majority in the Ossendorff case could have been undesirable consequences on British society. It reads, I quote, the police may find it necessary to take action</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3259.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3271.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to prevent an imminent breach of the peace in circumstances where there is no sufficient time to give a warning. An example might be a football match where two unruly groups collide</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3271.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3285.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the police see no alternative but to detain them or the ringleaders on both sides immediately for what may be quite a short time. Yeah, it might also be quite a long time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3285.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3303.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants do not agree on the fact that the police may be rendered powerless in a situation where the large crowds might be gathered and where unrest may take place, be it football hooligans, demonstrators or squatters. If it is possible for the police</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3303.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3322.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to apprehend members of two groups, for example football hooligans, with the purpose to detain them, it will most likely also be possible for the police in the first place to give those the sufficient warnings as an alternative to detaining them. In some situations it may</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3322.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3346.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>be possible to pursue a procedure carried out in the case of Austin and others versus the UK decided by the Grand Chamber on the 15th of March 2012 where the police cordoned off an area until unruly demonstrators in the area had calmed down. In that case the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3346.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3353.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>police did not have to resort to preventive detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3353.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3388.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A police force issued with power to detain people who have not committed any wrongdoing without giving these people any prior warnings that might encourage them to act in a way that renders subsequent detention unnecessary is likely in the long run to cause more unrest and get involved in more clashes with various groups of people than a police force that is known not to detain people without having tried other options beforehand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3388.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3409.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At last the applicants would like to point out that it was absolutely crucial for the decision by the Danish police to arrest the three applicants that they had been detained at previous football matches. This way of reasoning is a far cry from what is acceptable</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3409.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3415.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the case law of this court. I should draw the court's attention to paragraph 66 of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3415.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3422.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Ostendorp's case. On the basis of the court's case law the court emphasised that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3422.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3446.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>article 5 paragraph 1c does not permit a policy of general prevention directed against an individual or a category of individuals who are perceived by the authorities rightly or wrongly as being dangerous or having propensity to unlawful acts. Exactly that happened in</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3446.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3462.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>this case only obviously vague excuses have been produced by the government to justify the detention. The applicants invite this court to find that article 5 has been breached</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3462.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3462.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the present case. Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3470.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3474.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Bonnez, I thank both parties for their submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3474.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3482.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I invite my colleagues, members of the Grand Chamber, wishing to do so, to put their questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3482.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3483.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I see Judge Ranzoni, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Carlo Ranzoni</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3488.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3490.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would have two questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3490.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3492.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First one to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3492.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3507.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Which concrete measures the authorities could have taken if the risk of serious disturbance of public order and the danger to the safety of individuals had persisted for a longer period than only some hours?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3507.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3515.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let's say, for example, during a sports event or a political demonstration lasting two days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3515.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3533.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is there any possibility under Danish law for persons causing such a risk or danger who are not willing to keep the peace to be detained for one or two days if they have not yet committed any criminal offense?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3533.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3536.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And a second question to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3536.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3549.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the government, all applicants before the events of 10th October 2009 had been arrested several times in connection with other football unrest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3549.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3555.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How often have they actually been arrested and under which circumstances?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3557.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3559.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. Judge Lemmens please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3566.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3570.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3570.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3580.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government in this case argues that either Article 5, Paragraph 1b or c or both are applicable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3580.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3610.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant seems to argue in the first place that none is applicable, leaving aside that issue of applicability or not, and assuming for a moment, as the government argues, that either Paragraph 1b or c is applicable, and so that preventive detention in the circumstances of this case of a crowd control is possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3610.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3614.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to ask the parties to come back to an issue that they both have discussed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3614.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3630.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is the question of guarantees in such a situation where, again, I repeat, it is assumed that it would be possible in theory to have such a preventive detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3630.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3637.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like specifically to ask the parties what they would think of two issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3637.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3653.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One is in a situation of crowd control where there is a whole group that might be causing a risk to public order, what about the possibility of singling out a few individuals?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3653.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3658.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What are the risks against arbitrary action in this respect?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3658.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3666.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the guarantees against, I'm sorry, what are the guarantees against arbitrarily singling out specific individuals?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3666.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3672.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And secondly, I know that both parties have discussed this, but I would like to hear it again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3672.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3680.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What about the guarantees of judicial control in a situation of a preventive detention?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3680.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3683.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should it be something automatic?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3683.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3689.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should it be something that is possible within a very short time?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3689.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3693.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is the time limit for the court to decide?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3693.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3695.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And how to organize all that in a practical way?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3695.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3696.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3697.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3700.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. Judge Dedov, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Dmitry Dedov</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3705.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3725.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to ask the government to explain how the authorities determined the time when the applicants should be released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3725.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3733.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government said that they were released when the risk was minimized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3733.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3755.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I see from the facts that the last disturbance took place at 10.51 and especially at 11.21 p.m. and the first applicant was released at exactly after this, at 11.27.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3755.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3765.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second applicant was released at 11.34, just almost immediately after the last disturbance took place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3765.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3766.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What does it mean?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3766.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3784.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How did the police determine that there was no risk immediately after the clashes took place or just because the six hours time already elapsed at that moment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3784.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3793.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a general question to both parties and especially to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3793.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3814.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whether if the detention was governed by the Article 5, Paragraph 1C, so whether the guarantees against the arbitrary detention applied in accordance with the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3814.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3829.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mean that the concrete circumstances should be taken into account by the authorities, not the general assumption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3829.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3856.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So my question is what was the concrete circumstances which allowed the authorities to conclude that the risk, the imminent risk exists and the concrete persons, namely the applicants in the present case, would like to participate in the disturbance and the disorder.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3856.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3857.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3860.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3862.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Nußberger, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3864.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3866.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3866.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3870.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I just wanted to follow up on Judge Ranzoni's question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3870.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3877.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have heard that the applicants had been arrested before in other circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3877.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3879.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was this registered?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3879.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3883.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is there a register where you can find this information?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3883.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3891.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then we understand that the police force chosen for the arrests was a regional police force knowing these people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3891.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3904.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So they had some specific knowledge of the people and at the same time we find in the preparatory work to the law the statement that former behavior should not be relevant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3904.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3913.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for me it would be interesting to understand what was the relevance of the former arrests for the arrests in this case to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3913.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3913.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3914.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3916.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3916.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3919.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no more questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3919.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3934.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now withdraw for 20 minutes, following which the parties will be able to submit brief observations in reply to each other's submissions and reply to questions from the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3934.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3934.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4071.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4072.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4120.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4123.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4123.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4126.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I call Mr. Elling Rehfeld, please, to the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4137.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4143.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President, distinguished members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4143.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4158.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now respond to the submission made by behalf of the applicants in the first round, and then to the best of my ability, I would like to reply to the questions posed by the honorable members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4158.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4191.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, in response to the submission made on behalf of the applicants, I noted that a number of statements were made, including that depending on the result of the court's decision in this case, we would open the floodgates to arbitrary detention and that the checks and balances all over Europe would be stifled in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4191.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4199.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I would just warn against a too apocalyptic vision of what we're trying to do here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4199.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4215.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the specific case, Copenhagen at the day of the detention of the detainees, of the applicants, were in reality made into a battlefield by a number of hooligan groups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4215.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4235.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the entirety of the day, a number of violent incidents took place in the city center of Copenhagen by hooligan groups that had planned to meet and fight with complete disregard for the civilians and innocent citizens of Copenhagen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4235.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4251.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By the end of the day, more than 130 persons were detained, and as the fact shows, there was a number of fights taking place in Copenhagen on that day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4251.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4257.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think I would warn against such a dim look of what we are trying to achieve here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4257.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4271.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We're trying to strike the balance between arbitrary detention and the need for authorities to be able to have preventive detention as part of their crowd control measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4271.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4289.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also take issue with a statement made that the time limits of six hours where possible in Danish law were deliberately ignored by the authorities, as we have stated in our written observations and here today as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4289.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4308.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was a very precise and careful assessment of the requirements of the Police Act on the one hand, and then the factual situation on the ground in Copenhagen where the unrest had not ended by the end of the six-hour detention of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4308.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4330.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second point I would like to make is, in response to the applicants, that I think something along the lines of this was said by the applicants, that it was in contradiction with Article 5 of the Convention, as the applicants were not detained in order to be taken before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4330.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4338.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm afraid to say I find it very difficult to follow this line of argumentation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4338.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4344.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were released as soon as possible, as we've heard, seven and a half hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4344.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4362.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And according to the opinion of the Government, an early release from detention for preventive purposes will still be in accordance with Article 5 of the Convention, if the lawfulness of the detention can subsequently be challenged and decided by a court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4362.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4366.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was exactly the situation in the applicants' case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4366.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4387.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We find it contrary to the spirit and the underlying objective of Article 5 of the Convention if the applicants' early release placed them in a stronger position to complain a breach of Article 5 than if the police had decided to detain them for a longer period in order to take them before Danish courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4387.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4404.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is decisive in a democratic society in order to avoid arbitrary detention is that the lawfulness of all detentions can be tried in the courts as easy and quick as possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4404.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4410.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So those were the two points I just wanted to make in regard to the statements made by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4410.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4417.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now try to answer a number of the questions asked by the Honourable Judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4417.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4446.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question by Judge Ranzoni, which goes to say, which concrete measures could the authorities have taken in a situation where these unrests had lasted for more, for a longer period of time than actually happened in Copenhagen at the time, if this disturbance of peace had taken place for a number of days?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4446.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4462.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think the answer to that question is that we are bound also domestically by the limits of our constitution, which says that you have to be placed in front of a court or a judge within 24 hours of arrest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4462.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4464.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is according to our constitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4464.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4482.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I would also say, in accordance with the Police Act, as we have presented here today, there are certainly limits that would make it, probably would not make it a possibility to detain persons for such a longer period of time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4482.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4496.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have the six hours rule, as described in Section 5, and we have other rules in Section 8 and 9, in specific in situation of mass events where you can detain persons up to a limit of, a possible limit of 12 hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4496.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4513.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think in a situation of a long-term situation of unrest, we would probably find ourselves in a situation where we could not detain preventively, but we would have to look at options within our criminal law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4513.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4521.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second line of questioning was by Judge Lemons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4521.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4532.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A question of guarantees as the singling out of single individuals in a situation where you have to contain a crowd.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4532.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4551.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think that what we would say here is that our police authorities are under a strict obligation according to our Police Act to take the least intrusive measures when they decide to intervene in a specific situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4551.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4577.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in the end it will be an assessment of the police whether or not a person can be preventively detained, and then of course that assessment will be followed by our Danish courts deciding on whether or not this assessment was in accordance with our national and international obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4577.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4589.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think the case in front of the court is a very interesting example of how that type of assessment will play out and how that will be dealt with in our national courts subsequently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4589.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4594.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think that's our answer to that question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4594.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4624.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the question of judicial control, what can we, what would be the best way to proceed with this if we were in a situation where both subparagraph B and C were in place?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4624.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4644.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think we are in a situation where these preventive detentions, short-term detentions take place in a situation where a lot of things are happening at the same time, I think quite often most of the times it would simply not be realistic to put people before a court before they are actually released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4644.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4670.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These detentions are short-term, we have a specific situation here of a seven and a half hour detention, but most of the detentions would probably be of a much shorter character so it probably wouldn't be feasible to put persons in front of a court before they are released and I don't think it would be for the benefit of the persons having been detained they want to be released as soon as possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4670.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4676.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But then of course the question of arbitrariness and how can they then complain?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4676.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4685.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well I think the way we have set up the system in Denmark is a well-functioning system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4685.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4704.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the procedure rules in the Danish Administration of Justice Act, they stipulate that a person can request a judicial review of the lawfulness of his or her detention and then the authorities have five days to bring a case before the national court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4704.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4714.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course this could be made automatic but I think it's in the interest of the person themselves whether or not they want to try the detention that they have been exposed to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4714.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4722.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think maybe for the benefit of the persons detained, automaticity is not necessarily the best way ahead.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4722.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4732.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think it would be not necessarily in the interest of the authorities or the applicants but everyone that has been detained has the right to have a court proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4732.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4742.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think, I hope that at least gives some input to answering the question by Judge Slemmet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4742.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4748.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third question was from Judge Lidoff.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4748.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4758.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And here, also a very good question on the factual situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4758.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4771.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Basically going to the question of how can the police assess that there is no risk when the applicants have been released immediately after the last disturbance took place in Copenhagen?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4771.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4775.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How can they make such a fast assessment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4775.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4777.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is it based on?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4777.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4785.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think this is in effect a very concrete assessment by the police authorities in a specific case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4785.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4801.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this situation we had more than 180, 186 police officers involved in the operations on top of the already existing police operating in the city at the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4801.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4806.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a fairly good understanding of what happened in the different parts of the city.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4806.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4815.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You had a control center man with 10 to 15 persons constantly evaluating how the situation in the city developed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4815.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4840.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think it's fair to say that the answer to the question asked by Judge Lidoff is, well the understanding of the authorities at the time was that the last disturbances that took place, the last fight that happened in the city center, probably was also the last unrest of the evening.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4840.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4843.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that was a very concrete assessment by the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4843.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4856.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And obviously when you have a six hour rule as a starting point and you have detainees who are in your detention facilities for more than seven hours, you want to release them as soon as possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4856.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4858.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's a balance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4858.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4869.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We came to the conclusion that after the last fight, then the city would, peace and quiet, would settle on the city and that was actually what happened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4869.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4881.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore authorities came to the conclusion that the applicants could be released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4881.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4932.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the second question by Judge Lidoff relating specifically to subparagraph C, basically which concrete measures or circumstances existed so, or did we assess in order to assess whether or not there was an imminent risk, I think as we have stated in our written observations and also today at the oral hearing, this was a number of elements were part of this assessment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4932.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4949.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Obviously you had the overall framework of a city with a number of, unusual high number of persons in the city because of the football match and then you had the specific fights that started already at 3.40 in the afternoon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4949.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4952.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You had the specific behavior of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4952.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4987.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You had the police observations of the organizing of the situation, who they gave orders to and we had the specific situation of a witness coming to the police explaining that he had just overheard one of the applicants inciting others over his phone to initiate fights interiorly in the main family relaxation spot in the city of Copenhagen to initiate fights in that location.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4987.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4996.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's a number of different elements that played into the concrete assessment of whether an imminent risk existed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4996.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5015.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as the court has stated in its case law, the police must be afforded a degree of discretion in taking these operational decisions, primarily because the police are usually in the best position to make them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5015.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5049.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as Trude also underlined that this was an assessment that has been evaluated by two instances in Denmark and simply been accepted as facts by our national courts that all these different elements together made a situation where the best way ahead or the next step for the police would be to detain these specific persons in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5049.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5064.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A question which was raised by both Judge Nusberger and Judge Razzoni was to the history of the applicants in the specific situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5064.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5072.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the referral by us and the applicants that they had a known history for participating in these sorts of hooligan fights, they were known troublemakers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5072.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5105.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, I should say this is the case and here we base ourselves on the documents from the District Court of Aarhus which has also been sent to the court which basically outlines that here one of the applicants had been detained several times previously in connection with similar events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5105.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5109.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today we don't have specifics on these previous events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5109.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5115.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we cannot give the court today further information on specifically what had happened in previous events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5115.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5122.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can inform you that yes, we do have a hooligan register in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5122.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5123.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We haven't brought it with us.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5123.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5130.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm not sure whether or not the applicants are registered in this hooligan register.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5130.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5136.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would presume so based on what we've heard from our district courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5136.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5144.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But again, this is and should be a very, very minor element in the assessment made by the authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5144.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5154.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as we've said several times and stated also here today, it's not the history of these persons, it's the way they behaved on the day of the detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5154.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5160.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So obviously we have police present that knows these people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5160.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5174.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Police that has been brought in from different regions of Denmark because they have a known relationship to these or they know these different actors in the hooligan communities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5174.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5177.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5177.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5181.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5181.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5189.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think with the good advice of the President, I will now conclude my intervention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5189.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5199.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I will just invite the court to hold for each applicant and for the reasons put forward by the Government of Denmark that Article 5 of the Convention was not violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5199.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5200.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much for your patience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5201.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5204.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, please, Mr. Bonnez.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5208.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5210.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5210.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5214.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Mr. President and distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5214.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5222.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a few replies to the comments given by the respondent's state in the first place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5222.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5228.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was mentioned, it was suggested, that Copenhagen was made into a battlefield on the day in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5228.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5233.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And perhaps that might very well have been the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5233.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5249.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it's also important in this case to be aware of the fact that our clients, that the three applicants, at the time of their arrests or the time of their apprehension, they were nowhere near any fights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5249.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5251.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were not involved in fights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5251.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5262.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had just left a pub where the police said, according to the police, according to what the police told the Danish courts, there was a quiet atmosphere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5262.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5266.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had had a good time in the pub.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5266.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5277.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they had just left that pub and walked down the pedestrian street and were approaching a place where there had been fights sometime before they arrived.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5277.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5291.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's obvious in the applicant's view, where we compare to the German decision, the Ostendorff case, that our applicants, the two applicants, could have been asked to turn around.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5291.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5292.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, they did.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5292.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5294.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They did ask them to turn around.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5294.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5309.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not to give them the possibility to walk back to the pub, for example, or to walk back to some other place where there were no unrest, but to get into a side street where they could arrest them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5309.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5313.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That, in our opinion, is not fair.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5313.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5320.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had not committed any wrongdoing, according to the police, at any time during the day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5320.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5334.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I also noticed that the respondent state mentioned a specific behavior carried out by our applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5334.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5350.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I still need to hear which specific behavior we are talking about, apart from the behavior already mentioned by the police, that they sat in a pub and behaved in a proper way, apparently shouting out some orders, one of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5350.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5354.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We haven't heard anything about the contents of those orders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5354.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5356.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They might have ordered beer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5356.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5359.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't know what these orders were about.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5359.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5379.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we also hear that, yeah, but what I think is also the situation, the applicant who was on this mobile phone talking to someone, I find that's a bit dubious, actually.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5379.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5389.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a bit dodgy that the police did not actually, when a person was talking on mobile phone, if that was the case, he's talking on a phone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5389.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5400.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We heard from a person, from a citizen, from a passerby, that this guy was on the phone speaking to someone, apparently organizing riots.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5400.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5401.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5401.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5407.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why did the police seize that phone, watch out exactly what the Germans did?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5407.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5410.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They saw that Mr. Ostendorf, they</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5410.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5417.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>could see on the display on his phone that he had been in touch with some guys from the other group.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5417.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5421.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why didn't the Danish police seize that phone and do the very same?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5421.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5432.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That might be a way to prevent further disturbances, because they would actually be able to investigate into whether something was going to happen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5432.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5441.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In my opinion, it seems to be quite dubious what did actually happen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5441.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5443.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They just arrested them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5443.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5456.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It seems to be quite a lackadaisical way to handle the freedom of other people, the personal liberty of other people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5456.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5462.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also, I have got the same sort of comments when it comes to this hooligan register.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5465.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5475.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police, they have not produced any evidence that our clients, they have been organized in hooligan brawls before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5475.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5482.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have heard that they have been arrested, but not how many times or for what reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5482.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5494.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think the court should be very careful when you look into the statements produced by the government in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5494.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5499.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have very few answers to what the court asked about.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5499.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5526.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, to question number one, I would just like to put forward the fact that, in our opinion, the German government in the Ostendorff case behaved in a very appropriate manner by finding out what can we do to avoid arresting people, to avoid using preventive detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5526.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5535.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they did try out various options, but this person, Mr. Ostendorff, didn't respond in a proper way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5535.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5543.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He did hide in that toilet and apparently had plans to initiate fights with other hooligans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5543.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5548.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there was a good reason to arrest that person, in the applicant's opinion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5548.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5554.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in our case, there was in no way a heated atmosphere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5554.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5565.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police had plenty of time, in our opinion, to talk to these persons in question here, tell them to go somewhere else, tell them to go back to Aarhus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5565.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5583.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or in particular, when we hear that they've just left that pub and the police knew that there was unrest in other parts of the city involving hooligans, why didn't the police just tell them, stay back in this pub?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5583.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5588.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or we might, they mentioned the fact that the pub was too small for the number of people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5588.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5592.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>OK, though, stay back in this pub and we will organize.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5592.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5599.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We will help you or we will guide you to another pub, a larger pub, perhaps.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5599.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5608.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That seems it's not even discussed why these options were not carried out in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5608.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5618.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another thing that I can't get around my head, why didn't they thought of things like putting them on a bus and sending them back to Aarhus?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5618.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5636.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That might also have been an option, which has been less of an encroachment of their human rights than actually putting them in jail or depriving them of their liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5638.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5642.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yeah, I have no more replies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5642.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5642.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thanks for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5645.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5648.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Very much, Mr. Bonnez.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5648.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5652.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5652.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5658.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their submissions and answers to court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5658.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5663.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5663.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5666.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5666.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5670.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5670.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5672.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
