<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>3692507_28032018</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>17.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>18.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>63.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>65.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>83.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>92.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Güzelyurtlu and others versus Cyprus and Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>92.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>120.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on 16 August 2007 under Article 34 of the Convention by Mr. Mehmet Güzelyurtlu, Mrs. Aysa Güzelyurtlu, Mrs. Deniz Erdinç, Mrs. Emin Akerson, Mrs. Fezil Kiralar, Mrs. Meghem Osfirat, and Mr. Muzaffer Osfirat, Cypriot nationals of Turkish-Cypriot origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>120.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>130.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the third section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>130.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>136.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on 13 May 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>136.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>153.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 3 September 2009, the president of the third section granted leave to the Air Center to submit written comments as a third party by virtue of Rule 44, Paragraph 3 of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>153.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>161.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 4 April 2017, a chamber of the third section delivered its judgment in the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>161.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>165.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It unanimously declared the application admissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>165.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>182.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It held by five votes to two that there has been a violation of Article 2 of the Convention in its procedural limb by Cyprus and unanimously that there has been a violation of Article 2 in its procedural limb by Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>182.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>194.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 22 June 2017, both respondent governments requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>194.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>202.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted their requests on 18 September 2017.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>202.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>221.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Cypriot government are represented by their agent, Mr. Costas Clerides, Attorney General of the Republic of Cyprus, assisted by Mrs. Clare Montgomery, counsel, Mrs. Jessica Jones, and by Mrs. Theodora Christodoulidou,advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>221.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>251.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Turkish government are represented by Mr. Erdoğan İşcan, ambassador, assisted by Mr. Stefan Talmon, counsel, by Mr.Zaim M. Necatigil Mrs. Sülen Karabacak, Mr. Ali Murat Başçeri, Mr. Can Öztaş, Mrs. Növber Ferit Vechi, Mrs. Deniz Kalyoncu, Mrs.  Billur Bilen  Soydan, and by Mrs. Meltem Aksen, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>251.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>263.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mr. Alper Riza, counsel, assisted by Mr. Christopher Pascalides, advisor. Three of the applicants are also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>263.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>268.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>268.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>275.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome the following groups of judges who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>275.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>287.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A delegation of judges and prosecutors of the European Judicial Training Network, a delegation of Russian judges, and a delegation of Turkish judges and prosecutors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>287.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>296.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the representatives of both governments and of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>296.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>299.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Riza for the applicants will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>299.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>302.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mrs. Montgomery for the Cypriot government,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>302.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>306.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and finally Mr. Talmon for the Turkish government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>306.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>320.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpretation in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpretation into Turkish, Russian, and Armenian has been authorized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>320.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>330.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpretation is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>330.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>331.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Riza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>331.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>331.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>333.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>334.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May it please the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>334.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>340.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much for the welcome, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>340.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>350.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I have time constraints, I shall identify the issues in the case very briefly as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>350.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>378.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Basically, this case is to do with the failure of putting it neutrally, the parties, to cooperate in the investigation of a murder in Cyprus, the Republic of Cyprus, under the effective control of the Republic of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>378.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>391.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the murder was of three members of a family, including a child aged 16, a young girl who was shot point blank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>391.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>399.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issue, as the court below decided, was actually a very simple case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>399.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>411.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I know it raises, from the papers, it raises apparently all sorts of issues of human rights and indeed international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>411.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>427.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in our submission, this case is to do with nothing more than the failure of policemen to cooperate in order to detect, prosecute, and punish murderers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>427.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>432.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's as much as I'd like to say about the broad facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>432.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>441.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it is important for the court to appreciate the narrow issue involves the issue, the factual issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>441.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>448.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, having said that, I move at once to the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>448.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>459.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't really want to preach to you, this court, this august court, about what the European Convention is all about and all the rest of it, because you know it infinitely better than I do.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>459.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>467.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And consequently, what I want to do is go straight to the point and go to Article 15.2 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>467.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>470.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because in my submission, Article 15.2</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>470.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>487.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the Convention, which is the article that deals with derogations from obligations, including the right to life, including the procedural aspect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>487.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>494.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that is at the heart of this case, because of the nature of the case that has been put forward, in particular, by the Republic of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>497.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>518.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under this article, it is not permissible to derogate from the right to life, the right not to be subjected to torture, the right not to be enslaved, and the right not to be punished for an offense which was not an offense at the time of alleged commission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>518.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>527.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those three rights are rights which, in international law, would be termed jus cogens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>527.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>529.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They cannot be derogated from.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>529.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>534.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They override all other rights in all circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>534.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>540.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think in the case of the right to life, I think it is permissible in time of war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>540.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>549.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If you're engaged in war, if you kill whilst engaged in war, then I think that that's probably not covered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>549.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>557.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But apart from that, these rights are rights that are fully engaged in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>557.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>559.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fully engaged, I add.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>559.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>562.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I emphasize, rather.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>562.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>566.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they are fully engaged for a reason.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>566.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>573.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason is this, that this court, as I understand it, is a human rights court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>573.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>578.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not a court to do with international law in other spheres.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>578.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>581.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a human rights court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>581.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>589.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is concerned with the protection of human rights, not the rights of states, but human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>589.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>595.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it's extremely important that I make this point right at the outset.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>595.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>613.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in my submission, the way the convention works is that the convention protects some rights absolutely, the rights that I've just mentioned, and other rights, the right to privacy, the right to freedom of expression, and so on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>613.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>615.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These are relative rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>615.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>627.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These are rights that have clawback provisions, that there are circumstances in which states can say, well, for a legitimate purpose, if we act proportionately, then it's all right to breach those rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>627.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>633.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But these rights, not only can they not be breached, but they cannot be derogated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>633.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>637.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I've made that point, and I don't want to make it any further.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>637.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>663.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I really move now to the three points that I've identified as the points that are in play, the points that arise in this case, in the order in which they appear from the submissions of the parties and from the questions asked by the learned judge or rapporteur.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>663.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>668.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The three points are these, and I shall address them seriatim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>668.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>671.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first point is the non-recognition point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>671.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>675.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second point is the jurisdictional link point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>675.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>680.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the third point is the duty to cooperate point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>680.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>684.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I deal first with the non-recognition point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>684.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>695.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I understand the submissions of the Republic of Cyprus, they are to the effect that Cyprus is a sovereign state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>695.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>698.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Republic of Cyprus is a sovereign state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>698.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>705.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under international law, there is a duty of non-recognition of illegal states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>705.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>722.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The TRNC, which is the acronym for Turkey and the governing body in North Cyprus, I have to be careful here, because of course there are sensitivities involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>722.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>729.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the point is this, that so far as international law is concerned, the TRNC is an illegal state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>729.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>749.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so as I understand the submissions of the Republic of Cyprus, it being an illegal state, therefore the Republic of Cyprus is perfectly entitled not to recognize it and not to deal with it at all, not even by police officers, which is an extraordinary submission, you may think.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>749.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>755.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because of course, police officers do not have plenipotentiary powers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>755.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>756.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Police officers are police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>756.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>759.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have to engage in all sorts of investigations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>759.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>765.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But anyway, the long and the short of it is that that is the submission of the Republic of Cyprus as I understand it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>765.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>794.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My short answer to it is that actually that argument, the non-recognition argument, has been dealt with on at least five occasions before, Cyprus and Turkey, Fokah, Xenidis Aresti, and Dimopoulos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>794.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>798.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All these cases decide this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>798.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>802.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they decided time and time again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>802.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>812.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in my submission, it is not right to revisit the point time and time and time again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>812.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>818.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I know that there is no principle of binding precedent in this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>818.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>824.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as I understand the position, previous decisions are taken into account very seriously.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>824.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>827.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are often followed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>827.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>836.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And basically, well-established case law is not departed from, so far as I know, so soon after these decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>836.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>853.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, in my submission, it is not permissible to come to this court again and ask this court again to say that, well, yes, on this occasion, the previous decisions do not apply.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>858.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>865.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Republic of Cyprus sought to distinguish this case with the others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>865.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>872.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The others were to do mostly, I think, apart from Fokah, which was, I think, an Article 5.1 case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>872.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>876.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of the articles engaged was an Article 5.1 point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>876.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>878.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The other points were engaged with property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>878.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>898.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I understand the submissions of the Republic of Cyprus, they're saying that, well, in those other cases, they were not concerned with facts whereby the governor or a governing agency in the Republic of Cyprus had to deal with a governing agency in the TRNC.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>898.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>900.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they sought to make that distinction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>900.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>906.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In my submission, that is a distinction without a difference, without a difference at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>906.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>912.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If anything, the right to life is infinitely more important in my submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>912.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>917.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the right to life is infinitely more important than the right to property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>917.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>919.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't think I need to dwell on that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>919.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>921.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's obviously right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>921.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>936.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I can give you examples of where, factual examples of where the right to life can be engaged requiring cooperation between the two sides apart from police, apart from police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>936.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>943.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Say you have, as there are in Cyprus, big fires and that lives are in danger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>943.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>964.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it to be said really that the Republic of Cyprus Fire Brigade and the TRNC Fire Brigade, if they need to liaise and coordinate with one another in order to save lives across the line in Cyprus, is it to be said that actually they mustn't do that?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>964.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>966.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They mustn't talk to each other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>966.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>972.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They're not allowed, according, if the Republic of Cyprus submissions are correct, they're not allowed to talk to one another.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>972.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>976.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is evidence, clear evidence in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>976.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>980.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think that it's probably a paragraph 131, but I stand corrected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>980.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>982.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's in my latest submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>982.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>991.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police officers were saying, I'm not talking to the other policeman on the other side, even though a child was murdered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>991.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1015.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it to be said that if there is a need for medical treatment, that the ambulance service has to move from either the Turkish side to the Greek side or vice versa, depending on the circumstances, is it really to be said that the doctors cannot sort of do a handover, that they cannot talk to one another because they're government employees and it means recognition?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1015.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1018.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, our submission means nothing of the sort in any event.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1018.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1027.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that's what the submission amounts to, that we will not talk to the other side.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1027.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1031.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And let me give you another example, which actually happened, although it didn't happen in Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1031.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1037.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It happened as between Greeks and Turks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1037.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1043.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In, I think, 2000, there were very bad earthquakes in both Greece and Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1043.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1053.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as a result of these earthquakes, there was assistance given by both Greece to Turkey first, and then Turkey to Greece.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1053.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1056.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was called the period of earthquake diplomacy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1056.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1059.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mean, some of you may remember this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1059.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1081.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is being suggested here is that sort of thing, if it happens in Cyprus, should not mean that the two sides, trying to say you have a child or people buried in the rubble, and there is a need for salvage to take place, or for saving of lives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1081.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1083.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they say, no, no, you mustn't coordinate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1083.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1084.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We mustn't talk to each other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1084.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1088.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That, in my submission, cannot be right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1088.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1096.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Be that as it may, I move on, really, and say basically that this court is being asked to depart from previous decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1096.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1101.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The previous decision, the facts of this case, are not distinguishable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1101.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1115.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And consequently, in my submission, it is appropriate for the court to follow the previous decisions of, in particular, Cyprus and Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1115.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1121.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, Cyprus and Turkey is very important, because Cyprus and Turkey was an interstate case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1121.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1127.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It wasn't just a case between an applicant and a respondent government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1127.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1128.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was an interstate case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1128.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1134.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the state itself brought cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1134.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1139.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Republic of Cyprus won almost all the points, except one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1139.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1144.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The point that they lost on was this non-recognition point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1144.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1164.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On that point, the court, I think by a majority, if I remember rightly, decided that actually that human rights override the duty of non-recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1164.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1172.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think I should move on, because I've got limited time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1172.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1186.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What I really would like to say is really this, that in our submission, the unique circumstances obtaining in Cyprus, because they are unique.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1186.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1192.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We as Cypriots are not proud of the fact that the circumstances in Cyprus are unique at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1192.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1195.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the fact is that they are unique.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1195.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1199.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in our submission, it is not right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1199.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1202.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it would not be right, in light of all the authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1202.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1213.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not right that the law should be determined by a factual matrix that is unique and sui generis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1213.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1235.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I said before, there is authority from this court, I think, in the case of Wemhoff and Germany, that when you are faced with two interpretations, the interpretation that's at my point, page 2i, the interpretation that protects human rights should be followed, rather than the one that doesn't.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1235.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1239.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I emphasize, this is a human rights court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1239.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1248.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there are problems in Cyprus of a political nature, then those problems are to be sorted either politically or in another forum, but not this forum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1248.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1259.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This forum is concerned with preserving the human rights of the individuals that inhabit the European legal space.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1259.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1265.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I move on now to the next point, which is on the jurisdictional link point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1265.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1280.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I've tried very hard to understand the submissions made by the excellent submissions, I should say, by the Turkish side.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1280.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1290.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But they amount to this, that actually, Turkey has nothing to do with this crime, and therefore, there is no jurisdictional link.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1290.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1298.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You appreciate, obviously, that there needs to be a jurisdictional link, elsewise, there is a worldwide obligation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1298.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1301.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the Turkish side maintains there is no jurisdictional link.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1301.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1314.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And although the submissions are well-presented and long, the reality is that it is not the case that the Turkish side has no jurisdictional link.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1314.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1338.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first submission in reply to those points on the Turkish side is that actually, the jurisdiction which was given to Turkey by this court in the Loizidou case, the jurisdiction given to Turkey was not given to them because on territorial grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1338.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1346.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Actually, in international law, including the Treaty of Establishment of the Republic of Cyprus, the territory of Cyprus is one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1346.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1348.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is one and one alone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1348.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1351.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not actually divided in any way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1351.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1361.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The territory of Cyprus is not only indivisible, it is against the Constitution of Cyprus for it to be divided.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1361.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1370.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And consequently, in my submission, the jurisdiction exercised by Turkey is actually belongs to Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1370.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1382.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is only exercised by Turkey because, putting it neutrally, because of course this court is not concerned with the politics of it, because there have been issues between the two sides.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1382.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1386.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Turkey is in effective control of North Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1386.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1391.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the jurisdiction, the legal ownership of the jurisdiction belongs to Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1391.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1405.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, Turkey only has jurisdiction in North Cyprus because of the need to protect human rights, because of the need to have a state answerable in this court to human rights violations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1405.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1407.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's the only reason.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1407.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1419.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So really, the purpose of ascribing jurisdiction to Turkey was to close a human rights gap.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1419.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1420.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nothing more.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1420.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1425.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So far as the jurisprudence of this court is concerned, nothing more.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1425.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1456.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That being so, it would be very eccentric indeed if this court were to decide to open a huge gap in human rights protection by saying that when someone, a murderer, moves from the Turkish-controlled part of Cyprus to the Republic of Cyprus and commits a murder and then returns, according to the Turkish side, there is no jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1456.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1457.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But how can that be?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1457.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1459.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How can it be that there is no jurisdiction?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1459.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1477.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A, there is a jurisdictional link because, in my submission on the facts, it must be right that if someone, this is what was decided in Olochlin, Olochlin, the Irish case, that if terrorists come from one country to another country, commit murder, and then go back, I mean, how can you say?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1477.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1499.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But actually, in the case of Cyprus, it's beyond that because truth to tell, the fact is that the jurisdiction exercised by Turkey belongs to Cyprus and is temporarily not available to Cyprus, basically because Cyprus is not powerful enough to make sure it's not there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1499.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1503.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And consequently, in my submission, this is stating the obvious.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1510.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1526.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Had Cyprus been in the way it was without being divided, what would have happened was that these police officers would have gone over to wherever the criminals, the murderers were, they would have arrested them, questioned them, and then tried them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1526.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1530.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in my submission, the answer to the jurisdictional point is really a very simple one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1530.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1532.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Actually, it is the same jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1532.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1533.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is one jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1533.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1542.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in any event, Olochlin and Ratsev, the recent case of Ratsev, covers the point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1542.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1552.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, moving on to two forensic points, because I know that my time is limited, there are two forensic points which actually tell a lot about this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1552.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1561.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is the forensic points that I have in mind are on page 5 at paragraph 6.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1561.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1565.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The two forensic points are these, and they are linked to both the points that I've been making.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1568.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1579.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chief of police, this is paragraphs 132 and 138 of the, which I reproduce in my latest pleading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1579.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1585.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They're to do with the attitude of the chief of police of the Republic of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1585.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1591.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He said, in effect, I'm not talking to the policemen on the other side.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1591.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1595.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm not even prepared to talk to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1595.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1600.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm not even prepared to meet up with them, let alone cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1600.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1609.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You can't cooperate, you can't begin to cooperate if you're not talking to someone, if you are in denial about the existence of someone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1609.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1619.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In my submission, on the facts, there's obviously been not only a failure to cooperate, but a failure to contemplate cooperation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1622.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1633.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And he said that in those paragraphs that he's not even talking to them, because it would be recognition of a pseudo state, I think.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1633.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1662.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I don't want to repeat the submissions that I made earlier, but that is, in my submission, not the correct attitude, because, and this is the forensic point, in 2001, this court decided in an interstate case, Cyprus versus Turkey, they decided that dealing with one another to preserve human rights is not recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1662.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1667.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It doesn't, it's overridden by human rights considerations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1667.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1675.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would add another point, which I think is important in this case, is that when one policeman talks to another one about a case, that's not recognition anyway.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1675.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1677.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not recognition in fact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1677.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1682.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mean, recognition means some kind of official.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1682.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1698.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police officers do not represent their country, and therefore, there would have been nothing wrong with this policeman talking to one another about, let alone very shortly after the Cyprus and Turkey case decided that actually this would not be recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1698.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1704.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the Republic of Cyprus government was not following the decision in Cyprus versus Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1704.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1707.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not engaged in follow up.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1707.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1710.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's so far as the Republic of Cyprus side is concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1710.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1725.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as the TRNC, the Turkish side is concerned, there's a very interesting, there are some very interesting evidential points at paragraph 130.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1725.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1727.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>130 is on page 5.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1727.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1731.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I make references on page 5 at small Roman numeral 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1734.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1740.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Turkish side had a very sort of, a very ambivalent view.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1740.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1747.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At one and the same time, they were telling the Republic of Cyprus through, I think, through an envoy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1747.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1752.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a non-paper sent to him on 20, to the president of Cyprus, of the Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1752.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1760.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>25th January, you'll find this at footnote 4 on page 5.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1760.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1808.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A note was being sent by the Turkish side saying, citing rather, citing articles in the Republic of Cyprus convention, Constitution, saying in effect to the president of Cyprus that actually, under the Cyprus Constitution, I think, Article 158 or something like that, he was saying that under the Republic of Cyprus Constitution, the judiciary to try this case, if it were to come to trial, has to comprise only Turkish Cypriot judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1808.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1821.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because according to this Constitution of Cyprus, where the victim is Turkish and the alleged perpetrator is Turkish, in those circumstances, the judges must be Turkish.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1821.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1839.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But of course, the TRNC official who made this, and indeed the attorney general on the TRNC side repeated it later, he was citing the Republic of Cyprus Constitution, not the TRNC Constitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1839.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1848.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was citing, and therefore, he was accepting that actually, he was accepting the jurisdiction of the Constitution of the Republic of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1848.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1855.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because he was saying under that Constitution, it should be Turkish Cypriot judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1855.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1870.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in my submission, these two points, these two forensic points, make the point that was also made by the court below, the chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1870.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1872.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because the chamber below made two important points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1872.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1877.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first, the one that I've already mentioned, this is a very simple case on the facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1877.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1892.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second important point was that actually, the two sides, over a period of about, I think, eight years, were engaged with each other in bad faith.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1892.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1902.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's not only failure to contemplate cooperation, it is, and this is a finding of fact which has not been challenged, as I understand it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1902.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1907.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I understand it, there is no challenge to the factual challenge to the bad faith.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1907.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1909.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's nothing worse in my submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1909.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1923.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In negotiations of this sort, concerned as they were with the right to life, the murder of a young girl, for parties to be engaged with each other in bad faith.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1923.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1944.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A bad faith, said the court below, to the extent where so much time has passed, the evidence is now deteriorating, and the chances of getting the perpetrators of this dreadful murder to punishment are becoming less and less.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1944.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1949.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this because of bad faith.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1949.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1957.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I move on to my third point, if I may, and that is to do with the nature of the duty to cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1957.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1962.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That, of course, is before you in the jurisprudence of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1962.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1964.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Possible I may go?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1964.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1971.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I be so bold as to ask how much time do I have?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1971.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1971.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because I'm ...</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1973.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1975.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Minister Rizza, but you have less than three minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1976.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1977.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can deal with it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1977.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1978.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1980.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1981.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can deal with it in three minutes for this reason.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1981.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1987.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The law is clear because it's in the cases that you have before you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1987.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1996.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cases you have before you are O'Loughlin, Rantziff, and Cummings, I think.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1996.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2059.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And basically, in my submission, the court below was absolutely right when it said that where there are, I think the way they put it is where two territories, in this case, in Cyprus, are implicated, not used in the sort of criminal sense, but if they're intertwined in such a way as they are in Cyprus, and as they are in Ireland, in Ireland also, where you have a situation where you have criminals, murderers, drug dealers, all sorts of people like that, terrorists moving from one country to the other, engaging in murder and pillage and plunder, and then returning, where two territories are so intertwined, so closely intertwined, the duty to cooperate is obvious.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2059.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2061.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What happened in Cyprus is what the court said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2061.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2066.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not even actually very, it wasn't really great.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2066.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2069.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was just a mild step forward.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2069.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2085.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What it said is that faced with that sort of situation, what the court was prepared to do was look at whether a minimum effort were possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2085.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2090.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if it were, whether the parties engaged in a minimum level of cooperation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2090.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2101.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it found, as a fact, that these two sides, for political reasons, for perfectly good political reasons, I don't know.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2101.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2105.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But for political reasons, they decided not to engage in the minimum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2105.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2115.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And, in my submission, the court was absolutely right to decide so, and absolutely right to find against both countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2115.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2116.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think my three minutes are over.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2118.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2122.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If you want two minutes more, please, Miss Riza, go ahead for two minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2123.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2125.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Oh, for two minutes?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2125.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2131.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, I really have finished actually, because otherwise I'll have to go back and it's untidy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2131.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2131.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I have finished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2132.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2134.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Okay, thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2134.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2137.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Riza, I call Mrs. Montgomery, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2137.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2137.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2139.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2143.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2143.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2156.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>beginning on the 20th of July, 1974, over 40,000 Turkish troops, tanks, air forces, invaded the island of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2156.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2160.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They occupied about 40% of the northern landmass.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2160.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2166.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey confined thousands of Greek Cypriots to detention centers and prisons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2166.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2172.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkish troops killed and tortured civilians and raped women.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2172.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2178.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey detained or murdered about 2,000 missing Greek Cypriots.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2178.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2183.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It forced more than 170,000 people from their homes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2183.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2186.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The troops looted and robbed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2186.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2190.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They vandalized homes and cultural centers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2190.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2193.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Property was destroyed and expropriated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2193.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2200.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Turkey has taken no real steps by way of reparation for these wrongs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2200.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2206.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has not implemented the decision of this court in Cyprus and Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2206.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2216.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has not paid the just satisfaction awarded by this court in the Vanava and Zenedi's arrest cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2216.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2231.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And although it has cooperated to an extent in identifying missing persons in suspected burial sites in the north, no measures have been taken to ensure accountability for the perpetrators.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2231.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2240.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, as you know, since 2016, it's indicated a general intention to derogate under Article 15.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2240.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2247.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even now, the population in the north is increasingly dominated by Turks and Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2247.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2256.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cypriots and Maronites still living in the north are discriminated against, including from participating in elections.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2256.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2262.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey has taken steps to obliterate the rights of Cypriots.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2262.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2268.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Place names in the north have been changed without regard to the history of the place or the wishes of the people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2268.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2277.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The publication of material containing place names, different from those specified in official maps and documents, has been criminalized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2277.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2283.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Access to religious and cultural heritage sites are still restricted or denied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2283.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2290.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The UN has commented on the massive destruction of sites and artifacts in the north.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2290.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2298.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To this day, the UN estimates there are nearly 30,000 Turkish troops in the northern part of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2298.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2306.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thousands of armed Turkish troops confront the Cypriot National Guard along ceasefire lines and patrol the north.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2306.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2313.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>272,000 people remain internally displaced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2313.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2325.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The UN talks, as you know, seeking reunification, broke down in July 2017 when Turkey refused to withdraw its troops from the north of the island.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2325.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2336.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this case raises the central issue, whether a victim of state aggression has any obligation to cooperate with its aggressor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2336.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2340.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that the principle is clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2340.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2344.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is and can be no possible obligation to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2344.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2352.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The obligation upon the aggressor is to cease his wrongful acts and to withdraw.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2352.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2383.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet the decision of the third section would require the Republic of Cyprus to treat the Turkish occupiers of the north, TRNC, as if they were reliable, law-abiding, non-violent international partners with whom the Republic should share information and whose courts should be permitted to try citizens of the Republic of Cyprus for the murder of citizens of that republic on Cypriot territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2387.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2395.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the examples that are given of cases between Ireland and the United Kingdom or even Greece and Turkey by Mr. Risa</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2395.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2407.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ignore the fact that the Republic of Cyprus is being asked to cooperate with someone who is occupying its land, who's murdered its people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2410.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2437.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in the context where the crime is one of aggression and a refusal to withdraw from unlawful occupation, the public international legal obligation of non-recognition is not a meaningless international rule, but a vital protection against the wholesale violation of human rights that occurs in cases of state aggression.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2437.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2441.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is not a historic case of aggression.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2441.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2446.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is one where international wrongful acts continue to this day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2446.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2465.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If countries like Turkey can act within the European legal space with impunity in invading a country, murdering its citizens, and usurping power, human rights violations would occur much more frequently and with much greater severity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2465.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2479.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the aim of the rule against non-recognition in this context is not a bloodless public international law principle, but just as important as the aim of the European Convention on Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2479.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2484.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 14.2, read together with Article 41 of the ILC articles</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2484.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2497.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the responsibility of states for internationally wrongful acts, provides that in relation to serious acts of aggression, invasion, and occupation, they will have a continuing character.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2497.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2510.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there is an undiminished responsibility on Turkey under Article 30 of the ILC articles to bring to an immediate end its internationally wrongful conduct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2510.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2522.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third states and international organizations are therefore required not to aid and assist Turkey in maintaining this unlawful situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2522.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2528.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the rule against non-recognition in this context is protective of human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2528.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2531.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not some abstract principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2531.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2545.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if it weren't, even if it were simply a freestanding principle, this court has repeatedly acknowledged that the provisions of the convention can't be interpreted in a vacuum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2545.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2557.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite the fact it is a human rights instrument, the convention is also an international treaty to be interpreted in accordance with the relevant norms and principles of international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2557.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2567.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we would say that obligation must be a fortiori where the public international law obligation under the ILC articles is intended to protect human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2571.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2574.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And one can see the importance of that rule in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2574.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2586.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Were it not for Turkey's wrongful refusal to withdraw from the occupied territory in the north, the applicants would have no cause to complain to this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2586.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2589.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was, contrary to what Mr. Reeser says,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2589.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2594.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a prompt and effective investigation by the Republic of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2594.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2597.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The suspects were promptly identified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2597.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2599.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their whereabouts were discovered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2599.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2603.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The evidence was gathered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2603.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2609.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of those suspects would have been detained, tried, and if convicted, punished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2609.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2623.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Were it not for the obstruction to justice created by Turkish soldiers sitting on a ceasefire line, preventing those who hide in the north from being brought to justice by the Republic of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2628.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2632.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the court knows, Cyprus is a sovereign state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2632.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2640.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a member of the EU with inherent and supreme rights, as Mr. Reeser accepts, throughout the territory</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2640.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2641.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the island.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2641.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2649.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has the absolute right to enforce its laws in regard to all people in all of that territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2649.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2664.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any principle of criminal jurisdiction, whether territorial, nationality, residence, passive personality, support the Republic of Cyprus's claim to have sole and original jurisdiction in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2664.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2667.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no overlapping jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2667.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2673.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's no two territories, as Mr. Reeser says.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2673.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2675.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is only the territory of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2678.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2703.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 2 cannot require Cyprus to cede jurisdiction to Turkey, which claims, as you know, through this creature, the TRNC, the right to prescribe criminal laws in respect of people, property, and acts, all taking place outside Turkish territory in blatant contravention of the Bankovic principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2703.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2712.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So these are not political considerations, but considerations based on principle and law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2712.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2729.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey and its liability under the convention, which I will address, does not replace or supplant Cyprus's right to insist upon being the sole and original state properly capable of exercising criminal jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2729.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2757.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, Turkey's position in this case illustrates that it seeks to provide legitimate support for its refusal to withdraw troops by presenting as law a provision made by its creature, the TRNC, which purports to say that fugitive citizens of the Republic may not be tried by the Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2757.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2772.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It cites as state practice the idea that TRNC should be treated as having a system of criminal courts and that Cyprus should make an extradition request to the TRNC, as if it were a state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2772.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2781.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It claims, therefore, that the failures by Turkey and the TRNC have, and I quote, a sound basis in domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2781.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2791.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of that, as the court will understand, is anathema to a country who has seen its landmass violently occupied to this day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2794.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2807.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Other than submit to Turkey's demands for the Republic of Cyprus to provide evidence to the TRNC, Cyprus has done everything it can to meet its obligations under Article 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2807.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2820.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The real reason that there has not been a trial in this case is because Turkey has breached not only its international obligation to cease its occupation, but also its Article 2 obligation to cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2824.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2835.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no obligation comparable to that found in the Chinova and the Minsk Convention between two states to cooperate in prosecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2835.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2845.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, the majority of the suspects were Cypriot nationals committing crimes on Cypriot territory against other Cypriot nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2845.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2858.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no lawful basis for that case to be transferred to an organization such as TRNC, and indeed, no prospect of success, even if it was transferred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2858.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2873.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's therefore nothing equivalent between this situation and the sort of informal cooperation between the UK and the TRNC discussed in the English case of Akerke.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2873.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2877.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the UK is not a direct victim of Turkey's use of force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2877.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2880.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has its own national interest to serve.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2880.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2891.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the whole reasoning of the UK court was on the basis that the principle of non-recognition was not incorporated into UK law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2891.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2909.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That has no bearing on this court, which, as I've remarked, has an obligation to consider international obligations, and indeed, specifically, the ILC articles on the responsibility of states for wrongful acts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2909.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2920.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It certainly cannot be taken as authority for the idea that there is compatibility between cooperating with the TRNC and the rule of recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2920.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2925.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in particular, of course, the UK is not the injured state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2925.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2935.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here, the Republic of Cyprus is the state directly injured by the invasion and continued occupation of its land.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2935.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2944.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is for Cyprus to consider whether it wishes to protest, as it does, or whether it could otherwise waive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2944.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2949.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the right of the Republic of Cyprus as a victim of state aggression.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2949.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2970.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It certainly has no obligation, contrary to what the third section says, to accept as lawful laws of the TRNC as a valid basis for recognizing that its citizens have somehow acquired another nationality and are to be tried by another country's courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2970.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2990.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nor is that approach disproportionate or in bad faith, because it is in the long-term interests of Cyprus and the international community as a whole to deter states from acting in aggression, to deter the death that is brought by that conduct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2990.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3006.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The function of non-recognition in customary law and under the ILC articles is to vindicate the legal character of international law and to punish the violation of peremptory norms against aggression.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3006.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3025.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To state that occupation, forcible occupation and acquisition of territory is inadmissible, to protect against what Professor Crawford called the law-creating effect of facts, it is to deter future aggression that this court must uphold the rule against non-recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3025.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3034.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there is no room for attenuation over time in relation to this particular rule and no room for pragmatism.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3034.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3047.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is clear from the preamble to the European Convention itself, which speaks of the importance of a zone of freedom, of democracy and the rule of law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3047.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3055.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we suggest that the idea that the court has ruled against non-recognition in Demopolis is simply wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3055.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3082.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we pointed out in our written pleadings, the reasoning in Demopolis and the other cases turns upon the obligation in individual cases, not state-to-state cases, but individual cases where there is the possibility of correcting wrongs imputable to Turkey within TRNC, those opportunities should be taken by individuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3082.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3096.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that principle can't extrapolate out and deny Cyprus the right to protest, as it does about the occupation of the land, that it is a sovereign state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3096.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3104.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this is not a case where we say Article 2 trumps non-recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3104.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3110.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That principle of non-recognition, certainly in cases of state aggression, is equally fundamental.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3110.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3123.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be valued more highly, potentially, as a protection against individuals' right to life than possibly Article 2 itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3123.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3128.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there's no vacuum created by this insistence by the Republic of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3128.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3137.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any vacuum is created by the fact that Turkey continues to unlawfully occupy the north by force of arms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3137.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3139.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So Mr. Rees' fire example,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3139.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3147.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a fire raging on the Green ceasefire line, the Republic of Cyprus accepts its obligation is to put that fire out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3147.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3163.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only reason it can't is because troops, unlawfully present from a third state, are preventing it carrying out its sovereign rights to protect its land.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3163.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3186.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So although it is said this is not a case where recognition is going to take place, the reality is that everything that is said on behalf of TRNC and the applicants that suggests that the TRNC has citizens or laws or territory involve a claim to recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3186.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3197.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And indeed, the court may look at the facts found by the third section and conclude the claim that there was some desire to try people in the north or in Turkey was mere posturing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3197.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3212.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The full evidential file was provided to Turkey upon this case being admitted in 2009, and no steps have been taken to hold a trial either in TRNC or in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3212.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3224.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it is possible that what the court is looking at is merely an attempt to seek political advantage from the situation without any concern for the principles of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3224.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3228.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are not claiming to derogate from Article 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3228.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3242.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are simply asserting that the procedural obligation does not require an act in breach of the principles that underpin the ILC articles and the rules against aggression and state occupation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3242.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3250.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The finding of bad faith is, we suggest, entirely unjustified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3250.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3257.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The obligation is merely to take such measures that are in our power to take in accordance with international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3257.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3266.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cyprus has consistently sought to reassert control over the north that would solve the problem that comes before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3266.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3271.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has had the assistance of the international community in doing so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3271.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3275.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has requested the return of the suspects from the north for trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3275.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3277.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not indifferent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3277.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3283.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is and continues to be concerned to secure the return of the suspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3283.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3287.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has used the lawful means at its disposal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3287.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3299.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The failure to secure the result of return is not a breach of a procedural obligation, which, as the court knows, is a means and not results.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3299.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3326.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the passage of time since the events of 1974 should not dull the court's view of the true status of Turkey in the north of the island of Cyprus, nor should it obscure the importance of not lending legitimacy to TRNC's claims to have criminal jurisdiction over citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3326.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3351.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey should cease its unlawful occupation, and in the respectful submission of the Republic of Cyprus, nothing in the proceedings that have gone on to try and secure a peaceful resolution have the effect of diluting the principle of non-recognition, either to vanishing point, as was suggested by the applicants, or as was suggested by Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3351.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3355.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cyprus has no obligation to cooperate with Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3355.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3362.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It may choose to waive its rights, but it has no obligation to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3362.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3379.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I therefore propose to address briefly a second question, which we suggest does not arise in this case, but it is whether and when there may be an obligation to cooperate with states who are not aggressors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3379.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3400.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even in such a case, we would suggest that Article 2 does not place an obligation on the original state of jurisdiction to cooperate with a third-party state, particularly not where there is no legitimate claim in the third state's jurisdiction, or its claim violates the principle of subsidiarity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3400.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3421.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this is not a case where there is any legitimate, concurrent criminal jurisdiction of the sort dealt with in various European instruments on transfer of proceedings and on settlement of conflicts on the exercise of jurisdiction and the Eurojust guidelines.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3421.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3442.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But even if one looks at those European instruments, all of them confirm that a prosecution in a third state must always be subsidiary in application and should only be exercised if the state having original jurisdiction is unable to exercise it or waives its right to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3442.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3465.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And similarly, in relation to the mutual legal assistant text, the European evidence warrants and other European instruments, again, where a crime is committed on the territory of a state that is subject to a request, it is always an optional ground for refusal for that state to say, no, we have primary jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3465.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3483.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was a crime committed on our territory, and under all of the European instruments, that is regarded as an acceptable reason for declining to transfer evidence and insisting upon trial on the territory where the crime was committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3483.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3493.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We should say that we do accept that there is an obligation on third states to cooperate with an original state of jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3493.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3521.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There may obviously always need to be some margin of appreciation in that one-way cooperation obligation, for example, where the trial's impossible in the original state for humanitarian or asylum reasons, such as Shemaef, or where there's a policy reason, such as non-extradition of nationals, so that a trial outside the original jurisdiction can proceed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3521.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3529.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But otherwise, there will be a one-way cooperation obligation owed by the third state to the original state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3529.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3538.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then that will obviously then be subject to the typical restrictions on mutual assistance or extradition, nae bis in idem, and all those other principles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3538.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3548.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But there is an obligation subject to the normal protections that are built into the European instrument and treaty obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3548.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3558.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's not appropriate to argue, as Turkey does, that the only cooperation obligation is that established by domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3558.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3569.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's no reason in principle why a state should not be required to legislate ad hoc for cooperation where it's necessary in the interest of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3569.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3570.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Many states do.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3570.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3581.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They provide a domestic mechanism that can be used for any state, even one without a treaty relationship, in order to secure evidence or extradition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3581.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3589.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we do not accept the proposition either that there has to be a formal bilateral or multilateral treaty obligation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3589.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3594.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The procedural obligation under Article 2 can be read as requiring ad hoc cooperation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3594.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3601.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And indeed, on one view, Article 2 is the treaty obligation requiring ad hoc.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3601.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3617.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The alternative would be to leave people who carry out crimes in Cyprus a safe haven in the north of the island where they can operate with impunity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3617.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3637.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it is the submission of the Republic of Cyprus that Turkey, as the occupying power, could and should comply with its procedural obligation in any case in the TRNC, where there's a murder that's taken place in the north and a compliant investigation can take place there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3637.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3651.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it is an obstacle to that process that extradition is not provided or available, that is caused by the illegal occupation, not by anything done by the Republic of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3651.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3668.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And certainly in terms of Turkey's claim that there was no jurisdiction to find against it under Article 2, that is very hard to understand, where, according to Turkey, proceedings have begun in the TRNC.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3668.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3682.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The assertion of a right to investigate and prosecute in the TRNC must give rise to a sufficient jurisdictional link for the purpose of Article 2 under the Markovits principles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3682.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3708.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that Turkey doesn't mention the fact that the suspected perpetrators of these crimes are, in fact, either in the area in the north of Cyprus under its control or in Turkey itself shows the clarity of the jurisdictional link and the poverty of the explanation as to why the Article 2 obligations on Turkey have not been complied with.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3708.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3716.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, as Mr Reza has said, Turkey has a jurisdictional link by reason of the Al-Skaini principles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3716.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3725.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That does not give it primary jurisdiction, as the court knows, which belongs to the Republic of Cyprus, but it does mean that it may be required to cooperate with the Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3725.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3734.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also means there is a relevant jurisdictional link to Turkey requiring it to comply with the investigative obligation under Article 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3734.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3756.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the reliance that's placed on the admissibility decision in W and the UK is misplaced, because in W and the UK, the concern with protective measures prior to the crime being committed was the area of inquiry, whereas here it is the sufficiency of the investigation which is under consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3756.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3769.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as was decided in Loizetu, it is clear that under the Al-Skaini jurisdiction, Turkey, as the occupier, is banned by the Article 2 investigative obligation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3769.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3772.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, there would be a vacuum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3772.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3787.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if the court in Ranseth is read as saying that the obligation of cooperation only arises in a second state or third state because of special features, there are here two very special features.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3787.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3801.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the fact that Turkey occupies Cypriot territory and has obstructed quite deliberately Cyprus's investigation and request to have the suspects returned for trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3801.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3808.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And secondly, that Turkey knows those suspects are within its jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3808.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3815.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should deal briefly with the idea that Turkey was not sent a request for extradition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3815.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3819.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That ignores the facts as found by the third section.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3819.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3827.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, a red notice was diffused via Interpol by the Republic of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3827.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3841.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, an application for extradition was delivered formally from the Cypriot embassy in Athens to the Turkish embassy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3841.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3850.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And although Turkey claims the right not to extradite its citizens, it has not even responded to the request for extradition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3850.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3852.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has not gone through the process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3852.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3855.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has not even applied its own laws.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3855.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3866.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has simply returned the request without responding to it, as it's obliged to do under the European Convention on Extradition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3866.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3883.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the reference to Djibouti and France, we suggest, is just a cynical attempt to deflect attention from the fact that Turkey is simply unwilling to cooperate with any request for extradition and unwilling to hold a trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3883.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3896.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn, finally, to a very short theoretical question whether, if there were concurrent criminal jurisdiction, Cyprus would have a discretion to decline cooperation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3896.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3913.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our submission, it would have such a discretion, particularly as a trial in the TRNC risks further violations of Article 2 and can only produce results incompatible with the convention, comparable to the Mitrovic and Serbia position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3913.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3922.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And indeed, as the court will know, there is no domestic legal framework in the TRNC which would satisfy the Article 6 obligation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3925.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3932.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's no gap because Cyprus remains able and willing to prosecute these suspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3932.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3943.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in our submission, it is obvious that the only place capable of delivering an Article 2 compliant trial is the Republic of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3943.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3950.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's not a question of the court deciding where a trial should take place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3950.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3961.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None of the European instruments that exist in relation to extradition or mutual assistance would require the provision of evidence to the TRNC.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3961.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3967.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The focus, as the court knows, is on the means rather than the result. And the Republic of Cyprus</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3967.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3978.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>says it has taken all lawful means at its disposal to preserve the rule of law and has only failed because of the unlawful occupation of its territory by another state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3982.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3983.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3983.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3987.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mrs. Montgomery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3987.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3989.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I call Mr. Talmon, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3989.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3989.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4001.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4005.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4005.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4014.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it is an honor to appear once again before you and to do so on behalf of the Republic of Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4014.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4023.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before addressing the central issue in this case, let me make one preliminary remark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4023.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4048.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite of what you have heard from the other respondent this morning, this case is not about the events of 1974 or the political situation on the island of Cyprus or the legal status and recognition of the Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4048.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4063.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case is about whether the two respondents in this case have fulfilled their obligations under the procedural limb of Article 2 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4063.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4066.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, as concerns Turkey,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4066.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4102.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the central issue in this case is whether a state to whose territory or area of control a murder suspect has fled is under an obligation to investigate a murder occurring in another state, to cooperate with the investigation of the authorities of the state where the murder has occurred, and to extradite the murder suspect to the state where the murder has occurred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4102.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4118.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These questions are not unique to the situation in Cyprus, but may arise in any cross-border murder case where the suspect flees to another country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4118.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4127.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case, thus, has wide-ranging repercussions for all parties to the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4127.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4160.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the chamber were correct and there were, in fact, such a procedural obligation, the next of kin of murder victims who are dissatisfied with an investigation, the lack or level of cooperation, or the non-extradition of a murder suspect could bring a case for violation of Article 2 against any of the 47 member states of the Council of Europe to which a suspect has fled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4164.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4168.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, in the judgment you</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4168.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4190.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>are asked to review today, the chamber found that the respondents have a procedural obligation to investigate of their own motion murders taking place in other states and to cooperate with the investigation of these states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4190.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4210.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I quote, where there are cross-border elements to an incident of unlawful violence leading to the loss of life, or where the investigation of the unlawful killing unavoidably implicates more than one state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4214.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4220.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The wording employed by the chamber is as wide as it is vague.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4220.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4229.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, numerous states may be implicated in a cross-border murder investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4229.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4252.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The state where the murder was planned, the state where the murder weapon was acquired, the state or states where the murder suspect or the accomplices fled to, and in the case of contract murders, even the state where the principle was based.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4252.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4255.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, all these states are supposedly</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4255.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4271.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>under an obligation to investigate a murder taking place outside their own territory and to cooperate with the murder investigation of foreign police and judicial authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4271.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4281.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This clearly cannot be the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4281.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4290.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber did not provide any legal basis in the convention for such a wide-ranging obligation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4290.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4298.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the chamber offered were six common places and result-oriented arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4298.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4309.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the chamber stated, I quote, the fundamental importance of Article II requires an obligation to investigate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4309.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4318.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, those indulging in cross-border attacks would be able to operate with impunity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4318.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4328.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A duty to cooperate was in keeping with the effective protection of the right to life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4328.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4334.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The duty to cooperate was a corollary of the obligation to investigate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4334.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4342.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any other finding would severely diminish the purpose of the protection guaranteed by Article II.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4342.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4361.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, that it was of crucial importance that the convention as a system for the protection of human rights was interpreted and applied in a manner that rendered these rights practical and effective, not theoretical and illusionary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4361.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4364.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, these statements can</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4364.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4379.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>be applied to all high-contracting parties and thus make the procedural obligation to investigate and to cooperate a freestanding obligation of all high-contracting parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4381.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4386.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants do not do any better, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4386.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4415.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In their written submissions to the Grand Chamber, they state, and I quote again, in the case of murder with a trans-jurisdictional element, the procedural aspect requires the states responsible for securing the right to life to cooperate in securing evidence, because otherwise there would be a gap in human rights protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4415.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4429.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the duty to cooperate derives directly from the duty to secure the procedural aspects of the right to life within the legal space of Europe in Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4434.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4445.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants speak about an obligation to cooperate of, I quote, the states responsible for securing the right to life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4445.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4461.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Without addressing the question of which states are actually responsible for securing the right to life in a particular situation and how these states are to be identified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4461.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4481.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, the applicants do not explain on what legal basis Turkey should be responsible for securing the right to life in southern Cyprus, a territory under the control of the Greek Cypriot authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4485.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4488.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4488.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4517.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it is Turkey's submission that the reasons given by the chamber and the argument put forward by the applicants cannot explain in terms of the convention why Turkey should be under a procedural obligation to investigate on its own initiative murders in southern Cyprus and to cooperate with the murder investigation of the Greek Cypriot authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4522.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4527.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, in its questions to the parties,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4527.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4541.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the court asked Turkey to address the compatibility razione loci of the applicants' complaints against Turkey with the provisions of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4541.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4547.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey submits that this is the decisive question on which the applicants' case turns.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4551.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4569.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The admissibility requirement of competence razione loci limits the competence of the court to examine breaches of the convention to allege breaches taking place within the jurisdiction of the respondent state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4573.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4584.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The high contracting parties have not committed themselves to secure the rights and freedoms defined in the convention to everyone, everywhere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4584.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4594.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have rather committed themselves in Article I to secure these rights and freedoms to persons within their jurisdiction only.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4597.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4620.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The exercise of jurisdiction over the victim of a violation of the convention is thus a necessary condition, a threshold requirement for a high contracting party to be able to be held responsible for a violation of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4620.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4629.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, there must be a jurisdictional link between the victim of the violation and the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4634.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4639.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sorry, the victim of the violation and the respondent state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4639.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4651.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, there must thus be a jurisdictional link between the victims of the alleged violation of Article II and Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4651.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4666.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question of who is the victim of an alleged violation of the procedural limb of Article II was addressed by the European Commission of Human Rights in the case of W versus the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4666.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4685.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The commission held that the victim was determined by the person murdered, that is the direct victim, and not by the applicant, usually the next of kin of the person murdered, who qualifies only as an indirect victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4688.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4701.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The victims in the present case are thus the three members of the Güzeliotlu family murdered in the area of southern Cyprus under the control of the Greek Cypriot authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4706.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4710.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Turkey submits that there</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4710.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4719.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is no jurisdictional link in the present case between the persons murdered and Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4719.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4748.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is well established in the court's case law that a person comes within the jurisdiction of a state in terms of Article I if, first, the person is present in the territory of the state, or second, the person is present in an area under the state's control, or third, the person is subject to the authority and control of agents of the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4750.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4756.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None of these basis of jurisdiction is applicable here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4756.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4760.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The murders occurred in southern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4760.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4768.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Southern Cyprus is neither Turkish territory, nor is it under the effective control of Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4768.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4778.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is also no suggestion that Turkey or its agents were in any way involved in the murders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4778.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4795.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the time of their death, the persons murdered, the victims, were present in an area of southern Cyprus under the control of the Greek Cypriot authorities, that is, within their jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4795.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4804.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The jurisdictional link of the victims of the alleged violation of Article II is thus with the Greek Cypriot authorities, not with Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4806.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4817.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Without a jurisdictional link, there was no procedural obligation under Article II to investigate murders taking place in southern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4823.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4829.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, this position is supported both by the literature</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4829.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4832.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4832.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4844.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two cases concerning unlawful deaths in Cyprus with a cross-border element are of particular interest in this connection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4844.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4874.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Emin and others versus Cyprus, Greece, and the United Kingdom, the applicants alleged a violation of the procedural limb of Article II by the United Kingdom, claiming that the British government had not investigated the killing of their relatives in southern Cyprus, although the victims had held British passports and had worked in the British sovereign base areas in Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4877.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4896.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court ruled that the obligation to investigate did not fall on the United Kingdom, but solely on Cyprus, under whose jurisdiction the victim was at the time of death.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4896.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4922.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the second case, Rancev versus Cyprus and Russia, the applicant also alleged a violation of the procedural aspects of Article II, this time by Russia, claiming that the Russian authorities had not investigated the killing of his daughter in southern Cyprus, although the victim was a Russian national.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4922.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4932.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court held, and I quote, the court recalls that Ms. Rancev's death took place in Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4932.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4952.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, unless it can be shown that there are special features in the present case which require a departure from the general approach, the obligation to ensure an effective official investigation applies to Cyprus alone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4956.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4973.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court indicated that there may be special features which may require states to investigate murders occurring outside the territory or area of control, but failed to identify what these special features are.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4973.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4983.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It found, however, that neither the nationality of the victim nor the victim's place of residence qualified as a special feature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4990.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5019.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber held that Turkey had a duty to investigate the murders in southern Cyprus because, I quote, the suspected perpetrators of the murder are aware either in the TRNC or in mainland Turkey, and because the Turkish and TRNC authorities were informed of the crime and red notices concerning the suspects were published.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5019.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5034.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey submits that such factual circumstances cannot qualify any more as special features than the nationality or place of residence of the murder victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5034.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5044.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Seizing on such factual circumstances would create an obligation to investigate for all 47 parties to the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5044.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5056.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, this would be the first time in fact this would make the obligation to investigate a freestanding obligation of all high contracting parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5060.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5064.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5064.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5090.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>due to the lack of a jurisdictional link between the victims and Turkey and the absence of any special features, the applicants complained that Turkey failed to conduct an effective investigation into the killing of their relatives is outside the court's competence, ratione loci, and consequently inadmissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5099.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5104.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, let me now turn to Turkey's alleged obligation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5104.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5110.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to cooperate with the murder investigation of the Greek Cypriot authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5110.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5119.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey has established that there is no jurisdictional link between the persons murdered and Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5119.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5131.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber did not try to establish such a jurisdictional link, but simply asserted such an obligation on the part of Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5131.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5140.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber relied on the cases of Olochlin, Cummins, and in particular, Rantsev.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5140.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5148.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In none of these cases, the court found a violation of the procedural limb of Article II.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5148.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5169.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first two cases did not concern an obligation to cooperate at all, but dealt simply with the question of whether a state to which suspected perpetrators had fled and in which evidence of the offense could be located was under an obligation to investigate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5169.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5187.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Olochlin, the court even stated expressly that, I quote, the court does not need to decide whether or to what extent Article II could impose an obligation to cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5187.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5201.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the third case relied upon by the chamber, Rantsev versus Cyprus and Turkey, the court found that Russia was under an obligation to cooperate with a murder investigation in Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5201.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5222.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in that case, the court also did not address the question of the jurisdictional link requirement, but simply asserted that the duty to cooperate was the corollary of the obligation of an investigating state to secure evidence located in other jurisdictions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5229.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5243.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey has shown in its written submissions at paragraphs 49 to 54 that although at the time of her death, Ms. Rantsev was within the jurisdiction of Cyprus,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5243.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5253.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the case was first and foremost a case about human trafficking as slavery under Article IV of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5253.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5267.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unlike in the present case, the victim of the violation, the trafficked person, was at some stage in the trafficking chain within the jurisdiction of Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5267.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5278.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case thus does not call into question the requirement of a jurisdictional link between the victim and the respondent state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5281.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5284.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5284.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5318.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>due to the lack of a jurisdictional link between the victims and Turkey and the absence of a special feature such as human trafficking or a treaty commitment to investigate, as in the case of Aliyeva and Aliyev versus Azerbaijan, the applicants complained that Turkey failed to cooperate with the murder investigation of the Greek Cypriot authorities is outside the court's competence ratione loci and consequently inadmissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5323.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5326.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, in its question to the parties,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5326.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5341.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the court also asked about the extent of the procedural obligation imposed under Article II on the respondent states to cooperate with investigations held outside their jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5341.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5353.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is Turkey's submission that in the present case, this question does not arise with regard to Turkey because the applicants complained with regard to Turkey is inadmissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5353.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5358.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey would nevertheless like to offer two general observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5358.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5381.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, it is Turkey's view that the extent of the procedural obligation to cooperate under Article II is to be determined by reference to a state's existing international legal rights and obligations in the area of legal assistance in criminal matters outside the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5381.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5400.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The procedural obligation to cooperate is derived from the substantive obligation in Article II and as a derivative obligation cannot give rise to new independent substantive obligations under the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5400.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5416.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, a procedural obligation to cooperate cannot be defined as a derivative cannot establish an obligation to extradite in the absence of an applicable extradition treaty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5416.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5420.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This view is supported by the court's jurisprudence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5420.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5437.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In all cross-border cases where the court examined whether a state had met its obligations to cooperate, it made express reference to existing legal assistance instruments binding upon the states concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5437.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5458.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in Rancev versus Cyprus and Russia, the court found Cyprus in violation of its procedural obligation under Article II because it had not addressed any request for legal assistance to Russia under the bilateral and multilateral legal assistance agreements binding upon the two states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5461.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5489.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Similarly, in Huzinovah versus Azerbaijan, the court found a violation of the procedural limb of Article II because Azerbaijan had not examined the feasibility of transferring a criminal case to Georgia after Georgia had refused to extradite the suspects, although the various international legal instruments binding upon the two states clearly provided for such a possibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5489.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5506.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, Turkey takes the position that the extent of the procedural obligation to cooperate under extradition agreements depends on the particular circumstances of each individual suspect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5506.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5516.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, the extent of the obligation to cooperate may vary depending on a suspect's nationality or its place of residence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5516.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5526.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, Turkey would like to point out that the chamber did not properly distinguish between the various suspects in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5526.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5529.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some were Turkish nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5529.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5531.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Other were TRNC nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5531.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5534.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some were based in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5534.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5536.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Others were based in northern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5536.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5542.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some were based in Turkey, others were based in northern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5547.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5550.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Turkey would also like</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5550.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5573.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to offer a brief comment on the view that the extent of the Greek Cypriots' authorities' obligation to cooperate with the Turkish Cypriot authorities was zero because of an alleged duty not to recognize the TRNC and not to render aid or assistance in maintaining the TRNC as a state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5573.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5580.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is absolutely no support for this position in international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5580.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5590.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quite the contrary, state practice with regard to non-recognition points in the exactly opposite direction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5590.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5617.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey has set out in its written submissions at paragraph 69 to 75 that state practice clearly shows that other states cooperate with the TRNC in criminal matters and that such cooperation is not considered as amounting to implicit recognition of statehood or aid or assistance in maintaining the TRNC as a state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5617.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5624.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is probably no better authority for this position than the Greek Cypriot attorney general.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5624.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5654.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Commenting in February 2017 on a judgment of the English High Court in London, which approved police-to-police cooperation in judicial proceedings between the United Kingdom and the TRNC, he said, and I quote, this is purely a practical matter, but legally it entails no risk of recognition, even indirectly, of the North.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5657.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5662.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, in its questions to the parties,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5662.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5684.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the court further asked whether Turkey had fulfilled its procedural obligation to cooperate under Article 2, and in particular, whether that article had been breached as a result of the Turkish and Turkish Cypriot authorities' failure to extradite or surrender the suspects to the Greek Cypriot authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5684.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5696.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is Turkey's submission that these questions on the merits do not arise because the applicant's complaint with regard to Turkey is inadmissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5696.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5708.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Assuming for the sake of argument that the complaint was admissible, Turkey submits that there was no breach of the procedural obligation to cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5708.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5715.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The obligation to cooperate is triggered only by a request to cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5715.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5731.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court in Rancev versus Cyprus and Russia held that in the absence of a legal assistance request, the authorities were not required under Article 2 to secure the evidence themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5731.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5743.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the absence of a specific cooperation request, there was thus no obligation on Turkey to cooperate with the Greek Cypriot authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5743.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5758.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only request ever made by the Greek Cypriot authorities, either directly or through the United Nations force in Cyprus, was for the surrender of the suspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5758.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5771.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under its existing treaty commitments, Turkey, however, was under no obligation to extradite or surrender the suspects to the Greek Cypriot authorities for three reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5771.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5787.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the European Convention on Extradition, like the European Convention on Mutual Assistance in Criminal Matters, is binding on Turkey only with regard to its metropolitan territories.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5787.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5798.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Metropolitan territories have been defined by the International Law Commission as territories over which a state has sovereignty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5798.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5806.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Clearly, Turkey does not claim or enjoy sovereignty over northern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5806.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5817.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regard to the seven suspects present in northern Cyprus, there was thus no obligation to extradite under the Extradition Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5817.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5829.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, there was no valid request for extradition through diplomatic channels, as requested by the European Convention on Extradition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5829.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5850.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third, with regard to the fifth suspect who was present in Turkey and thus fell within the territorial scope of application of the Extradition Convention, Turkey was entitled to refuse extradition because of the suspects' Turkish nationality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5850.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5856.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is also no obligation to extradite suspects present in a state's territory or in an area under its control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5856.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5858.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Talmon, forgive me for interrupting,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5858.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5860.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>but may I ask you to conclude, please?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5870.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5876.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, to conclude, let me just question whether in the present case there was actually</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5876.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5886.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>any practically feasible and more importantly any legal way to surrender the suspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5886.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5900.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Chamber, the applicants and the other respondents have made the following suggestions for what they considered possible measures of cooperation on the part of the Turkish Cypriot authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5900.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5907.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First the suspects were simply to be handed over to the Greek Cypriot authorities for trial in southern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5907.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5918.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second the suspects were to be handed over to the Greek Cypriot authorities upon a decision by the United Nations, a task the United Nations refused.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5918.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5932.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third the suspects were to be put on trial at a neutral venue on the basis of an ad hoc agreement by an ad hoc tribunal comprising retired Turkish Cypriot judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5932.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5954.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What all these suggestions have in common is that the case file, including the incriminating evidence against the suspects, was not to be handed over to the Turkish Cypriot authorities or to Turkey because of the Greek Cypriot outright refusal to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5954.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5969.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Against this background it is difficult to see how without any new evidence the Turkish Cypriot authorities could lawfully have re-arrested and handed over the suspects to the Greek Cypriot authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5969.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5985.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any such arrest and surrender of the suspects for trial by an ad hoc tribunal would have been in breach of Article 5, Paragraph 1C, and Article 6, Paragraph 1 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5985.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6011.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The idea that the suspects could just have been arrested by Turkish Cypriot police, put in a police car, driven to the border, and handed over to the Greek Cypriot authorities in fulfillment of an alleged duty of cooperation reveals an utter disrespect for the rule of law and the rights of the suspects guaranteed by the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6011.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6019.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Members of the Court, on behalf of the Delegation of Turkey, I thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6019.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6025.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mr. Talmon and I thank all the parties for their submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6025.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6032.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I invite my colleagues, the judges of the Grand Chamber who wish to resort to put their questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6032.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6032.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I see Judge Sicilianos, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6037.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6039.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci, M. le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6040.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6043.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je voudrais poser une question aux requérants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6056.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6061.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je voudrais poser une question aux requérants et plus particulièrement à M. Riza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6062.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6070.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>M. Riza, vous avez présenté l'affaire comme un cas banal, quotidien, de coopération entre agents de police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6062.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6070.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You said, I'm quoting you in English, a trivial case of cooperation between police officers. Thats what you said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6079.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6081.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce que le transfert... Ma question, maintenant. Est-ce que le transfert...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6118.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6119.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pas de problème.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6120.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6127.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je disais, M. Riza, que vous avez présenté l'affaire comme un cas banal, comme un cas quotidien de coopération entre agents de police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6128.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6136.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous avez dit, en anglais, je vous cite: "This is a trivial case of cooperation between police officers." Et ma question est la suivante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6136.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6153.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce que le transfert d'un dossier judiciaire à une autre entité pour que celle-ci exerce son pouvoir de sanction pénale, un pouvoir souverain par excellence, peut être assimilé à un simple cas de coopération policière?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6153.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6153.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci M. le president.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6157.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6161.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup. Now, Judge Bošnjak, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Marko Bošnjak</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6163.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6166.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6166.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6180.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question essentially for the Turkish government, but of course both the Cypriot government and the representative of the applicants are welcome to comment as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6180.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6197.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both in their observations before the Grand Chamber and also today during the hearing, the Turkish government asserted that there was no valid request for extradition of the suspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6197.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6214.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the extradition request relied upon by the government of Cyprus, the government of Turkey claimed that there is no evidence of communication of that request through proper diplomatic channels.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6214.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6229.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the course of events in respect of that extradition request renders that request invalid in the eyes of the Turkish government, I would like to ask what would be a proper diplomatic channel under the circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6229.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6229.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6232.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6234.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6234.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6235.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Spano please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6237.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6238.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6238.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6248.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have one more question of clarification, which is prompted by an argument intimated by Mrs. Montgomery just now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6249.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6261.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is mainly to Mrs. Montgomery and also to the government of Turkey, Mr. Talmon, but I would invite Mr. Riza also to comment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6259.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6275.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In your pleadings, Mrs. Montgomery, you referred to the issue of Rasyon-i-Loki of Turkey and you mentioned that in your view, the jurisdictional link was clear, and I quote, based on the Markovitsch principles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6275.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6288.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Might I ask you to clarify, because that element I don't see from your written observations, I assume you're referring to the Grand Chamber judgment in Markovitsch and others versus Italy of 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6288.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6300.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Could you explain in your view how that case comes in to the equation of a possible recognition of jurisdiction by Turkey?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6300.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6302.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also invite Mr. Talmon,,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6302.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6310.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because Markovitsch and others is only referenced in footnote 45 of your written observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6310.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6313.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If I'm not incorrect, there is no further reference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6313.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6335.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Could you explain what bearing that case, and in particular, paragraphs 53 and 54 of the Grand Chamber judgment on the jurisdictional link, of course, mutatis mutandis, would have in this case, considering the fact that Turkey indeed, or the TRNC indeed, instituted an investigation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6335.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6342.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question arises, does that suffice to trigger the jurisdictional link under the Markovitsch principles?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6342.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6344.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would ask Mr. Riza if you have a view on this as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6344.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6346.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would be very useful, thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6346.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6349.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6349.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6364.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there are no further questions, the court will now withdraw for 20 minutes, following which the parties will be able to submit brief observations in reply to each other's submissions and reply to questions from the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6364.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6366.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6524.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6524.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6566.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6567.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6567.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6584.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed and I call Mr. Riza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6584.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6585.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you have the floor, Mr. Riza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6586.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6588.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, thank you, Mr President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6588.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6596.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I'll deal with, obviously, the judges' points first, and then these decisions made by the other sides, if I may.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6597.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6598.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6598.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6602.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You want to address first the questions of the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6604.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6606.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is that okay? Or do you want me to do it the other way around?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6606.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6608.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No, you are completely free Mr. Riza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6608.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6610.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You decide how to organize now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6609.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6618.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, I'm very grateful because I want to deal with, obviously, the judge's point, just in case I run out of time, and then deal with any other points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6618.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6640.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think the first point is to answer Judge Siciliano's point concerning the liaison between the two police forces in play in this case, and the question of why it is that that is recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6640.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6644.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My submission is as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6644.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6650.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Normally, as I understand the position, recognition is direct or indirect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6650.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6660.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Direct recognition is obviously when the relevant plenipotentiary of one country decides to recognize directly another state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6660.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6661.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's direct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6661.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6665.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The problem arises because of implied recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6665.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6669.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And implied recognition can arise in different sets of circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6669.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6697.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, because it is implied, what normally happens, as I understand it, I mean, I'm not a diplomat, so I don't really know, but as I understand it, what normally happens is that if there is non-recognition, then what happens is that a particular agent of the government says, well, look, I'm going to provide you with the evidence in this case because you need it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6697.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6700.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm referring to the facts of this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6700.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6707.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because you need it in order to arrest, detain, and hand over the suspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6707.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6717.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm only giving it to you for that purpose and that purpose alone, and on the strict understanding that it in no way amounts to recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6717.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6723.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That would have dealt with the problem in my submission immediately without any difficulty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6723.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6724.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's done that way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6724.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6736.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's, as I understand the position, where there is a serious question of recognition or lack of it, then it's made absolutely clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6736.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6747.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason why I made the submission, of course, is because police officers are not really engaged in the foreign relations or the diplomatic relations of their country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6747.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6755.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their job is to investigate crime, apprehend the criminals, and bring them to trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6755.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6758.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the role of the police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6758.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6775.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police in this case, in my submission, also knew or ought to have known that in Cyprus and Turkey, it had been decided that human rights considerations override any duty of recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6775.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6778.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I know Ms. Montgomery has made submissions and I'll come to them in due course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6778.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6781.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You've got them in the pleadings anyway.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6781.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6785.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the position is like this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6785.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6802.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There should have been a clear understanding between the police and the central government in the Republic that when it comes to human rights, questions of non-recognition are not in play.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6802.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6805.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's what the court decided in Cyprus and Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6805.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6810.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is what it decided in a case in which Cyprus was a party.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6810.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6814.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Montgomery says, well, actually it's individuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6814.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6816.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that's not right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6816.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6823.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of Cyprus and Turkey, it was an interstate case, and it was a case in which Cyprus won everything else.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6823.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6827.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It won, I think, on about maybe 25 points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6827.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6831.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It lost on one point only, on this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6831.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6841.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet the police in 2000, that was 2001, the police in 2005 were saying we're not prepared to deal on a fundamental question of recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6841.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6858.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In my submission, all they had to do, quite frankly, was to say to the Turkish Cypriot police via the UN if necessary, we are going to give you the evidence so as to enable you to arrest these murderers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6858.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6860.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But you give them to us.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6860.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6876.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should emphasize, you hand them over, I should emphasize it has never been our case, on the applicant's side, it has never been our case that the evidence would be handed over so that a trial would take place in the TRNC.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6876.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6878.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was not our case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6878.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6882.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope I've made it absolutely clear that that is not our case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6882.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6891.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our case was when the iron was hot, when the murdered people were still unburied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6891.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6894.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let us not forget that this is 2005.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6894.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6904.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2004, the Turkish Cypriot community was not interested in the independence of the Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6904.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6908.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had just voted to reunite Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6908.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6923.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the feeling there at the time, under I think, this of course is tradition, I'm asking you to take traditional notice of political facts, but the reality was that at the time the question of the TRNC was not foremost on anyone's agenda.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6923.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6937.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And consequently, in my submission, it would have been very easy for the Republic of Cyprus police to say to the UN and the TRNC, all right, we'll show you the evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6937.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6939.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was necessary for them to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6939.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6954.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I really do invite the court to consider this because the court has ruled time and time again that within the TRNC, the Human Rights Convention applies and it should be upheld.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6954.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6966.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the Turkish Cypriot police to have gone and arrested these men without evidence would have been a breach of Article 5.3 of the convention, I think, because it would have been done on</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6966.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6967.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>no reasonable grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6967.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6974.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was just the police in the TRNC going to their premises and arresting them and then handing them over.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6974.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6979.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, that would not have been convention compatible at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6979.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6994.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And consequently, for the Turkish Cypriot police to make a valid arrest and a valid handover, it was necessary for them to have reasonable evidence, some evidence in order to arrest and hand them over.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6994.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7012.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that in my submission, provided the Republic of Cyprus police made it clear in writing to the UN and to the TRNC that this does not mean recognition, then that would have not in any way flouted the non-recognition rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7012.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7016.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But beyond that, I think I should inform the court and ask you to take judicial notice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7016.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7019.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'll be contradicted if I'm wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7019.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7026.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But actually, there is a contact between the two law enforcement agencies in Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7026.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7036.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because for example, if it's a Greek Cypriot who escapes to the north of Cyprus, I think there is cooperation between them, and it does take place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7036.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7042.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it is a bit odd that in this case it didn't happen, even though it was a murder.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7042.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7053.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think it is the case that, so far as I know, there is quite a bit of crime across the dividing line, and the two sides do talk to one another.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7053.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7055.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They just didn't talk in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7055.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7061.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, it falls on the others to make submissions about how that is dealt with.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7061.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7066.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that, as I understand it, is the position in Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7066.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7088.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I deal with Judge Spano's point about the question of whether submitting—I think I'm putting it in English terminology, but I think it amounts to this, that when you submit to a jurisdiction, then the jurisdictional link is established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7088.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7111.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in the Markovic case, I think the authority is to the effect that whether or not there is any jurisdictional link, the fact is that when you do engage in an investigation of your own, then the link is established by dint of that investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7111.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7125.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I question, however, the wisdom of the Turkish, the TRNC, embarking on what was bound to be a futile exercise, because of course they didn't have the evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7125.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7130.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And not having the evidence, what's the point of engaging in an investigation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7130.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7146.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I know the court below has ruled that the investigation was fine, but actually it was an investigation that was bound to fail in Limini, because it could not really get off the ground, the evidence wasn't there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7146.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7154.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But may I therefore move to the next point, which is, well, where is the jurisdictional link?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7154.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7160.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think you've heard many submissions on behalf of Turkey that there is no jurisdictional link.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7160.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7161.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I do not understand that submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7161.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7170.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I must confess I do not understand it, because it's in the Treaty, the Treaty of Establishment of the Republic of Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7170.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7200.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does say, first of all, it guarantees the rights set out in the European Convention, and then it goes on in Article 10 to say, this is the Treaty of Establishment of the 1960 Treaty of Establishment of the Republic of Cyprus, it then goes on to say that if there's any dispute about any of the provisions, including the reference to the European Convention rights, then the answer is to engage through the diplomatic channel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7200.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7219.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So they've got to, Cyprus, or rather Turkey and Cyprus, and if anyone else was involved in the two, should have engaged in this case, according to Cypriot laws of establishment of the Republic, if there was any doubt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7219.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7250.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You can look, I don't want to take time now, but when you look at it, you see that in Article 5, it does say that all the rights of the Convention apply to Cyprus, and then in Article 10 it says if there's any dispute about the meaning or application of it, then what you do is that you engage in diplomatic negotiations to sort it out, and if not, you refer it to a body of judges presided over by a judge chosen by the President of the International Court of Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7250.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7256.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there was a mechanism, it's just that the political will to do anything in Cyprus was not there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7256.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7259.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's the problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7259.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7269.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the submissions made by Ms. Montgomery concerning the effect of the international</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7269.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7295.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>articles, I think, on wrongful acts, my submission is that those are, the commentary round that I read, says that they're subject to the exception in the Namibia case, and the Namibia case was actually considered and applied, the exception to it, and applied in Cyprus and Turkey and all the other cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7295.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7326.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So really, the submissions concerning the duty not to recognize have already, and I emphasize this, have already been dealt with by this court in a number of cases, and the distinctions drawn, or the attempt to distinguish those cases from the present is really not applicable here, because in our submission, there is no difference in principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7326.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7336.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no difference in principle between this case and all the other cases where human rights was held to override the duty not to recognize.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7336.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7350.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no difference in principle at all, because it is the fact that you are dealing with fundamental human rights that are use slogans, that they take such precedence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7350.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7360.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this, and I will end with this point, is made clear in Article 15.1 of the European</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7360.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7368.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Convention on Human Rights, because that article does not permit any derogation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7368.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7370.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'll end as I began.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7370.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7385.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does not permit any derogation, not only that, but it does mention international law in the text of Article 15.1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7385.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7413.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>51 does refer to international obligations, but it refers to international obligations in the context of making sure that although a state can derogate from some of the articles in the Convention, the ability to do so may be impeded further by international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7413.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7418.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So far from supporting the argument of the Republic of Cyprus, it undermines it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7418.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7433.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would ask you, please, I would invite you to look at the terminology right at the end of 15.1, where it does make reference to international law, but it does so in the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7433.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7441.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>opposite way, in support of the protection of human rights rather than derogation from them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7441.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7443.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is anything else, those are my submissions in the club.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7444.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7446.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Riza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7446.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7448.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mrs. Montgomery, please, on the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7450.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7451.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7451.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7456.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>may I address Judge Spano's question first in relation to Markovich?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7456.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7474.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do indeed suggest that there was sufficient jurisdiction, given the fact that Turkey, through TRNC, commenced criminal proceedings in this case and purported to arrest suspects and interrogate them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7474.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7496.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in those circumstances, the paragraphs to which Judge Spano's referred in paragraphs 53 and 54, the decision in Markovich recognizes that where proceedings are brought under the law of a state, then the rights of those who are party to those proceedings have to be recognized in accordance with the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7496.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7507.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so it is one of the ironies of the Turkish government's submissions that they've said no jurisdictional link to TRNC.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7507.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7519.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And yet in the same breath, the TRNC has said, oh, there is a sufficient jurisdictional link, and we require you to send the evidence so that we can try the suspects in TRNC.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7519.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7522.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That appears to be a contradictory position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7522.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7525.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the true position is indeed that there's jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7525.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7541.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But even if we were wrong on that, looking at the RANSEV position, this is not a case where we would submit its mere nationality or presence that engages Turkey's jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7541.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7544.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are two very special circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7544.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7558.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One is the fact that it is in unlawful occupation of the Republic of Cyprus's territory, and that occupation is itself preventing Cyprus exercising jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7558.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7573.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And secondly, in the case particularly of the Turkish nationals, it is known that even if a request for extradition were to be made, it would be refused on the ground of non-extradition of nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7573.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7581.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also known that there are Turkish nationals who are suspect, and therefore, according to Turkish law, can only be tried in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7581.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7587.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that would be a sufficient special circumstance within the context of RANSEV.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7587.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7598.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we're not arguing for the 47 members of the Council of Europe to be liable for non-cooperation in every offense where there are cross-border elements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7598.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7604.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But where there are the particular elements that are present here, we suggest that Turkey is liable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7604.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7618.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The alternative, as I said, is simply to create a land of outlaws and gangsters who can go freely to the TRNC and stay there without any risk of redress in complete impunity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7621.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7634.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should turn to deal with the second point that was raised by the government of Turkey, which was the suggestion that there were a limited number of practical steps, all of which would involve illegality on its part, that it could have taken.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7634.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7640.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, I can suggest one that it could have taken, which would be in conformity with international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7640.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7646.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It could withdraw from northern Cyprus without its troops on the Green Line.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7646.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7651.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Republic of Cyprus could simply resume jurisdiction over its territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7651.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7657.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the second suggestion, that it would be obviously unlawful, made by both Mr. Risa and Mr. Talman,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7657.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7668.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that it would have been obviously unlawful, according to domestic law, to put the suspects into a police car and take them to a court in southern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7668.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7685.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I remind the court that there was a warrant for arrest, which was a valid domestic instrument throughout the whole of the Republic of Cyprus, for the arrest of these suspects on the basis of substantial evidence implicating in the crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7685.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7693.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The suggestion there was something unlawful in the execution of that valid domestic process seems bizarre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7693.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7724.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But no doubt the court will take into account that the concern for the rule of law and the existence of respect for it is rather difficult to maintain on the part of the government of Turkey, where it continues unlawfully to prevent access for the police, the fire services, the officers of the Republic of Cyprus to maintain control over its citizens in the north.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7724.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7732.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, as I have already observed, the claim that somehow, as Mr. Reza says,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7732.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7751.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the frustration was caused by the absence of the file being available, I emphasize the file was provided to all the parties when the case was admitted by this court in 2009, and yet no steps have been taken in relation to any of the suspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7751.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7767.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn then to a point that arises as a result partly of the question asked by Judge Sicilianus, which is, was this really about police-to-police contact, as is suggested by the applicant?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7767.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7775.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the reality is, as is clear from the Turkish government's submissions, that more was required.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7775.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7796.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is plain from what Turkey has said, speaking as the mouthpiece for the TRNC as well as for Turkey itself, that it would not have responded to anything other than formal diplomatic contacts based upon existing treaty obligations, whether bilateral or multilateral.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7796.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7823.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So given that position, it really is ironic that we are also confronted with the submission that this case is not about recognition, because if we have to have treaty relations with TRNC, whatever that is, or with Turkey in order to ask for mutual legal assistance or for extradition, that is clearly and simply recognition of statehood.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7823.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7825.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It cannot be anything else.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7825.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7831.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the suggestion that state practice tells against us on that is just wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7831.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7841.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will no doubt have time to consider the state practice, particularly the English case of Akerke, which the Turkish government places great weight on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7841.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7853.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But if you read the judgment, as I have done, and I'm sure the court will, the English court was saying this is not about recognition, because it doesn't involve any treaty arrangement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7853.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7857.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it did, then it would violate the principle of non-recognition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7857.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7878.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So far from supporting the case for the government of Turkey that non-recognition isn't engaged here, non-recognition is directly engaged for as long as Turkey insists that it will not cooperate without a domestic and an international legal instrument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7878.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7886.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can deal very briefly, I hope, with the suggestion the principle of non-recognition is in some way internationally invalid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7886.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7906.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The International Law Commission's report on the responsibility, articles on the responsibility of states for internationally wrongful acts has not only been the subject of detailed study and final report, it has also been approved ad referendum on a number of occasions by the General Assembly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7906.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7911.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it represents the codified principles of international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7911.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7926.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as I've already said, in fact, in relation to the non-recognition of acts of aggression of illegal occupation, the position is in any event established by the general peremptory norms of international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7926.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7931.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the suggestion by Mr. Reeser most recently</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7931.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7939.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that in some way the Namibia principle nevertheless requires cooperation is completely wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7939.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7951.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the court will know, the Namibia principle is concerned only with acts which are essential to the welfare of the people whose land is unlawfully occupied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7951.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7959.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for example, recognition would have to be given under the Namibia principle to registrations, births, and deaths in Namibia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7959.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7977.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it would not extend so as to require Cyprus as a matter of obligation to enter into treaty arrangements with Turkey in order to exercise its own sovereign rights over its own territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7977.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7985.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that brings me back to the final point, which perhaps I need to address.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7985.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7991.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or perhaps I should mention first a point just recently made by Mr. Reeser, the suggestion</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7991.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8002.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that somehow the applicability of the rule of non-recognition was dealt with in Cyprus and Turkey in the decision of May 2001.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8002.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8020.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court needs to refer in that decision if it's to give any credence to that submission to paragraphs 234 to 238, which make it quite plain, as I made plain in our opening submissions, that that is relevant only to individual applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8020.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8030.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does not require a sovereign state to exhaust domestic remedies that are available in the north.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8030.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8034.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I return perhaps to a point that is central here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8034.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8051.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants had no right to obtain a conviction, or indeed no right to insist that an investigation ended with some concrete result, because the obligation is of means only and not of result.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8051.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8083.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But importantly, all the case law in this court emphasizes that where there are concrete constraints upon the means being effective, and here the most concrete of constraints is the presence of Turkey in the north of Cyprus, no state will be held liable in relation to its investigative obligations if it is those constraints that prevent the outcome that the applicant seeks, rather than the methods that have been used to seek it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8083.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8086.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So Mr. President, I think that is all</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8086.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8090.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I need to say by way of response, and I hope in answer to the questions that have been raised.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8092.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8094.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mrs. Montgomery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8094.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8096.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I call Mr. Talmon, please, to the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8098.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8101.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8101.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8106.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me start with the two questions addressed to Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8106.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8112.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I'll start with the question of Judge Bosniak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8112.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8120.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Bosniak asked how or what would a valid request for extradition look like.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8120.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8133.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we suggested in line with the case law of the International Court of Justice that such documents have to be transmitted through the ordinary diplomatic channel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8133.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8139.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in this case, this was not the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8139.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8149.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The file or the extradition request was handed to an usher at the Turkish embassy in Athens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8149.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8167.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As you probably all know, if you have ever tried to serve papers on a foreign government and you have tried to serve them on a foreign embassy and you try to hand them to someone at that embassy, they will normally be immediately returned because the usher is not competent to receive any papers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8170.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8189.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ordinary diplomatic channel in the present case was not available to the Greek Cypriot authorities for the simple reasons, not because of non-recognition, but because there are no diplomatic relations between Turkey and the Greek Cypriot authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8189.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8212.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the reason why Turkey adds a proviso to any convention under the auspices of the Council of Europe that treaty membership does not create or cannot create any legal obligations between Turkey and the Greek Cypriot authorities in southern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8212.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8228.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is, therefore, Turkey's submission that there was no valid transmission of the extradition request as requested, expressly requested, by the European Convention on Extradition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8228.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8241.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me move to the second question by Judge Spano concerning Markovic versus Italy and the jurisdictional link requirement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8241.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8254.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We used Markovic versus Italy in footnote 45 simply to support the proposition that there is a general jurisdictional link requirement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8254.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8267.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But having looked at the case, I would also like to distinguish the case of Markovic versus Italy from the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8267.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8288.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we have argued, the content, the extent of the duty to cooperate is defined by a state's international legal obligations and rights under existing international instruments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8288.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8303.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A purely voluntary investigation cannot trigger the obligations under Article 2, under the procedural limb of Article 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8303.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8314.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And even if it did, it would trigger the obligation to investigate in accordance with the case law of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8314.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8320.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would not necessarily trigger an additional obligation to cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8320.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8329.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Voluntary investigation cannot give rise to obligatory cooperation in Turkey's view.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8332.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8360.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the one case where there was an obligation to investigate, Aliyev versus Azerbaijan, and we have dealt with that case at paragraphs 37 to 38 of our memorial, the duty to investigate was based on the Minsk Agreement, an international binding treaty between the two states concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8363.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8368.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having looked at Markovic versus Italy, I would also like to distinguish this case further.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8368.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8377.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That case concerned the NATO bombing campaign in Serbia and subsequent judicial proceedings in Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8377.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8400.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What the court said in this case was that if there is a right to institute legal proceedings under domestic law, here Italian law, these judicial proceedings must be in compliance with the convention under Article 6.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8400.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8409.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court did not rule on the question of competence razione loci with regard to the bombing campaign, which happened in Serbia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8409.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8412.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was a purely internal matter in Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8412.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8417.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once under the Italian laws, there was a right to judicial proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8417.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8422.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then these judicial proceedings had to be conducted in line with Article 6.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8426.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8436.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me also respond to what the other respondent in this case said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8436.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8451.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case of Cyprus is unique because parts of the territory of Cyprus are under the control, the effective control, of another state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8451.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8461.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I may remind the court of the situations in Georgia, where Abkhazia and South Ossetia are under the control of another state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8461.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8472.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I may remind the court of Azerbaijan, where parts of that state, Nagorno-Karabakh, is under the control of another state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8472.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8476.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or I may remind the court of Moldova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8476.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8482.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Parts of Moldova, Transnistria, are under the control of another state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8485.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8512.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Ilashko and others versus Moldova and Russia, this court did not follow the applicant's submissions that the measures of judicial cooperation between the Moldovan government and the authorities of the unrecognized Transnistrian authorities amounted to de facto recognition of the Tiraspol regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8512.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8526.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I remind you that the only reason why there is the Tiraspol regime is the 6th Russian army that is still stationed in that part of Moldova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8526.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8549.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The measures of judicial cooperation in that case included requests for cooperation, the transmission of documents which were sent by the Moldovan government to the public prosecutor of Transnistria, more or less de facto relations between the Moldovan and Transnistrian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8549.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8556.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Moldovan Ministry of Justice was in constant contact with the Transnistrian Ministry of Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8556.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8563.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were unofficial relations between the Moldovan and Transnistrian authorities on judicial matters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8563.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8577.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the Moldovan prosecutors or officers investigating criminal cases often rang their colleagues in Transnistria, particularly to obtain evidence and to summon witnesses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8577.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8590.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This may all be found in paragraphs 177, paragraph 225, and paragraph 345.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8590.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8600.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court in that case found that these acts, and I quote, cannot be regarded as support for the Transnistrian regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8600.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8603.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me move to my next point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8603.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8614.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to what we have heard from Ms. Montgomery,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8614.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8624.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Greek Cypriot authorities are the only authorities that are entitled to exercise jurisdiction over crimes committed in southern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8624.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8639.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think this argument shows some confusion with regard to criminal jurisdiction under international law and jurisdiction in terms of Article 1 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8642.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8653.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We must distinguish between criminal jurisdiction, that is, the competence of a state to enforce a state's jurisdiction, and the competence of a state to enforce a state's jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8653.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8660.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Competence of a state to prescribe and enforce criminal law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8660.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8675.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the jurisdiction under Article 1 of the Convention that defines the personal, territorial, and temporal scope of the obligations under the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8675.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8685.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jurisdiction in both cases, criminal jurisdiction and jurisdiction under Article 1, is not limited to territorial jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8685.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8692.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The basis of criminal jurisdiction are determined by general international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8692.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8703.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The territoriality principle is just one of several bases for the lawful exercise of jurisdiction under international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8703.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8722.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And here I am very grateful to Judge Spano redirecting us to Markovic versus Italy, because there the court at paragraph 49 said, international law does not exclude a state's exercise of jurisdiction extraterritorially.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8722.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8734.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The suggested basis of such jurisdiction, including nationality, effect, protection, passive personality, and universality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8734.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8758.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is Turkey's submission that both Turkey and the TRNC can exercise extraterritorial criminal jurisdiction over their nationals committing crimes outside their territory, including in southern Cyprus, on the basis of the nationality principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8758.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8767.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The United Kingdom has accepted that the TRNC can exercise extraterritorial criminal jurisdiction over its nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8767.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8779.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it transferred TRNC nationals who had committed crimes in the United Kingdom back to the TRNC for trial in the TRNC courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8782.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8792.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, I would like to remind the court that six of the suspects in the present case are TRNC nationals, two are Turkish nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8792.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8822.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there were no extraterritorial criminal jurisdiction on the basis of the nationality principle, all crimes committed by Turkish Cypriot citizens outside northern Cyprus would have to go unpunished because, according to the other respondent, the TRNC cannot exercise extraterritorial criminal jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8822.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8834.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court, of course, itself has accepted the exercise of extraterritorial criminal jurisdiction by the TRNC.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8834.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8841.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I may remind the court of the case of Manson versus United Kingdom that is referenced in our memorial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8841.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8850.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case concerned the murder of a British national committed by a Turkish Cypriot national in the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8850.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8858.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The perpetrator fled to northern Cyprus and was tried in northern Cyprus by the TRNC courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8858.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8874.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court found that the United Kingdom had discharged its obligation under Article II to investigate by achieving a conviction of the perpetrator in northern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8874.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8883.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wonder how the court could have reached that conclusion if the courts in northern Cyprus had had no criminal jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8883.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8891.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The other case I want to refer the court to is Isaac and others versus Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8891.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8916.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case concerned the killing of a Greek Cypriot national by Turkish Cypriot policemen in the neutral UN buffer zone in Cyprus, which, according to the court's case law in Stevens versus Cyprus, Turkey, and the United Nations, is not under the control of either Turkey or the Turkish Cypriot authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8916.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8929.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Extraterritorial jurisdiction in terms of Article I of the convention in that case was based on state agent authority and control over the person killed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8929.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8936.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Criminal jurisdiction in that case was based on the nationality principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8936.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8951.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of Isaac and Turkey, the court found a violation by Turkey because Turkey had not investigated the killing by using criminal law remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8951.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8953.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Criminal law remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8953.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8969.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because those responsible for the killing had not been arraigned before a domestic tribunal in northern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8969.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8975.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me move on to another argument by the other respondent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8975.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8985.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the other respondent, the obligation to cooperate bears on third states only, not on the state of primary jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8985.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9000.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The other respondent argued there is no duty of cooperation on the state with the primary obligation beyond taking the steps reasonably necessary to progress its own investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9000.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9007.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in the case of Cyprus, the duty of cooperation is purely a one-way street.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9007.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9012.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Everybody has to cooperate with Cyprus with regard to crimes in southern Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9012.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9015.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But Cyprus is not a one-way street.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9015.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9019.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cyprus does not have to cooperate with anybody else.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9023.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9034.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At best, if Cyprus would consider that there was any need for cooperation, it would be at Cyprus's discretion, we were told.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9034.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9038.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is contrary to any principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9038.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9050.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The obligation to investigate and the obligation to cooperate are both obligations under the procedural limb of Article 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9050.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9059.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The procedural limb and the substantive limb are two aspects of the obligation to secure the right to life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9059.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9071.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The high contracting party that has an obligation to secure the right to life has that obligation both substantively and procedurally.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9071.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9079.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if it has that obligation procedurally, it has an obligation both to investigate and to cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9079.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9103.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course, there is, again, no better authority for this view than Judge Sergides, who wrote in his partly dissenting opinion at paragraph 45, I quote, the obligation to cooperate could be considered as a specific aspect of the obligation to investigate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9103.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9109.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there is no obligation to investigate without there also being an obligation to cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9117.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9120.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Talmon, may I ask you to conclude, please?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9120.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9120.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9121.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9129.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me conclude, Mr. President, on a sober and on a funny note.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9129.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9132.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me start with a sober note.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9132.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9136.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When Ms. Moscone-Marie started her speech this morning,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9136.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9144.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I was rather puzzled because I thought I am in a court of law, not in the political arena.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9144.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9151.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We heard about state aggression, invasion, and occupation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9151.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9161.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The situation in Cyprus is much more complicated than the one-sided views put forward by the Greek Cypriot authorities this morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9161.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9180.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I may just state here for the record that neither the United Nations nor any other international organization has ever referred to the situation in Cyprus as state aggression, as an invasion, or as occupation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9184.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9188.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me move to my funny note.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9188.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9203.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Counsel for the applicants said this morning, imagine what would happen if we had this little girl that was in a fire and the two fire brigades would have to cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9203.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9208.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Would that be really hindered by non-recognition?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9208.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9210.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And he said, this cannot be the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9210.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9214.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there is a fire, people must cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9214.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9223.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I may just state for the record that there is a technical committee between the two sides in Cyprus concerning fire brigades.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9223.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9248.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In discussions in this committee, the Greek Cypriot authorities have insisted that if Turkish Cypriot fire brigades should ever come to the southern part of Cyprus to help extinguish a fire, they have to cover the emblems on the fire engines so that there is no recognition involved in extinguishing the fire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9248.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9248.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9252.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9254.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9254.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9258.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9258.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9264.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their submissions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9264.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9268.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9268.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9271.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9271.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9275.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9275.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9276.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
