<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>3859010_01042015</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>14.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>14.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>67.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>74.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Biao against Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>74.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>81.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on the 12th of July 2010 under Article 34 of the Convention by Mr. Ousmane</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>81.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>88.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Biao, a Danish national, and his wife, Miss Asia Adamo Biao, a Ghana national.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>88.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>97.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the second section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1, of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>97.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>114.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 25th of March 2014, a chamber of that section declared the application admissible and delivered a judgment in which it held that there had been no violation of Article 8 of the Convention and no violation of Article 14 in conjunction with Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>114.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>132.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 24th of June 2014, the applicants requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention, and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on the 8th of September 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>132.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>145.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 5th of December 2014, the president of the Grand Chamber granted leave to the Air Center to submit written comments as a third party by virtue of Rule 44, Paragraph 3 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>145.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>150.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government, represented by their agent, Mr. Jonas</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>150.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>158.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bering Liisberg of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, assisted by their co-agent, Mrs. Nina Holst-Christensen,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>158.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>163.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and by Mr. Kim Lunding, Mr. Anders Herping Nielsen,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>163.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>168.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Martin Bang, and Mrs. Maria Aviaja Sander Holm, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>168.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>172.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mr. Steen Petersen,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>172.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>178.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>counsel assisted by Mr. Niels-Erik Hansen and Mr. Henrik Karl</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>178.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>180.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nielsen, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>180.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>184.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>184.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>197.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to welcome a delegation of judges and prosecutors from the European Judicial Training Network and a group of Bulgarian judges who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>197.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>207.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>207.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>211.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Peterson for the applicants will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>211.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>215.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mr. Bering Liisberg for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>215.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>217.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Petersen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>221.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>223.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>223.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>239.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I appear before the court on behalf of both the applicants and argue that the rights of the applicants under Article 14, taken in conjunction with Article 8, as well as the European Convention on Nationality, Article 5.2, have been interfered with,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>239.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>266.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that interference is not justified under Article 8, paragraph 2, the interference is not proportionate, not sufficiently to pursue a legitimate aim, that Denmark cannot lawfully treat its citizens differently solely on the basis of how and when they have acquired their citizenship, that a difference in treatment of Danish nationals is to a decisive extent based on the applicant's race and or ethnic origin and not on other status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>266.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>269.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That Mr. Bjau's acquisition of citizenship later in life,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>269.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>284.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>2002, meant that he, after living in Denmark for nine years at the age of 31, still was treated differently than indirectly on his and his spouse's race and or ethnic origin and not on other status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>284.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>307.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That the government's specific aim with the introduction of the 28 years rule, as per 1st of January 2004, was to single out and solely help Danish native expatriates who, after introduction of the attachment rule in 2003, had experienced great difficulties when they wanted to return and to settle in Denmark with their foreign family in their third age.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>307.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>323.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That the 28 years rule is excessively strict, that is not evident nor proved that the strength of one's ties continuously and significantly increases after, for example, 10, 15, 26, or 28 years in a country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>323.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>339.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That the 28 years rule exempt an unknown number of Danish native expatriates, whether or not they have lived in Denmark and whether or not they have retained strong ties with Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>339.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>345.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That the interference do not completely fall within the state's marking of appreciation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>345.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>358.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That any marking of appreciation in a case like this is not very wide because respect of family life and family reunion are core values and aspects of particular important human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>358.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>365.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That it is indisputable that direct and indirect discrimination has occurred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>365.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>375.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, I argue that the rights of the applicants under Article 6, 13, and 41 also have been interfered with since 2003 as to the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>375.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>378.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The responsibility of Denmark has been engaged.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>378.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>392.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the applicants should be awarded just compensation for non-pecuniary damage in the form of anxiety, stress, frustration, and damage under respect of the applicant's family life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>392.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>405.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The just compensation should be awarded to according to Article 6, 13, and 41 based alone on the unreasonable long time this particularly important case has lasted since 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>405.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>421.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The amounts awarded to the applicants should be totally €44,000 or €48,000 or at least €36,000 according to the court's decision in Sulu, Cocchierelle, and Pisati v.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>421.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>426.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Italy, judgments of 10th November 2004, paragraph 26.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>426.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>431.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I come back to the amounts later in my speech.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>431.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>443.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if the court do not find violations of Article 14 taken in conjunction with Article 8, the court should award the set amount based on Article 6, 13, and 41.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>443.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>449.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I refer to the leading case, Spångarenlundråd, Sweden, 1982.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>449.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>455.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the applicants dispute that the 30-years-old Abdulaziz v.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>455.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>470.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>United Kingdom is fully comparable with this case, apart from the fact that the former commission found serious violations of Article 14 taken in conjunction with Article 8 based on racial discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>470.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>486.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's unclear on what basis the court in 1985 did not reach the same conclusion as the commission as the purpose to limit immigrants' access to the English labor market was to lower the number of colored immigrants from India and Pakistan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>486.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>497.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants fully agree with the reasoning in the minority report in the Danish Supreme Court in 2010 and the minority opinion in the Biao case last year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>497.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>506.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the applicants agree with the minority's serious critique in the Biao case last year, paragraphs 99 to 102.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>506.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>517.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is noteworthy that the Danish judge, Per Luransen, is one of the very critical judges in the majority opinion, together with Paul Lemmens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>517.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>522.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I emphasize that as per 2004, Denmark had approximately 8.2</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>522.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>529.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>percent of immigrants and their descendants out of a population of roughly 5.3 million.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>529.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>534.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the applicants are indisputably in a minority group in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>534.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>544.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, these figures cannot explain the government's fears in 2000 to 2003 of a severe risk of Denmark being flooded with immigrants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>544.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>550.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It seems unlikely that the sheer number, 8.2 percent out of 5.3 million of immigrants,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>550.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>555.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is solely responsible for the new restrictive measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>555.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>580.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the uncertain and insufficient statistics produced by the government first in 2015, I refer to the statement of 15 of January 2015, page 17, and exhibit 2, does not explain the full story nor give the court or the applicants a real and valuable insight into the state's real motives for excessively tightening the Illin Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>580.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>593.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I dispute that the government should not be able to answer completely all of the court's relevant questions so the court and the applicants at last could obtain a true and fair picture of all the issues at hand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>593.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>602.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also dispute that the government is not allowed to identify cases and persons in a true and fair view because of prohibitions in Danish legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>602.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>606.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See page 18 in the said statement from the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>606.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>623.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The figures, however, shows in the statement, page 19 and exhibit 2, that other aliens is a very tiny, little figure compared to refugees and Danish Nordic nationals for a period 1st of January 2004 to ultimo 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>623.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>633.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, I argue that the statistics is not sufficient, they are not detailed enough, and not in favor of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>633.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>657.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the High Court judgment of September 2002, sorry 2007, the applicants and the government have agreed that in spite of the neutral and stereotype wording of the Illin Act, section 9, subsection 7, in practice, indirect discrimination is created, especially for non-Danes coming from primarily non-Western countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>657.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>663.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the High Court's reasoning in the Biao judgment, page 21.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>663.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>682.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties agree that the facts fall within the ambit of article 14 and 8, so the dispute is, was this discrimination justifiable, proportionate, and pursue a legitimate aim, and does it fall exclusively within the scope of Denmark's marking of appreciation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>682.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>701.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the statistical and factual background, I dispute that the applicants are to blame for anything, and for not fully understanding the very complex, unclear, and unforeseeable Illin Act, with over 100 amendments since 1983.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>701.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>708.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Various insufficient and misinformative public websites has been the case, too.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>708.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>720.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the exhibits from the applicants, the websites criticized by the Danish ombudsman in 2005 and 2008.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>720.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>734.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Compared to the Abdelaziz case, paragraph 38 statistics, the court can see here that the English government in fact was able to produce detailed and valid statistics as opposed to the government in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>734.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>749.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I dispute also that the Danish alien authorities do not have an exoficient duty to guide and advise the applicants, particularly when the relevant law and other rules are so complex, so unclear, and so unforeseeable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>749.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>766.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ombudsman in the exhibits in the file criticized the lack of sufficient guidance from the alien authorities, and he had to tell the alien authorities back in 2003 how to do things correctly and inform correctly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>766.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>777.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is in this light the court has to read Exhibit 1, the revised memo of the government of 1 December 2005.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>777.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>782.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I emphasize that this memorandum is not part of the Alien Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>782.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>793.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government in its statement totally omits to tell the court about the real background of this Exhibit 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>793.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>806.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The alien authorities did not have enough or any attention paid to the EU law and Luxembourg court's judgment, among others the very important Metox judgment I refer to the court's letter of 6 March this year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>806.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>824.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if the applicants could and still cannot even trust the correctness of all published and relevant information from the alien authorities, and these authorities quote, forget, unquote, to publish in due time relevant and vital information, I ask the court who is to blame in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>824.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>829.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My answer is not the applicants for sure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>829.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>836.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to my written letter of March 10th this year concerning the three questions from the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>836.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>842.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I won't repeat them, but I'm very much looking forward to hear the answers from the government today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>842.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>855.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it really is true that the applicants coming from Togo and Ghana in reality by the alien authorities should have been granted family reunification in 2005, the government has acted very irresponsible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>855.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>860.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same goes for the situation described in the court's letter of 6 March, question 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>860.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>876.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The main casualties were after 2008 a lot of years or at least a lot of time to realize and implement the consequences of Metox and other very important judgment from Luxembourg in their administrative practice and on the website New in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>876.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>890.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Probably Denmark is likely to be responsible for the applicants' losses because of the maladministration, misinformation, omissions, and a total lack of timely correct guidance and advice to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>890.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>897.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I remind the court of that the Convention with Protocols and Dynamic U.S. Prudence was incorporated by law in Denmark</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>897.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>900.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as of 1 July 1992.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>900.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>916.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The convention seems to have an almost crazy constitutional character in Denmark, and this court has several times emphasized that a convention is a living instrument which has to be interpreted in the present day condition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>916.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>921.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to Tyre v. United Kingdom, 1978, paragraph 31,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>921.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>926.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Marx v. Begum, 99, paragraph 41, and Lucido v. Turkey,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>926.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>929.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>1998, paragraph 71.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>929.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>939.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The convention is intended to guarantee not rights that are theoretical or illusory, but rights that are practical and effective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>939.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>945.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to Arry v. Ireland, 1979, paragraph 24.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>945.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>952.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The condition imposed for the exercise of a human right must not impair their very essence and deprive them of their effectiveness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>952.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>959.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See Mathieu Mohin v. Begum, 1987, paragraph 52.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>959.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>973.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because the interpretation of the convention is particularly concerned with substance, not form, the courts may need to look behind the appearances and investigate the realities of the procedure in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>973.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>988.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither the Danish court in 2007 nor the Supreme Court in 2010, in the applicant's opinion, looked sufficiently and sort of enough behind the Alien Act's formal appearance and into the complete realities in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>988.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>999.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The High Court finding that the indirect discrimination occurred in practice stated that the High Court finds no sufficient basis for holding that your refusal was not valid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>999.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1002.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Look at the words, no sufficient basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1002.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1020.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, perhaps with more detailed information and complete statistics from the Danish Alien Assortatives, as to the substance and to the effect of the Alien Act, the result in the High Court in 2007 and Supreme Court in 2010 might have been finding in favor for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1020.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1028.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a fact that the government is unable to answer how many Danish expatriates benefited from the 28-years rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1028.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1029.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's a fact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1029.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1031.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't know anything about it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1031.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1032.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't know the number.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1032.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1034.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't know anything.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1034.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1050.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government's reasoning in its statement this year with Exhibits 1 and 2, neither is very convincing, nor live up to the quality, the details, and the far more useful statistics we saw in Abdulaziz, paragraph 38.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1050.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1059.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the burden of proof lies on the government's table, I urge this court to dismiss the unuseful and irrelevant statistics as valid evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1059.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1079.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if this court does not review the system of the domestic in abstracto, the court have to determine now whether the manner in which the Danish Alien Act system in Denmark was applied to or affected, the applicants give rise to any violations of convention rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1079.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1082.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's crucial for this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1082.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1089.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A banner must ensure the fair and proper treatment of minorities and avoid the abuse of a dominant position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1089.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1096.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I remind you of the applicants' vulnerable situation in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1096.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1117.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since Denmark in 1983 got its first Alien Act, at that time one of the most liberal laws in the world, amendment acts have been made over 100 times, and the immigration and family unification policies have been cited, primarily backed by the Danish People's Party, whose support has been needed, whoever was in government, to stay in power.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1117.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1124.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This right-wing People's Party has become well known for its strong and provoking anti-immigration ideas and policies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1124.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1135.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In a newspaper information on 8th of November 2010, the party's spokesman, Martin Henriksen, said, we have for years said that it's quite all right to discriminate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1135.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1136.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is okay with us.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1136.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1144.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is to a large extent the Muslim immigration we want to stop.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1144.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1157.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I urge this court to look very softly behind the appearances and look into the intense and human rights violations that are the consequences for the applicants of the Danish Alien Act and the 28 years rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1157.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1166.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can refer to my statement of 14th of December 2012 to this court where things are elaborated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1166.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1176.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in practice, the applicants are placed in a significant poor situation as opposed to Danish natives and Danish expatriates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1176.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1178.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why this difference?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1178.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1185.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants have no possibility of being born in Denmark and being citizens from birth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1185.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1198.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In a way, if you look at the rule, you can see that apart from many other demands, it is almost illusory to obtain family reunion in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1198.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1205.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the court's Biaudjustment, paragraph 90 and 99 to 102 and the dissenting opinion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1205.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1215.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The mechanical rules in the Alien Act, section 9, for calculating in which country a couple has lived longest affects especially immigrants from non-Western countries and their descendants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1215.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1219.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is Mr. Biaudjustment coming from Togo and Mrs. Biaudjustment</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1219.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1221.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>coming from Ghana.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1221.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1235.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Among a lot of international critiques, the Swedish government, the Danish rules have also been attacked by the United States and Thai Commission for Refugees and the Council of Europe Human Rights Commissioner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1235.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1239.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One thing is crucial in this thing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1239.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1256.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Act 1204 of 27th of June 2003, which amended the 28-year rule as of 1st of January, it lacks for a special group of Danish natives this attachment requirement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1256.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1278.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason, well, we can't see any proof or evidence, but if you look in the preparatory work, you can see that one assumed that the Danish living abroad, say in Brazil, in Ghana, in Togo, in China, in Taiwan, et cetera, he probably spoke Danish with his foreign wife.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1278.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1283.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He probably read Danish books, saw Danish television, and everything else.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1283.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1287.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I ask this court, why was Mr. Biaudjustment not given the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1287.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1289.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>same opportunity?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1289.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1293.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Biaudjustment fulfilled the Danish conditions to be a</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1293.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1294.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Danish citizen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1294.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1305.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the file, circular number 90 of 6th of June, 1999, very tough rules, after residing in Denmark for nine years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1305.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1325.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why wasn't he given the same opportunity if a Dane with Danish extraction was assumed to speak and talk and read English with his foreign spouse and then return in his third age with the foreign spouse without fulfilling the attachment requirement?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1325.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1327.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We can see nothing about that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1327.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1331.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is assumed that that's what you do.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1331.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1341.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the file where I produced a resume of the website Danish Worldwide.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1341.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1347.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court can see in this that there's about 250,000 Danish abroad.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1347.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1353.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you can see from the file, too, that they are very keen on commenting on the 28 years rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1353.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1368.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the reason why the rule was amended was, in fact, by enormous political pressure from this group and others abroad to the Danish Minister of Refugees, Mr. Bertel Horda.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1368.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1377.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants do not have the same possibilities to make such a pressure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1377.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1394.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think also it's important to emphasize that before 1st of January, 2004, before the introduction of the 28 years rule, there was no possibility for discriminating between Danish citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1394.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1408.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The attachment requirement as before 1st of January would apply to all Danish nationals, whether or not the date was a foreign extraction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1408.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1414.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the trouble and why we are standing here today is you exempt a special group.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1414.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1423.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think even if you exempt a special group because you say you assume they have long and strong ties to Denmark, it has not been proven.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1423.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1425.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have no statistics.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1425.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1437.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have no answers to how many Danish people of Danish extraction benefited from this rule and how many people, Danish citizens of foreign extraction, benefited from this rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1437.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1443.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't know.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1443.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1455.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The contemporary European standards and the US prudence of this court is extremely concerned about indirect discrimination based on the ground of race and or ethnic origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1455.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1460.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See the judgment last year, paragraph 23.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1460.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1472.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the three dissenting judges did not claim that the 28 year rule resulted in the kind of racist or ethnic discrimination that we saw in Abdullah's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1472.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1486.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I urge the court not to turn the blind eye to the obvious discriminatory character of the 28 year rule of Danish alien legislation, thus applied would not contribute to implementing justice under the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1486.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1493.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the dissenting opinion, paragraph 24.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1493.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1501.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think that the convention was not meant to deprive the applicants and their soon 11 year old son the right to pursue happiness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1501.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1505.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The dissenting opinion, paragraph 33.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1505.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1518.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One can see from the protocol 12 to the convention that out of 47 member states, 18 states have ratified as per 2011, this protocol.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1518.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1524.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It may indicate a new and growing consensus in Europe concerning a general prohibition on discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1524.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1540.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The European Commission against Racism and Intolerance recommended in its monitoring report on Denmark, 22nd of May 2012, that the 28 year rule risk disproportionately affecting non-ethnic Danes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1540.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1560.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the committee urged the Danish authorities to carry out a wide ranging reform of the spousal reunification rules in order to remove any elements which amount to direct or indirect discrimination and or which are disproportionate to their stated aim, they say.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1560.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1576.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was not the first time they said it, because on page 36 in the same report, you can see in a survey report from 2006, they urged the Danish authorities not to adopt laws which in effect indirectly discriminate against minority groups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1576.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1579.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think that's a case for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1579.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1583.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are from Africa, from non-Western countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1583.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1587.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And even if Mr. Biau has fulfilled all requirements to</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1587.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1595.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>being a Danish citizen, and he should be equal with all other Danes, he is treated differently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1595.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1598.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How should he integrate his wife?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1598.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1599.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are living in Sweden.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1599.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1604.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were forced to move to Sweden when the refusal came in 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1604.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1607.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But from that moment, Mrs. Biau was not allowed to stay or work</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1607.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1609.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1609.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1616.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She is staying and working in Denmark every day, pays his tax, security and everything.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1616.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1624.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But how should he integrate his wife when he's staying in Denmark, traveling between Malmö and Copenhagen every day?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1624.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1633.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And compared to the Danish native expatriate abroad, he's supposed to talk and walk Danish, read and everything.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1633.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1640.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then he can return when he wants in his third age without fulfilling the requirement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1640.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1644.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is, in practice, a very severe effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1644.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1646.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think it's not justifiable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1646.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1647.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not proportionate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1647.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1654.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think that the Alien Act has another unintended consequence apart from the 28-year rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1654.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1659.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is the case we're standing with here today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1659.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1665.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Family reunion is a very important aspect of family life in the context of one's citizenship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1665.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1671.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the judgment of Biau, paragraph 7.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1671.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1680.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the applicants dispute the steps this court took last year to dismiss their claim on indirect ethnic discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1680.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1693.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's very unclear how the court, without saying explicitly, come to the conclusion that this is a case of direct difference in treatment, the discrimination being other status, namely links of citizenship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1693.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1697.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reasoning is hardly motivated and thus difficult to follow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1697.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1703.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See paragraph 90 of the court's judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1703.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1713.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court's mentioning of the Abdulaziz case is not sufficient to describe what is racial discrimination and what is not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1713.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1718.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's exactly one of the points where Abdulaziz is outdated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1718.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1725.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The 30-year-old Abdulaziz judgment provides no guidance anymore what should count as racial discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1725.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1737.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, it's very disturbing in a general context that both the majority in the Danish Supreme Court and the majority last year pay so much attention to this interpretation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1737.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1739.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think it's not an interpretation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1739.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1749.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You can call a convention a living instrument which has to be interpreted in the present day conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1749.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1759.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, I think that the result last year goes against the purpose of the conventions, Article 1, and the contemporary jurisprudence of this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1759.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1762.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court must never lose sight of the general context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1762.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1763.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Never.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1763.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1769.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So now is the time for a more authoritative and clarifying judgment in the grand chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1769.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1780.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has, for the first time, in the Nakova versus Bulgaria 2004, held a state accountable for racial discrimination in a chamber judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1785.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1804.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the majority in this court's judgment, as well as the 10 national Danish judges in the applicant's opinion, failed to apply indirect discrimination principles in the applicant's case and failed to recognize the context of the treatment which reinforced negative stereotypes regarding integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1804.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1811.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They should have applied the principles in the court's judgment of DH versus Czech Republic as such.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1811.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1829.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this judgment, DH, paragraph 175, the court states, a general policy or measure that has disproportionately critical effects on a particular group may be considered discriminatory notwithstanding that it's not specifically aimed at that group.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1829.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1837.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that discrimination, potentially contrary to the convention, may result from a de facto situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1837.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1848.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, the court states, indeed, in certain circumstances, a failure to attempt to correct inequality through different treatment may, in itself, give rise to a breach of the article.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1848.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1850.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think that is very important.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1854.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1876.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, we know that the Danish government intended to single out, as per 1st of January 2004, Danish expatriates like a class of first citizens, resulting in that the applicants, in fact, became a class of second class.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1876.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1887.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, I could refer to the old case, East African Asians versus United Kingdom from ages three, where you had the same problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1887.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1892.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The arguments for exempting the first class Danish expats is not very convincing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1892.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1894.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The proof is missing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1894.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1906.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think that the government has not provided any objective justification for this disparate, disadvantageous treatment of a minor group of Danish citizens, naturalized citizens, the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1906.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1918.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There should have been far more weighty reasons, especially given the rather narrow margin of appreciation states have in family reunion matters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1918.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1927.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the Biao case dissenting opinion, paragraphs 15 and 33.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1927.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1946.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The majority last year surprisingly agreed with the European Commission for Human Rights, saying that this exemption places undue restrictions on naturalized Danish citizens and places them in a considerable disadvantageous in comparison to Danish native citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1946.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1952.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's a bit surprising last year, because you see in the majority that you go a bit of the way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1952.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1962.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You conclude that it's not for the court to evaluate the legislation in abstracto, but you criticize this rule as excessively strict.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1962.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1967.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You state that the applicants are placed in a significant poor situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1967.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1973.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you go the third step and say, well, in fact, it's almost illusory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1973.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1983.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How can we imagine to get a family reunion in Denmark if you are a third country wife coming from non-African countries?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1983.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1988.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think the court has taken some steps.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1988.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1997.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But then they, of course, stop up and say, well, we can't go further, but why then raise the critique in the majority?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1997.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2001.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I ask the court to look into that, too.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2001.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2018.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I dispute the government's arguments in the written statement of 15 of January, especially the pages 7 to 8, 12, 13 to 14, and 16, as to the possibilities for the applicants to obtain family reunion earlier than 28 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2018.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2020.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's no proof of that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2020.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2026.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think I've had the case since the high court in Denmark in 2007.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2026.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2030.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is the first time I hear about that in the arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2030.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2038.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The arguments we hear for this court, I think, they haven't been argued in the court cases in the high court and the Danish Supreme Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2038.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2040.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And where is the proof?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2040.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2052.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another aspect, they say, well, if you have been in Denmark for about 12 years, you normally could reunite successfully or at an earlier stage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2052.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2054.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's no proof of that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2064.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2067.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Petersen, may I ask you to conclude?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2067.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2068.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, of course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2067.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2070.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, of course, I was just doing that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2070.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2087.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My concluding remarks is that, as I started out with the headlines I started with, that there is a violation of Article 14, taken in conjunction with Article 8, and the Convention on Nationality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2087.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2096.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's no justifiable reasons for treating a naturalized Danish citizens the way we have seen in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2096.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2113.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I also think that the Alien Act, well, indirectly have some racial or ethnic motives, because all that are hampered or barred from having family reunion is, of course, the people from non-Western countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2113.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2126.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I ask this court to look very thoroughly into the appearance of this Alien Act, because the applicants is a particular one in a situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2126.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2133.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are still facing the risk of remaining in Sweden as a divided family, or risk another refusal of family reunion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2133.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2144.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in fact, at latest in 2030, perhaps after 28 years, they have perhaps a success, a possibility to get family reunion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2144.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2149.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think that is not worthy in a member state of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2149.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2151.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this case is about substance, not form.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2151.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2151.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2154.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2156.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Petersen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2156.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2158.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I Call Mr. Bering Liisberg.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2161.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2162.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2162.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2165.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2165.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2169.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it's an honor to appear before you on behalf of the Danish government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2169.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2171.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A rare honor, I might add.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2171.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2178.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has been almost 10 years since the government of Denmark last time appeared before the court at a hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2178.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2202.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case before you today, your honors, let me underline from the outset that the Danish legislature, the Danish government, as well as the Danish courts, including the Supreme Court, have all been extremely diligent in assessing both the legislative measure in the abstract and the specific circumstances of the applicant's case from the perspective of the European Convention on Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2202.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2216.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they have done so on the basis of the case law of the court, more specifically the seminal decision from 1985 by the plenary in the Abdulaziz, Cabales, and Balkandali case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2216.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2227.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Supreme Court of Denmark relied on this important president and wrote a very precise analysis of why both the facts of the case of Mrs. Balkandali</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2227.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2239.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the domestic immigration legislation of the UK were similar to the case before it in Denmark, not only in the abstract, but also in the concrete circumstances of Mr. and Mrs. Bial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2239.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2250.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Like the majority of the Danish Supreme Court, we believe the relevant parts of the Abdulaziz decision are still good law and are applicable in the case before you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2250.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2267.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the court should disagree contrary to what we expect, we respectfully encourage the court to explicitly state so in its decision and explain why present day conditions require the court to revise its own case law on this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2267.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2285.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Immigration control measures and conditions for spousal reunification with third country nationals vary a lot from country to country within Europe, even within the European Union, depending on national circumstances, tradition, and political choice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2285.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2305.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the 30 years since the Abdulaziz decision, national rules and standards on immigration from third countries, including through spousal reunification with third country nationals, have hardly, on average, become less strict, less selective, or less competitive in European countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2305.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2322.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't see any evolving standards, or as the applicants' counsel referred to, emerging consensus in the direction of a more relaxed, more liberal, or immigration-friendly policies across Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2322.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2336.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the contrary, we submit, at least on average, a revision of the Abdulaziz decision, the president would, in our opinion, not be warranted by present day conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2336.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2348.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it would involve a significant and undesirable curtailment of the margin of appreciation in immigration and citizenship matters of the contracting parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2348.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2352.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the government has set out its position in law</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2352.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2356.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in detail in its written observation of 15 January 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2356.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2360.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I shall not repeat our comprehensive line of argumentation here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2360.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2363.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My oral submission will fall in two parts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2363.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2377.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, I will try to explain in a nutshell why the government, like the majorities of the Supreme Court and the chamber of this court, believes there has been no violation of Article 14 in conjunction with Article 8 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2377.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2388.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, I will address the two questions on the facts of the case and domestic law put forward by the court in their letter to the government of 6 March 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2388.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2401.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before moving on to the first part of my oral submission, allow me briefly to draw attention of the court to a section of our written observations where we comment on elements of the chamber judgment of 25 March 14.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2401.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2407.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to section 3.2 on pages 13 to 16 in our observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2407.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2419.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here, the government tries to clarify some points on the relevant Danish rules in light of apparent misunderstandings, both in the majority and the minority opinions of the chamber judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2419.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2428.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The misunderstandings relate to the practical consequences of the attachment requirement and the 28-year exception rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2428.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2435.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a footnote, I would remark that this case is about the 28-year exception rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2435.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2446.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not about the attachment requirement, as some of the comments made by my colleague just now seem to assume.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2446.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2459.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our written submissions, we explain why the 28-year exception rule introduced in 2003 did not and does not restrict the possibility for naturalized Danes, such as Mr. Biao,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2459.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2465.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to obtain spousal reunification with a foreign national spouse, such as Mrs. Biao.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2465.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2470.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The rule is an exception, not a requirement or a condition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2470.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2487.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A naturalized Dane is not required to have been a Danish national for 28 years in order to obtain spousal reunification in Denmark, contrary to what especially the dissenting minority of the chamber seems to assume.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2487.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2491.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I now turn to the first part of my submission,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2491.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2497.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the law and the question of whether there's been a violation of the European Convention on Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2497.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2506.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will not devote time to the question of the alleged violation of Article 8 of the Convention, which the chamber was unanimous in rejecting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2506.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2514.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, I focus on the issue of the alleged violation of Article 14 in conjunction with Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2514.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2524.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To begin with, allow me to address the question of whether a review in abstracto by the court of relevant Danish legislation is warranted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2524.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2536.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government agrees with the observations in paragraph 103 of the chamber judgment and in paragraph 3 of the concurring opinion of judges Raimondi and Spano.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2536.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2551.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these paragraphs, the majority of the chamber emphasize, with reference to relevant case law, that where national legislation is an issue, it is not the task of the court to review the relevant legislation in the abstract.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2551.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2559.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, it must confine itself, as far as possible, to examining the issues raised by the case before it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2559.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2574.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This principle seems indeed relevant in the present case, also keeping in mind that the Supreme Court of Denmark has, in fact, explicitly carried out a review of the domestic legislation, not only in its application to Mr. and Mrs. Biao,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2574.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2580.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>but also in the abstract held up against the convention and the case law of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2580.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2599.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the court, contrary to what we expect and contrary to the approach of the majority of the chamber, chooses to engage in a review in abstracto, we respectfully submit that the reasoning of the Danish Supreme Court is compelling and that its conclusion should be upheld.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2599.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2605.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this point, I will only add one additional element to the Supreme Court's analysis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2605.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2612.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It relates to the relevance of the Abdulaziz decision with respect to Mrs. Balkandali.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2612.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2615.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the court will recall, Mrs. Balkandali</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2615.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2631.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was a naturalized British national of Egyptian extraction seeking spousal reunion in the UK with her husband, a Turkish national, on the basis of British immigration rules enacted in 1980.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2631.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2653.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She complained that she did not benefit from a British immigration rule according to which a citizen of the United Kingdom and the colonies, quote, who or one whose parents had been born in the United Kingdom, end of quote, could more easily be granted a spousal reunion residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2653.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2672.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's important to note that at the time in the UK and until 1983, rules on the acquisition of British citizenship were based primarily on the Lex Solei principle rather than the Lex Sanguinis principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2672.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2682.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, children born on United Kingdom soil became British nationals irrespective of the status and origin of the parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2682.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2698.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is, we believe, relevant to understand why the UK 1980 immigration rules gave preferential treatment to UK citizens born in the UK and not to a naturalized UK citizen such as Mrs. Balkandali</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2698.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2700.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>born elsewhere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2700.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2714.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The distinction based on the place of birth could, in the UK context at the time, just as well have been formulated as a distinction between naturalized citizens and citizens by birth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2714.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2718.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I now turn to the application of Article 14</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2718.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2724.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in conjunction with Article 8 to the specific facts of the matter before you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2724.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2731.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are basically, as we see it, two themes of disagreement between the applicants and the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2731.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2735.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One, the nature of and grounds for the difference of treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2735.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2745.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And two, the legitimacy and proportionality of the 28-year exception rule as applied in the case of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2745.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2751.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The two themes overlap to some extent, but I will try to address them one by one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2751.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2756.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, as to the nature of and grounds for the difference of treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2756.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2763.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government agrees that there has been a difference in treatment of persons in similar situations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2763.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2773.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we strongly disagree that this difference of treatment is based directly or indirectly on ethnic or racial grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2773.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2779.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The difference in treatment follows from the fact that Mr. Biao, having been a Danish citizen for less than two</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2779.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2793.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>years, was not able in 2004 to benefit from the special 28-year exception rule introduced for the benefit of nationals with particularly long and lasting ties to Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2793.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2798.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was thus treated differently on the ground of the length of his period of Danish nationality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2798.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2804.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in this sense, he enjoyed other status in the words of Article 14.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2804.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2826.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government disputes the applicant's allegation that they have been subjected to an indirect difference in treatment relative to other persons in analogous or relevantly similar situations in the terminology of the court based on the ground of the first applicant's non-Danish ethnic origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2826.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2840.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants have submitted that persons born in Denmark as Danish nationals will, in general, benefit more from the 28-year exception rule than persons acquiring Danish nationality later in life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2840.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2860.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants have also stated that the vast majority of persons born in Denmark as Danish nationals would be of Danish ethnic origin, while persons acquiring Danish nationality later in life would generally be of other ethnic origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2860.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2866.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is hard to disagree with these general assertions and assumptions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2866.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2875.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They seem self-evident, even in the absence, and I regret that, of accurate and detailed statistics.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2875.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2876.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2876.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2897.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because it is in the nature of things that immigration controls, and in particular, preferential measures for nationals with long and lasting ties with the country, on average, work less to the benefit of people of foreign extraction compared to people born nationals of the host country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2897.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2902.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On average, that is, not completely or exclusively.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2902.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2911.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This fact does not mean that the applicants have been directly or indirectly discriminated against on the basis of the ethnic origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2911.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2932.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The 28-year exception rule is aimed at persons who, seen from a general perspective, can be assumed to have ties with Denmark that are so strong that, in view of the integration considerations on which the attachment requirement was based, it would be unreasonable to enforce the attachment requirement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2932.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2952.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My colleague seems to imply that only if statistical proof at the time of the legislature's decision was available could the legislature have aimed by political measures to benefit this group of Danish nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2952.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2953.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We disagree.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2953.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2964.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Political decisions do not necessarily have to be based on statistical surveys.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2964.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2989.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government agrees with the Danish Supreme Court that a 28-year-old person who acquired Danish nationality by birth will generally have stronger and more genuine ties with Denmark and greater insight into Danish society than a 28-year-old or older person who, like the first applicant, only came to Denmark as a young person or an adult.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2989.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3001.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, the government refers to the Abdulaziz decision where British exception rules were alleged to amount to discrimination based on race or ethnic origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3001.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3016.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court replied in paragraph 85 that it regarded the provisions as being exceptions, quote, designed for the benefit of persons having a close link with the United Kingdom, which do not affect the general tenor of the rules, unquote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3016.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3022.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this reasoning was followed by the chamber in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3022.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3025.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I now move on to the second theme</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3025.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3029.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of disagreement between the applicants and the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3029.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3037.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The legitimacy and proportionality of the 28-year exception rule as applied to the facts of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3037.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3049.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The 28-year exception rule, which was changed to a 26-year exception rule in 2012 for political reasons after a change of government, pursues a legitimate aim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3049.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3064.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was introduced in 2003 and took effect from January 2004 to exempt from the attachment requirement a group of nationals who, seen from a general perspective, had strong and lasting ties with Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3064.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3072.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is clearly motivated in the preparatory acts from 2003 reproduced on page 11 in our written observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3072.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3088.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I quote, the aim is to ensure that Danish expatriates with strong and lasting ties with Denmark in the form of at least 28 years of Danish nationality will be able to obtain spousal reunification in Denmark, unquote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3088.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3114.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to give, quote, Danish expatriates a real opportunity of returning to Denmark with a foreign spouse or cohabitant, end quote, and giving young Danes wishing to go abroad, quote, the certainty of not being barred from returning to Denmark with a foreign spouse or cohabitant as a consequence of the attachment requirement, end quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3114.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3134.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Politically, it was felt in 2003 that this group of actual or potential Danish expatriate nationals had been unintentionally and unfairly disadvantaged by the tightening of the attachment requirement introduced one year earlier in 2002.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3134.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3146.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The original attachment requirement was introduced by a previous government in 2000 and accepted to begin with all Danish nationals, regardless of how long they had been Danish nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3146.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3164.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, does this measure, this exception rule of 20 years of nationality, amount to an illegitimate or disproportionate or discriminatory preferential treatment of certain Danish nationals?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3164.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3165.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3165.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3178.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Many countries in Europe have various provisions in their immigration and citizenship legislation for the preferential treatment of expatriates and the diaspora of their nation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3178.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3192.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Keeping the door open for expatriates is far from unusual and seen in many countries as a contribution to preserving a national identity, a completely legitimate societal aim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3192.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3210.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, it was explicitly recognized by the court in Abdullah's paragraph 88 that there are, quote, in general, persuasive social reasons for giving special treatment to those whose link with a country stems from birth within it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3210.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3216.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This exact paragraph from Abdullah's was not only relied on by the Danish legislature and courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3216.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3222.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has also been relied on recently by the European Court of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3222.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3250.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Pono Marijof case, the court in 2007, citing paragraph 88 of Abdullah's, dismissed as manifestly ill-founded a complaint under Article 14 about a considerably lower residence permit fee for expatriate Bulgarians as compared to fees charged ordinary aliens in Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3250.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3271.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, does the measure at issue in today's case disadvantage other groups, such as other Danish nationals, whether younger than 28 years or persons having become Danish nationals later in life, as compared to the status quo ex ante?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3271.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3273.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3273.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3283.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No one would be better off if the exception rule had not been in place in 2004 or were to be repealed as a result of this case, neither Mr. and Mrs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3283.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3290.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Biao nor other persons in similar situations in the future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3290.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3292.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, let me briefly comment</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3292.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3298.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the issue of Article 5, paragraph 2 of the European Convention on Nationality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3298.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3308.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We agree with the Danish Supreme Court and the majority of the chamber that the provision has no importance for the interpretation of Article 14 of the convention in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3308.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3312.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to paragraph 95 of the chamber judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3312.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3317.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have set out our arguments and interpretation in our written observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3317.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3349.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if there might be conceivable competing interpretations of this convention's Article 5, paragraph 2, we fail to see how a non-binding, somewhat ambiguous provision in an instrument ratified by only 20 members of the Council of Europe could inform the interpretation of Article 14 in a judgment which will set an important precedent with de facto effect for all contracting parties on matters relating to immigration law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3349.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3351.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, before I end the first part</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3351.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3359.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of my oral submission, let me briefly address the issue of proportionality in the specific circumstances of the applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3359.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3368.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Danish Supreme Court found that the consequences of the 28-year exception rule could not be considered disproportionate relative to the first applicant, Mr. Biao.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3368.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3373.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was born in Togo in 1971, came to Denmark in 1993.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3373.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3377.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After nine years of residence, he became a Danish national in 2002.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3377.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3381.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2003, he married the second applicant, Mrs. Biao,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3381.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3386.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and they then submitted an application for spousal reunification in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3386.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3392.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was refused by final administrative decision in 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3392.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3394.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this point, Mr. Biao had been a Danish national</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3394.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3395.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for less than two years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3395.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3398.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The approximately 10 years that Mr. Biao spent in Denmark</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3398.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3414.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>prior to the refusal of family reunification did not confer on him a special link to Denmark comparable to the special link held by a person falling within the 28-year exception rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3414.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3416.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I will now turn to the second part</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3416.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3420.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of my submission on the written questions of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3420.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3425.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the court has asked whether it would be correct to assume that if Mr. Biao had remained</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3425.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3437.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in Denmark and the applicants had reapplied for family reunification, they would have had prospects of success in fulfilling the attachment requirement in 2005.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3437.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3442.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In short, the answer to this question is, yes, that is correct to assume.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3442.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3454.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Spousal reunification is generally subject to an attachment requirement, meaning that the party's aggregate ties with Denmark must be stronger than their aggregate ties with another country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3454.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3467.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A resident spouse who has made efforts to become integrated in Danish society will normally be able to fulfill the attachment requirement at the latest after about 12 years of residence in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3467.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3478.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the case regardless of whether the resident spouse has become a Danish national, as long as the foreign spouse has paid a visit to Denmark, even a short one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3478.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3480.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Biao came to Denmark in 1993.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3480.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3487.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in 1996, he was issued with a residence permit for Denmark on the basis of his marriage with a Danish national.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3487.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3491.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in 1997, he was granted a permanent residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3491.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3494.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In April 2002, he became a Danish national.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3494.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3498.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And from 1997 until 2005, Mr. Biao</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3498.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3502.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>held different jobs and completed different courses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3502.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3506.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2003, Mrs. Biao entered Denmark on a tourist visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3506.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3511.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2005, thus, Mr. Biao would, if he had stayed in Denmark,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3511.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3525.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>have enjoyed 12 years of residence in Denmark and would indeed have had prospects of success in fulfilling the attachment requirement if, at that point, he had reapplied for family reunification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3525.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3529.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, I would like to emphasize that Mr. Biao was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3529.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3540.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>explicitly informed about the 12 years of residence practice in the final administrative decision of August 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3540.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3544.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we know, the applicants moved to Sweden in 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3544.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3552.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they have not submitted a new application for family reunification in Denmark since the initial application was rejected in 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3552.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3556.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They could have done so also after the move to Sweden.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3556.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3560.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the second written question of the court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3560.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3582.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>relates to a decision by the EU Court of Justice from July 2008 in the so-called Mittok case and whether it would be correct to assume that in the light of this decision, the applicants and their child would have had prospects of success in applying from Sweden for a residence permit in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3582.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3587.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In short, yes, that would be correct to assume.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3587.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3597.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question of the court seemed related to the third-party comments submitted by the Ayer Center on 6 February 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3597.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3631.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Ayer Center states that the court, in examining the proportionality of the 28-year exception rule, should take into consideration that the EU Court of Justice, in its ruling in the Mittok case, has held, quote, from the Ayer intervention, that it is not permissible to require the third country national family member of an EU citizen exercising treaty rights to leave the country and return to his or her country of origin in order to regularize his or her status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3631.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3642.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government respectfully submits that this is not a correct account or interpretation of the Mittok ruling or EU law as it stands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3642.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3648.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allow me, therefore, to dwell on this point of EU law for a moment and in some detail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3648.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3666.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Mittok ruling establishes that the EU free movement directive only provides a right of residence for third country nationals who are family members of a union citizen, where that citizen has exercised his or her right of free movement by becoming established in a host member state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3666.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3675.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the ruling, it is furthermore a requirement that the third country family members accompany or join the union citizen in the host member state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3675.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3687.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The EU Court of Justice recently confirmed this in its grand chamber ruling in case C-456-12, O and B, from March 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3687.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3712.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In accordance with this case law, a third country family member of a Danish national who has exercised his or her right of freedom of movement by becoming established in a host EU member state can enjoy a derived right of residence on the Danish national's return to Denmark, provided that the third country family member was joining or accompanying him or her in the host EU member state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3712.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3724.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The EU Court of Justice made clear in the recent O and B case that the provisions of the EU free movement directive should be applied by analogy in such a situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3724.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3747.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The EU Court emphasized in paragraph 54 of the decision that on the condition that family life is created or strengthened during the genuine residence of an EU citizen in a host EU member state, other than that of his or her nationality, the effectiveness of the rights conferred on the EU citizen by the EU treaties requires that the family life can be continued in the home member state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3747.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3753.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Based on the information available, Mr. Biao has established himself in Sweden with his family</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3753.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3758.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and has thus exercised his EU right of free movement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3758.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3761.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If Mr. Biao were to return to Denmark with his family,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3761.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3772.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>he would be able to continue the family life he has led in Sweden through the grant of a derived right of residence under EU law to the family members concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3772.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3783.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But let me emphasize, an EU citizen cannot benefit from the EU treaties or the EU free movement directive unless he moves to another EU member state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3783.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3799.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, EU law cannot have any impact on the proportionality assessment under the European Convention of Human Rights in the applicant's case before the court, which regards the situation as it presented itself back in 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3799.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3810.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope I have answered both written questions to the satisfaction of the court, and I now reach my conclusion, Mr. President, in which I would like to stress three points</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3810.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3813.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which the Danish government finds particularly important.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3813.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3821.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One, the Abdulaziz President from 1985, including on the points related to the case of Mrs. Balkandali,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3821.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3836.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is still good law, and the reasoning and the holding of the case should be applied to the similar facts and domestic legislation of the present case, like the Supreme Court of Denmark did in its judgment from 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3836.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3849.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two, the 28-year rule is not a requirement or condition for Danish nationals to be able to enjoy family life in Denmark with a foreign national spouse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3849.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3866.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is an exception to the attachment requirement, and it is aimed at helping in a non-discriminatory way a group of disadvantaged Danish nationals, expatriate Danes who are deemed in general to have long and lasting ties with Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3866.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3870.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Three, the fact that Mr. Biao was not exempted from the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3870.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3883.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>attachment requirement based on a period of less than two years of Danish citizenship cannot in any case be considered disproportionate relative to the aim of the 28-year rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3883.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3898.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the time of the final administrative decision in 2004, the applicants were probably just a year away from satisfying the attachment requirement based on what would have been approximately 12 years of residence by Mr. Biao in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3898.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3913.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The introduction in 2003 of the 28-year rule did not make the situation of the couple more difficult, and repealing the exception as a result of this case will not help anyone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3913.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3926.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On this basis, Your Honours, the Court respectfully requests the Court to find that there has been no violation of Article 8 or Article 14 in conjunction with Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3926.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3926.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3930.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3931.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your interventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3931.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3937.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would now like to invite the judges of the Grand Chamber to put any questions they may have to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3937.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3939.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are there any questions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3939.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3939.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Kjølbro.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Jon Fridrik Kjølbro</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3943.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3945.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3945.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3946.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I do have three questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3946.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3952.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first one is addressed to the representative of the applicant, and the other two questions are addressed to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3952.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3963.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question addressed to the representative of the applicants is, in fact, the repetition of a question already raised by the court in writing, but in my view, not sufficiently answered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3963.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3979.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why did the applicants never lodge a request for family reunification after the final administrative decision in 2004, as they were entitled to, according to domestic legislation, either invoking the Aliens Act or the relevant applicable EU legislation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3979.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3984.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is the explanation that in the assessment of the applicants, it was in any event bound to fail?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3984.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3994.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or in the alternative, is the explanation that for personal reasons, the applicants no longer were interested in family reunification in Denmark?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3994.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3997.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question is addressed to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3997.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4002.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It concerns access to relevant information about administrative practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4002.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4015.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government relies on administrative practice as it is described in the memorandum of 1 December 2005, replacing an earlier memorandum of 29 September 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4015.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4023.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants, however, argue that information on the application of the attachment requirement were not at all accessible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4023.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4029.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they are invoking that they did not have access to information about this 12-year practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4029.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4035.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they also refer to criticism voiced by the parliamentary ombudsman, albeit it concerns other provisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4035.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4048.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, my question is, how is information on administrative practice made public to persons affected by the legislation and to lawyers assisting such applicants?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4048.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4050.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Have the two memorandums been published?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4050.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4056.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are they, for example, made available on the website of the relevant authority?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4056.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4059.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My third question is somewhat hypothetical.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4059.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4062.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, I do accept if it's not possible to answer the question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4062.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4065.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But nevertheless, I'll try.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4065.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4082.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In case the court were to find that a 28-year rule, and thus the exception to the generally applicable attachment requirement, amounted to discrimination in violation of Article 14 read in conjunction with Article 8, what would be the likely consequences of such a judgment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4082.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4093.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If I listened attentively, seemingly it has already been hinted, at least when the government agent said if it were to be repealed as a consequence of this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4093.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4101.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But nevertheless, I would like to, if it is possible, to give at least some kind of assessment of what would be the likely consequence of a ruling against the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4101.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4101.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4101.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4104.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4105.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4106.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4106.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4108.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question goes to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4108.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4115.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, the applicant may also take the opportunity to express his views on this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4117.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4164.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the government has said repeatedly in various international fora that one of the purposes or one of the reasons why this legislation was enacted was the fact that, and I'm quoting from a reply that the government gave to the Committee on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination, but this quotation may be found in many other places, that among foreigners and Danish nationals of foreign extraction who live in Denmark, there is a widespread tendency to marry a person from one's own country of origin, among other reasons due to parental pressure, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4166.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4175.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is, is this still today the position of the Danish government that this is the reason why this measure was taken?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4178.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4198.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if not, why does the Danish government keep an annual statistical report concerning foreigners published by the Ministry of Refugee, Immigration, and Integration Affairs with the purpose of assessing the marriage patterns among immigrants and descendants from non-Western countries?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4198.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4198.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4198.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4200.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Motoc.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4202.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4204.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, M. le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4204.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4235.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ma première question concerne, s'adresse au gouvernement, et ma première question concerne comment est-ce que le gouvernement danois réagit par rapport aux critiques qui ont été formulées à l'égard de cette loi par les instances du Conseil de l'Europe, ça veut dire le commissariat des droits de l'homme, aussi par le Haut commissariat pour les réfugiés et aussi par les organes des traités où on avait cité ici tout à l'heure le comité pour l'élimination de toute forme de discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4235.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4241.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On a aussi des autres comités des Nations unies, le comité pour l'élimination des droits de la femme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4242.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4255.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et bon, ça veut dire que la plus grande totalité de ces comités qui ont dû analyser cette loi ont formulé à juste titre des fortes critiques par rapport à cette loi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4256.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4268.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quelle était la réaction de votre gouvernement par rapport à ces critiques qui ont été formulées et comment est-ce que vous avez jugé de les mettre en place?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4268.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4277.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ma deuxième question est d'une certaine manière liée à la question qui a été posée par mon collègue tout à l'heure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4277.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4300.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et il s'agit d'une partie de notre jugement même, du jugement d'Abdulaziz, que les deux parties ont cité, qui, ce jugement, fait des références à cette pratique de mariage traditionnel entre les personnes qui viennent des autres continents que l'Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4300.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4311.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et le jugement aussi fait référence à la possibilité d'avoir des mariages blancs pour justifier leur...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4313.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4316.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>leur effus d'accepter ce type de mariage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4316.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4326.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, quelle est votre position par rapport à cette sorte d'affirmation aujourd'hui?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4326.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4331.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cela veut dire que 30 ans après ce jugement d'Abdulaziz.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4331.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4331.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4337.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4338.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No other questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4338.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4343.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now... sorry, Judge Turković, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4346.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4355.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just when you are responding to the question of Judge Kjølbro, I would just like to clarify, if you could clarify two points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4355.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4363.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is living in Sweden, but he's working in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4363.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4378.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for the purposes of the 12 years rule, whether he would be considered living in Sweden or in Denmark, and for the purposes of free movement, whether he would be considered free moving since he's still working in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4378.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4378.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4381.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4382.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. No other questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4382.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4393.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the court will now rise for 20 minutes, following which the parties will return for a second round of short pleadings to respond to the submissions in the first round and to the judges' questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4466.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4466.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4514.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4517.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated. The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4517.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4521.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Petersen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4527.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4529.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Distinguished Member of the Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4529.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4535.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I shall address the question from the Danish judge, Mr. John Kjellboe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4535.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4550.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I want to go a bit back because, as opposed to what the government has claimed, the family did not voluntarily move to Sweden when they got the refusal in November 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4550.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4559.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the moment they got the refusal, Mrs. Bjau was no longer allowed to stay in Denmark</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4559.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4561.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>or to work in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4561.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4563.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So they were forced to move there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4563.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4576.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I heard my colleague say that, at the refusal, they were explicitly advised about this so-called 12-year rule mentioned by you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4576.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4583.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so if that's not correct, I refer to the file, the High Court's judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4583.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4589.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on page 9 on this, there is a long, long list.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4589.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4592.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, a note, a memo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4592.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4604.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But nowhere in the refusal from the alien authorities nor from the Ministry of Refugees, it is explicitly pointed out, well, you have to wait to 2005.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4604.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4608.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then you fulfill 12 years, and then you can be reunited in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4608.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4612.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not the worthing of the refusal from the ministry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4612.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4626.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the reason why they have not reapplied is that, according to their conception, they had to wait, in fact, 28 years to 2030.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4626.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4634.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you have to bear in mind that when they moved to Sweden, Mr. Bjau has to give up his apartment in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4634.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4637.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He had an apartment in Nistved where he worked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4637.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4640.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But he was forced to move with her, too.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4640.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4648.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in 2030, Mr. Bjau will be 59 years old.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4648.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4650.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His wife will be 51 years old.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4650.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4654.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the son will be 26 years old.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4654.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4657.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Perhaps at that moment, they can apply again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4657.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4666.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But if it's going to be a success, nobody knows the answer, so to speak, is blowing in the wind.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4666.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4672.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there's no reason for disputing again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4672.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4677.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the court can see, we have two different opinions about that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4677.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4690.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I want to emphasize one thing, and that is that the fact that the rule is made like a form of Lex Danish expatriates, that's how I see it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4690.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4693.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we can't see anything about how much it was.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4693.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4701.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I want to draw the court's attention to Exhibit 2, which is the statistics in the government statement this year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4701.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4708.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here you can see on the last page how many uncertainties there are to these statistics.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4708.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4720.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in my view, I think when a government claims there's no violations of Article 14 taken in conjunction with Article 8, you have to have all the papers in order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4720.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4722.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to this day, I cannot understand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4722.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4726.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I've had this case since 2006 in the High Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4726.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4740.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I cannot understand why it is not possible for the government to specify or to be as detailed as the English government, for example, was in the Abdel Rassous case, paragraph 38, statistics.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4740.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4754.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think this court can see it as a fact that no one told the applicants about the 12-year possibility or an earlier possibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4754.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4778.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's also confirmed in the two exhibits in the file, where the Danish Ombudsman severely criticized the information on the website, New in Denmark, severely criticized the administrative practice, severely criticized that the EU law has not, so to speak, mirrored in the administrative practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4778.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4780.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I hope that answers the questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4780.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4780.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thanks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4786.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4787.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4787.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4791.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Bering Liisberg, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4793.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4798.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President, distinguished members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4798.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4808.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If I may, let me first reply to the comments made just now by the applicant's counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4808.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4813.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, it was alleged that Mr. and Mrs. Biao</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4813.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4818.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>were forced by Denmark to move to Sweden.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4818.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4821.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I emphasize this is not the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4821.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4832.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This couple had the possibility to move to Sweden and be reunified there as a family, thanks to EU free movement law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4832.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4838.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no forcing of the couple to Sweden or any other country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4838.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4843.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were certainly alternatives, as was laid down by the Danish authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4843.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4851.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was assessed at that time that the couple's aggregate ties to Ghana was bigger than to Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4851.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4858.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was perfectly possible for the couple also to move to a third country, such as Ghana.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4858.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4884.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, I would also like to reply to the comment made that the applicants were not informed of the 12-year practice that some of the members of the court asked some questions about.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4884.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4892.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, we have been frantically trying to see if we had an English translation of the entire Supreme Court judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4892.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4895.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it seems that we have not submitted such a full translation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4895.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4916.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in the statement of facts in the official gazette of Danish law reports on page 1,039 and onwards, the entire decision, the entire administrative decision of 2004 is reproduced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4916.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4953.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there is a paragraph which says, and I'm translating here in an unofficial way, in practice, as a point of departure, it is required that the residence in Denmark must amount to approximately 12 years, provided that the person has also made an effort to become integrated, which is exactly applicable, or would have been applicable, to the situation of Mr. Biao</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4953.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4955.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>if he had stayed in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4955.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4966.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, why was this piece of information, this practice, not communicated to Mr. Biao before?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4966.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4976.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason is simply that this practice of 12 years, or approximately 12 years, of residence in Denmark was established only in 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4976.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4983.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is after the first administrative decision of the Immigration Authority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4983.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4988.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, that leads me to the question posed by Judge Kjellbrug.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4988.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4996.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question to the government relates to exactly this question of the administrative practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4996.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5013.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, it is correct that the Danish parliamentary ombudsman criticized, in two instances, insufficient public availability of information about the practice of the immigration authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5013.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5021.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the first case, in 2005, it did, in fact, relate to the 12 years practice rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5021.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5039.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in the second case, in 2008, which the applicants have also referred to, it did not relate to the attachment requirements, even less to the 28-year rules, but entirely to EU law after the METOC ruling.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5039.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5045.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have since developed the website and the public information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5045.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5061.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think for the purposes of deciding this case on the facts of it, what is important is to note that the applicant was indeed informed about the 12-year practice in the final administrative decision of August 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5061.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5077.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We will, with the permission of the court, gladly provide a full translation and official translation of the Supreme Court decision in which the administrative decision is reproduced in its entirety.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5077.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5093.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, in relation to the administrative practice, Judge Turkovich asked the question whether the fact that Mr. Biao lives in Sweden</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5093.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5104.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and works in Denmark would count in a positive way towards accomplishing the 12-year residence practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5104.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5108.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It wouldn't because it's based on residence, not work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5108.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5118.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I think more importantly, it is not even applicable, the 12-year practice rule, in the case of Mr. Biao,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5118.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5143.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>if he were to reapply, because the EU rules would at that point have primacy and would be applied and would lead to the result which I explained in my initial oral submission, that he would be granted resident right also to his third country national spouse in Denmark on the basis of EU law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5143.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5169.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That brings me to the question which Judge Kirbel raised, the hypothetical question, what would be the likely consequences that the government of Denmark would draw if the court were to find that there had been a violation, that the 28-year exception rule constitutes a violation of Article 14 in conjunction with Article 8?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5169.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5189.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is correct that in my submission, I referred to the hypothetical that if you were to reach that decision, it would benefit no one if the conclusion would be that the exception rule was repealed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5189.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5200.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I have no possibility to answer the question on what political consequences would be drawn from a finding of violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5200.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5210.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But one consequence, as I stated in my submission, could be the repealing of this preferential treatment to expatriate Danes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5210.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5214.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Certainly, other possibilities could also be envisaged.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5214.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5227.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I guess it would also depend to some extent on the reasoning of the court and to what extent the court would revise or even annul its previous case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5227.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5245.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On top of that, we are having elections later this year, which makes it even more difficult for me to give you an estimate of how the next government would react and what a parliament majority would find appropriate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5245.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5252.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What I can say is that, of course, the government of Denmark would respect the decision of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5252.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5254.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is beyond question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5254.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5274.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, Judge Pinto and Judge Motok raised questions about criticism of Danish immigration policy from also other instances than this court, that is, the UN bodies and the Commissioner for Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5274.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5291.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that the Danish immigration rules introduced from 2000, 2002, 2003, and onwards have been subject to a lot of scrutiny by international partners and bodies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5291.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5301.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have engaged in a very constructive dialogue with all of these bodies and commissioners and others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5301.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5311.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sometimes they have expressed opinions on the nature and quality of Danish immigration legislation, which we do not agree with.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5311.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5332.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sometimes they have led to further reconsideration, and some of the policy measures have been amended throughout this period of 10 years, even the 28-year rule has been reduced to a 26-year rule because of a change of government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5332.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5338.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What I would say is that this is about political choice to a very wide extent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5338.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5341.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We take seriously all the comments we get.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5341.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5343.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some of them are based on law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5343.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5346.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some of them are based on more political considerations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5346.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5354.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And many of the criticisms raised, most of them, in fact, do not relate to the 28-year exception rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5354.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5361.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that the Commissioner for Human Rights of the Council of Europe did criticize the 28-year rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5361.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5379.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe his assumptions were wrong, namely that you could only become reunified with your spouse if you were a naturalized Danish citizen if you reached the age of 56, which I have tried to explain is not a correct understanding of the Danish law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5379.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5393.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have received criticism on many other elements of the Danish immigration law, but they are not at issue before the court today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5393.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5395.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The attachment requirement is one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5395.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5398.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The so-called 24-years rule is another.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5398.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5401.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They work in combination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5401.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5444.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is true, as Judge Motok drew our attention to, that the underlying purpose of these rules, the attachment requirement and the 24-year rules, which are not the subject of our case today, were aimed at trying to avoid immigration problems, integration problems, and trying to avoid a practice or prevent a practice seen in certain immigrant communities in Denmark of forced marriages, sham marriages, or covertly forced marriages through the use of arrangements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5444.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5460.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I'm afraid I have not been able to produce statistics on this issue, which in itself is not so relevant for this case, I submit, because the 28-year rule is what we have to look at today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5460.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5472.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that was never reasoned with any reference to sham marriages or forced marriages or other practices we were trying to avoid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5472.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5489.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm told by my colleagues that it is very rare, but it happens, that applications for family or spousal reunification are denied because authorities find that it is an instance of a sham marriage or a forced marriage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5489.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5496.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the fact that these instances are few, I don't think is proof that our rules don't work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5496.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5519.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the contrary, perhaps, that in fact, the general requirement of closer ties to Denmark, aggregate ties for the couple, and the requirement that only normally persons of 24 years or above that age can have a spousal reunification in Denmark serve their purpose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5519.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5535.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At least that is why the political consensus, almost consensus in Denmark, is that these rules are fair and should stay in place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5535.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5539.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope I have answered the questions to the court's satisfaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5539.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5539.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Your Honor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5547.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5550.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5550.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5556.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5556.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5559.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5559.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5561.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5561.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5565.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5565.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5566.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
