<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>3931506_19062012</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>18.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>19.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>57.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>58.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sit, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>74.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>76.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Good morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>76.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>87.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case Telegraaf Media Netherlands versus Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>87.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>108.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case was lodged on the 29th of September 2006 with the court under Article 34 of the Convention by five Netherlands nationals, Telegraf Media Netherlands, by Mr. Joost de Haas and Mr. Bart Mos,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>108.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>115.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and also by the Netherlands Association of Journalists and the Netherlands Society of Editors-in-Chief.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>115.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>124.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the third section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52 of the Rules of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>124.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>141.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 18 May 2010, the application was declared inadmissible in respect of the Netherlands Association of Journalists and the Netherlands Society of Editors-in-Chief, and adjourned in respect of the remaining applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>141.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>147.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The defending government are represented by their agent, Mr. Böcker, agent of the Government of the Netherlands,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>147.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>152.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Dr. Kuijer of the Ministry of Security and Justice,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>152.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>157.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. van Sasse van Ysselt, and Mr. Dielemens,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>157.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>168.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>both of the Ministry of the Interior and Kingdom Relations, and by Mrs. Jarigsma of the Public Prosecution Service Advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>168.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>176.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mr. Le Poole and Mr. de Kemp, counselors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>176.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>182.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. van Meurs-Bergsma, head of the legal department of the first applicant,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>182.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>186.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is present on the first applicant behalf.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>186.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>191.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants, Mr. De Haas and Ms. Bart Mos, are present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>191.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>196.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representative and applicants in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>196.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>229.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome the delegation of members of the French Conseil d'Etat, the delegation of judges of the Hungarian Supreme Court, the delegation of judges and prosecutors from the Netherlands, the delegation of judges and prosecutors from the European Judicial Training Network, the delegation of judges and prosecutors from Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, and Uzbekistan, and the delegation from Lincoln's Inn.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>229.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>237.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicants, I have determined the order of address as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>237.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>240.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Böcker, for the government, will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>240.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>249.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mr. de Kem and Mr. Le Poole for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>249.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>249.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Böcker.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>254.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>255.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>258.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>265.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There used to be microphones here, but I think they have been replaced by new devices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>265.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>268.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope you can hear me.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>268.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>272.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>272.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>278.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it cannot be denied that there is a certain complexity due to the case we are discussing today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>278.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>291.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This complexity, however, relates to the proliferation of procedures which emanated from the original facts underlying the case, rather than to the facts themselves, which are not so complicated at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>291.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>294.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will try to demonstrate that in a moment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>294.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>314.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will then describe the various domestic proceedings relevant to the case, not only because they are essential to the complaint, but also because the court, in its recent letter of 16 May, specifically asked the parties to address the question of legal safeguards against abuse of powers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>314.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>328.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are convinced that a description of the procedures followed in this case will eliminate any doubts about the availability of effective remedies, and hence legal safeguards, to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>328.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>340.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, I will explain why the government does not believe that a violation of Article 8 or 10 of the European Convention on Human Rights has occurred in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>340.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>350.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In doing so, we will also answer the second question raised by the court in its recent letter concerning the balance of interests in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>350.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>360.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But before embarking on all this, please allow me to highlight a few very basic principles which underlie the government's position in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>360.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>371.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the press, in its role of public watchdog, has the task of imparting information and ideas on matters of public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>371.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>377.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Protection of sources is an important requirement for proper fulfillment of that task.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>377.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>384.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the public has the right to receive that information and those ideas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>384.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>394.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, intelligence and security services have the task of protecting the democratic legal order and the security and other important interests of the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>394.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>402.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The nature of that task requires a specific regime as to special powers and confidentiality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>402.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>413.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourth, the public has the right to have the democratic legal order and the security and other important interests of the state protected from threats against them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>413.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>426.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fifth, shortcomings in the organization of the intelligence and security services, which threaten their reliability and effectiveness, are by definition a matter of public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>426.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>437.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And sixth, the contents of the files of the intelligence and security services are not, by definition, a matter of public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>437.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>440.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me now present the bare facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>440.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>463.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 20th of January 2006, the Telegraaf informed the General Intelligence and Security Service, which I will refer to hereafter as the IEVD, after its Dutch acronym, that the newspaper was in possession of documents containing secret classified information and was intending to publish articles about them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>463.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>472.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That same day, one set of documents, which after inspection turned out to be copies, was collected by the IEVD from the Telegraaf.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>472.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>481.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The IEVD sent a letter stating that it would assume, in the absence of express notice to the contrary, that all documents had been handed over.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>481.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>486.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No notice to the contrary was received.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>486.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>490.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next day, the Telegraaf published its first article on the matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>490.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>501.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The article disclosed details of the secret classified documents, including quotations, code names of IEVD informants, and contextual information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>501.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>506.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The article confirmed that the documents had been returned to the IEVD.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>506.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>511.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Various other articles were published in the days that followed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>511.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>530.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the Public Prosecution Service was not convinced that all the documents and copies thereof had in fact been handed over, and since unauthorized possession of the documents constituted a criminal offense, an order to surrender any remaining documents was served on the Telegraaf.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>530.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>547.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Telegraaf then handed over a set of documents in a sealed envelope, not to the public prosecution itself, but to the National Police Internal Investigations Department, or Rijksrecherche.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>547.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>560.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was agreed that this sealed envelope would remain in a safe at the office of the investigating judge until such time as the district court had ruled on the lawfulness of the order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>560.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>574.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After the district court had declared the order lawful, the sealed package was found to contain 37 documents fewer than the set which had been handed over to the IEVD on the 20th of January.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>574.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>584.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After a second order to surrender the missing documents was served, and following a subsequent handover of documents, it was found that 11 documents were still missing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>584.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>593.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the meantime, a criminal investigation had been instituted, originally against six persons, including the two Telegraaf journalists, Messrs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>593.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>598.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>de Haas and Moss, here present, who are both applicants in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>598.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>608.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After the investigation into the journalists had been discontinued, they were summonsed to appear as witnesses in the case against the remaining suspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>608.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>622.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, since they repeatedly refused to answer the investigating judge's questions, they were committed to prison for three days for failure to comply with a judicial order, and subsequently released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>622.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>630.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Entirely separate from the criminal investigation, the IEVD started its own investigation into the leaked files.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>630.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>643.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the context of this investigation, the IEVD exercised special powers in relation to the two journalists, notably the power to intercept and record telecommunications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>643.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>647.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These, Mr. President, distinguished members</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>647.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>651.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the court, are the essential facts underlying the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>651.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>655.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In a nutshell, a leak within the IEVD had occurred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>655.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>657.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A criminal offense had been committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>657.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>667.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Telegraaf had reported not only on the leak as such, but also on the highly confidential and sensitive contents of the leaked documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>667.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>680.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Documents had been held back, and both the IEVD and public prosecution service, as is their public duty, had taken measures in response to the leak and the criminal offense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>680.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>684.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'll now give an overview of the many procedures that were initiated in the context of this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>684.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>689.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is essential for a proper understanding of its merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>689.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>696.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, I have already mentioned the complaint procedure instituted by the Telegraaf against the seizure of the documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>696.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>706.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This complaint, which was based on the assumption that examination of the original documents could reveal the journalist's sources, was dealt with at two instances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>706.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>711.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The district court sitting in chambers and the Supreme Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>711.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>727.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both instances, referring to Article 10 of the Convention, considered the right of the Telegraaf to protect its sources, and concluded that under the circumstances, this right had not been violated by the order to surrender the documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>727.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>749.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Supreme Court specifically referred to the interests of national security set out in paragraph 2 of Article 10 of the Convention, as well as to the fact that examination of the documents, although possible, was not necessary in order to identify the leak within the IJVD, since this was already possible by reference to the contents of the documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>749.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>760.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, I also mentioned the criminal investigation into the unauthorized possession and disclosure of secret classified information, an indictable offense under the criminal code.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>760.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>780.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the context of this investigation, the two journalists were committed to prison for three days, since in their capacity as witnesses, they refused to answer most of the questions put by the investigating judge, irrespective of the relevance of these questions to the protection of their sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>780.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>788.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should stress here that the committal to prison was requested by the defense in the proceedings, not by the public prosecutor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>788.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>797.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was in the context of these proceedings that ultimately a former IJVD employee was sentenced to two years' imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>797.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>802.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, I mentioned the IJVD's investigation into the leaked files.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>802.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>826.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This type of investigation, also referred to as the subsection 2A investigation after its statutory basis, is directed at organizations and persons whose objectives and activities give rise to grave suspicions that they pose a threat to the continued existence of the democratic legal order or the security or other important interests of the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>826.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>839.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the framework of this investigation, the IJVD exercised special powers with regard to the journalists, based on the Intelligence and Security Services Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>839.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>858.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourth, the applicants instituted civil law interim injunction proceedings, or Kortgeding, against the state, requesting the termination of the use of any special powers against the journalists and the destruction of all information obtained in this way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>858.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>862.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The district court granted the applicants' request in full.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>862.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>893.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court of Appeal, however, while leaving unaffected the order to terminate the use of special powers, did not follow the district court in ordering destruction of the information, but barred the state from passing on the information obtained by the use of special powers to the public prosecutor, pending a ruling on the lawfulness of the use of those powers by the Intelligence and Security Services Supervisory Committee, which I will hereafter refer to as the Supervisory Committee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>893.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>899.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Supreme Court subsequently dismissed appeals in cassation by both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>899.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>912.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fifth, the Minister of the Interior and Kingdom Relations, responsible for the Ayvede, requested the Supervisory Committee to assess the lawfulness of the Ayvede's investigation into the leak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>912.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>926.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The committee concluded that the investigation had been lawful, meaning that it had been necessary and in accordance with the law and the criteria of proportionality and subsidiarity, save for a few exceptions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>926.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>938.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These exceptions did not influence the committee's conclusion that the data that had been forwarded by the Ayvede to the Public Prosecution Service had been obtained lawfully.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>938.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>956.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sixth and last, the applicants lodged a complaint with the Minister under the Intelligence and Security Services Act, alleging an abuse of special powers and that the investigations by the Ayvede and the Public Prosecution Service had become intertwined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>956.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>962.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Advice on the complaint was requested from the Supervisory Committee as prescribed by law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>962.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>968.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This advice should be distinguished from the committee's lawfulness investigation, which I just mentioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>968.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>978.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The committee advised that the complaint be declared unfounded except for one point relating to the transcription and recording of intercepted conversations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>978.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>981.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The minister endorsed that advice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>981.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>990.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for the record, I would add here that the applicants subsequently lodged a complaint with the National Ombudsman, which was eventually not pursued.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>990.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1007.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If this overview of procedures proves anything, it is that this case raises no issues concerning any lack of access to domestic remedies under Article 13 of the Convention, which, incidentally, was not invoked by the applicants, and rightly so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1007.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1019.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is beyond doubt that several avenues were open to the applicants, in which their complaints under the Convention were carefully examined and, in some instances, upheld.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1019.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1038.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the Court specifically asked the parties to address the issue of safeguards against abusive powers by the Ayurvedic, I should stress here the interim injunction proceedings, the Supervisory Committee's full review of the lawfulness of the use of special powers, and the examination of the applicants' complaint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1038.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1048.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government deems the aggregate of the above-mentioned remedies to have been as effective as they can be, given the national security considerations involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1048.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1061.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The seriousness of these proceedings is, apart from anything else, borne out by the fact that they all led to certain retrospective corrections, for example, with regard to the Ayurvedic investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1061.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1076.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the applicants were clearly not satisfied with the outcome of the various proceedings, Article 13, as confirmed by the Court in its case law, merely provides the right to an effective remedy, but does not guarantee the applicant a favorable outcome.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1076.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1084.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I refer to the Court's established case law, such as Leander v. Sweden and Al-Nashif v. Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1084.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1100.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, I should mention the fact that, given the public interest inherent in the case at hand, the Minister kept the House of Representatives of the States General informed of developments in the various procedures I have summarized, insofar as this did not harm the investigations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1106.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1110.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1110.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1126.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>this brings me to the key question which needs to be answered this morning, namely whether, having regard to the facts of the case, including the many domestic procedures followed, the applicants are right to claim that their rights under Articles 8 and 10 of the Convention were violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1126.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1131.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All in all, the applicants complain about three different acts by the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1131.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1133.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One, the seizure of documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1133.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1137.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two, the committal to prison of the two journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1137.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1143.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Three, the use of special powers by the IJVD in relation to the two journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1143.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1160.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In contrast to the approach adopted in our written observations of 3 December 2010 and further observations of the 5th of July 2011, I will not now make a distinction by Article of the Convention, since Articles 8 and 10 in this particular case are closely connected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1160.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1166.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, and for the sake of clarity, I will deal with the three acts by the state, one after another.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1166.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1169.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the seizure of documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1169.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1188.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government postulates that the order to surrender the classified documents, as was made abundantly clear to the Telegraaf at the time, was not intended to discover the journalist's sources, but first and foremost, to ensure that all documents and copies had in fact been returned to the IJVD.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1188.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1193.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Identification of the journalist's sources was explicitly not the intention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1193.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1203.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The contents of the documents pointed in the direction of a former employee as being the leak within the IJVD, for which he was later convicted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1203.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1217.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the government holds that this case does not involve the right to protection of journalistic sources, since the order to surrender the documents was not aimed at disclosing those sources, as demonstrated in the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1217.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1230.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the applicant's right to freedom of expression was not interfered with in any other way by the seizure of documents, the government concludes that this seizure raises no issue under Article 10 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1230.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1242.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should the court hold otherwise, the government would recall that Article 10 of the Convention states that those exercising their right to freedom of expression have duties and responsibilities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1242.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1249.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In two areas, the government finds that the applicants did not respect those duties and responsibilities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1249.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1258.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, contrary to the impression it repeatedly gave, Telegraaf had not surrendered all the classified documents in its possession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1258.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1266.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After all, the judicial orders did in fact lead to the handover of additional documents that were not submitted initially.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1266.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1270.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no justification whatsoever for these omissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1270.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1281.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the articles in the Telegraaf went far beyond serving the public interest by exposing shortcomings within the Intelligence and Security Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1281.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1291.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They undoubtedly crossed the line between reporting on the leak itself and reporting on details of investigations by the IEVD, which is a totally different matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1291.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1306.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result, not only were the lives of IEVD informants and their relatives put at risk, but the manner of disclosure could also affect the willingness of existing and future sources to cooperate with the IEVD.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1306.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1312.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None of this serves any public interest of which the applicants claim to be the watchdog.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1312.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1324.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants invoked their rights to protect journalistic sources, but have themselves demonstrated a complete lack of care with regard to the safety of sources used by the IEVD.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1324.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1340.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In case the Court should find that Article 10 of the Convention is at issue, we submit that any interference with the rights to freedom of expression serve the legitimate aims of national security, the prevention of crime, and the protection of the rights of others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1340.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1348.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After all, a leak within the National Intelligence and Security Services poses a serious threat to national security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1348.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1360.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The possession of secret classified documents constitutes a criminal offense in case at hand, the lives and well-being of IEVD informants and their relatives were put at risk, as I said a moment ago.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1360.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1365.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the next question is whether that interference was prescribed by law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1365.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1374.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer to that question can only be affirmative, since the order was based on Article 96a of the Code of Criminal Procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1374.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1387.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as the Court confirmed in its judgment in the Sanoma case, this provision meets the requirements of accessibility and foreseeability and carries with it procedural safeguards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1387.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1409.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That brings me to the last question concerning the seizure of documents, namely whether the interference was necessary in a democratic society, or in the words of the Court, whether the reasons adduced by the national authorities to justify the interference were relevant and sufficient, and whether the measures taken were proportionate to the legitimate aims pursued.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1409.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1418.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would, at the outset, draw attention to the essential difference between the case at hand and the Sanoma case, in which the Court found a violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1418.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1429.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the lawfulness of the order to surrender the documents was assessed by a court before the documents were handed over to the public prosecutor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1429.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1438.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that this prior judicial review was the result of an ad hoc arrangement and not of legislation in force at the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1438.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1442.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dutch law is currently being amended on that particular point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1442.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1448.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having said that, the Court has repeatedly stated that it looks at the facts in concreto.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1448.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1455.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, in this particular case, judicial oversight prior to the surrender of the documents was carried out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1455.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1474.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant handed over a set of documents in a sealed envelope to the National Police Internal Investigations Department, after which this sealed envelope remained in a safe at the office of the investigating judge until the district court had been able to rule on the lawfulness of the order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1474.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1486.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I said earlier, the possession of secret classified documents constitutes a criminal offense, carrying a maximum penalty of six years imprisonment or a fine of 76,000 euros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1486.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1494.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Possessing such documents does not cease to be an offense, just because the perpetrator is a newspaper or a journalist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1494.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1504.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, it is crucial that unauthorized possession of secret classified documents is terminated as speedily as possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1504.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1511.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government considers the order to surrender the documents a perfectly proportionate measure under the circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1511.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1518.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I repeat that the measure would not have been necessary had the telegraph surrendered all the documents in the first place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1518.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1527.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In that regard, the order to surrender documents was the mildest possible measure to ensure return of all the documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1527.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1532.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was milder, for instance, than a search of the telegraph's premises.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1532.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1547.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This argument is reinforced by the cautious approach displayed by the authorities, allowing the telegraph to hand over the documents in a sealed envelope and leaving them sealed until the district court had had the opportunity to rule on the matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1547.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1565.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In comparison with cases where the court considered a seizure of documents to be in violation of the right to protection of journalistic sources towards the government's opinion, in Financial Times and Goodwin, both against the United Kingdom, the seizure concerned confidential information within private companies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1565.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1573.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, the rights of others were undoubtedly at stake, but not national security or the prevention of crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1573.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1582.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, in the Goodwin case, the applicant had also separately been forbidden to publish the information obtained, which clearly never happened in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1582.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1592.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it may, a considerable minority of the court in the Goodwin case found the interests of the private company constituted a sufficient justification for the seizure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1592.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1600.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This would apply a fortiori to the legitimate interests at stake in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1600.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1608.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We cannot but conclude, therefore, that the order to surrender the documents did not in any way constitute a violation of the applicant's freedom of expression.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1608.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1616.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, I will discuss the committal to prison of the two journalists for failure to comply with the judicial order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1616.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1632.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The comments I made in relation to the order to surrender the documents pertaining to the question of whether the protection of journalistic sources, and hence an interference with Article 10 of the Convention, are at issue, and pertaining to the question of duties and responsibilities, are equally relevant here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1632.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1638.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I respectfully request that the court to take them into account.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1638.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1647.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Obviously, however, a committal to prison constitutes an interference with a person's right to private life, guaranteed in Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1647.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1658.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The statutory basis for the committal to prison of witnesses refusing to testify is Article 294, paragraph 1, of the Code of Criminal Procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1658.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1664.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court held in its judgment in the Foscale case that this basis in domestic law is adequate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1664.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1674.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The legitimate aim here is primarily the prevention of crime, which leaves the question of whether the interference was necessary in a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1674.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1688.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The primary consideration is the fact that the journalists refused to answer most of the questions put by the investigating judge, not only questions that could arguably have a bearing on protection of sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1688.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1695.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That being so, there is no compelling reason why the interference of the court is not a valid basis for the judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1695.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1709.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no compelling reason why the judge could not reasonably avail himself of the power vested in him by virtue of the Code of Criminal Procedure, as would have been possible with regard to witnesses who are not journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1709.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1714.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the facts here are significantly different from those in the Foscale case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1714.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1722.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the latter case, the applicant was detained for 17 days, whereas the committal in the present case lasted three days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1722.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1731.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Foscale case, the journalists in the present case were clearly the only persons able to shed light on certain elements of the criminal case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1731.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1738.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regard to the committal to prison two, we therefore conclude that there has been no violation of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1738.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1746.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lastly, I come to the complaint concerning the Ayyubids' use of special powers against the two journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1746.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1757.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here, too, there is no doubt that the use of these powers constituted an interference with the journalists' right to private life, which served the legitimate aim of national security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1757.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1769.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In that regard, let me first stress that there is a real difference between the activities of intelligence and security services on the one hand and law enforcement authorities on the other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1769.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1779.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This difference has a bearing on how covert action by the former category is assessed, in the sense that a wider margin of appreciation should be applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1779.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1789.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The difference also affects the extent to which the government can be open in its communications, including in the context of the present proceedings before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1789.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1804.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is of crucial importance, however, is that the supervisory committee can, and in fact did, have access to all the information in the context of both the lawfulness investigation and the complaint advisory process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1804.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1819.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As set out in my overview of the procedures followed, the committee basically concluded that the investigation had been lawful, meaning that it had been necessary and in accordance with the law and with the criteria of proportionality and subsidiarity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1819.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1832.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The minister did not deviate from the committee's advice and recommendations in respect of the lawfulness investigation and the complaint advisory process, but instead adopted them in their entirety.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1832.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1843.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our written observations, we explained in detail why we consider the use of special powers in the present case to be in accordance with the law, i.e. the Intelligence and Security Services Act,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1843.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1846.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which is accessible and foreseeable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1846.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1854.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In doing so, we referred extensively to the required safeguards developed by the court in its judgment in the case of Weber and Saravia versus Germany.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1854.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1866.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Scrutiny of the present case in the light of the court's judgment in the relevant case of Kennedy versus the United Kingdom would lead to exactly the same conclusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1866.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1874.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With the interference thus being firmly based in law, the final question is whether it was necessary in a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1874.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1884.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A leak of secret classified information damages the IJVD's ability to operate reliably and hence national security as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1884.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1906.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case at hand, a large quantity of documents, over 1,000 pages, had been leaked, including reports of conversation with human sources, scheme reports, transcriptions of intercepted telephone calls and so forth, extremely sensitive information with particular implications for the safety of the IJVD human sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1906.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1923.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This posed a direct threat to the pillars on which the statutory duty of secrecy in the Intelligence and Security Services Act is based, namely protection of sources, protection of current status of intelligence, and protection of working methods.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1923.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1928.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These three interests are why secrecy must be observed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1928.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1938.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the leaked documents concerned an investigation into a hardcore criminal organization that had a reputation for serious violence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1938.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1951.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since Telegraf had published both code names and contextual information, there was a real danger that disclosure of the identity of the IJVD sources would result in revenge attacks against these people or their relatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1952.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1964.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the continued uncertainty about the exact volume and nature of documents which had been leaked, it was impossible to assess the damage to current investigations and dangers to other human sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1964.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1968.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No effective alternatives were available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1968.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1972.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Openly asking for the information would have been to no avail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1972.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1980.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of a leak, those involved have a vested interest in keeping the facts and circumstances secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1980.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1987.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The use of special powers was terminated by order of the District Court, ruling in interim injunction proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1987.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2006.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In view of all these facts and circumstances, the government considers that there were interests at stake in this case which outweighed both the applicant's interest in protecting journalistic sources and the applicant's right to private life, namely national security and the prevention of serious crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2006.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2018.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the government's opinion, the exercise of special powers in relation to the journalists was therefore justified, having regard to paragraph 2 of articles 8 and 10 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2018.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2025.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It fully complied with the requirements of subsidiarity and proportionality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2025.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2026.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2026.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2026.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2036.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2039.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. De Kemp.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2046.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2051.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2051.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2062.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for the third time in a relatively short period, this court will have to examine judicial coercive measures against journalists taken by the Dutch government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2062.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2071.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The previous two times, this court rightly criticized the actions and conduct of the government with respect to journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2071.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2094.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Voskaal case, this court ruled in clear terms as follows on the actions of the government to find out the identity of the source of the journalist Voskaal, and I quote, whatever the consequences might have been for the source, the court is struck by the lengths to which Netherlands authorities were prepared to go to learn his or her identity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2094.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2111.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such far-reaching measures cannot but discourage persons who have a true and accurate information relating to wrongdoing of the kind here at issue from coming forward and sharing their knowledge with the press in future cases, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2111.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2125.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Sannema case, this court again stated in clear terms how seriously it takes infringements on the protection of journalistic sources, and again I quote your court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2125.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2156.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court knows that orders to disclose sources potentially have a detrimental impact not only on the source, whose identity may be revealed, but also on the newspaper or other publication against which the order is directed, whose reputation may be negatively affected in the eyes of future potential sources by the disclosure, and on the members of the public who have an interest in receiving information imparted through anonymous sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2156.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2163.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The present complaint is equally fundamental as the complaints in the previous two cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2163.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2169.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has again seriously overstepped the boundaries set by this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2169.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2184.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has in different ways and over a long period of time infringed on the right of freedom of expression enshrined in Article 10 of the Convention and the right to protect journalistic sources arising therefrom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2184.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2200.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has not treated applicants of the Haas &amp; Moss as journalists, but as targets within the meaning of Article 6, Paragraph 2 of the Dutch Intelligence and Security Services Act, to which I will refer as the Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2200.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2224.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Dutch government, the Haas &amp; Moss are persons who, because of the objectives they pursue or their activities, give rise to serious suspicion that they constitute a danger to the continued existence of the democratic legal order or the security or other weighty interests of the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2224.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2235.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government apparently has learned nothing from the previous two convictions by this court, and has decided to continue its actions as it did before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2235.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2244.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not only did the Dutch authorities investigate the sources of journalists of the Telegraaf in 2006, but did it again in 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2244.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2258.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also in 2009, the Dutch courts prohibited the Secret Service from continuing the use of its special powers against the journalists in that matter, which matter is also pending before this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2258.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2266.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to learn the identity of the sources of the Haas &amp; Moss, the government has undertaken the following actions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2266.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2277.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One, the General Intelligence and Security Services, the Secret Service, has for a long time, over a period of several months, listened in on the Haas &amp; Moss.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2277.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2286.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two, the Secret Service has for a long time systematically kept the Haas &amp; Moss under observation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2286.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2300.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Three, the Public Prosecution Service, or the Secret Service, we don't know who did it, has retrieved the telecom and print data of the Haas &amp; Moss from the 1st of September 2005.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2300.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2315.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And based thereon, it could determine exactly with whom the Haas &amp; Moss have called since that date, by whom they have been called, and using positioning via GSM masts, where they have been.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2315.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2324.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The public, the four, the Public Prosecution Service has ordered the seizure of documents that were in the hands of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2324.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2342.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And five, the Public Prosecution Service has knowingly agreed to the three-day detention of the Haas &amp; Moss when they were heard as witnesses in the criminal proceedings against the person who leaked state secret documents outside the Secret Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2342.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2353.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to the use of these coercive measures by both the Public Prosecution Service and the Secret Service, the Haas &amp; Moss have for a long time considered themselves to be hunted game.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2353.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2373.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that feeling was justified, considering the fact that the government in these proceedings for the first time explicitly recognised that the Haas &amp; Moss are persons who constitute a danger to the continued existence of the democratic legal order, or the security, or other way, to the interests of the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2373.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2380.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The actions by the Dutch government are incorrect, incomprehensible, and exceed all bounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2380.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2384.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After all, Mrs. de Haas &amp; Moss have done nothing more</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2384.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2388.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>than exercise their task as journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2388.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2394.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In a democratic society, it is their task to fulfil their role as a public watchdog.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2394.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2403.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This task is quite relevant when persons employed, or formerly employed by the Secret Service, appear to be leaking state secret documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2403.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2409.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This very fact in itself already constitutes a matter of public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2409.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2421.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is all the more so if the leaked documents end up in the criminal circuit, even precisely the criminal circuit to which the documents relate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2421.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2440.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If journalists discover such a wrongdoing has been perpetrated within a governmental organisation, it is their journalistic duty to publish about it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2440.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2451.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In response to the Voskow judgment, the government has prepared a legislative proposal that should provide a legal basis for the protection of journalistic sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2451.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2460.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I remind you that the Voskow judgment dates from more than four and a half years ago, and there still only is a legislative proposal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2460.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2472.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is unclear when this legislative proposal will be discussed in the House of Representatives and will be or may be passed into law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2472.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2479.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the government is in no hurry to pass this proposal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2479.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2489.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Sánamá judgment, this court ruled that Dutch legislation, to the extent relating to the seizure of journalistic material, is deficient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2489.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2502.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After all, Article 96A of the Dutch Code of Criminal Procedure does not provide for the review by a judge or an independent and impartial decision-making body.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2502.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2507.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, this clear wording of this court has not incited the government to action.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2507.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2517.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 96A of the Criminal Code of Criminal Procedure has not been adjusted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2517.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2534.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the applicants in these proceedings have made agreements with the Public Prosecution Office in order to have the seized documents sealed and deposited in the safe of the examining judge, it is clear that also in this case, there has been no prior judicial review of the seizure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2534.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2552.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having regard to the provisions of the Sánamá judgment of this court, also this case does involve a violation of Article 10 of the Convention, for the very same reason that the legislation still is deficient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2552.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2561.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, the court, the applicants draw the court's attention to the new instructions on the application of coercive measures against journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2561.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2574.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These instructions came into force on the 1st of March 2012, and they originate from the College of Procurators General and therefore are not official legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2574.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2589.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although these instructions are an improvement compared to earlier versions, the instructions do not apply to retrieving telecom and print data, nor to the use of coercive measures by the Secret Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2589.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2607.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When the Secret Service uses special powers against journalists, it still does so without a prior consideration of the interests involved by judicial or other independent and impartial body.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2607.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2611.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now address the questions of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2611.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2625.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question of the court was whether or not, in this case, the legal safeguards in place were sufficient to protect the applicants, the House and Moss, from abuse by the IJVD of its power.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2625.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2628.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer to this question is simple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2628.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2635.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, with regard to the use of special powers by the Secret Service, the legislation is deficient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2635.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2643.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason for this is that no prior review by a judge or an independent and impartial decision-making body is involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2643.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2658.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the situation is exactly the same as in the claim for seizure of journalistic material, which, according to this court, constituted a violation of Article 10 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2658.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2668.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decision to have the Secret Service use special powers is taken by the Minister of Interior and Kingdom Relations or by the head of the Secret Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2668.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2679.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Commission for the Supervision of the Intelligence and Security Services is authorized to conduct a subsequent review of such use.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2679.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2686.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prior to the use of special powers, journalists do not have any safeguards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2686.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2705.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The lack of legal protection continues once special powers are being used, as nobody knows whether the Secret Service carries out any investigation, which investigation methods it uses, and since when and during which period it has carried out the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2705.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2718.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not until a few months after the House and Moss had been designated as targets by the government did they become aware of the fact that the Secret Service was using special powers against them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2718.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2730.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They acquired this knowledge after they had been given access to some official reports from the Secret Service to the Public Prosecution Service in May 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2730.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2744.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the House and Moss had not by chance had the opportunity to inspect these official reports, they would have never become aware of the fact that the Secret Service had been carrying out an investigation into them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2744.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2756.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the person against whom an investigation by the Secret Service is carried out is from the start on always three to nil behind.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2756.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2769.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only legal protection available to the House and Moss under the Act was filing a complaint to the National Ombudsman pursuant to the provisions of Articles 83 and 84 of the Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2769.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2780.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has meanwhile recognized that this procedure does not provide an effective remedy within the meaning of Article 13 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2780.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2794.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, to make use of this judicial procedure, one must first become aware of the use of special powers, and finding out about that is extremely difficult.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2794.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2813.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If and when a period of five years after the use of special powers has lapsed, Article 34 of the Act imposes on the Minister the obligation to decide whether or not a report can be issued to the person against whom the special powers were exercised.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2813.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2820.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, the Minister has not issued such a report to the House and Moss.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2820.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2838.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, Article 47 of the Act grants every person the right to request the Minister to inform him of whether personal data concerning him have been processed by or on behalf of the Secret Service, and if so, which personal data.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2838.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2853.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants filed such a request to the Minister in April of this year, although the applicants have thereafter repeatedly asked the Minister by telephone to respond as soon as possible, in connection with the plea in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2853.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2861.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Minister has not given any substantive response to this request so far.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2861.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2873.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, the House and Moss have instituted preliminary injunction proceedings against the government in order to have the use of special powers stopped.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2873.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2878.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These proceedings also do not constitute an effective remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2878.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2887.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of preliminary relief proceedings, again, only a subsequent review is involved, no prior review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2887.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2900.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And these injunction proceedings can only take place, again, after it has been discovered that special powers are being used or will be used.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2900.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2911.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The conclusion must therefore be that Dutch law does not provide the House and Moss with any safeguards against any abuse of powers by the Secret Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2911.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2914.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now my colleague, Mr. Lepola, will continue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2914.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2914.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2920.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2923.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2923.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2925.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will address the second question of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2925.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2943.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whether or not in this case, the public interest requiring the maintenance of the secrecy of information properly in the keeping of the BVD AIVD alone outweighed the applicant's interest in maintaining the secrecy of the identity of their informants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2943.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2951.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government obviously has an interest in the maintenance of the secrecy of information properly in the keeping of the Secret Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2951.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2956.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, however, that interest should be put into perspective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2956.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2974.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the publication of the 21st of January 2006, the Telegraaf has not disclosed any secret information, but only informed the public that state secret information of the Secret Service circulated in the criminal circuit of Amsterdam.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2974.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2981.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It requires no explanation that this publication should be regarded as a contribution to a debate of general interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2981.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2993.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the decision of your court in the Van Hannover 2 case from February this year, and that the Telegraaf fulfilled its vital public watchdog role with this publication.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2993.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3001.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The documents that the Haasen was obtained are related to the period 1997 till the beginning of 2000.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3001.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3016.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government's interest in maintaining the secrecy of information should therefore be put into perspective in this case as it concerned relatively outdated old information, which moreover was already public in certain circles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3016.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3026.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, I do wish to emphasize once more that the Telegraaf has been extremely prudent in the handling of the information it obtained from its sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3026.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3033.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was not only confirmed by the then Minister of Justice, Mr. Donner, but also by the Dutch courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3033.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3044.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I quote from the judgment of the preliminary relief judge of the District Court of The Hague of the 21st of June 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3044.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3063.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is also the case if the two journalists have only acted as an intermediary, a conduit, which regards the state's secret information at issue here in the sense that, one, the documents in question circulated elsewhere, according to them in criminal circles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3063.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3069.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two, these documents have come into their possession unrequested and unsolicited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3069.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3087.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And three, they, after verifying with the IVD that copies of state's secret documents of the BVD or the AVD were actually involved, have exercised restraint in quoting from them in their publications in the Telegraaf.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3087.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3088.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>End of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3088.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3102.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And another quote from that verdict, these preliminary relief proceedings have not revealed any evidence to suspect that the two journalists have basically done more than what paragraph 4.7 refers</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3102.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3106.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to as acting as an intermediary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3106.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3119.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The preliminary relief judge of the District Court in The Hague and the Supreme Court also assumed that the two journalists could not be regarded as targets within the meaning of Article VI, paragraph 2a of the Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3119.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3134.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, and that's very important, the Secret Service has never objected to the contents of the publication in Telegraaf, nor requested the Telegraaf informally or formally to reframe from further disclosing certain information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3134.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3139.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No phone call, no letter, no request, no summon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3139.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3142.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I stress this because that's a very relevant fact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3142.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3150.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's also decided in the judgment of your court in the case Financial Times against the UK from December 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3150.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3163.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government's interest in keeping information secret has not been prejudiced by publications in the Telegraaf, but, and that's again important, by the leaking of information from the Secret Service to the criminal circuit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3163.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3173.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The actions of the government were therefore not aimed at preventing further disclosure of information in the Telegraaf, but at tracing the leak within the Secret Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3173.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3176.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was the aim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3176.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3180.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, I note in this context that the Telegraaf has been very helpful here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3180.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3194.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prior to the publication on the 21st of January 2006, the Telegraaf has provided a copy of the written information it had obtained from its sources to the then head of the Secret Service, a copy of all the documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3194.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3201.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Secret Service just knew from Friday, the 20th of January 2006, which documents were involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3201.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3208.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the government decided, sorry, the government subsequently took two decisions that are extremely relevant to the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3208.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3217.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One, the government decided to have the required investigation carried out not by the public prosecution service, but by the Secret Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3217.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3234.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And two, the government decided not to limit the investigation to an internal one, into the leak within the Secret Service, but also to immediately start an investigation into the identity of the journalist's sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3234.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3248.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although it had reported to the public prosecution service on the 22nd of January 2006, so one day after publication, the Secret Service started an investigation of its own in which it used extremely far-reaching powers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3248.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3253.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This deliberate choice has the following consequences in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3253.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3265.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An investigation by the public prosecution service is subject to judicial review prior to the investigation by the examining judge and after the investigation by the criminal court judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3265.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3268.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An investigation, as Mr. De Kamp has explained,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3268.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3274.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by the Secret Service is carried out without any judicial review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3274.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3281.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The investigation against a journalist by the Secret Service could be carried out secretly without the Secret Service having to account for it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3281.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3286.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is also apparent from the government's course of action in the civil proceedings in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3286.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3290.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government did not want to comment on the investigation anyway.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3290.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3299.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government even has refused to answer questions of the court of whether or not any powers had been exercised against the journalist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3299.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3313.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this way, the government has also evaded the burden of proof, resting on it regarding whether the use of powers against the journalist complied with the principles of proportionality and subsidiarity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3313.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3325.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under the subsidiarity principle, the Secret Service should first have tried to trace through an internal investigation who could have leaked information from the Secret Service to the criminal circuit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3325.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3328.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was a realistic option.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3328.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3332.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That this was a realistic option appears from the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3332.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3342.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I already stressed before, the Telegraaf has provided to the Secret Service a copy of all the documents it had received from its sources on Friday.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3342.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3346.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From that time, the Secret Service knew which document had been leaked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3346.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3380.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 6 February 2006, the head of the Secret Service issued an official report to the Public Prosecution Service in which he stated, I quote, given the nature and composition of the set of documents with state secret data concerning operational activities of the BVD that the Telegraaf has received, I can inform you that four probably former employees of the BVD and or the IVD have or had access to copies or originals of the complete set of documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3380.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3395.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So within no more than 16 days after the publication of the Telegraaf, it had been established by means of an internal investigation using documents obtained from the Telegraaf that no more than four employees of the Secret Service could regard it as a potential leak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3395.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3402.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we assume that within a couple of days, these four had been limited to one person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3402.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3416.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Secret Service has deliberately opted for not limiting the investigation into the leak to an internal investigation, but also decided to immediately take extremely far-reaching coercive measures against journalists in order to trace their sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3416.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3423.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is apparent from, again, an official report also dated the 6th of February.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3423.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3452.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's exhibit 21 to the complaint in which the head of the Secret Service informed the Public Prosecution Service that the investigations by the Secret Service had revealed that journalists in the Haas and Moss had meetings with several persons on the 24th of January and on the 26th of January, and noted explicitly with respect to the meeting on the 26th of January 2006, I quote, this meeting has to do with the above-mentioned publication in the Telegraaf.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3452.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3458.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the Secret Service was listening in, they knew what was discussed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3458.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3470.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same official report also states that two of the aforementioned persons, I quote, had already had telephone contact with Bart Moss prior to the aforementioned publications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3470.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3477.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The journalists did not get to see these official reports by coincidence until May 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3477.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3489.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, it was also established that the Secret Service had continued using powers against the journalists at least until in May 2006, so January, February, March, April, May.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3489.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3507.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is apparent from the official report submitted as exhibit 22, in which the Secret Service reports to the Public Prosecution Service that the journalists at the Haas and Moss, I quote, are making preparations for publishing an article about Paul H. in the short term.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3507.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3510.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What exactly made this official report so relevant and shocking?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3510.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3521.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prior to 4 May 2006, the Haas and Moss were the only persons who knew of the planned publication of 6 May.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3521.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3526.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had not discussed this with anyone else prior to 4 May.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3526.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3529.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither with people within the Telegraaf, nor with people outside the Telegraaf.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3529.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3532.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not even the chief editors of the Telegraaf were informed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3532.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3540.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Haas and Moss had only had telephone contact with each other about this planned publication of 6 May.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3540.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3550.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the only possible conclusion is that the Haas and Moss were still being listened in on by the Secret Service at the beginning of May 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3550.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3556.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The problem is that the Dutch authorities opt for the easiest way in cases like this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3556.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3559.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have seen that again and again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3559.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3569.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, tracing the source of the journalist, because it's much easier to start an investigation at the end of the information chain than at the beginning of the information chain.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3569.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3572.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I refer to the drawing in my notes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3572.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3576.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tracing the source of the journalist is relatively easy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3576.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3587.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, by retrieving retroactively data that show with whom the journalist has called and by whom the journalist had been called, has been called prior to the publication.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3587.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3598.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By listening in on a journalist and keeping him or her under observation, it can also be established with whom he or she has had contact after the publication.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3598.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3601.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is exactly what happened in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3601.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3616.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As appeared afterwards, the government has retrieved telecom data of both journalists as from 1 September 2005 and as appeared from the official reports, has listened in on the journalist and kept him under surveillance or observation for months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3616.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3628.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The official reports also show that the Secret Service attention was aroused by another person or other persons fairly soon after it had proceeded to use special powers against the journalist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3628.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3635.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a quote from the judgment of the Court of Appeal in The Hague of 31 August 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3635.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3639.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For now, we arrive at the essence of this dispute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3639.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3657.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court of Appeal ruled, and I quote, in the absence of further information on that person or of those persons, the Court of Appeal will assume for the time being that it is a person or persons with regard to whom the journalistic source protection is not an issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3657.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3659.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>End of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3659.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3666.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Court of Appeal, the Secret Service should immediately thereafter cease the use of special powers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3666.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3669.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the Telegraaf believe this is not enough.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3669.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3679.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the ruling that the use of powers should be ceased after another person has drawn the Secret Service attention touches on the essence of source protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3679.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3686.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why could not the person who drew the Secret Service attention be the source of the journalist?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3686.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3698.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This Court will understand that I cannot comment on this, but I draw the Court's attention to this point because the Court of Appeal's ruling is not only puzzling, but even fundamentally wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3698.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3702.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then I'm, of course, referring to the judgment of the Court of Appeal, the Hague.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3702.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3715.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For it leads to a remarkable conclusion that the Secret Service can go on listening in until the source of the journalist has been identified, which is precisely what this case is about.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3715.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3727.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Professor Schout has commented very clearly on this ruling and concluded, I quote, that would be tantamount to granting full license, which in my view is incompatible with the principle of the ECHR.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3727.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3731.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not permitted unless.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3731.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3732.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I come to my conclusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3732.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3739.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unfortunately, the Supreme Court has not allowed the Telegraaf's objections against the contested rulings of the Court of Appeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3739.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3745.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's the main reason why the Telegraaf and the applicants has applied to this Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3745.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3752.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Supreme Court, the position taken by the Telegraaf amounts to making the right to protect sources absolute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3752.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3753.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that's incorrect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3753.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3757.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Telegraaf is aware that the right to protect sources may be limited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3757.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3770.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to consistent case law of this Court, taking a measure to break the right to protect sources is in violation of Article 10 of the Convention unless it's justified by an overriding requirement in the public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3770.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3784.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, there is no such overriding requirement because, at least initially, it would have surfaced to carry out an internal investigation within the Secret Service to find a leak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3784.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3793.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the government has taken disproportionate coercive measures against journalists, DAS, and Moss for far too long, for at least months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3793.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3795.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't know how long for at least months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3795.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3806.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Without judicial review, these facts tip the balance of competing interest in favor of the interest of democratic society in securing a free press.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3806.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3806.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3812.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3813.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Le Poole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3816.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3821.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your interventions in this first round.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3821.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3823.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn now to the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3829.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3832.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>OK.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3832.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3833.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Ziemele, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3836.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3838.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3838.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3842.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would have, roughly speaking, two questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3842.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3851.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are addressed to the government primarily, but of course the applicant representatives are very welcome to comment if they find it appropriate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3853.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3871.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the questions really relate to the application of the Intelligence and Security Service Act or what the government has named as IVD investigations in relation to the applicants in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3871.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3889.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would really appreciate if the government were to specify more concretely what kind of threat to the national security did the applicants pose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3889.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3896.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What exactly was in their actions of such a character?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3896.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3903.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because as far as I can see, Article 6, Paragraph 2 requires a rather high threshold.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3903.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3909.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So what was in their actions that endangered the national security?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3909.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3933.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if you could, in this connection, also clarify this contradiction that we have in the case file when it comes to the application of Article 6, Paragraph 2, where the applicants considered targets or non-targets on the debate in the Court of Appeal, indeed as just referred by the applicant's representative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3933.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3968.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question, also linked to IVD investigations, is the government of the opinion that the minister's authorization of these special investigative activities on the basis of the Act, that the minister's authorization, or sometimes it seems that it is the head of the Secret Service, is a sufficient safeguard for the purposes of Article 8 and Article 10.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3968.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3973.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I understand that you will obviously look at it in the broader picture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3973.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3987.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I'm more interested that you address the whole issue of prior guarantees in relation to the possible interferences with fundamental human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3987.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3987.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3989.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3991.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge López Guerra.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3997.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4004.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yeah, my question refers to the, directed to both the government and the application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4005.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4009.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first one refers to the nature of these documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4010.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4030.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mean, these documents were in possession of the Telegraph, and whose surrender was asked by the government from the Telegraph, where they were the same original documents which physically had been in possession of the Secret Services and had been given to the Telegraph.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4030.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4034.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a material, physical identity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4034.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4049.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question, also both parties, in page 11 of the observation of the government, there is reference to several investigations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4049.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4060.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is reference to an investigation by the AIBD under section six of section two of the Intelligence Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4060.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4069.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is also a reference to an investigation by the National Police Internal Investigation Department.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4069.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4078.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also there is reference to an investigation by the Secretary General of the Ministry of the Interior and Kingdom Relations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4078.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4102.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then it says in paragraph 37 that before the start of the investigation and at the request of the Minister of the Interior and Kingdom Relations, the supervisory committee of the Intelligence and Security Service examined whether the investigation had been designed and organized in such a way as to comply with the requirement of the civil service information and so on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4102.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4116.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, my question is concerning the particular investigation by the AIBD using special powers, that seems to include telephone tapping.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4116.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4128.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This investigation was subject previously to any kind of control or advice or authorization by the supervisory committee or by any other independent agency.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4128.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4134.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's my question because I don't get it very clearly from this government observation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4134.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4134.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4136.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4137.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Judge Myjer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Egbert Myjer</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4141.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4143.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thanks, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4143.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4173.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, on paragraph 37 of the government's observations, just to go in more detail, the supervisory committee for the intelligence and security services, the CETEVD in Dutch, is that supervisory committee, that's the first question, is that also for the applicants in general a sufficient independent body.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4173.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4182.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'd just like to hear what also the applicant thinks about the role in general of the supervisory committee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4182.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4196.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But then, indeed, the question arises, did the supervisory committee ex ante, so on forehand, not just afterwards, have a look at the special powers or not, special powers exercised?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4196.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4220.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in that connection, I go to paragraph 82 of the government's observations, where it says that where the person in respect of whom the power is to be exercised is acting in a special capacity, for instance, as a journalist, this must be stated in the request for authorization together with the reasons why it is necessary to exercise the power in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4220.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4251.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there, in fact, we come to the question also asked by Judge Ziemele when a journalist, when against a journalist, looking at 82, special powers are exercised, is it indeed just the minister who, at the request of the head of secret service, authorizes or is there a special, some kind of special procedure because it is about a person in special capacity like a journalist?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4251.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4269.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The last question, a question addressed especially to the applicant, as I take it, the documents in question were documents or copies of documents belonging to the secret service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4269.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4276.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They came from a secret service and whether they were originals or copies made of originals, they belonged to the secret service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4276.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4284.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So what the secret service does is, hey, these things are stolen from us or copied from us in an illegal way, hand them back.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4284.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4286.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is there anything against that?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4286.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4294.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is there anything against a surrender order when people ask something back what belongs to them?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4294.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4294.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These are my questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4298.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4299.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Okay, thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4301.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4310.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, I propose to take a break, a 15-minute break to resume the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4373.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4373.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4413.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4419.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sit please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4419.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4422.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4422.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4437.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Taking in account the number of questions, I think I can give you 15 minutes each part to answer the questions and to make some conclusions about the other part.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4437.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4439.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I give the floor to Mr. Böcker.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4444.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4456.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will, to the best of my ability, answer the questions of several of the judges, as well as respond to a few points made by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4457.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4461.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I apologize beforehand for anything I might overlook.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4463.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4476.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, as always, we are fully prepared to provide the court and our opponent party with any additional information that might be required by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4477.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4493.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, Judge Zimmler asked the question, what kind of threat the two journalists constituted and why they were considered targets rather than non-targets.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4493.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4497.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To answer this question, several factors are relevant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4497.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4505.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the case involved, as I have said, an investigation under Section 6, Subsection 2A of the Intelligence and Security Services Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4505.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4524.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, an investigation of organizations and, and these words are important, individuals whose objectives or activities give rise to grave suspicions that they pose a threat to continued existence of the democratic legal order or to security or other important interests of the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4524.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4543.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any leak, especially a leak as extensive as in the present case, and I told you there were a thousand pages involved at least, immediately poses a risk to the AIVD's integrity and effective functioning and therefore to national security which the AIVD seeks to protect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4543.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4548.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The AIVD enjoys far-reaching powers in the context of national security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4548.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4558.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if its integrity cannot be relied upon, this directly undermines its legitimacy and confidence in it, leaving it unable to carry out its tasks effectively.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4558.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4564.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For instance, sources and foreign agencies would no longer be willing to cooperate with it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4564.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4567.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This directly impacts national security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4567.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4571.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was therefore essential to launch the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4571.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4581.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The principal aim, as I have stated, was to examine the leaked documents and establish whether more documents had been leaked and who was in possession of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4581.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4597.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the Telegraaf had handed over a set of documents to the AIVD consisting of copies of the classified documents, it was unclear whether they comprised all the classified documents or whether further classified information had been leaked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4597.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4601.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The two journalists were in possession of the leaked documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4601.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4607.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And given the purpose of the investigation, therefore qualified as targets.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4607.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4613.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the record, we would note that the purpose of the investigation was not to determine the identity of the journalist's source.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4613.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4615.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have said it a few times before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4615.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4625.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I refer particularly to paragraphs 48 and 144 and following of our observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4625.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4642.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the journalists being in possession of these documents with all the risks involved, it not being clear whether they had in fact returned the documents was the trigger that made them into targets.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4642.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4648.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is as much information as I can give in reply to your question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4648.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4663.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And perhaps as a general caveat, and this perhaps may come back in some of the other answers I will give, and I have said it before, when we are in the area of the Secret Services, there are some limitations to what we can say.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4663.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4667.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I trust the Court understands that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4667.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4683.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question of Judge Ziemelle was whether it is only the Minister of the Interior who is responsible and who is taking the decision to launch an investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4683.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4685.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer is yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4685.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4688.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is the Minister of the Interior.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4688.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4697.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And he or she is under no obligation to consult the supervisory committee or any other body beforehand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4697.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4698.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why is that so?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4698.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4712.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is so because the Minister is responsible, is ultimately responsible, is politically responsible, has to respond to questions from Parliament, and can eventually be dismissed if Parliament doesn't agree.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4712.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4735.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bringing in the supervisory committee or any other body which may be set up would compromise and jeopardize, rather, the standing of that committee, and it would jeopardize its ability afterwards to truly supervise what has been going on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4735.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4742.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, there is no special procedure beforehand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4742.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4750.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That brings me to the first question of Judge López-Guerra.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4750.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4755.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What was the nature of the documents concerned?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4755.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4772.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The documents proved to be copies of working files of the ancestor of the AIVD, the BVD, in fact, containing sensitive operational data, broadly speaking, for the period 1996 to 2000.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4772.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4779.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the years are not crucial, as we have explained in our observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4779.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4793.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>About investigations of the Secret Service into possible links between the underworld and legitimate society and into possible breaches of ethical behavior in public administration and the courts in the Netherlands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4793.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4801.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the nature and content of the data, their interconnection and the classification marked on them, they were clearly secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4801.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4815.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to go a little bit more into detail, the documents concerned secret classified reports of conversations with the BVD's human sources in the criminal community, who are referred to by their codenames.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4815.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4823.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These reports contain detailed information about the criminal group around Mink K and their associates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4823.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4838.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secret, another category, secret classified internal reports about the status and progress of the investigation concerned and where and how special powers, for example, the power to install surveillance microphones, could be applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4838.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4845.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Reports of discussions with the national public prosecutor for BVD-related matters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4845.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4855.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Official reports of a hearing by the Vieringa committee, which investigated the inter-regional crime squad in the regional recherche team.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4855.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4867.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Confidential police notification forms addressed to the BVD and concerning organized crime, including all kinds of detailed information and official reports of the criminal intelligence service findings and information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4867.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4876.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Internal memos about strictly confidential consultations with the committee on the intelligence and security services of the House of Representatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4876.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4880.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secret classified analysis of intercepted telephone conversations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4880.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4883.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Transcripts of intercepted telephone conversations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4883.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4888.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secret classified reports of conversations between persons mentioned by name.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4888.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4911.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in as much as Judge López-Guerra was referring rather than to the contents of the documents, or their actual incarnation, to use that word, I should say that the documents, as I have said before, turned out to be copies of originals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4911.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4916.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We're speaking here about the first set that was handed over on the 20th of January.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4916.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4927.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it wasn't simply, it wasn't sure whether other copies still were circulating or were in the hands of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4927.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4942.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Later on, and this is crucial to the government's position that we're defending here today, it transpired that further copies were indeed in the hands of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4942.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4955.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it took at least two orders to surrender them to provide those further copies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4955.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4957.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me see.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4957.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4973.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That brings me to the second question of Judge López-Guerra, which would seem to cover also the first question of Judge Mayer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4973.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4996.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whether the supervisory committee looked at the special powers, the use of special powers ex-unters, particularly since there was a special category of persons involved, namely journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4996.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5000.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should say the following here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5000.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5013.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Where the person in respect of whom the power is to be exercised is acting in a special capacity, for example as a journalist, this must be stated in the request to the minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5013.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5020.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, as I have said before, this is all still within the ambit of the responsible minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5020.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5038.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For authorization, together with the reasons why it is necessary to exercise the power in this case, where an existing authorization is to be renewed, a recent request that meets the minimum requirements set out must be submitted on each occasion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5038.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5053.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A request for renewal of an authorization to exercise a special power, therefore, provides a natural opportunity for evaluation, including the question of whether the exercise of the power has yielded the information relevant to the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5053.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5094.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, the conclusion is no, there is no separate procedure different from what is customary, but as I have just said, the nature of the persons investigated as being journalists is an element, an important element which has to be stated in the request to the minister, so the minister is fully aware of the important stakes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5094.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5113.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since Judge Mayer's second question was related to the applicants, I will not now spend any time on that question, but I do have a couple of comments with regards to the applicants' presentation of this morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5113.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5126.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants forcefully state that the journalists did not do anything else than their journalistic duty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5126.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5133.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would repeat myself if I said that we are of a different opinion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5133.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5142.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We think that they certainly did their duty by bringing to light what they seek in the Secret Service, which is a matter of public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5142.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5153.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also think they went beyond that by giving too much information from the, too much content from the file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5153.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5156.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We can have a long discussion about whether they did.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5156.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5160.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The proof is simply in the articles that were published in the Telegraaf.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5160.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5163.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are in the Court's possession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5163.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5165.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I do not recall we had them translated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5165.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5167.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We, of course, still do that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5167.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5190.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Suffice to say that there is reference to code names and contextual information, and the government is of the opinion that in publishing these elements, access by third parties to the informants involved would have been possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5190.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5201.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants also criticized the fact that there was no judicial control ex ante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5201.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5202.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That may be true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5202.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5206.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I cannot deny that is the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5206.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5234.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All that matters, and I borrow a few other Latin words, is that in CASU, the arrangement was fully satisfactory, one can criticize the arrangement from a national law point of view, but what we're here for today is to see whether under the convention the arrangement was satisfactory, and we submit that it was.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5234.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5239.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have explained all the details in my pleadings before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5239.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5257.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants also seem to depart from the assumption that permission for use of special powers should have been asked from them, or from anybody else, I'm not sure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5257.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5262.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, let's be short and frank on this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5262.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5275.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Asking permission for the use of special powers to those investigated or third parties who have a direct interest in the matter, that would be totally unworkable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5275.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5281.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me see.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5281.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5303.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, and finally also, the applicants bring as a possibility that, or no, they come with the argument that no request was received by them from the authorities not to publish the information in the telegraph.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5303.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5326.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, I am sure that if that had been done, we would also have been here today, perhaps with some different allegation, but certainly that would have been a matter of censorship, which would equally raise questions, and perhaps even more pertinent questions, under Article 10 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5326.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5348.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A few remaining issues, also in response to the applicants, and I'm sure the court will be interested to hear this as well, in the context of the Voskaal and Sanoma cases, the government has already expressed its intention to introduce new legislation on protecting journalistic sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5348.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5363.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The current situation, well, five days after the judgment in the Voskaal case, which dates from the 22nd of December, 2007, the then Minister of Justice informed Parliament that he would present a bill on the protection of sources in criminal cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5363.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5372.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After extensive consultations with the Dutch Association of Journalists, the Netherlands Press Council, and other organizations, the cabinet approved the bill.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5372.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5376.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was submitted to the Council of State for an advisory opinion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5376.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5386.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In preparing its response to the Council of State, the government took account of the fact that the court's grand chamber would give judgment in the Sanoma case in the foreseeable future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5386.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5396.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Minister of Justice wanted to await this judgment, and I think that is a wise decision, before introducing the bill in Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5396.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5414.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following the judgment, the bill underwent a fundamental review, and given the current government's caretaker status, we will have elections on the 12th of September, I unfortunately cannot say when the cabinet will resubmit the amended bill to the Council of State for advice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5414.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5426.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would point out, however, that the Public Prosecution Service has modified its practices in anticipation of the new legislation, as was indeed acknowledged by the applicants as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5426.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5434.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 1st March of 2012, new instructions on the application of coercive measures in respect of journalists took effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5434.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5438.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They replaced the old instructions from 2002.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5438.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5451.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court concluded in the Sanoma case that Dutch legislation lacked a procedure requiring a prior judicial review to strike a balance between the right to freedom of expression on the one hand, and the interests of the investigation on the other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5451.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5454.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The new instructions provide for such a procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5454.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5466.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They stipulate that in order for a journalist to surrender documents can only be issued by an investigating judge, either exproprio motu, or in response to an application by a public prosecutor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5466.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5470.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same applies to a search in respect of a journalist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5470.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5479.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The instructions also specify the principle that journalistic material is to be handed over in the manner least incriminating to the journalist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5479.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5491.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I have noted the fact that the applicants criticize that this is merely a regulation and not an act of formal legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5491.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5505.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But again, in the context of responding to the requirements of the convention, what matters is how things work out in practice, and this is how they work out in practice these days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5505.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5511.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Final point, Mr. President, if you allow me, the question of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5511.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5512.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>notification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5512.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5518.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why have the journalists not yet been notified that special powers were exercised against them?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5518.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5521.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Has this not damaged their interests?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5521.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5535.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The two journalists, through their authorized representatives, asked the Minister of the Interior and Kingdom Relations on the 18th of April, 2012, to allow them to access any data related to them and to report on the use of special powers against them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5535.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5539.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A decision on the request is yet to be taken.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5539.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5549.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The law provides that a decision on access to data be taken within three months, which period may be extended by a month.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5549.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5554.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think that I have been speaking already too long, probably, so I'll leave it at that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5554.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5554.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5560.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5562.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. Böcker.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5562.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5564.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't know, Mr. De Kem, Mr. Le Poole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5568.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5582.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will start by addressing a few of the questions of your court, and then I have one reply to the plea of the Dutch government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5586.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5604.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of the questions was, and it was asked by Judge Ziemelle, if the Dutch government could point out more concretely what exactly or what kind of threat the journalists were.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5604.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5615.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have not heard today any more concrete answers than what has already been written down.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5615.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5623.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And what I would like to point out to the court is that the journalists in this case, they were not the threat.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5623.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5634.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were not the threat to the democratic legal order because all documents were already in the possession of the criminal circuit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5634.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5637.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were in the possession of criminals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5637.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5656.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that was the true danger because those criminals could use the information in the documents to, let's say, attack people or employees of the prosecution service or whatever.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5656.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5662.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's, of course, nothing that the journalist, De Haas-Mos would do.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5662.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5678.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And what I also would like to point out is that all Dutch courts stated that what the applicants have done was nothing more than fulfilling their job, and they were only intermediaries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5678.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5685.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that decision is upheld by all Dutch courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5685.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5695.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another question of the court was whether or not there has been...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5695.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5707.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>whether or not the supervisory committee afforded any safeguards prior to the use of special powers by the Secret Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5707.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5718.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicants of the opinion that the supervisory committee is not sufficient because of the fact that there is no prior review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5718.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5727.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, the supervisory committee can see all relevant documents, and they can hear both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5727.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5736.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But they are not in the same position as an independent and impartial judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5736.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5744.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The supervisory committee does not stand above the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5744.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5763.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And even more so is applicable to the minister, which is the only person who's responsible for starting or allowing the Secret Service to take special measures against journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5763.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5773.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The minister is a party himself, so we cannot expect from the minister to have a look at all interests involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5773.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5792.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's a pity that there is no special way or procedure within the ministry to decide or to take a look at the interests of the journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5792.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5809.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And with respect to there being safeguards or not, I would also like to draw your attention to the decision of the president of the Hague Court in the preliminary relief proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5809.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5823.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because in those proceedings, the state said, well, the applicants, they have the ability to go to the supervisory committee, and they can file a complaint with me, the minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5823.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5827.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there are enough safeguards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5827.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5847.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the president of the court explicitly said that for the applicants, there were no other options to obtain at very short notice a judicial review of the actions of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5847.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5851.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And he also said in paragraph 4.3</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5851.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5859.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the options presented by the state will not lead to a judicial verdict on a very short notice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5859.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5867.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there is no prior judicial review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5867.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5875.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that also brings me to the last point I would like to make today, which is the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5875.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5909.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its plea, the government said that the Sanema case is not applicable to the present case because the Dutch public prosecutor did not have a look at the files or the state secret files because they first awaited the judgments of the district court in chambers, which had to decide on the seizure of the documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5909.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5915.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that's not the issue here in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5915.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5942.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And what I would like to point out here is that today, one of the points the applicants would like to make is that the decision to ask a journalist to surrender documents or the decision to seize documents, that decision should be subject to prior judicial review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5942.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5946.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's what has not happened here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5946.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5955.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's what, to my opinion and to the opinion of the applicants, is exactly what your court rules in the Sanema decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5955.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5955.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5965.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5967.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Discuss.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5972.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5975.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maybe I was not too precise in my question to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5975.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5992.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question would be, any of the documents in possession of the Telegraph, did any one of them, or was any one of them, be it a paper or tape or picture or whatever, was it physically subtracted from the files of the Secret Service?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5992.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6000.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mean, they were just transferred, taken physically from the possession of the government to the newspaper.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6005.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6005.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Böcker.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6009.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6010.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6010.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6019.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It concerned copies from the files, from the secret service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6019.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6040.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If I haven't been sufficiently clear in my answer, the reason is probably that up until today, we are not completely sure what has been the trace of all the documents, what the exact volume has really been.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6040.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6049.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so the question is now quite clear to me, and it's a simple and straightforward question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6049.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6054.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unfortunately, the answer is more complicated than that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6054.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6067.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would actually – I think that if we would all get together, the two parties and the court, we could have a discussion on, well, tell us what happened at what exact time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6067.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6072.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have to deal with the information that we have in government circles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6072.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6081.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there's nothing more I can say.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6081.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6082.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to look at my colleague here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6091.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6095.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No, I'm sorry, I cannot be any more precise than I have been.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6095.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6095.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm sorry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6099.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6100.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6100.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6102.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, will you please allow me to get back</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6102.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6104.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the third question of Mr. Mayor,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6104.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6110.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because Mr. Kemp and I were dividing the questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6110.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6111.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do you allow me?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6111.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6115.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6115.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6117.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yeah, thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6117.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6120.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm going to answer your question, because I think you're fully right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6120.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6127.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You're asking if documents are stolen, shouldn't you give them back to the owner of these documents?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6127.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6135.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, you're right, but that's not all I have to say, because that's exactly what the Telegraaf did.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6135.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6142.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Telegraaf gave a complete set of documents back to the Secret Service on Friday before publication.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6142.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6147.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And what is very important, the Telegraaf told the Secret Service that that was a copy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6147.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6163.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they explained to the Secret Service that they kept the original in its possession because the documents received from their sources contained DNA material and fingerprints of these sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6163.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6168.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that was explained to the Secret Service on Friday, and that was sufficient for the time being.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6168.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6177.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After the publication, there was this surrender order you were referring to of the Public Prosecution Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6177.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6186.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This order, I think it's Exhibit 6 to the complaint, only relates to state secret information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6186.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6190.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the Telegraaf still had to surrender all state secret information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6190.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6193.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, that's what the Telegraaf did.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6193.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6201.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They gave all the documents without 37 pages which were not marked as state secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6201.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6202.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were not state secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6202.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6204.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So they kept 37 pages.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6204.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6212.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They handed over all the other documents to the state prosecutor and to the examining judge, and we followed the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6212.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6222.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Afterwards, we had another discussion, and the Secret Service said we also want to have these 37 documents, and they were handed over to the public prosecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6222.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6227.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there were no 11 pages kept into possession of the Telegraaf.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6227.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6234.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That must be a miscount or a misunderstanding, but all documents were given back to the Secret Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6234.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6244.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the only reason to try to keep them was the reason that these documents could contain fingerprints and DNA material.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6244.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6246.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they were researched for that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6246.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6248.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You know the discussion from the file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6248.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6270.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One other point I would like to address that is, as the government is stressing again and again that the Telegraaf did reveal highly sensitive information and even that the proof is in the publication because of the code names, et cetera, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6270.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6281.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I want to stress that we had the discussion before in the Dutch courts with also the publications present, and the courts ruled that there was no sensitive information revealed by the journalists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6281.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6283.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They acted as intermediary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6283.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6284.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were very careful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6284.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6285.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were very prudent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6285.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6292.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And nobody was at no sources where the identity of sources were not revealed, et cetera, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6292.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6297.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I will make one final remark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6297.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6311.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has acknowledged in this court at this hearing today that the government has never asked or summoned the Telegraaf not to publish certain information, has not protested after publication, you shouldn't publish this anymore.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6311.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6317.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's I think a very relevant circumstance for this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6317.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6317.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6324.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6328.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6328.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6336.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and for the answers to the call questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6336.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6341.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The call will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6341.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6346.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the decision or the judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6346.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6350.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of the delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6350.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6352.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
