<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>4141804_03092014</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>301.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>302.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>358.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>365.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated, I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case of Khoroshenko against Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>365.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>376.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on the 6th of October 2004 under Article 34 of the Convention by Russian national Mr. Andrey Anatolyevich Khoroshenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>376.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>388.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was allocated to the first section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court, and communicated to the government on the 13th of January 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>388.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>399.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 11th of February 2014, the chamber decided to relinquish jurisdiction in favor of the grand chamber, none of the parties having objected to a relinquishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>399.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>416.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 12th of May 2014, leave was granted to a group of professors of the University of Surrey School of Law to submit written comments as a third party by virtue of Rule 44, Paragraph 3 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>416.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>419.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Mr. Georgy</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>419.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>430.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Matyushkin, head of the Office of the Representative of the Russian Federation at the European Court of Human Rights, assisted by Mr. Nikolay Mikhaylov, counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>430.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>436.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and by Ms. Yana Tsimbalova and Mr. Stanislav Kovpak, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>436.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>441.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Ms. Oxana Preobrazhenskaya,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>441.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>446.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>counsel, assisted by Ms. Marina Makarova, advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>446.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>452.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>452.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>458.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome a delegation from the High Council of Judges and Prosecutors of Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>458.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>468.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>468.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>472.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Matyushkin for the government will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>472.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>476.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Ms. Preobrazhenskaya for the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>476.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>492.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting into Turkish has been authorized for the benefit of delegation from the High Council of Judges and Prosecutors of Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>492.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>507.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, interpreting into Armenian has been authorized for the benefit of a delegation of Armenian legal professionals, and interpreting into Moldavian has been authorized for the benefit of a delegation from the Moldovan Ombudsman's Office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>507.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>519.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>519.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>520.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Matyushkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>528.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>538.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, at the beginning, the Russian Federation authorities would like to state their position concerning the admissibility of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>538.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>548.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it follows from the questions posed by the Grand Chamber of the Court, the subject matter of the present case is the right of the applicant to conjugal visits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>548.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>558.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A conjugal visit is a scheduled period in which a convict is permitted to spend several hours or days in private with a legal spouse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>558.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>571.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it follows from the applicant's persuasion, in 1996, he divorced from his wife on her initiative after the sentence in respect of him had become final.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>571.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>581.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, from 1996, the applicant did not have the right to conjugal visits, solely for the reason that he had no spouse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>581.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>587.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, the government considered that the present application is inadmissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>587.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>604.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the present case deals with the issue of whether the restrictions of the right of persons convicted to life imprisonment to conjugal visits during the first 10 years of the service in life imprisonment sentence complies with Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>604.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>615.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In connection with this, the government's ambition, attention will mainly be paid to the clarification of the reasons for the restriction on the right in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>615.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>632.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before answering the questions posed by the court, the Russian Federation authorities would like to draw attention to the general position of the court regarding conjugal visits for convicts and the level of the court's case law development in this field.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>632.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>658.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Starting from the first decisions as to the admissibility of such complaints delivered in 70s, again, Germany and the United Kingdom, as for example, in the case X of the Federal Republic of Germany, number 360368, and X versus United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>658.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>663.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was delivered in May 1975.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>663.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>682.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The commission found the restrictions on either total prohibition of conjugal visits in prison was not contrary to Article 8, part 2 of the Convention, on the ground that it is necessary in the interest of public safety.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>682.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>720.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the latter case, again, the United Kingdom, with regard to the allegation that the applicant has been deprived of the adequate exercise of his parental rights, the commission held that measures limiting a prisoner's access to his children can be justified in view of Article 8, part 2 of the Convention, which allows an interference with the right to respect for family life if it is lawful and necessary in a democratic society for the protection of health or morals or for the protection of the rights and freedoms of others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>720.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>758.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the 90s, the commission has repeatedly stated that although the refusal of conjugal visits constitutes an interference with the right to respect for one's family life under Article 8 of the Convention, for the present time, it must be regarded as justified for the prevention of disorder of crime under the second part of the provision, as well as that the difference in treatment between the convicts and those who are not detained in the direct result of lawfully imposed prison sentence, and as a result, has a reasonable and objective justification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>763.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>773.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the beginning of this century, the court's practice has not been changed or amended in the way that somehow requires providing for conjugal visits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>773.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>793.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this context, the government draws the court's attention to the case of Aliev versus Ukraine, where the court recognized that some measures of control of prisoners' contacts with the outside world is called for and is not of itself incompatible with the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>793.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>818.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whilst noting with approval their reform movements in several European countries to improve prison condition by facilitating conjugal visits, the court considers that the refusal of such visits may, for the present time, be regarded as justified for the prevention of disorder and crime within the meaning of the second part of Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>818.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>836.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the circumstances of the case, the court found that the restriction of the applicant's wife's visits was proportionate to the legitimate aim pursued and that there was no violation of Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>836.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>863.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case Dixon versus United Kingdom, the court stated that conjugal visits in prison is an area in which the contracting states could enjoy a wide margin of appreciation in determining the steps to be taken to ensure compliance with the Convention with due regard to the needs and resources of the community and of individuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>863.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>884.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the recent case, the Russian Federation authorities referred to the case of Epners-Gefners versus Latvia and Grimailos versus Latvia, where the court still supported the position that the Convention does not require the contracting states to make provisions for conjugal visits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>884.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>919.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, in the latest case of Varnas versus Lithuania, the court emphasized that such restriction as limitations imposed on the number of the family visits, supervision over these visits, and if so justified by the nature of the offense, subjection of a detainee to the special prison regime or special visit arrangements constitute an interference with the rights of Article 8 of the Convention, but are not by themselves in breach of that provision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>919.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>945.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, based on the extensive case law, the government is deeply convinced that the provision of the Russian legislation, which provides for the restrictions of the rights of the persons convicted to life imprisonment to long-term visits during the first 10 years of service in life imprisonment sentence, are in the wide margin of appreciation recognized by the court for nearly four decades.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>949.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>969.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Punishment, in accordance with Section 2 of Article 43 of the Criminal Court of the Russian Federation, shall be applied for the purpose of restoring social justice and also for the purpose of reforming a convicted person and of preventing the commission of further crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>969.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>979.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The purposes of the punishment are in line with the principles of criminal justice and humanism, declared in Article 6 and 7 of the Criminal Court of the Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>979.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>997.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, pursuant to the principle of justice, punishment, and other legal measures applicable to a person who has committed a crime, shall be just, that is, they shall correspond to the character and decree of the social danger of the crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>997.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1017.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The circumstances of this commission and the personality of the guilty party, following the principle of humanism, punishment, and other legal measures applicable to a person who has committed a crime, may not pursue the aim of causing physical suffering or debasement of human dignity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1017.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1025.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The order and conditions of sentence servicing are established in the Penitentiary Court of Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1025.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1039.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Article 1 of this court, the purpose of the Russian Penitentiary legislation are reforming a convicted person and preventing the commission of further crimes, both by the convicted and other persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1039.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1060.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government informed the court that the provisions of the Penitentiary Court of the Russian Federation, disputed by the applicant, have been examined by the Constitutional Court of the Russian Federation on several occasions and its legal position was formulated in a number of its decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1060.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1072.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, decision on June 2005, the text of which have been submitted to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1072.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1092.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian Federation authorities, based on the position of the Constitutional Court of the Russian Federation, admit that there are restrictions on the right to long-term visits during the first 10 years of service in life imprisonment sentence amount to an interference with their pride to private and family life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1092.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1101.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the government are convinced that the interference in question complies with the requirements of Article 8 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1101.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1116.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, the government would like to state that, pursuant to Article 89 of the Penitentiary Court of Russian Federation, the convicted persons have a right to be visited by their relatives and other persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1116.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1121.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are two types of such visits, short-term visits and long-term visits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1121.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1127.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The difference between these two types of visits is in their duration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1127.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1134.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, a short-term visit lasts four hours and a long-term visit lasts three days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1134.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1146.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Along with that, the set legal provision does not provide for a right to have long-term visits during their first 10 years of service in life imprisonment sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1146.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1168.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As provided by Article 126 of the Penitentiary Court, the persons convicted to life imprisonment and the convicts in whose respect their capital punishment was replaced by life imprisonment by way of pardon serve their sentences in special regime correctional colonies separately from the other convicts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1168.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1187.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In accordance with Article 127 of the Penitentiary Court, there are three types of regimes in a special regime correctional colony, strict conditions for the first 10 years, normal, and the less restrictive conditions after 10 years in normal conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1187.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1196.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The number of both above-mentioned types of visits for the convicts servicing life imprisonment sentence depends on the regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1196.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1219.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Section 3 of Article 125 of the Penitentiary Court stipulates three conditions of serving sentences, namely the condition for their first 10 years of service in life imprisonment sentence, and in particular, envisage that the convicts are allowed to have two short-term visits annually.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1219.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1234.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After servicing their first 10 years of life imprisonment sentence in strict conditions, convicts are placed in normal conditions and allowed to have two short-term and two long-term visits annually.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1234.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1249.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having completed servicing no less than 10 years in normal conditions, convicts may be transferred to less strict conditions of servicing sentence, and they are allowed to have three short and three long visits annually.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1249.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1264.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regard the aims of the interference in question, as well as whether these aims are legitimate in accordance with the requirements of the second part of Article 8 of the Convention, the government would like to submit the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1264.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1277.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In accordance with the court case law, any measure depriving a person of his liberty under Article 5 of the Convention entails inherent limitation on his private life and family life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1277.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1290.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it is an essential part of the detainee's right to respect for family life that the authorities enable him, or if necessary, assist him in maintaining contact with his close family.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1290.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1313.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such restrictions as limitations put on the number of family visits, if so justified by the nature of the offense, subjection of the detainee to a special detention regime or special visit arrangements constitute an interference with the rights under Article 8 of the Convention, but are not by themselves in breach of that provision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1313.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1328.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, any restriction of that kind must be prescribed by law, must pursue one or more legitimate aims listed in Article 8 Part 2 of the Convention, and in addition, must be justified as being necessary in a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1332.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1364.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Being guided by the seated principles, the government maintained that Article 55, Section 3 of the Constitution of the Russian Federation, allows for a possibility of limitation of the rights and freedoms of men and citizens by the federal law to such an extent, to which it is necessary for the protection of the fundamental principles of the constitutional system, morality, health, rights, and lawful interests of other people, for ensuring defense of the country and security of the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1364.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1392.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such limitations may be connected with the application to persons who have committed crimes of a criminal punishment as a measure of public compulsion, the regularity of which is that during the execution thereof, a convict is influenced in a special way which is expressed in deprivation of limitation of some of his rights and freedoms and imposition of specific obligations on him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1392.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1433.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Constitution of the Russian Federation refining the adoption of criminal and penitentiary legislation to the Russian Federation legislative branch, Article 71, Subjection 0, give the power to the federal legislature to provide for such restricting measures in respect of a person who has committed crimes and has been subjected to punishment, which, as it falls from Section 1 of Article 43 of the Criminal Court of the Russian Federation, in its essence, consists of the depreciation of limitation of the rights and freedoms of a convict envisaged by law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1433.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1468.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that, the legislator, when establishing the responsibility for the crime, as well as the law enforcement agencies, when resolving the issue of imposing thereof on the person who has committed a crime, shall take into account the nature of the crime, its danger for the values protected by the Constitution of Russia, and the criminal law intensity, reasons, and other circumstances of the commission thereof, as well as information concerning the person who has committed the crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1468.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1501.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Adopting measures of criminal punishment with different sets of limitations corresponding to the gravity of the crime committed by the convict and the severity of the sentence imposed, as well as defining the order of service in his sentence, the legislator shall proceed from the fact that the convicts have the same rights and freedoms like other citizens, with some exceptions conditioned by the peculiarities of their personality and the crimes committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1501.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1518.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Conditions of sentence servicing are re-entered to the individualization of penalty, differentiation of sanctions, and application thereof, as well as they provide for preconditions for the achievement of punishment aims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1518.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1526.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, rectification of injustice, reformation of a convict, and prevention of new crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1526.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1539.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A person committing an intentional crime shall, under all circumstances, take into account that as a result, he or she could be deprived of liberty and limited in rights and freedoms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1539.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1556.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that such person consciously condemned him, herself, and his or her family to these restrictions, including the rights to communication with family, inviolability of private life, personal and family privacy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1556.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1602.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Set of restrictions established by the criminal and penitential legislation for convicts, including the restriction on visits received by the convict by their number, duration, and conditions, limitation on the number and duration of telephone calls, as well as number of parcels, post packages, and packages in differential depending on, first of all, severity of the sentence imposed by the court corresponding to the nature and degree of public danger of the crime, the circumstances of the commission thereof, and the personality of offender, as well as depending on the conduct of the convict within the period of sentence serving, which ensures proportionality and fairness of the punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1602.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1642.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The necessity of legislative regulation of convicts' visits by their relatives and friends finds its footing in their provision of the body of principles for the protection of all persons under any form of detention or imprisonment adopted by the United Nations General Assembly on December 1988, in particular in principle 19, and arises from the specifics of both criminal proceedings and substantive legal relations, including the application within the framers of punishment in the form of deprivation of liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1642.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1656.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Restrictions on visits as to their number, duration, and conditions are an inevitable consequence of this nature of restraint consisting of isolation of the convict in a special place under guard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1656.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1675.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And from this viewpoint, the provisions disputed by the applicant establish no additional limits by themselves beside the ones that follow from the essence of such measures of restraint as deprivation of liberty within the means of Article 55, Section 3 of the Constitution of Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1675.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1692.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The rights to respect for private life, Article 23, Section 1 of the Constitution of Russia, means the opportunity granted to the person and guaranteed by the state to control information about him herself and to prevent dissemination of intimate personal data.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1692.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1710.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then that notion of private life includes the area of human vital activities, which refers to an individual and only applies to him and is not subject to control on the part of the society and the state unless such activities are contrary to law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1710.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1720.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, as the court stated, the main purpose of Article 8 is to protect an individual against arbitrary interference of state authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1720.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1737.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When deciding on the measures of punishment in the form of deprivation of liberty for the crime committed, the state does not perform arbitrary interferences with the private life of a citizen, but simply fulfills sanctions on protection of public interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1741.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1766.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, the disputed provisions stipulating that the prison sentence to life imprisonment for committing especially grave crimes make an attempt on human life have a right to long-term visas, but not sooner than after 10 years of imprisonment do not violate the fair balance between the public interest in general and the interests of an individual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1766.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1775.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, limitation of the right of person sentences to life imprisonment to long-term family visits pursues legitimate aims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1775.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1780.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does not provide for the total prohibition and is temporary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1780.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1799.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In connection with the question concerning the proportionality of the restrictions to the legitimate aim pursued, in particular, concerning the necessity in democratic society of such interference, the Russian Federation authorities would like to refer to the seated above relevant court case law, for example, Aliyev versus Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1799.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1814.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should also be noted that as regard of other countries or the Council of Europe, more than half of the contracting states allows for contrigual visits for prisoners subject to a variety of different restrictions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1814.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1825.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, there are also countries in the Council of Europe in which their prisoners have no right to conjugal visits at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1825.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1839.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concluding the oral submission, I would like to emphasize that the severity of punishment imposed on the applicant, including the restrictions on visits, is not disproportionate to the criminal offenses he had committed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1839.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1839.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1842.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1845.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Matyushkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1845.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1850.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call now Ms. Preobrazhenskaya.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1856.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1858.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1858.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1862.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Monsieur le Président, mesdames et messieurs les juges, je m'appelle Oksana Pribrazhenskaya.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1863.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1868.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moi et ma collègue Marina Makarova, nous vous présentons la position de Rokuron concernant son cas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1869.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1877.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tout d'abord, permettez-moi de vous exposer très brèvement la situation personnelle de Rokuron, Khrachenko Andriy Anatolyevitch.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1877.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1883.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le Rokuron a été arrêté en 1994 et placé en détention provisoire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1883.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1886.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Depuis cette année, il n'est jamais sorti de la détention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1886.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1892.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jusqu'en 2009, il n'a eu droit à aucune visite longue avec ses proches.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1892.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1902.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le 13 octobre 1995, le Rokuron a été jugé coupable de crimes particulièrement graves, tandis qu'il n'a jamais admis sa culpabilité.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1903.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1906.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le Rokuron a été condamné à mort.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1906.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1914.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En 1999, le Rokuron a été crassé et sa peine a été commise en réclusion à perpétuité.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1915.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1937.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En 2011, le Comité des droits de l'homme des Nations unies a émis une constatation en réponse à la communication de Rokuron dans laquelle le comité constate des manquements répétés au droit à un procès équitable, ainsi que la violation des droits à la vie et l'interdiction de la torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1937.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1943.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Enfin, le comité conclut que l'affaire pénale de Rokuron doit faire l'objet d'un nouveau procès.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1944.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1949.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Actuellement, le Rokuron poche toujours sa peine de réclusion à perpétuité.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1950.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1958.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les conditions d'exécution de la peine des personnes condamnées sont réagies par le Code des procédures d'exécution de la Fédération de Russie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1958.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1967.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ce Code définit pour les condamnés à perpétuité les conditions dans lesquelles la peine est purgée dans les colonies pénitentiaires de régime spécial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1968.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1977.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Notamment, à l'arrivée à la colonie pénitentiaire de régime spécial, tous les condamnés sont placés dans des conditions strictes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1978.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1985.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le transfert des conditions strictes aux conditions ordinaires s'effectue après au moins 10 ans dans des conditions strictes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1986.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1995.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ainsi, toutes les personnes condamnées à perpétuité, sans exception, sont placées dans des conditions strictes pour au moins 10 ans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1996.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2005.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La procédure de réclusion dans des conditions strictes prévoit que les condamnés sont autorisés à avoir deux visites courtes au cours de l'année.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2006.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2011.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quant au droit à des visites longues, il n'est pas prévu et il n'existe aucune exception.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2012.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2017.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Après 10 ans, les condamnés à perpétuité peuvent être transférés.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2017.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2022.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans ce cas, ils ont droit à deux visites courtes et deux visites longues au cours de l'année.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2022.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2035.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ainsi, conformément aux règles de la législation pénale, la situation des personnes condamnées à perpétuité après les 10 premières années peut être améliorée sous certaines conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2036.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2051.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ce qui concerne l'ingérence dans la vie privée et familiale, la jurisprudence de la Cour indique que la détention ou toute autre mesure privative de liberté implique la restriction de la vie privée et de la vie familiale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2051.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2071.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les mesures telles que la limitation du nombre de visites familiales, la surveillance des visites et le choix d'un régime spécial pour les prisonniers ou l'octroi des visites constituent une ingérence dans le droit garanti par l'article 8, mais en soi, ne violent pas cette disposition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2071.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2090.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cependant, cette restriction doit être conforme à la loi pour suivre un ou plusieurs buts légitimes à numérer, plusieurs buts légitimes à numérer dans le paragraphe 2 de cet article, et être justifiée par la nécessité dans une société démocratique.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2090.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2103.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les instruments internationaux prévoient que la personne condamnée doit garder des contacts avec le monde extérieur, notamment avec leur famille et leurs proches le plus souvent possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2103.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2114.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La procédure d'attribution de visite est régie par le Code des procédures d'exécution de la peine et par le règlement interne des établissements pénitentiaires.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2114.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2128.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le chef de l'établissement a le droit, en cas de non-respect de règle de la procédure de visite, de priver la condamnée de ses visites et ou d'y mettre fin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2128.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2139.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La législation nationale ne prévoit pas la possibilité pour l'administration de prison ou le tribunal d'augmenter la durée de visite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2139.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2147.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'interdiction de visite longue pour les condamnés à perpétuité constitue une attente à leur droit à la vie privée et familiale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2148.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2161.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cependant, l'ingérence est admissible si elle est absolument nécessaire dans une société démocratique et l'équilibre entre les intérêts privés et publics est été sauvegardé.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2162.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2174.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le requérant ne conteste pas que l'abus de la peine est de protéger les intérêts de la société et que la sanction entraîne des limitations en matière de communication avec les proches.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2174.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2185.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le requérant ne peut pas accepter le fait que l'interdiction totale de visite prolongée pendant 10 ans soit proportionnelle au but légitime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2185.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2196.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En outre, l'absence complète de visite de longue durée est une sorte de peine complémentaire imposant des restrictions supplémentaires.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2196.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2203.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La loi s'applique à toutes les personnes condamnées à perpétuité et ne prévoit pas d'exception ou d'alternative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2203.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2212.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ainsi, la législation pénale ne prévoit pas l'analyse de la situation individuelle de chaque personne condamnée à perpétuité.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2213.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2226.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il est nécessaire de commenter l'allégation des autorités selon laquelle l'interdiction de visite longue pour les personnes condamnées à perpétuité a un caractère temporaire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2227.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2242.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Étant donné que la réclusion à perpétuité est prescrite comme une punition pour les crimes particulièrement graves, la mesure préventive choisie est la mise en détention provisoire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2242.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2248.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En général, le jugement statuaire sur la culpabilité intervient des années plus tard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2249.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2252.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pendant cette période, la personne se trouve en détention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2252.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2260.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le délai de cette détention dépend de la vitesse d'avancement de l'enquête préliminaire et judiciaire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2260.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2272.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La législation de la procédure pénale prévoit le délai d'enquête préliminaire pour la catégorie de crimes particulièrement graves allant jusqu'à un an et demi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2273.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2280.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ce qui concerne le délai au stade de la procédure judiciaire, leur durée n'est pas réglementée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2280.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2288.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il convient de souligner que la Cour a déjà reconnu ce problème systémique de la Russie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2289.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2299.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Conformément à la législation nationale, les personnes mises en détention provisoire n'ont pas le droit aux visites longues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2299.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2310.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Par ailleurs, la législation prévoit une période d'entrée en vigueur de jugement qui donne le cas d'appel qui dure plusieurs années.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2311.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2317.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pendant cette période, l'accusé se trouve toujours en détention provisoire sans visite longue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2318.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2325.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ainsi, une personne condamnée à perpétuité n'a pas de visite longue pendant plus de 10 ans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2325.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2338.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cette période englobe le temps de détention provisoire avant le jugement, le temps après le prononcé du jugement, ainsi qu'au moins 10 ans après l'arrivée dans une colonie pénitentiaire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2340.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2354.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En outre, le changement dans les conditions d'exécution de la peine ne se font pas automatiquement après 10 ans, mais uniquement en l'absence d'une sanction sous forme de mise en cellule disciplinaire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2355.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2365.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans le cas contraire, les condamnés ne sont pas transférés dans les conditions ordinaires pendant encore au moins un an.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2368.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2376.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ainsi, l'interdiction de visite longue à des condamnés à perpétuité, bien que la loi les limite à 10 ans, est beaucoup plus longue en pratique.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2377.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2387.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans le cas du requérant, cette période a duré plus de 15 ans, ce qui représente une période importante de sa vie et celle de ses proches.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2389.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2401.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'aimerais commenter la deuxième allégation des autorités selon laquelle au Royaume-Uni et en Irlande du Nord, la législation pénale ne prévoit pas de visite conjugale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2402.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2410.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ici, les autorités comparent la situation de ces pays avec celle de l'existence en Fédération de Russie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2411.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2420.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Néanmoins, il convient de souligner que dans ces pays, il existe le congé pénant pendant lequel les détenus rentrent à la maison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2420.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2429.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, il aurait été une simplification abusée de dire qu'au Royaume-Uni, il n'y a pas de visite longue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2429.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2435.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et par conséquent, leur interdiction temporaire en Russie est justifiée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2438.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2444.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ensuite, il faut préciser que la législation prévoit quelques possibilités d'être libérée de la peine réelle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2445.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2462.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Notamment, un acte d'amnistie se trouvant en incompétence de parlant ou en incompétence de parlement, la grâce en compétence de président, la libération conditionnelle pour les personnes condamnées à perpétuité après 25 ans d'emprisonnement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2462.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2470.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En outre, une peine peut être modifiée ou annulée en raison d'un nouveau procès en supervision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2470.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2477.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ainsi, le requérant peut être amnistié, gracié ou bénéficié d'une libération conditionnelle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2477.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2483.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Actuellement, son affaire peut être réexaminée dans le cadre de nouvelles circonstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2483.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2490.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A ce stade, malheureusement, le requérant a été débuté d'une réouverture de la procédure par le tribunal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2491.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2506.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cependant, la Cour constitutionnelle russe a statué dans l'affaire de requérant que la constatation du comité des droits de l'homme présente une base suffisante pour la réouverture de la procédure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2506.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2514.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Par conséquent, l'affaire pénale de requérant est à réviser dans un futur proche.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2514.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2522.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cela signifie que malgré le fait qu'une personne soit condamnée à vie, elle a une chance légitime de sortir de prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2523.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2535.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ce sens, une question importante est de savoir dans quelle mesure le détenu qui a passé beaucoup de temps en prison serait prêt à s'adapter à un changement de la société.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2535.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2539.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et est-ce que la société serait prête à l'accepter?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2540.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2549.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il est évident que la communication constante avec la famille et les amis répond le mieux à la question de son adaptation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2549.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2557.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et son espoir, comme la tente à l'extérieur de la prison, le stimule à une correction plus rapide.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2558.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2566.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Monsieur le Président, mesdames et messieurs les juges, je vous remercie de votre attention et j'aimerais passer la parole à ma collègue Magdalena Macahoran.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2567.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2568.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, Madame Makarova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2577.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2587.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les juges, je vais vous exposer d'autres aspects concernant les visites des condamnés à perpétuité, ainsi que je vous présenterai des conclusions finales.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2587.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2600.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tout d'abord, j'aimerais préciser à la Cour que, conformément aux règlements internes des colonies pénitentiaires, les visites courtes sont autorisées une fois tous les six mois et ne peuvent pas dépasser quatre heures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2600.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2606.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>De plus, le requérant ne pouvait rencontrer plus de deux visiteurs adultes en même temps.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2606.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2617.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, il voulait garder le contact avec plusieurs membres de sa famille et des amis, y compris avec son enfant, qui était mineur à l'époque.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2617.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2624.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nous rappelons à la Cour qu'à présent, les relations du requérant avec son fils sont pratiquement anéanties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2624.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2630.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Son fils n'a pas envie de communiquer avec son père, qu'il n'a pas vu pendant 20 ans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2630.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2648.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le règlement interne prévoit également la limite d'âge des visiteurs, qui signifie que dès l'âge de la majorité du fils du requérant, un autre membre de sa famille ne pouvait plus prendre part à une visite, étant donné l'existence de la restriction sur le nombre de visiteurs adultes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2648.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2654.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les visites se déroulaient en présence d'un inspecteur, qui écoutait les conversations avec les visiteurs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2654.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2658.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le requérant était séparé des visiteurs par une paroi d'auvert.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2658.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2669.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ainsi, la méthode des visites de membres de la famille excluait toute intimité et tout contact tactile entre le requérant et les visiteurs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2669.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2679.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cette procédure de visite a eu un impact négatif sur les divers aspects de la vie privée et familiale du requérant, puisqu'il avait des relations particulières avec chaque visiteur.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2679.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2689.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En outre, la présence d'un inspecteur ne pouvait pas ne pas influer sur le degré de confidentialité, de communication avec les membres de sa famille.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2689.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2694.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le requérant ne voit aucune preuve de nécessité de telles restrictions dans son cas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2694.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2710.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il fait valoir que les visites courtes ne peuvent pas être une alternative à une visite longue, compte tenu des restrictions qui eut lieu pendant les visites courtes, et que ces restrictions s'appliquaient à tous, sans exception.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2710.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2722.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il convient de conclure que même dans le cas des visites courtes, l'État ne respecte pas l'équilibre entre les intérêts privés et publics, en violation du droit à la vie privée et familiale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2722.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2735.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>D'ailleurs, la même conclusion a été tirée par la Cour européenne dans l'affaire concernant les visites de courte durée pour les personnes condamnées à perpétuité dans l'affaire Troysen contre l'Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2735.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2746.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En outre, j'aimerais souligner l'importance de la communication avec sa femme, y compris les relations sexuelles, ainsi que la possibilité de concevoir et de lever des enfants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2746.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2757.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le requérant attire l'attention de la Cour sur le fait que la portée du droit à la vie familiale comprend également les relations conjugales, qui se composent de différents aspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2757.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2764.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Par exemple, les conjoints ont le droit à la vie sexuelle, le droit de devenir parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2764.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2771.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ce qui concerne la situation des condamnés, la détention est accompagnée d'une restriction importante du droit à la vie sexuelle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2771.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2781.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'interdiction des relations sexuelles avec sa femme signifie autant pour le détenu que pour sa femme une impossibilité automatique de devenir parent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2781.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2799.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La femme du condamné à perpétuité ne peut a priori ni avoir de vie sexuelle avec son conjoint, ni avoir des enfants de son mari au moins pendant 10 ans, parce que la législation, telle qu'elle a été formulée, interdit les visites prolongées pour les condamnés à la réclusion à perpétuité.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2799.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2805.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour s'est prononcée au sujet du droit à la vie sexuelle dans l'arrêt à L'Eif contre l'Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2805.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2811.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Elle a de nouveau rappelé que la vie privée et familiale du prisonnier est l'un des aspects les plus importants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2811.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2819.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et même en restreignant ce droit, le gouvernement doit aider à maintenir un contact efficace avec la famille.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2819.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2828.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Parallèlement à cela, le requérant souligne qu'une des conséquences de la détention peut être la privation de la possibilité de devenir parent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2828.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2842.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, concernant ce droit, la grande chambre dans l'arrêt Dixon et Dixon contre le Royaume-Uni avait statué que le refus de l'insémination artificielle est contraire à l'article 8 de la Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2842.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2854.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour a rappelé que le détenu conserve leurs droits fondamentaux garantis par la Convention et qu'un équilibre entre les intérêts privés et les intérêts communs devrait être respecté.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2854.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2864.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans cet arrêt, la Cour a conclu que l'intérêt privé doit l'importer sur l'intérêt général et que l'ingérence disproportionnée a eu lieu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2864.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2874.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>D'une part, il convient de noter que le droit de devenir parent pour le détenu ainsi que pour sa femme était déterminé par les circonstances particulières de cette affaire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2874.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2879.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ici, la femme du condamné ne pouvait pas tomber enceinte d'une manière habituelle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2879.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2889.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>D'autre part, la capacité de la femme de procréer peut être limitée par son état de santé, l'âge, le temps, etc.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2889.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2901.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le droit de devenir parent se transforme dans le droit de l'enfant de voir ses parents, même si l'un d'eux est reconnu coupable et condamné à la réclusion à perpétuité.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2901.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2910.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'intérêt supérieur de l'enfant implique une relation avec ses deux parents et il est très important que cette communication soit effective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2910.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2918.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Toute restriction à la communication de l'enfant avec ses parents risque d'impacter leur relation familiale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2918.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2926.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En l'espèce, le requérant souligne qu'il a un fils qui a vécu depuis son arrestation jusqu'à ce jour il ne l'a pas vu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2926.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2934.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le requérant a eu la possibilité de voir son fils 15 ans plus tard, mais à ce moment, la relation avec lui était rompue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2934.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2942.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Comme il a été dit avant, le fils du requérant l'aide financièrement, mais il évite le contact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2942.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2957.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ce qui concerne le terme de la vie familiale, il convient de préciser qu'il s'étend à des relations entre les parents et les enfants, ainsi qu'à des relations entre les grands-parents, les petits-enfants, autres parents et les personnes proches.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2957.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2965.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La sphère privée comprend aussi les relations avec les amis et le droit d'entretenir une telle relation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2965.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2981.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Une interdiction totale de visite longue, ainsi que les conditions dans lesquelles se déroulent les visites courtes, influencent fortement sur les relations entre le condamné et ses proches, ainsi que sur la capacité à maintenir le contact avec ses amis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2981.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2993.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Un soin particulier devrait être prêté au droit des parents âgés et autres personnes proches âgées qui, pendant au moins 10 ans, ne peuvent ni toucher leurs proches ni de les trendre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2993.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3001.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Compte tenu de leur âge, il est possible que chaque visite à une personne condamnée puisse être leur dernière.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3001.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3010.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ce qui concerne le cas présent, il convient de rappeler que le vieux père du requérant venait plusieurs fois à des visites courtes jusqu'en 2007.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3010.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3015.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ensuite, son état de santé ne lui permettait plus de visiter le requérant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3015.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3027.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Depuis l'arrestation, son père n'avait pas la possibilité de toucher son fils et, quand cela est devenu possible, il ne pouvait plus exercer ce droit en raison de sa maladie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3027.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3040.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En d'autres termes, pendant plus de 20 ans, le père n'avait pas le droit et actuellement n'a plus la possibilité de toucher et de trendre son fils.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3040.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3044.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En conclusion, il convient de souligner les points suivants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3044.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3054.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La législation nationale ne prévoit pas de visite de longue durée dans les 10 premières années pour les personnes condamnées à la réclusion à perpétuité.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3054.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3061.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cette règle s'applique uniformément à toutes les personnes condamnées à la réclusion à perpétuité.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3061.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3072.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La législation nationale ne prévoit pas la possibilité de lever les restrictions sur les visites longues, quelles que soient les caractéristiques et la situation individuelle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3072.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3086.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les visites courtes, dans la forme dans laquelle elles sont réglementées par la loi, ne peuvent pas être une alternative à une visite longue et, en elles-mêmes, ne prévoient pas la réalisation du droit à la vie privée et familiale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3086.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3104.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ainsi, le requérant estime que la mesure des restrictions de visite longue sans alternative quelconque et prise en considération de circonstances individuelles n'est pas uniquement une restriction du droit, mais une violation directe du droit à la vie familiale des personnes condamnées et leurs proches.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3104.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3114.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Étant donné que cette loi a été adoptée en 1997 et qu'une telle norme n'a jamais existé auparavant, se pose la question suivante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3114.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3121.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quels intérêts privés ont été poursuivis par l'adaptation de cette loi?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3121.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3142.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le requérant estime que la réglementation juridique de ces questions ne peut pas prendre une forme de restriction rigide et le gouvernement devrait élaborer des méthodes pour évaluer la proportionnalité des restrictions qui permettraient aux autorités à parvenir à un équilibre entre les intérêts de l'individu et les intérêts de la société.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3142.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3167.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Au final, le requérant insiste sur le fait que l'interdiction législative sans alternative quelconque et une approche individuelle pour des visites longues et familiales pendant au moins dix ans est excessive et par conséquent, un juste équilibre n'a pas été ménagé entre les intérêts publics et sa vie privée et familiale, en violation du droit garanti par l'article 8 de la Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3167.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3170.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les Juges, je vous remercie de votre attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3173.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3176.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup Madame Makarova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3176.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3183.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn now to the judges and ask them if there are questions, Judge Ziemele.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3188.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3189.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3189.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3193.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, I have a rather technical question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3193.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3208.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have been explained now that there are essentially two relevant laws regulating, within different prison regimes, the question of visits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3208.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3223.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we have been said that, of course, it's the code of procedure for the execution of sentences, but the applicants also refer and explain internal rules of correctional establishments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3223.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3227.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my question is, in fact, to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3227.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3234.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is the legal character of these internal regulations?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3234.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3243.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are they law in a sense that the case law of the court has defined?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3243.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3246.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Have they been published in the official gazette?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3246.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3247.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are they accessible?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3247.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3263.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also, I understand that on the basis of these internal regulations, a number of important arrangements in relation to visits take place or carried out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3263.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3276.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are these arrangements, if the persons concerned are not satisfied, can they be appealed, these decisions taken within the correctional establishment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3276.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3283.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So any information concerning the nature, essentially, of these internal rules would be helpful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3283.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3283.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3286.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3288.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Steiner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Elisabeth Steiner</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3290.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3291.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3291.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3293.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions to each party.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3293.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3297.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One question, I will start with the question to the government first.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3297.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3314.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's representative suggested that during all short-term visits he received from his family members, the meeting room was separated by class participation and the guard was listening at hearing distance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3314.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3316.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was that really so?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3316.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3327.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And were such modalities related to the applicant's personality and individual situations, or were they generally applied to all prisoners?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3327.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3337.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to the applicant's representative, I would like to get the information, how is now the situation with respect to family visits of the applicant?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3337.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3340.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Does he receive any visits from his family members?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3340.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3344.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, which, what frequency?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3344.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3344.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3346.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3350.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, juge Sicilianos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3353.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3354.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci, M. le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3354.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3361.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je voudrais aussi poser une question aux représentants du gouvernement, M. Matyushkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3361.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3379.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La représentante du requérant nous a dit que les années passées en détention provisoire ne sont pas prises en compte, ne sont pas comptées pour l'application du délai de 10 ans pendant lequel il existe une prohibition de visite longue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3379.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3390.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Par conséquent, en réalité, nous dit la partie requérante, l'interdiction en question est bien plus longue que 10 ans et qu'en l'occurrence, elle a duré 15 ans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3390.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3400.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc je voudrais savoir si vous confirmez ou non ces affirmations de la partie requérante à la fois en droit et factuellement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3401.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3404.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, juge Kalaydjieva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Zdravka Kalaydjieva</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3409.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3411.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3411.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3414.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question goes to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3414.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3431.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I understand from the government's presentation that the purpose which the restriction is supposed to serve is the reforming of convicts sentenced to life imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3431.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3451.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To what extent, and this is related to the question of Judge Steiner, to what extent is this level of reforming measured or assessed throughout the 10 years in which the restriction is automatically imposed by the law?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3451.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3466.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on the other side, when considering requests for early release, do your courts take into consideration the extent of reforming?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3466.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3471.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And does this extent form a part of the criteria for such assessment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3471.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3471.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3476.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3478.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Nußberger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3480.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3486.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. The government has argued on the issue of admissibility that the applicant</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3486.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3496.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>has been divorced in 1996. And I first wanted to ask the applicant to comment on this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3496.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3510.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And second, I wanted to ask the government how this rule on conjugal visits generally is interpreted. Is it only applied to really married partners or also to partners living</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3510.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3515.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>together in some other form? Is it really dependent on the fact of being married? Because</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3515.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3522.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I understand in the material of the case that the applicant kept in contact with his ex-wife.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3522.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3523.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3524.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3536.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. We will have now a break of 15 minutes and we will resume the hearing around 10.25.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3747.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3748.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3789.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3792.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated. The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3794.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3795.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Matyushkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3795.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3797.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, Mr. Matyushkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3803.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3805.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3805.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3830.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>answering the first question, I should tell that all restrictions for convicts are based on the law, based on the Penitentiary Court of the Russian Federation, and the prison rules are based on this law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3830.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3838.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All these rules are contrary to the Penitentiary Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3838.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3851.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These prison rules are published in mass media officially and could be appealed to the courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3851.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3873.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the rule itself appealed in the Supreme Court of the Russian Federation, and we have this practice of the Supreme Court of Russia, and some particular appellation takes place in practice of Russian courts against these prison rules.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3873.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3912.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Answering the question of Honorable Judge Steiner, first of all, government should object to attempt of the representative of applicant to extend the limit of the case, because only long-term visits are in the scope of this consideration, and it falls for all materials of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3912.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3919.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's why we could not tell about short-term visits, strictly speaking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3919.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3940.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But answering the question of the judge, I should tell that officer present only on short visits and not a person of officer during their long-term visits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3940.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3956.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Speaking and answering the question of Judge Tsitsilianos, I should tell that the detention remand in this case of Mr. Khoroshenko</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3956.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3969.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>took place before 1998, before the date when Russia became a member of convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3969.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3981.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's why we think that it's out of the scope of this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3981.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3998.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Answering the fourth question, it should be always kept in mind that the original sentence imposed by the competent court legally called the convict's duty to serve his term until the last day of mandated imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3998.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4016.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should he behave well and thus justify for a benevolent expectation concerning his future becoming a law-abiding member of society, this cannot mean that the conditional release has become his right, his legitimate expectation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4016.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4021.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The conditional release of convict can only be a privilege.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4021.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4032.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the life imprisonment, assessing it as the original sentence imposed by the competent court, a convict has a duty to serve it for life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4032.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4049.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If a convict committed such particularly grave crimes, which entail sentencing to life imprisonment, this category of criminals demonstrate that they totally lost their relation to society and respect to its morality and the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4049.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4057.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such a general aim as social reintegration is not expected to be achieved in case of sentencing a criminal to life imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4057.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4064.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, service in life imprisonment convicts spend their whole time in a cell for two persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4064.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4072.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They work separately in special working cells, eat, take shower, have daily work separately.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4072.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4082.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The regime of service in life imprisonment sentence differs a lot from one of service in imprisonment imposed for a particular period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4082.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4094.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The isolation from the society is the main principle in the regime of service in life imprisonment sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4094.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4116.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, on the fifth question, I should tell that initially long-term visits includes relatives and are there close people to convicts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4116.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4139.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If a person is not close relative or, for example, the officially registered wife, the relations between non-relatives should be additionally explained in order to prevent disorder and protect safety.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4139.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4149.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I should tell that refusal to grant such visit could be appealed to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4149.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4149.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4154.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4156.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Matyushkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4156.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4159.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I give the floor to Ms. Preobrazhenskaya.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4159.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4161.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, Ms. Makarova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4177.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4189.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ce qui concerne la première question, il convient de dire que le gouvernement a déjà répondu que ces lois sont publiées et donc sont les lois au sens de la jurisprudence de la Cour.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4189.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4195.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La législation telle qu'elle est formulée ne prévoit pas d'exception.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4195.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4208.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Par conséquent, ni l'administration de la prison, ni le tribunal ne peuvent pas changer la situation prescrite par ces lois.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4208.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4218.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Comme le gouvernement a indiqué, le Code pénitentiaire et le règlement interne des colonies pénitentiaires prévoient la possibilité d'offerts à appels.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4218.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4229.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il convient de préciser qu'en pratique, ni le chef de la colonie pénitentiaire ni le tribunal ne peuvent pas changer la situation prescrite par ces lois.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4229.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4245.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il convient de rappeler que le requérant a fait un recours contre cette loi à la Cour constitutionnelle de Russie et que la Cour conclut à la non-violation de la Constitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4245.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4259.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pour répondre à la deuxième question, il faut dire que, comme le gouvernement a déjà dit, les conditions de visite sont prévues par le Code pénitentiaire et le régime interne.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4259.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4275.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ce qui concerne le droit à des visites des amis et des couples non mariés et d'autres personnes, ils peuvent venir à des visites courtes et longues quand cela est permis par le chef de la colonie pénitentiaire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4275.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4289.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Monsieur le Président, j'aimerais bien vous demander la permission de lire la lettre du requérant concernant sa situation individuelle pour pouvoir répondre au plus pleinement à vos questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4289.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4291.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4291.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4300.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, étant donné que le requérant ne se trouve pas en mesure d'être présent à l'audience d'aujourd'hui, il nous a demandé de nous adresser à la Cour à son nom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4300.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4303.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je le cite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4303.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4308.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Au moment de mon arrestation, j'étais mariée et j'avais un fils de trois ans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4308.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4314.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Un autre, ma famille proche, est composée de mes parents, de mon frère et de ma grand-mère.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4314.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4323.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'étais en contact avec toutes ces personnes ainsi qu'avec tous les parents éloignés que je connaissais, qui sont au nombre de 17 personnes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4323.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4326.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je souligne avec tous.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4326.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4337.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Depuis mon arrestation et jusqu'à la fin de l'enquête préliminaire en été 1995, j'ai été retenue en alternance dans plusieurs maisons d'arrêt dans les villes différentes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4337.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4349.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pendant tout ce temps, c'est-à-dire pendant cinq ans, on m'a autorisé une seule visite ne dépassant pas une demi-heure avec ma femme en présence d'un inspecteur.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4349.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4354.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Aucune autre visite avec mes parents et amis n'a pas été autorisée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4354.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4360.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Par ailleurs, mes parents et amis n'étaient même pas autorisés à être présents à mon procès.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4360.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4371.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les visites longues m'ont été autorisées en octobre 2009, soit dix ans après mon arrivée à la colonie pénitentiaire et environ 15 ans après mon arrestation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4371.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4379.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'ai utilisé toutes les possibilités que la loi m'attribue pour ces visites, soit une fois tous les six mois.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4379.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4384.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Chacune de ces visites a duré le maximum autorisé par la loi, c'est-à-dire trois jours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4384.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4388.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Outre ma mère, mon frère vient généralement pour les visites.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4388.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4391.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mon père n'est pas venu après 2007.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4391.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4398.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Son état de santé ne le permettant pas, il n'est jamais venu pour une visite longue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4398.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4405.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En décrivant mes relations avec ma famille et les vieux amis, je tiens tout d'abord à souligner une particularité.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4405.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4415.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je suis bien consciente que, du point de vue objectif, il y a des raisons de douter de mon innocence, sur laquelle j'insistais et j'insiste encore.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4415.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4424.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais aucun de mes parents et de mes amis ne m'ont jamais exprimé ce doute, ce dont je leur suis extrêmement reconnaissant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4424.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4427.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est le meilleur soutien moral.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4427.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4434.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Après mon arrestation, l'État m'a privé de toutes sortes de possibilités de rester en contact avec ma famille et mes amis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4434.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4440.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'ai été interdit de correspondance, de conversation téléphonique, de toute visite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4440.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4446.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'ai reçu le droit à la correspondance en janvier 1997.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4446.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4460.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'ai immédiatement repris tous les contacts avec mes parents et mon frère, avec trois de mes amis de longue date et avec mon ex-femme, avec laquelle nous avons divorcé à son initiative en 1996.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4460.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4465.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'ai reçu le droit à des visites courtes en octobre 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4465.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4470.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je les utilisais aussi souvent que permis par la loi et les circonstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4470.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4474.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pour ces visites sont venus en alternance les membres de ma famille.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4474.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4479.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mes amis sont venus deux fois, mais ils n'ont pas été autorisés à me rendre visite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4479.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4482.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, ils ont mis fin à ces tentatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4482.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4483.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fin de la citation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4483.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4502.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Malgré le fait qu'après le changement des conditions pour purger la peine, le requérant ait été en mesure de rétablir et de maintenir le contact avec certains parents et amis, il a perdu irrévocablement le contact avec d'autres proches, comme par exemple avec son fils, qu'il n'a pas vu depuis 20 ans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4502.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4515.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je cite, mon fils refuse catégoriquement de me voir, de m'écrire, de parler avec moi et en même temps, il est prêt à m'aider financièrement, juridiquement et avec les informations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4515.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4526.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il semble que mon fils n'a pas de doute quant à mon innocence, sinon il ne m'aurait pas aidé, mais je n'arrive pas à construire une relation acceptable avec lui.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4526.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4528.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fin de la citation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4528.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4537.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En outre, j'aimerais bien préciser, enfin, en ce qui concerne la possibilité de prendre en compte la durée de la détention provisoire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4537.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4549.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Même cela est théoriquement possible, selon la décision de la Cour constitutionnelle dans l'affaire Gerasimov du 21 décembre 2004, en pratique, cette possibilité ne s'applique pas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4549.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4558.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Même si cette norme est théoriquement applicable, dans tous les cas, cette durée d'au moins de 10 ans paraît excessivement longue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4558.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4571.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il convient de souligner que pendant les premières années d'emprisonnement, la personne se trouve dans la situation la plus stressante, quand elle est non seulement privée de la liberté, mais son destin est en train d'être décidé.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4571.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4578.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pendant ce temps, la personne peut s'habituer à sa nouvelle situation ou peut être démoralisée et dégradée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4578.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4588.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pour éviter cela, la communication avec ses proches est très importante, car ses proches jouent un rôle d'un élément de liaison entre le détenu et la société.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4588.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4588.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je vous remercie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4591.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4599.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4599.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4606.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the Court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4606.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4610.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4610.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4614.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of any decision in due course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4614.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4617.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
