<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>4246113_08072015</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>21.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>21.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>73.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>86.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the cases of Karácsony and others against Hungary and Szél  and others against Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>86.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>103.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first application was lodged with the court on the 14th of June, 2013, under Article 34 of the Convention, by four Hungarian nationals, Mr. Gergely Karácsony, Mr. Péter Szilágyi,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>103.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>108.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Dávid Dorosz and Ms. Rebeka Katalin Szabó.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>108.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>126.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second application was lodged with the court on the 5th of July, 2013, by three Hungarian nationals, Ms. Bernadett Szél, Ms. Ágnes Osztolykán and Ms. Szilvia Lengyel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>126.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>136.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were allocated to the second section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>136.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>144.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were communicated to the government on the 7th of November, 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>144.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>153.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 16th of September, 2014, a chamber of that section delivered two parallel judgments in the cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>153.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>165.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In each case, it held that there had been a violation of Article 10 of the Convention and a violation of Article 13, read in conjunction with Article 10 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>165.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>185.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 15th of December, 2014, the government requested that the cases be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention, and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on the 16th of February, 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>185.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>206.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 20th of May, 2015, the governments of the Czech Republic and of the United Kingdom were granted leave under Article 36, paragraph 2 of the Convention and Rule 44, paragraph 3 of the Rules of Court, to make written submissions to the court as third parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>206.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>212.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by Mr. Barna Berke, Secretary of State in the Ministry</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>212.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>221.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Justice, and by their agent, Mr. Zoltán Tallódi, assisted by Ms. Ágnes Bruszt, Mr. Tibor</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>221.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>230.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bárány, Ms. Zita Tóth, Ms. Noémi Sebők, and Mr. Attila Vági, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>230.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>238.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mr. Daniel Karsai, counsel assisted by Mrs. Flóra Kollarics</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>238.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>242.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. Vikor Kazai, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>242.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>249.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two of the applicants, Ms. Lengyel and Ms. Szél, are also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>249.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>255.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>255.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>267.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to welcome delegations from the Ministry of Justice of Armenia and from the Moldovan Constitutional Court who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>267.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>281.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting from and into Hungarian has been authorized at the request of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>281.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>297.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, interpreting into Armenian has been authorized for the benefit of the Armenian delegation and interpreting into Serbian has been authorized for the benefit of a group of judicial associates who attend the hearing today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>297.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>308.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>308.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>319.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>319.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>326.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Karsai for the applicants will speak first and then Mr. Tallódi for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>326.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>326.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Karsai.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>333.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>336.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable European Court of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>336.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>341.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a special honor to address the Court today in this important and interesting matter at hand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>341.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>347.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The present case deals with the freedom of expression of members of Parliament belonging to the opposition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>347.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>353.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This freedom was restricted by not an external force, but from within the Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>353.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>358.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This restricting and rather strong force was the governing majority itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>358.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>385.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, today we have to find an answer to the question whether opposition members of Parliament in a situation being systematically deprived of the effective participation in the parliamentary decision-making are allowed under Article 10 of the Convention to express their opinion on subjects of high public importance by way of using symbolical speech without causing any significant disruption in the working of the House.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>385.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>394.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also need to address the issue whether the applicants are entitled to an effective remedy under Article 13 if their freedom of expression was seriously violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>394.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>403.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We accept that symbolic speeches, like displaying billboards, should be considered as exceptional tools of expressing political opinions in plenary sessions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>403.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>420.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the applicants are of the view that in the specific circumstances of the present case the use of these means was justified under Article 10 and the sanction imposed on the applicants violated the article in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>420.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>432.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honourable Judges, The applicants would like to underline that they do not argue that the notion of parliamentary sovereignty shall be put aside in the present case or it shall have a completely new meaning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>432.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>439.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants do not argue for a general reform of the parliamentary disciplinary law throughout the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>439.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>447.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They do not argue that members of Parliament who gave this trap the working of the House should not be sanctioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>447.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>456.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, they do not argue that the imposition of a fine on members of Parliament is in itself or in abstracto contrary to the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>456.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>468.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the applicants note that the application of the same or similar legal institution can differ significantly in different Member States depending on the specific political context and the national case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>468.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>479.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, finding a violation in the present case will not necessarily bring about changes in parliamentary law in general throughout the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>479.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>490.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What the applicants argue is that freedom of speech of opposition members of Parliament shall be protected against not only external but against internal attacks as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>490.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>494.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The rights of opposition are inherently part of parliamentary sovereignty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>494.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>500.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, we argue that parliamentary sovereignty cannot be used against itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>500.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>503.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this sense, it has boundaries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>503.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>514.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A parliamentary majority cannot hide behind the notion of sovereignty while restricting opposition MPs' rights under the Convention since this would constitute a clear misuse of that notion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>514.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>527.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We therefore argue that establishing conventional limits of disciplinary law is not a deprivation of parliamentary sovereignty of its very essence which is offering protection from any illegal interference with its work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>527.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>542.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the parliamentary sovereignty is strengthened by protecting the opposition members of Parliament when their freedom of political speech, the heartland of parliamentary sovereignty, is endangered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>542.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>550.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honourable European Court of Human Rights, For this brief introduction, first we would like to address the admissibility of the applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>550.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>558.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question is whether the constitutional complaint can be considered as an effective remedy within the meaning of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>558.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>563.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer is a clear no to this question for the following reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>563.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>577.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It must be noted at the outset that the Government's submission is misleading because it simply disregards the fact that on 1 January 2012 a completely new Act on the Constitutional Court came into force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>577.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>588.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This new Act created a new procedure of the Constitutional Court, therefore its previous related case law cannot be, or only to a very limited extent can be applied in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>588.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>598.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, the applicants underline that the Government failed to show any relevant case law of the Constitutional Court concerning parliamentary disciplinary procedures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>598.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>610.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not surprising, since the Constitutional Court has never ruled on constitutional complaints dealing with parliamentary disciplinary law prior to the events of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>610.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>622.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is undisputed that the type of constitutional complaint invoked by the Government can only be directed against legal provisions, but not against parliamentary disciplinary decisions themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>622.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>631.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, it is not a German-type constitutional complaint resulting possibly in the annulment of the impugn decisions or any court judgments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>631.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>646.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the so-called constitutional complaint being in fact a petition for norm control, the applicants could have challenged only the constitutionality of the legal provisions based on which they were sanctioned for expressing their political view.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>646.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>657.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such a procedure has never been classified in the Court's case law as an effective remedy since it cannot redress the actual prejudice suffered, it only quashes its legal background.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>657.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>676.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The disciplinary decisions and their consequences would have remained intact even in the event of an eventual violation, eventual success before the Constitutional Court, because this kind of constitutional complaint is not capable of triggering a new disciplinary procedure within the Parliament or any other review mechanism.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>676.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>687.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Based on the above-mentioned reasons, which we expressed in more detail in our written related memorandum, the constitutional complaint cannot be regarded as an effective remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>687.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>690.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let us now turn to the merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>690.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>699.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the correct assessment of factual and legal background of the issue at hand, it is necessary to start with shortly describing its political context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>699.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>715.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, it shall be noted that from 2010, the governing coalition, based on its two-third majority in the Parliament, started to gradually abolish the system of checks and balances and to eliminate all those voices who are critical towards it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>715.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>749.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not only domestic and international NGOs, but also prestigious international organizations and bodies, such as the Office for Democratic Institutions and Human Rights, the Commissioner for Human Rights of the Council of Europe, the Venice Commission, the different institutions and bodies of the European Union, have permanently criticized the Hungarian government for changing the written and undetermined rules of democracy and rule of law to create a political environment which is hostile towards the critical voices, including those of the opposition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>749.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>757.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the opportunity of the opposition to meaningfully participate in the parliamentary decision-making deteriorated drastically.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>757.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>770.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government tries to create an image about the applicants, picturing that they were simply too careless to use the ordinary means of parliamentary communication, so instead they decided to obstruct the working of the House.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>770.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>773.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The truth is the exact opposite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>773.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>779.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The facts clearly show that the applicants actively use the ordinary means of parliamentary communication.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>779.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>787.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the governing coalition made these communications devoid of any success to the point of almost total irrelevance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>787.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>790.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let us give you a few examples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>790.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>805.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the governing coalition introduced the so-called exceptional urgent procedure, which allows the adoption of statutes in an extremely limited time frame and under conditions which preclude any meaningful examination of and debate on the act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>805.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>818.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government used this procedure 27 times between 2010 and 2014 for the adoption of very important statutes having a huge impact on the economy and the society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>818.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>831.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, in the 2010 to 2014 parliamentary term, the applicants' party submitted 105 legislative proposals, but only one was adopted by the governing majority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>831.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>840.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parliamentary opposition altogether submitted 445 legislative proposals in total, but only two were adopted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>840.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>851.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants' party suggested the modification of legislative proposals in almost 5,000 points, but less than 1% of their proposals were adopted by the parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>851.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>859.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The opposition in total suggested almost 17,000 modifications, but only 3.4% of their suggestions</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>859.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>862.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>were adopted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>862.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>873.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These are extremely low figures, even if we accept that the majority naturally has the right and responsibility to govern and pass laws corresponding to its political and vocational views.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>873.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>882.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The above statistics clearly indicate that the governing coalition did not let the opposition to have any impact on the policymaking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>882.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>892.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition to that, it can be also observed, although it is more difficult to express in exact figures, that the parliamentary debate itself lost its depth in general terms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>892.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>902.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants and the opposition members of parliament very often do not receive meaningful and meritorious answers and reactions to their questions and proposals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>902.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>908.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The real vocational debate nowadays is painfully missing from the Hungarian parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>908.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>915.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these circumstances, the applicants, opposition MPs, found themselves in a difficult situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>915.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>924.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were elected and therefore obliged both legally and morally to represent the views and interests of their voters and of the public interest in general.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>924.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>937.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, they had to realize that they were not in the position to pursue these aims with a reasonable chance of success by using the ordinary means of communication, since the serious vocational debate disappeared from the parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>937.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>951.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We need to add at this juncture that such a debate is often missing from the Hungarian national television and radio, being under the total control of the government, but which is the only media source accessible in the whole territory of the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>951.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>960.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, it is a matter of fact that the government is overrepresented in general in the Hungarian media.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>960.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>973.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this situation, the applicants have chosen not to give up, but to raise their voices by using symbolical speech, since it was the only way they could express their disagreement in an audible manner with the government's actions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>973.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>975.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We again underline at this point that a.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>975.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>981.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicants protested against government policies related to affairs of high public importance and b.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>981.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>988.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicants' actions caused only a minor disturbance, if any, in the working of the House.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>988.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1000.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The characterization of the events by the government as a vicious obstruction of the parliamentary work and the deprivation of other MPs of their basic prerogatives is simply an exaggeration and completely misleading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1000.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1008.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The sheer facts show that other MPs were not deprived either of their right to speak or of their right to vote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1008.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1019.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The minutes of the plenary sessions clearly demonstrate that after a few minutes the other MPs could continue their speech and could vote and successfully adopt the legislative proposals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1019.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1028.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite this minor impact on the working of the House, the applicants were punished with one of the most severe sanctions they were fined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1028.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1036.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not even considered whether a more lenient sanction could have served the purposes of the disciplinary regulations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1036.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1048.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We now have to reach a conclusion on whether the restriction on applicants' freedom of political speech was in compliance with the requirement of Article 10.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1048.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1052.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the outset, we shall note that the case law of the Court is clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1052.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1063.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any restriction on the applicants' right to freedom of political speech must carry very weighty reasons and at the same time calls for the closest scrutiny on the Court's part.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1063.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1070.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In general, freedom of expression constitutes one of the essential foundations of a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1070.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1082.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because of its privileged status in the convention system, every restriction of this freedom must be interpreted narrowly and the necessity of any restriction must be convincingly established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1082.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1087.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This special protection naturally applies to symbolic speeches as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1087.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1101.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, this case concerns the political speech of elected representatives, for whom it has utmost importance since they represent the electorate, draw attention to their preoccupations and defend their interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1101.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1110.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, we completely agree with the Chamber's finding that the political speech deserves higher protection when it is expressed in the Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1110.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1121.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court has acknowledged many times that while freedom of expression is important for political parties and politicians, it has particular significance for the opposition parties and MPs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1121.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1127.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the freedom of expression of opposition MPs calls for the closest scrutiny on the Court's part.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1127.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1141.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In a parliamentary system, where the government and the parliamentary majority create one unified political power, which is the case in Hungary, the real division of power is between the governing majority and the opposition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1141.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1150.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to the dominance and the power of the governing majority, the opposition may easily find itself in a vulnerable and disadvantageous position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1150.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1160.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the proper functioning of a democracy and Parliament, the opposition needs special legal guarantees and special rights to be somehow compensated for this vulnerability.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1160.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1171.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also note that this was the view of the Venice Commission expressed in its report on the role of the opposition in a democratic Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1171.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1181.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the above criteria, to the facts of the present case, for the applicants only one logical conclusion follows, finding the violation of Article 10 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1181.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1195.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants expressed political opinions on subjects of high public importance in their capacity of opposition members of Parliament without causing any significant hindrance to the working of the House.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1195.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1201.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The expression of such opinions requires the utmost level of protection according to the law of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1201.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1205.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in this case, this protection was missing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1205.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1222.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants' political opponents misusing and misinterpreting the parliamentary sovereignty and the disciplinary regulation by the force of their parliamentary majority throughout a partisan and biased procedure punished the applicants for voicing critical views towards the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1222.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1234.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The malafide nature of the actions of the parliamentary majority is also manifest from the fact that the application of a more lenient sanction was not even considered, but the imposition of a fine was immediately applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1234.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1243.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these circumstances, the interference with the applicants' rights under Article 10 cannot be justified under the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1243.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1248.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We finally address the issue of the violation of the applicants' right to effective remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1248.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1257.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was described already in detail in our written submissions that the applicants did not have an effective remedy at their disposal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1257.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1266.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a summary, we just refer to the fact that all stages of the disciplinary proceedings were politically biased and controlled by the governing coalition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1266.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1276.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants drew attention to the fact that from 1 January 2013, the Hungarian disciplinary law has changed at the expense of the opposition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1276.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1289.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also a telling fact that only after that date and only against opposition MPs were such disciplinary proceedings initiated, which ended by the imposition of a pecuniary sanction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1289.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1292.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants could turn nowhere for redress.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1292.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1299.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was neither an internal forum within the Parliament nor any external one which could review the disciplinary decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1299.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1304.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, there was a violation of the applicants' right to an effective remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1304.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1313.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants underline that they do not want to speculate on what form of redress shall be chosen which is compatible with the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1313.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1318.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We humbly note that not even the Court shall describe a specific form of a legal avenue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1318.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1325.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our view, this may be even impossible given the different rules and traditions of the Member States of the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1325.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1330.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, this is not necessary for finding the violation in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1330.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1341.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is enough to establish that the actual Hungarian procedure was at odds with Article 13, which requires the existence of an independent and impartial forum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1341.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1361.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honourable Judges, To summarise it all, this case concerns members of the opposition who had to fulfil their duties in a very hostile political and media environment and who were systematically deprived of any meaningful participation in the legislative process and parliamentary debate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1361.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1373.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this situation, they expressed their political opinion on subjects of high public importance by way of using symbolical speech but without causing any significant disruption in the working on the House.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1373.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1382.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, they were immediately fined without even considering the imposition of any more lenient sanction in an unfair and biased disciplinary procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1382.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1392.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was a disproportionate sanction and thus violated their right to freedom of political speech and the right to an effective remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1392.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1401.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We therefore ambly ask the Court to find the violation of Article 10 and 13 of the Convention and adjudicate just satisfaction for the prejudices suffered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1401.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1401.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1404.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1408.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mr. Karsai. I give the floor to Mr. Tallódi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1419.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1423.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tisztelt Elnök úr, tisztelt Bírák, Hölgyeim és Uraim!</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1423.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1432.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nagy megtiszteltetés, hogy a magyar kormány képviseletében lehetőségen van a szél és társai és a karácsony és társai kontra Magyarország ügyben előadni szóbeli észrevételeinket.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1432.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1442.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Miután az írásos beadványban mindkét félnek volt lehetősége részletesen ismertetni érveit, most az ügykel kapcsolatos legfontosabb kérdésekre szeretnénk kitérni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1442.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1459.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Látszólag jelen ügy tárgyát 7 magyar képviselő házszabályellenes magatartása és annak szankcionálása képezi, azonban az ítélet nem csupán a teremben jelenlévő feleket érinti, hiszen a bíróság most határozza meg a parlamenti szólásszabadság általános kereteit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1459.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1469.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>2013 tavaszán és nyarán 7 képviselő zavarta meg a Magyarországgyűlés munkáját molinók, táblák felmutatásával és megafon használatával.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1469.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1473.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ám nem elszigetelt jelenségről van szó.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1473.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1476.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A politikai kultúra világszerte átalakulóban van.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1476.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1486.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az egyes vélemények könnyűszerre lejjutnak a választópolgárokhoz, ez biztosítja a vélemények pluralitását és a véleményjelvánítás szabadságának széles körű érvényesülését.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1486.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1492.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>E kedvező hatás mellett számolni kell azonban a folyamat kontraproduktivitásával is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1492.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1501.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A sokféle vélemény közül kitűnni vágyó szereplők egyre szélsőségesebb akciókkal tudják csak felhívni magukra a figyelmet, az egyébként megosztott figyelmet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1501.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1507.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>E figyelemért folytatott harc része a kérelmezők jelen ügyben tanúsított magatartása is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1507.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1530.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Célzottan házszabályellenes fellépésük, a véleményük kifejtésére biztosított házszabályszerű lehetőségek figyelmen kívülhagyása, az őket ért szankciókkal kapcsolatos kommunikáció a médiában és a bírósághoz benyújtott indítványaik mindarról tanúskodnak, hogy a kérelmezők a bíróság eljárását is saját adott esetben politikai céljaikra kívánják felhasználni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1530.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1546.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormány visszautasítja a kérelmezők beadványaiban újra és újra megfogalmazott azon vádakat, amelyekkel a magyar parlamenti demokrácia működését illették, a kormány megítélése szerint ugyanis ezek messze túlmutatnak a jelen eljárás tárgyát képező ügyön.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1546.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1551.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tisztelt Bíróság! A kormány nem ért egyet a kérelmezők provokatív magatartásával,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1551.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1558.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>amelyel a bírósági eljárást a magyar parlament demokratikus működésének elmarasztalása felé kívánják orientálni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1558.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1566.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A magyar parlament a több száz éves európai és hazai hagyományoknak és a közös európai értékeinknek megfelelően szabályozottan működik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1566.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1576.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Magyarország elkötelezett az egyezményben deklarált szabadságjogok mellett, alaptörvénye és számos törvénye biztosítja a véleményjelvánítás szabadságát.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1576.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1582.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az Országgyűlés fegyelmi szabályozása egyszerre szerez érvényt a működő képesség követelményének és a szólásszabadságnak is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1582.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1592.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A demokrácia nemcsak a szabadság, hanem az együttműködés és alkalmazkodás rendje is, amelyet azonban a kérelmezők magukra nézve nem tekintettek követendőnek.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1592.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1600.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Magyarország alaptörvénye alapján az országgyűlési képviselők jogai és kötelezettségei egyenlők.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1600.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1612.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Valamennyi képviselő jogosult törvényjavaslat benyújtására, interpellációt és kérdést intézhet a kormányhoz, és kérdést meghatározott állami vezetőkhöz.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1612.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1619.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Felszólalhat a törvényjavaslatok tárgyalása során, és szavazatával dönthet azok elfogadásáról vagy elutasításáról.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1619.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1626.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az országgyűlésről szóló törvény pedig biztosítja, hogy a képviselők részt vegyenek az országgyűlési bizottságok szakmai munkájában.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1626.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1638.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A törvényjavaslatok plenáris vitái során az előterjesztőt és a kormány képviselőjét követően a kormánypárti és az ellenzéki képviselők között változó sorrendben egymást váltva szólalhatnak fel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1638.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1656.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A 2010-2014-es parlamenti ciklusban az ellenzéki képviselők mintegy 1632 órányi időtartamban szólaltak fel, míg a kormánypárti képviselők és a kormánytagok együttes beszédideje ennél jelentősen kevesebb, 1288 órányi volt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1656.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1676.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ezek a tények kellően szemléltetik, hogy a kérelmezőknek a törvényjavaslatok tárgyalása során épp úgy joguk volt a tárgyalási és felszólalási rendre irányadó szabályok betartásával szabadon felszólalni, mint a kormánypárti képviselőknek, valamint szavazatukkal nyomatékosíthatták álláspontjukat.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1676.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1688.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ehelyett a plenáris ülésmenetét szándékosan félbeszakítva, tudatosan választották a véleményeket, a válítási jogsértő formáit. A kormány nem ért egyet a kérelmezők azonállításával,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1688.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1703.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>mely szerint az ellenzék lehetőségei a fontos politikai döntéshozatali eljárásokban való hatékony részvételre elhanyagolható alacsony szintre csökkentek. A parlamenti döntéshozatal egy többségjelven működő demokráciában</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1703.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1709.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>értelemszerűen a többség akaratát üttetje érvényre, mivel a többségjelv a kisebbségjogokkal számít.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1709.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1716.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A többségjelv a kisebbségjogok védelmének biztosításával a demokratikus intézményrendszer alapvető pillére.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1716.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1739.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az eljárás tisztességességét pedig nem kérdőjelezi meg, hogy a parlamenti döntésben a demokratikus választások eredményeként kialakult többség akarata jut érvényre, mint ahogy az általukhozott törvények érvényességét és kötelező erejét sem vonja a kétségbe, mivel az ellenzék a törvény ellenében szavazott. Ezért a kormány egyrésztről elutasítja a kérelmezők ezen megállapításait,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1739.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1757.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>mivel azok lényegében a parlamentális demokráciákban érvényesülő többségi elvet kifogásolják, másrésztről egyetnem értését fejezi ki azzal szemben, hogy a bíróság előtt zajló eljárást, annak konkrét tárgyától elvonatkoztatva, arra használták fel, hogy politikai szembenállásuknak hangot adjanak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1757.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1772.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A provokatív jellegű magatartás védelemben részesül, úgy a parlamenti viták jelentős átalakulásával kell számolni az európai parlamentek mindegyikében, és újfajta parlamenti magatartás és kultúra térhódításával kell szembenézni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1772.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1774.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tisztelt Bíróság!</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1774.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1785.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A magyar kormány ezt a fajta tendenciát igen aggasztónak találja, már csak azért is, mert az Európa-tanács számos országában tetten érhető, a kérelmezők magatartása nem kezelhető egyedi ügyként.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1785.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1792.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az e fajta képviselői magatartásra pedig a tagállami fegyelmi jogi szabályozások nagyon hasonló képen reagálnak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1792.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1803.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bár a részletszabályokban találhatóak eltérések, egyetlen tagállami fegyelmi jog sem tolerálja a parlamentek működő képességét veszélyeztető politikai akciókat.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1803.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1806.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A Bíróság ítéletének precedens ereje vitathatatlan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1806.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1817.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Erre tekintettel Magyarország kormánya a Bíróság figyelmébe ajánlja az Európa-tanács többi tagállamának vonatkozó szabályozását és azok alkalmazási gyakorlatát is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1817.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1842.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A magyar kormány megítélése szerint a tényállás nem értékelhető kizárólag önmagában, mert a döntés elvi megállapításai folytán meghatározó jelentősséggel bír a teljes európai parlamenti fegyelmi jogra nézve, és ezen keresztül a tagállami képviselőknek nyilvánvalóan meghatározza a nemzeti parlamentekben tanúsított magatartását a házszabályi rendelkezések betartása terén.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1842.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1850.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A tagállami parlamentek fegyelmi szabályozásai közötti hasonlóság a közös európai kultúrában és hagyományokban gyökerezik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1850.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1860.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ezen felül valamennyi nemzeti parlamentben kiemelt érdek fűződik a törvényalkotás hatékonyságához és a testület munkájába vetett közbizalomhoz.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1860.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1873.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A tagállami parlament rendezett keretek között biztosítja a parlamenti beszédjogot, és a képviselők magatartása alapján valamennyi tagállam szembesül a fenti érdekek és a parlamenti szólásszabadság között feszülő ellentéttel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1873.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1888.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ez az ellentét azonban csak látszólagos, hiszen a hatékony működést biztosító szabályok a valamennyi képviselőt egyenlő módon megillető beszédjog érdekében születtek, és a parlamenti szólásszabadság szükséges és arányos korlátozásával járnak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1888.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1903.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ily emelt jelentősséggel bír, hogy a bíróság hol húzza meg vizsgálati jogosultságának határait, milyen mértékben tartja magát kompetensnek a nemzeti szuverenitás legfőbb szerve belső szabályainak felülvizsgálata során.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1903.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1913.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormány rá kíván mutatni, hogy a nemzeti szuverenitás legfőbb letéteményese a választók-polgárok közössége által választott képviselőkből álló országgyűlés.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1913.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1934.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A parlament, mint autonomszerv és mint demokratikus államberendezkedés intézménye, belső szervezeti, egy fegyelmi szabályai is különös védelmet igényelnek a külső beavatkozástól, mind tagállami szinten a hatalmiágak elválasztására, mind európai szinten a nemzeti szuverenitásra való tekintettel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1934.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1948.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ezzel kapcsolatban a kormány felhívja a figyelmet a tisztelt bíróság Kárt kontra Törökország ügyben hozott ítéletének azon megállapítására, amely szerint a parlamenti jogterületén a tagállamok széles mérlegelési jogkörrel rendelkeznek.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1948.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1963.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ezt széles mérlegelési jog magában foglalja bizonyos eszközök, így például molinók, megafonok használatának tiltását a parlament területén és a tagállami parlament jogát, hogy értékelje ezeknek a magatartásoknak a súlyosságát.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1963.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1975.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kamara döntésében általános jelleggel állapítja meg, hogy a molinók felmutatása és a megafon használata a politikai véleményjávánítása részét képezték.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1975.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1996.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormány álláspontja ezzel szemben az, hogy annak eldöntése, hogy az adott jogsértő, szimbolikus magatartás súlyosan sértée az országgyűlés tekintéjét, az adott tagállam történelmi hagyományai, politikai kultúrája és mindenkori házszabálya alapján a tagállami mérlegelési jogkör kompetenciájába tartozik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1996.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2010.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ez támasztja alá, hogy vannak tagállamok, amelyekben a szóban forgó jogsértő magatartás kezelhető házelnöki megrovással, és vannak amelyek egyáltalán nem tolerálják a politikai véleményjávánítás e, úgymond nem verbális módjait.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2010.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2025.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Németországban a Bundestag házszabálya, bár lehetővé teszi a pénzbüntetés alkalmazását, általában mégis elegendő a képviselők házelnök általi figyelmeztetése és a jogsértő magatartás folytatásának következményeire való felhívás.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2025.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2035.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ukrajnában viszont kifejezetten házszabályilag rögzített, hogy tilos a molinók, hangosító vagy egyéb rendhagyó kommunikációs eszközök használata az ülésteremben.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2035.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2043.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Amíg a Bíróság elfogadta, hogy az Egyezmény 10. cikkének második pontja értelmében a beavatkozás mások jogainak védelmét</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2043.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2052.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>és a rendzavarás megelőzését mint legitim célt szolgálta, a beavatkozások arányosságát nem ismerte el.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2052.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2062.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A következőkben a beavatkozások arányosságát kívánom igazolni a kormány korábban benyújtott beadványainak megfelelően.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2062.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2072.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kisztelt Bíróság! Először is arra kívánom felhívni a figyelmet, hogy jelen ügyben a beavatkozások arányosak voltak az ügy sajátos körülményeire tekintettel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2072.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2088.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A parlamenti képviselők jogállásából fakadó képviselői szólásszabadság az Európai Államok alkotmányos rendszereiben sajátos jogintézmény, amelynek a véleménynyilvánítási joghoz, mint alapjoghoz képest speciális szabályai korlátozásának különleges formái vannak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2088.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2098.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A képviselői beszédjog és a szólásszabadság korlátozásai más megítélés alá tartoznak, mint a véleménynyilvánítás szabadságához fűződő más emberi jogoké.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2098.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2115.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A képviselők véleménynyilvánítási szabadsága képviselői jogállásukból származik, mert bizárolag ezt teszi lehetővé számukra, hogy felszólaljanak a parlament ülésein, illetve véleményüket más formában, például szavazatuk leadásával kifejezzék.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2115.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2127.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A képviselők számtalan módon és eszközzel elérhetik választóikat és a kívánt médiafigyelmet, anélkül, hogy ezzel a parlament tekintéjét sértenék, vagy méltóságát veszélyeztetnék.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2127.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2134.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A parlamenten kívüli véleménynyilvánítás lehetősége ugyanolyan formában áll a képviselők, mint bármely állampolgár rendelkezésére.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2134.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2147.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Szabadon kifejthetik véleményüket számos fórumon, ám parlamenti tagságukból következően, figyelemmel az országgyűlés elsődleges funkciójára, parlamenti beszédjoguk szabályozott keretek között érvényesülhet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2147.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2159.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mindenképpen elfogadhatatlan, ha egy törvénysértő, rendzavarú módon viselkedő képviselő magatartásával jogkövető képviselőtársát akadályozza beszédjoga gyakorlásában.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2159.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2171.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Szükséges megjegyezni, működő képességük biztosítása érdekében nem csak a parlamentek fogadnak el eljárási szabályokat, és alkalmaznak a megsértésük esetére irányadó jogkövetkezményeket.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2171.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2179.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A rendfentartása legalább ekkora jelentőséggel bír más szervek, így többek között ezen bíróság számára is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2179.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2197.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A tárgyalások során elhangzó felszólalások kötött szabályok szerint zajlanak, a molinó, illetve megafon használatával történő vélemény kifejtésnek nincs helye, így a bíróságon sem, az súlyosan megzavarna az eljárást, arról nem szólva, hogy komolyan sértené a bíróság és a felek méltóságát.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2197.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2209.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A beavatkozás arányosságát alapozza meg mindenek előtt az a körülmény, hogy a molinó és a megafon használata minden vizsgált esetben fennakadást okozott a parlamenti vitában, illetve a határozathozatalban.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2209.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2225.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A Karácsony Gergely és Dorosz Dávid akciója a kormány képviselőjének felszólalását szakított a félbe, Szabó Rebaka, Dorosz Dávid, Szél Bernadett, Lengyel, Szilvia és Osztojka Nágnes pedig a szavazások folytatását akadályozták.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2225.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2232.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A képviselői magatartásuk emellett mind tartalmuknál, mind megjelenésüknél fogva sértették az országgyűlés tekintélyét.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2232.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2240.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az intézkedések arányosságát a törvényben rögzített fegyelmi jogi szankciók fokozatos alkalmazása is megalapozta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2240.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2260.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az ügyekben kiszabott pénzbírságok mértéke szintén az intézkedések fokozatos és arányos alkalmazásának tényét támasztja alá, hiszen a házelnök és az országgyűlés az esetek felében eltekintett a pénzbírság törvény alapján kiszabható legmagasabb mértékének megállapításától.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2260.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2270.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az országgyűlésről szóló törvény alapján ugyanis az érintett ügyekben a képviselők egyhavi tiszteletdíjának egy harmadát elérő pénzbírság kiszabására is lehetőség volt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2270.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2284.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A házelnök azonban javaslatai megtétele során figyelemmel volt az ügyek sajátos körülményeire, az elkövetett magatartások súlyára, és arra, hogy a házszabálysértő képviselők tanúsítottak-e már korábban is hasonló viselkedést.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2284.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2294.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ezzel szemben a tagállami szabályozások egy része is lehetővé teszi a képviselői utatások, akár egészének visszatartását is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2294.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2304.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormány cáfolja a kérelmezők azonállítását és a bíróság kielentését, mely szerint a szankciókat mindenféle előzetes figyelmeztetés nélkül szabták ki.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2304.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2312.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ennek alátámasztására a kormány a nagykamara számára megküldött beadványához csatolta az érintett ülések jegyzőkönyveit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2312.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2329.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ezekből egyértelműen kitűnik, hogy az ülést vezető elnök minden esetben felhívta a képviselőket, hogy hagyják abba rendzavaró magatartásukat, ám a kérelmezők ennek egyik alkalommal sem tettek eleget, és csak többszöri felszólítás után sikerült helyreállítani a rendet az ülésteremben.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2329.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2355.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ezzel együtt a kormány megjegyzi, hogy számos tagállam szabályai alapján lehetőség van bizonyos jogsértő magatartások tanúsítása esetén arra, hogy a házelnök vagy javaslata alapján a parlament előzetes figyelmeztetés vagy kevésbé korlátozó intézkedés nélkül közvetlenül szabjon ki a pénzbüntetés utólagos alkalmazásánál a vélemény nyilvánítási szabadságot súlyosabban korlátozó szankciót.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2355.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2370.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Súlyos rendzavarás esetén lehetőség van azonnali kizárásra Németország, Horvátország, Litvánia, Málta, az Egyesült Királyság, Grózia, Görögország és Olaszország házszabályi rendelkezései szerint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2370.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2381.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kiszabott szankciók is arányban álltak a tanúsított magatartásokkal, hiszen természetüknél és súlyuknál fogva nem akadályozták meg az érintett képviselőket abban, hogy véleményüket kifejtsék.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2381.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2395.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kamara döntése szerint a pénzbüntetés utólagos alkalmazása dermesztő hatással volt a képviselőkre, amely megállapítást sem a bíróság, sem a kérelmezők nem támasztották alá érdemben.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2395.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2409.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A dermesztő hatás fennállása a bíróság által csupán vélelmezhető és nem mérhető egzakt módon, mivel szubjektív eleme a tényállás megítélésének és az adott képviselő személyétől függ, hogy van-e visszatartó hatása.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2409.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2423.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A magyar kormánynak meggyőződése, hogy az elsőfokú döntésben foglaltakkal szemben nem a vélelmezett következményei, hanem a ténylegesen bekövetkezett joghatások alapján szükséges megítélni egy adott szankció súlyát.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2423.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2448.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ez előszakban úgy véljük, hogy a pénzbírság utólagos kiszabása alkalmas a jogsértő magatartások megelőzésére, ugyanakkor nem sérti a véleménynyilvánítás szabadságának lényegi elemét, szemben a képviselők jogait ténylegesen és azonnal korlátozó, valamint visszavonhatatlan felszólalástól eltiltás, kizárás vagy ideiglenes felfüggesztés büntetések alkalmazásával.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2448.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2464.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ez utóbbi büntetésfajták a tagállamok jelentős többségének fegyelmi szabályaiban megtalálhatók, 31 tagállam esetében, melyek létjogosultságát és alkalmazásának gyakoriságát az elsőfokú döntés tovább erősíti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2464.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2488.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vagyis szóval azért van szükség, hogy a súlyosabban korlátozó szankciók alkalmazása a tagállamok parlamenti fegyelmi szabályaiban általában nem zárjak és sőt, Y-re vagy külön döntés alapján együtt jár pénzügyi jellegű büntetéssel, mivel rendszerint a felfüggesztés vagy a kizárás időtartamára maga után vonja a képviselői juttatások teljes vagy részleges megvonását is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2488.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2505.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Egy ilyen szabályozás megtalálható Albánia, Bulgária, Belgium, Dánia, Franciaország, Görögország, Grózia, Lengyelország, Litvánia, Luxemburg, Moldova, a spanyol felsőház és a román alsóház szabályaiban is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2505.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2528.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az Egyesült Királyság beavatkozásában tett észrevételei között külön kiemeli, hogy a magyar képviselők által tanúsított hasonló magatartásokat a házelnök súlyosan rendzavarónak nem megfelelőnek minősítheti, amelyek folytatólagos tanúsítása ideiglenes felfüggesztéshez vezethet a képviselőházban, amely időre a képviselő juttatások is elvesznek.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2528.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2545.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormány itt külön szeretné felhívni a figyelmet arra, hogy a tagállami parlamentek többsége súlyos rendzavarás esetére olyan intézkedéseket helyez kilátásba, amelyek a képviselők véleménynyilvánítási jogát azonnali és közvetlen beavatkozással korlátozzák.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2545.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2557.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A szó megvonása, a kizárás és a felfüggesztés a pénzbírságval szemben ténylegesen alkalmas a képviselői vélemények elfolytására.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2557.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2558.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tisztelt Bíróság!</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2558.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2569.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormány szeretné kiemelni, hogy a kérelmezőkkel szemben alkalmazott intézkedések meghozatalára minden esetben a tisztességes eljárás követelményeivel összhangban került sor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2569.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2589.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A tisztességes eljárás követelményeinek érvényesülését nem csak a szankciók arányossága és fokozatossága alapozta meg, a fegyelmi jogi normák pontos megfogalmazásukkal, könnyű hozzáférhetőségükkel minden képviselő számára lehetővé teszik a megsértésükből eredő jogkövetkezmények megismerését.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2589.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2613.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormány ezenfelül korábbi beadványaiban már részletesen kifejtette, hogy a képviselők házszabálysértő magatartásának céltudatossága, az ülést vezető elnök eljárása, a plenáris ülésről készített jegyzőkönyv és a pénzbírságot kiszabó határozatok szövegezése nyilvánvalóvá is megismerhetővé tette az intézkedések indokát.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2613.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2620.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormány elengedhetetlennek tartja, hogy ehelyett reagáljon a házelnök szerepével kapcsolatos kérelmezői észrevételekre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2620.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2642.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A magyar szabályozás alapján a képviselőkkel szemben alkalmazott szankciókról a házelnök javaslatára a plénum dönt, míg más házszabályokban a házelnök nem csupán javaslatot fogalmaz meg a szankció alkalmazására, hanem önállóan hozza meg a döntést, amely ellen a ház valamely bizottságához, illetve a plénumhoz lehet fellebbezéssel élni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2642.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2658.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A tagállamok egy részében a házelnöki döntést a plénumnál jelentősen kisebb legitimitással bíró testület, az elnökség vagy a házelnökség bírája felül, mint például Albániában, Franciaországban, Lengyelországban, Olaszországban vagy Spanyolországban.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2658.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2668.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A házelnök törvényben meghatározott kötelezettségének elegettéve részrehajlás nélkül vezeti az üléseket és gyakorolja egyéb házelnöki jogkörében eredő jogait.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2668.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2679.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kamara döntésének meghozatalakor vizsgálattárjává tette, hogy a kérelmezők szankcionálását indítványozó házelnök rendelkezette a megfelelő függetlenséggel és pártatlansággal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2679.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2693.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormány meglátása szerint annak meghatározása, hogy mely kifejezés kirívóan sértő, illetve mely magatartás sérti az országgyűlés tekintéjét, az ülést vezető elnök egyedi mérlegelését igényli.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2693.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2704.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mindaddig nem sérül a képviselők egyenlőségének, valamint a tisztességes eljárásnak az elve, amíg a házelnök hasonló mércét alkalmazva jár el valamennyi képviselővel szemben.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2704.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2723.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormány hangsúlyozni kívánja, hogy a fegyelmi döntés akkor megalapozott és legitim, ha az adott megnyilvánulás tényszerűen sérté a házszabályi rendelkezéseket, és az ezt megállapítani kívánó indítványt a választók akaratát közvetítő képviselők döntéshez szükséges többsége megszavazza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2723.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2740.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mindemellett további fontos eljárási garanciát jelent, hogy a parlament szervezetrendszerén belül a képviselők számára rendelkezésre állnak olyan fórumok, ahol a velük szemben alkalmazott intézkedések továbbá kiszabott szankciók tárnyában felszólalhatnak, azokat vitathatják.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2740.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2758.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A képviselő a plenáris ülésen szót kérhet ügyrendi vagy napi renden kívüli felszólalás keretei között, kifejtheti véleményét a házbizottság ülésein, ugyanígy kérheti fegyelmi ügyének megvitatását az Országgyűlés házszabályi rendelkezések értelmezésért felelős bizottságától is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2758.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2766.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az európai parlamenti jogban egyébként bevegy akorlat, hogy a fegyelmi döntést közvetlenül nem előzi meg plenáris vita.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2766.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2767.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tisztelt Bíróság!</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2767.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2780.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A nagykamara továbbá azzal a kérdéssel fordult a magyar kormányhoz, hogy rendelkezésre állta a kérelmezőknek a 13. cikk által megkívánt hatékony hazai jogorvoslat a 10. cikk szerinti panaszuk vonatkozásában.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2780.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2782.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ezzel kapcsolatban a magyar kormány rögzíti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2782.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2792.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A magyar szabályozás a fegyelmi döntés legnagyobb fokú legitimitását biztosítja azzal, hogy már az első fokon a legmagasabb szintű fórum a plénum hozza meg a határozatot.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2792.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2803.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>E nagy fokú legitimitással azonban együtt jár, hogy az így meghozott határozattal szemben az Országgyűlés szervezeti rendjén belül fellebbezés értelemszerűen nem lehetséges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2803.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2809.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Több tagállamban semmilyen belső jogorvoslattal nem élhetnek a szankcióval érintett képviselők.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2809.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2822.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Milyen rendelkezéseket tartalmaz többek között Észtország, Görögország, Litvánia, Macedónia, Norvégia, Olaszország és Örményország parlamenti joga, valamint a Hollanda Alsóház ház szabálya.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2822.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2837.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az Európa Tanács parlamenti közgyűlésének eljárási szabályzata a kizárásról szóló döntést az elnök komolyabb esetekben az elnök indítványa alapján a közgyűlés kezébe teszi, e döntésekkel szemben jogorvosati lehetőséget nem biztosít.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2837.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2848.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az Európai Államok alkotmányos gyakorlata tehát azt mutatja, hogy a parlamenti fegyelmi ügyekben csak nagyon korlátozott vagy semmilyen fellebezési lehetőségen nem élhetnek a képviselők.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2848.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2856.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Amennyiben rendelkezésre áll valamiféle jogorvoslati lehetőség, az általában a parlamenten belüli jogorvoslatot jelent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2856.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2869.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A hatalmiágok elkülönülésének, valamint a parlamenti autonomiának az elvét sértené, a legfőbb döntéshozó fórum a parlament határozatait egy külső szerv felül bélelhatná.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2869.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2882.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A magyar szabályozás az országgyűlés döntéseit megalapozó jogszabályi rendelkezésekkel szemben azonban biztosít külső jogorvoslatot, amelyet az alkotmánybírósághoz benyújtott Alkotmányugi Panaszintézménye garantál.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2882.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2898.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormánya nagykamara kérdésére megküldött írásbeli válaszában már részletesen kifejtette az alkotmányugi panasz sajátosságait, valamint az alkotmánybíróságnak az ide vonatkozó gyakorlatát, ezért itt csak néhány gondolatban kívánja összefoglalni a panasz főbbi ellenzőit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2898.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2912.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az alkotmányugi panasz, mint az egyéni jogsérelmek orvoslására alkalmas és hatékony jogorvoslati forma, a kérelmezők rendelkezésére állt az országgyűlés pénzbírságot kiszabó határozatainak elfogadását követően.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2912.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2925.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>E jogorvoslati lehetőséget azonban elmulasztották kimeríteni, noha az, a kormány álláspontja szerint, alkalmas lett volna a képviselők egyedi ügyében esetlegesen megállapításra kerülő jogsérelmek orvoslására.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2925.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2927.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tisztelt Bíróság!</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2927.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2933.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ugyanügyben állunk most a bíróság előtt, amely döntő jelentőségű valamennyit tagállami parlament számára.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2933.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2942.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A bíróság első alkalommal foglal állást a tagállami parlamenti önszabályozás érvényesítése körében hozott fegyelmintézkedésekről.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2942.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2973.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A szólásszabadsággal kapcsolatos bíráskodás most egyfajta válaszút elé érkezett, támogatja-e a provokatív jellegű politikai akciókat a törvényhozásban, amely könnyen az érdemi viták erodálódásához vezethet, vagy a tagállami fegyelmi szabályozás tiszteletben tartására ösztönzi a törvényalkotás eljárásának szereplőit, amely fegyelmi szabályozás a parlament működő képességének megóvása mellett megfelelően érvényt szerez a véleményjelvánítás szabadságának is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2973.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2989.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az évszázadok alatt kiforrott és valamennyi európai tagállamban hasonló formát öltő parlamentális demokrácia működése során kialakította azokat a házszabályi kereteket, amelyek valamennyi képviselő számára lehetővé teszik véleményük szabad kifejtését.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2989.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2998.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ezek a szabályok a törvényhozás működő képességét és tekintéjét, a testület szuverenitását és védelmét is szolgálják.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2998.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3009.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Miként szerezhetnek majd érvényt a tagállamok eszabályozásnak, ha a házszabálysértő és provokatív jellegű, célzatos képviselői magatartások bátorítást nyernek egy nemzetközi fórumon?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3009.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3015.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A tagállami törvényhozás működő képességének biztosítása a tagállamok szuverén felelőssége.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3015.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3023.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hogyan tehetnek e kötelezettségnek eleget, ha elveszítik eszközeiket, amelyekkel mederben tarthatják a politikai vitákat a parlamentben?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3023.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3033.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az állam elsőrendű kötelessége, hogy biztosítsa az alapvető emberi jogokörvényesülését, amely egyfajta fegyelmezettséget és következettséget kíván a törvényhozásban is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3033.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3046.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A törvény alkotási eljárás szereplőitől elvárható magatartás, hogy elsősorban ne a látványos politikai akciókra fektessék a hangsúlyt, hanem a házszabályi keretek között jogszerűen adjanak hangot véleményüknek.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3046.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3054.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A szimbolikus gesztusoknak akkor van csak helye a parlament falai között, ha azok nem akadályozzák a testület rendes működését.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3054.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3063.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Annak megítélése pedig, hogy milyen cselekmények akadályozzák vagy obstruálják a törvényhozást, a tagállami parlamentek szuverenitásának körébe tartozik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3063.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3080.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tisztelt Bíróság, a kormány leszögezi továbbá, hogy Magyarország elkötelezett a véleményjelvánítás szabadsága mellett, a képviselői beszédjogot ezért körültekintően a többi európai tagállaméhoz hasonló elvek és részletszabályok mentén határozta meg.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3080.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3090.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Azt azonban elfogadhatatlannak tartja, hogy lényegében a kommunikáció bármilyen formája megengedett, sőt, adott esetben nem vagyoni kártérítéssel jutalmazott legyen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3090.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3098.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kérelmezői magatartás bátorítása hosszú távon éppen a védeni kívánt értékek sérálméhez vezethet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3098.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3111.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A képviselőket egyenlő mértékben megillető szólásszabadság és a közügyek szabad megvitatása nem biztosítható egy olyan parlamentben, amelynek tagjai nem tartják tiszteletben a működés szabályait és egymás jugait.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3111.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3121.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A kormány erre figyelemmel kéri, hogy a bíróság döntése során tartsa szem előtt a parlament a törvényhazás fóruma és nem a politikai akciók díszlete.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3121.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3137.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az elhangzottak alapján a kormány kéri a bíróságtól továbbá, hogy a kamara ítéletében foglaltakat változtassa meg, vagyis állapítsa meg, hogy Magyarország kormánya nem sértette meg a kérelmezőknek az Egyezmény 10. cikke által garantált véleménynyilvánítási szabadságát,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3137.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3141.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>sem a 13. cikke által garantált hatékony jogorgoslathoz való jogát.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3141.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3145.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ezúton köszönöm elnökónak és a tisztelt bíráknak a megtisztelő figyelmet. Sziasztok!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3150.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3151.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Tallódi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3151.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3154.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3154.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3156.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question comes from Miss Nußberger, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3161.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3162.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3162.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3166.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would have two questions to the government, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3166.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3187.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One question concerns Article 49, Paragraph 4 of the Act on Parliament, on which the sanctions in this case were based, which provides or which it's necessary to state a conduct that is gravely offensive to the authority of the parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3187.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3195.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I wanted to ask how it's defined that a conduct is gravely offensive, not only offensive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3195.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3207.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Which criteria are used to determine the gravity of the disturbance, a length of time of the disturbance, number of people involved, size of billboards, deprivation of the rights of others?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3207.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3216.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if I understood the agent of the government correctly, also previously exhibited conduct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3216.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3220.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I just want to know which criteria are applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3220.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3225.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question is closely linked to the first one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3225.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3239.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it necessary for such a sanction to be reasoned on the basis of Section 49, Paragraph 4 and 49, Paragraph 7 of the Act on Parliament?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3239.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3249.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case at hand, it was explained why the amounts of the sanctions were differentiated according to the status of the MPs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3249.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3261.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it was not explained otherwise why it was considered that there was a gravely offensive conduct, gravely offensive to the authority of the parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3261.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3261.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3265.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3267.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, le juge López Guerra.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3273.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3275.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3275.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3279.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is directed to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3279.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3298.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it results from the dossier, the fines to the applicants were proposed by the Speaker of the House several days after the facts, and these fines were approved without debate by the plenary of the parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3298.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3323.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is whether within this disciplinary proceedings within parliament, whether the applicant has any effective possibility to state their position or adducing any arguments in the defense or challenging the charge formulated by the Speaker before the final decision by the plenary of the House.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3323.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3331.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has made some passing reference to this point, but I would appreciate some precision of whether this possibility were effective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3331.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3347.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I know that there was a reform of the law last year on this matter, but my question refers to the situation in the moment of the fact discussed in this case, that is, in the spring of 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3347.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3348.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3352.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3353.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3353.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3371.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the court will now rise for 20 minutes, following which the parties will return for a second round of short pleadings to respond to the submissions in the first round and to answer also the judges' questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3847.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3847.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3894.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3898.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So please be seated. The hearing is now resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3898.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3901.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I call Mr. Karsai.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3907.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3919.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable European Court of Human Rights, we would like to briefly address first the questions raised by the judges to us and then briefly what was raised to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3919.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3926.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then we would like to put forward some short comments on the government's speech today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3926.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3933.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, I would like to address the question of Judge Guerra.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3933.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3943.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question was whether the applicants had any opportunity within the Parliament at least to address the sanction imposed on them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3943.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3947.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer is quite clear and quite simple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3947.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3948.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was none.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3948.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3950.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no such possibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3950.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3956.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Speaker, at the time of the events, the Speaker had the right to propose the sanction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3956.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3966.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then the plenary, without any debate, without giving the floor to the applicants, voted on the subject.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3966.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3968.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is what happened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3968.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3981.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in my view, it's a quite serious breach of the Convention, which is shown by the fact that after the events of the present case, the impugned regulation in Hungary has changed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3981.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3985.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nowadays, the system is more complex.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3985.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3991.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nowadays, today, the applicants would have the possibility to address at least a committee within the Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3991.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3998.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this was not the case at the time of the events of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3998.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4004.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, I would turn to the questions of Judge Nussberger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4004.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4005.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Actually, it was two questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4005.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4019.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question was how in the Hungary law at the time of the events was defined grave violation or grave disturbance of the working of the house.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4019.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4029.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants' position was constant and clear throughout the whole procedure, that the impugned regulations are value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4029.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4038.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants couldn't tell in advance what would constitute a serious breach of the working of the house.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4038.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4044.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were of the view that their actions didn't disturb the house, the working of the house, gravely.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4044.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4049.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, we put forward a lot of arguments in our written submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4049.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4055.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we did not repeat it in substance again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4055.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4061.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, I think the second question is also very important.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4061.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4072.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question of Judge Nussberger was whether there was any acceptable reasoning for the sanctions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4072.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4078.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It must be noted that these decisions are very short, contains three pages only.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4078.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4090.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in these decisions, there is only a value referral to the grave disruption of the working of the house, but nothing more.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4090.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4100.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the applicant's view, this cannot be classified as a detailed reasoning as the courts understands it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4100.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4107.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to turn briefly to the government's speech and government's observation put forward today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4107.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4124.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Throughout the government's oral plea, there was numerous referral to international case law, the legal regulations of certain member states of Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4124.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4131.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In my view, these argumentations cannot be taken into consideration as the governments would like it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4131.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4141.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government tries to convince the court that there was no violation in the present case because all the impugned elements of the disciplinary procedure exist in one or another member states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4141.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4149.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have serious problems with the government's argumentation because, in my view, it does not prove anything.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4149.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4154.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My view is that the government committed two fatal mistakes in this respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4154.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4158.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the comparison is not systematic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4158.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4164.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It refers to different member states randomly, which is called cherry picking and which is highly opposable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4164.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4172.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And second, it fails to pay due regard to the legal and political context of these legal institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4172.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4182.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it is an extremely important principle of comparative constitutional law that legal institutions can only be understood if they are examined in their legal and political context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4182.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4186.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government failed to show this legal and political context, in my view.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4186.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4190.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the government referred to Germany, we refer also Germany.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4190.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4200.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Germany, the chair of the meeting may impose a fine without any previous warning when a given disruptive conduct has violated the dignity of the Bundestag.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4200.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4213.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we know very well that due to the electoral rules, the specific composition of the Bundestag and the Bundesrat and the characteristics of the legislative process, the German government needs to cooperate with the opposition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4213.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4221.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, it is unlikely that the government will use disciplinary procedure to systematically suppress the opposition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4221.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4227.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, I would like to put forward some general remarks concerning the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4227.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4232.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the political context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4232.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4241.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that we express the view that in Hungary, the democracy, the state of democracy and rule of law deteriorated in the last five years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4241.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4246.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not a subjective or, if you like it, political view of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4246.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4250.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not the subjective view of the legal representatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4250.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4259.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This view is backed by facts and backed by the opinion of other quite prestigious institutions and bodies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4259.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4262.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Earlier, we referred to the Venice Commission and other NGOs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4262.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4272.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We referred to the bodies of the European Union who has strongly and permanently criticized the Hungarian government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4272.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4281.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In my view, these opinions shall be taken into consideration with adequate weight.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4281.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4291.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in this respect, I shall add that the court, especially in Article 10 cases, takes into consideration the whole context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4291.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4293.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is a political case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4293.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4296.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has obviously political context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4296.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4309.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in this respect, I have to add a new factual element to this case, which occurred on Monday this week, two days ago in the Hungarian Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4309.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4316.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of the applicants being present in the room, Ms. Sayle, addressed the Hungarian Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4316.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4319.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Sayle addressed one of the hottest topics</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4319.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4321.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>nowadays in Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4321.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4326.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This topic was the low wages compared to the European Union average.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4326.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4332.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How can these wages be amended and why a lot of Hungarians leave the country?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4332.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4340.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the estimates, 300,000-400,000 Hungarians left Hungary and are looking for jobs somewhere else.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4340.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4344.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think it's easy to see why it is a hot topic in Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4344.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4348.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I repeat, it was Ms. Sayle's own speech.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4348.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4355.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During her speech, she and three other members of her party raised billboards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4355.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4365.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these billboards, there were written the names of the groups mostly endangered by this quite negative trend about which Ms. Sayle was talking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4365.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4370.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The speaker immediately cut the word and Ms. Sayle</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4370.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4373.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>couldn't finish her speech.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4373.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4378.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why am I mentioning this quite sad episode?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4378.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4383.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm mentioning it because I think that we are now on the top of a slippery slope.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4383.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4389.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't know how the disciplinary law will be applied in the nowadays Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4389.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4392.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It seems that the situation is deteriorating.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4392.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4398.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It seems that the disciplinary law is applied at will of the speaker and the governing majority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4398.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4404.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is used in a way which silences the opposition views.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4404.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4405.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4407.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4410.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Karsai.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4410.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4412.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I give the floor to Mr. Tallódi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4415.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4418.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Köszönöm, elnök úr, a szót.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4418.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4430.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Először Nuszberger bíróasszony kérdésére szeretnék röviden válaszolni, ami a súlyosan sértő kifejezés értelmezésével kapcsolatos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4430.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4440.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A vonatkozó rendelkezések nem tartalmaznak külön definíciót a súlyosan sértő kategóriára, vagy ennek definíciójára.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4440.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4454.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hangsúlyozni kell azonban, hogy ez nem csak a magyar házszabályban és a vonatkozó szabályokban, de más tagállamok szabályozásában és az európai szervezetek szabályozásában sem található meg, illetve lelhető fel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4454.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4464.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Itt az Európa-Tanács parlamenti közgyűlésének eljárási szabályzatára utalnék, amely szerint az a közgyűlési tag szankcionálható, aki megzavarja a rendet az eljárás során.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4464.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4479.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az eljárási szabályzat úgy fogalmaz, hogy a közgyűlés tagjai udvarias és tisztelettudó módon viselkednek egymással, a közgyűlés elnökével vagy más elnöklő személlyel, tartózkodnak minden olyan magatartástól, amely megzavarna az eljárást.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4479.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4500.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Definíció hiányában viszont értelem szerint az ülést vezető személy, elnök, házelnök, illetve vannak helyettese, akik éppen az ülésteremben helyet foglalnak, köztük adott esetben ellenzéki képviselők is, határozzák meg, hogy az adott fogalomhasználat miként értelmezhető.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4500.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4511.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mindig a konkrét ügyben a konkrét mérlegelés kérdése ennek az eldöntése, tehát a gyakorlatban alakul annak a megítélése, hogy mit értünk súlyosan, sértő alatt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4511.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4533.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Azt lehet mondani, hogy a beadványokban említett típusú magatartásokkal kapcsolatban egyfajta gyakorlat kialakult, mégpedig az, hogyha az illető a molinó vagy a drapéria felemelésével egyidőleg elhagyja az üléstermet, akkor szankciót alkalmaznak vele szemben.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4533.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4542.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ha azonban nem hagyja el a helyét, és a helyén marad, akkor ebben az esetben vele szemben nem alkalmaznak szankciót.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4542.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4568.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nagyon fontos itt utalni az indoklás kapcsán arra, hogy a kommunikáció formája, és nem a tartalma volt a lényegjelleme ennek a kérdésnek, és gyakorlatilag a jelenlévők, vagy a televízión az üléstkövetők egyértelműen láthatták, és megtapasztalhatták, hogy milyen típusú konkrét magatartásokról volt szó.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4568.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4601.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ami a második kérdésre vonatkozik, vagy a második kérdést illeti, azzal kapcsolatban szeretném jelezni López Gerra úr kérdése kapcsán, hogy a képviselők lehetőségei a házelnöki kezdeményezéssel kapcsolatban mindenfajta lehetőségek részletes felsorolásával a kormány első beadványában, annak is a 43. és 44. pontjában kerültek kifejtésre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4601.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4611.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Gyakorlatilag itt egy folyamatról van szó, nem egy egyszerű cselekményről, hanem egy folyamatról beszélhetünk, ami kezdődik a képviselői magatartással.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4611.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4621.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ezt követően egy bizonyos időszak elteltével következik a házelnöki javaslat, majd egy újabb időszak elteltével születik meg a plenáris ülésen a döntés.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4621.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4632.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ebben az időintervallumban és ebben az időtartamban van lehetősége adott esetben a képviselőknek bizonyos jogosultságukkal élni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4632.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4638.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az egyik ilyen lehetőség az ügyrendi bizottsághoz való fordulás.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4638.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4647.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lehetősége volt jelen ügyben is egy ilyen kezdeményezéssel való élésre a képviselőknek, hogy álláspontjukat kifejthessék.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4647.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4656.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nagyon fontos itt megígézni, hogy ezek a típusú ügyrendi bizottsági ülések gyakran és többször foglalkoznak ülésvezetési kérdésekkel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4656.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4660.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tehát van példa arra, hogy ilyen típusú kérdéseket vitatnak meg.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4660.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4669.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>És arra is érdemes utalni röviden, hogy az ilyen típusú döntések ellen van fellebezési lehetőség adott esetben a plenáris ülés elé.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4669.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4673.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tehát a plénum elé kerülhet a kérdés.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4673.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4691.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A másik ilyen lehetőség, amelyet ebben az időintervallumban lett volna lehetősége a képviselőknek igénybe venni, az az ügyrendi felszólalásnak a lehetősége, valamint a napirend utáni felszólalás, amely úgyszintén a rendelkezésükre állt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4691.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4698.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Végül, de nem utolsó sorban érdemes megemlíteni a házbizottság lehetőségét a képviselőjogok gyakorlása kapcsán.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4698.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4708.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A házbizottság az a bizottsága az országgyűlésnek, ahol valamennyi képviselőcsoport képviseltetve van, valamint az országgyűlés vezető tisztségbizselői.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4708.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4716.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fontos megégyezni, hogy fegyelmi ügyekkel kapcsolatban is eljár a házbizottság, tehát ilyen típusú ügyekben is dönt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4716.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4725.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ráadásul ezt a bizottságot, ha a frakció vezetők kezdeményezik, akkor kötelező összehívni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4725.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4728.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ami szintén egy fontos garanciális szabály.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4728.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4742.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Itt kell megemlíteni azt a szintén kiemelkedően fontos kérdéskört, hogy nem a véleményilvánítás tartalmáról, hanem a formájáról van szó ebben az ügyben, illetve ezekben az ügyekben.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4742.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4761.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nagyon fontos megemlíteni, hogy azok a tártkörök, amelyben a mulinók feliratai felírásra kerülnek, és egyáltalán amely kontextusban ezek megjelentek, ezek már máshol is megjelentek és megjelenhettek, mind az országgyűlés keretein belül, mind az országgyűlés keretein kívül.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4761.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4769.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tehát tulajdonképpen elmondható, hogy a valódi politikai diskurzus lefolytatására ezekben a tártkörökben lehetőség volt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4769.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4777.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nem lehet azt mondani, hogy tartalmi tekintetben bármilyen korlátozás érte volna a kérelmezőket.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4777.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4795.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ehhez kapcsolódva lehet utalni arra, hogy miután nem tartalmi kérdésekről van szó, érdemes leválasztani ezt az egész kérdésköröt, az ellenzéki jogok kontra kormánypárti jogok vagy kormánypárthoz tartozó képviselők jogai kérdésköről.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4795.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4800.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Valójában nem tartalmi, hanem formai kérdésekről van szó.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4800.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4813.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Amire szintén utalnék, és ezt már a beadványban is említettük, hogy ebben az ügyben egy általános jellegű olyan döntés szüledik, amelyik adott esetben precedens jelleggel fog bírni a későbbiekre vonatkozóan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4813.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4818.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tehát ezeknek az előbb említett kérdéseknek a tisztázása is rendkívül fontos és fontos lesz.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4818.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4831.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Szeretnék még, tisztelt ügyvéd kollega, alkotmánybírósági panaszsal kapcsolatos kitételére röviden reagálni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4831.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4846.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ugye itt a kormány valóban ezzel kapcsolatban egy részletesebb beadványt nyújtott be, ezt nem szeretnénk pontosan és ismételten felidézni, hiszen ez mindenki rendelkezésre áll, aki a döntésmeghozatalára jogosult.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4846.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4854.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Itt most csak arra szeretnék utalni, hogy az új szabályozás valójában a régi bázisan született meg.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4854.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4864.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A 2012 előtti alkotmánybírósági joggyakorlat azt lehet mondani, hogy élő a 2012 utáni ügyekben is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4864.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4885.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Született ugyanis egy alkotmánybírósági határozata, 20 per 2012-es határozat, amely rögzíti, hogy ha az alaptörvény szabályozási koncepciója azonos vagy hasonló a korábban hatályban volt alkotmány rendelkezéseihez, akkor a kiepített alkotmánybírósági gyakorlat az újabb ügyekben is irányadónak tekinthető.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4885.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4901.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Az alkotmánybíróság 3367 per 2012-es AB határozata az alkotmányjogi panaszsal kapcsolatos gyakorlatát az új alaptörvény és az alkotmánybírósági törvény alapján is fenntartottá.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4901.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4907.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tehát ennyiben egy élő jogról és egy folytatólagosságról beszélhetünk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hu</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4907.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4907.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nagyon szépen egyszerettem volna.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4913.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4915.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4915.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4920.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4920.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4925.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4925.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4928.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4928.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4930.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4930.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4936.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery, and I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
