<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>4337004_25012012</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>23.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>24.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>76.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>89.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Catan and others against Moldova and Russia. The applications were lodged with the Court under Article 34 of the Convention</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>89.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>95.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by several Moldovan nationals. In the case of Catan and 27 others, the application was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>95.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>102.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>lodged on 25 October 2004. In the case of Caldare and 42 others, it was lodged on 20</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>102.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>109.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>December 2004. And in the case of Cercavschi and 98 others, it was lodged on 4 April 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>113.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>120.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An oral hearing before the Chamber was held on 9 June 2009. On 15 June 2010, the applications</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>121.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>128.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>were joined and declared admissible. On 14 December 2010, the Chamber decided to relinquish</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>128.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>138.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>jurisdiction in favour of the Grand Chamber, none of the parties to the case having objected to the relinquishment. The Government of the Republic of Moldova are represented by their</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>138.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>145.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>agent Mr. Grosu, assisted by Mr. Apostol, counsel. The Government of the Russian Federation are</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>145.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>152.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>represented by their agent Mr. Matyushkin, assisted by Ms. Sirotkina, Ms. Korieva, Ms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>152.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>159.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dzutseva, Mr. Fomin, Ms. Molodtsova, Ms. Utkina, and Mr. Makhnev, advisors. The applicants</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>163.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>170.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>are represented by Mr. Hughes and Ms. Duffy, counsel, and by Mr. A. Postică and Mr. Manole,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>170.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>176.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>advisors, assisted by Mr. P. Postica. One of the applicants, Mrs. Turkan, is also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>176.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>183.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives and the applicant in the name of the Court. Having consulted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>184.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>194.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the agents of the two governments and the representatives of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows. Mr. Hughes and Mr. A. Postică for the applicants</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>194.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>201.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>will speak first, followed by Mr. Grosu for the Government of Moldova, and then Mr. Matyushkin</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>201.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>207.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for the Government of the Russian Federation. I would explain that in addition to interpreting</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>207.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>218.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the two official languages of the Court, English and French, interpreting from Russian into English and French has been authorized at the request of the representative of the Government of the Russian Federation. I call Mr. Hughes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>223.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>225.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>225.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>228.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>228.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>247.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>these cases come before the court as a result of serious violations of the rights of a group of ethnic Moldovan children, their parents, and teachers in Transnistria, part of the territory of the Moldovan state, and under the de facto control of the Russian-supported separatist administration known as the MRT.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>247.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>265.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants have experienced harassment, intimidation, threats, detention, the storming and forced closure of their schools, and discrimination, all because they fell foul of the MRT administration's efforts to ban and criminalize the use of Latin script in schools in Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>265.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>278.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These events were described by the OSCE at the very height of these violations in 2004 as linguistic cleansing of ethnic Moldovans from a territory moving ever closer to the Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>278.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>296.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These violations are taking place on the sovereign territory of Moldova within the Council of Europe, yet as reflected in the positions of the respondent governments, neither state accepts that they owe any obligations of protection to these individuals resident in Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>296.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>310.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court has, on many occasions, identified the object and purpose of the convention as the protection of individual rights and the maintenance and promotion of the ideals and values of a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>310.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>321.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to be effective, the convention must protect individuals, especially the more vulnerable members of society, such as many of the applicants in this case, from violations of their human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>321.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>325.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There can be no black hole in the legal territory of the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>325.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>329.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will address the court on the issue of jurisdiction, followed by my colleague, Mr. Postika,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>329.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>333.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>who will address the court in more detail on the violations of those rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>333.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>338.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like, first of all, to address the question of Russian jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>338.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>344.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has asked the parties to consider this question in light of its recent decision in Al-Skhini.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>344.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>364.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before considering Al-Skhini, we would remind the court that issues relevant to the determination of the present case are addressed in a long line of authority, in cases involving the presence of Turkish troops in northern Cyprus from Loizidu right up to the decision of Andreas Manotaris and others versus Turkey in 2008.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>364.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>375.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court has consistently confirmed Turkish jurisdiction in northern Cyprus, a situation that is, in many respects, similar to the one existing in Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>375.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>386.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of even more direct and immediate relevance is the Grand Chamber's decision in Alashku and the recent decision in Ivantuk and others versus Moldova and Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>386.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>391.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These confirm jurisdiction of the Russian Federation over acts of the MRT administration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>391.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>404.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Al-Skhini, although arising in different circumstances, follows and builds on those cases, confirming essential principles concerning extraterritorial application of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>404.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>409.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The relevant principles that emerge from this body of law are dealt with in detail in our written submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>409.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>413.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They may, we submit, be reduced as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>413.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>435.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, that a state's jurisdiction under Article I can be triggered in one of two ways, either by the acts of its organs and agents abroad or by its exercise of effective control, or in the words of the Grand Chamber in Alashku, at the very least, decisive influence over an area outside its territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>435.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>447.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, as this court has consistently held, it is immaterial whether a state exercises this effective control directly or through a subordinate local administration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>447.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>454.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, determining whether there is effective control over an area is a question of fact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>454.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>463.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It falls to be established through an assessment of the military, political, and economic control or influence exercised over the territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>463.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>471.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourth, where states have such effective control of an area, they are obliged to secure the full range of rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>471.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>492.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Grand Chamber in Al-Skhini, reflecting earlier jurisprudence, made this quite clear when it stated, and I quote from paragraph 140 of that decision, the controlling state has the responsibility under Article I to secure within the area under its control the entire range of substantive rights set out in the convention and those additional protocols which it has ratified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>492.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>497.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It will be liable for any violation of those rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>497.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>506.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian Federation, in its written submissions, asks this court to set aside its carefully considered and well-developed jurisprudence on extraterritorial jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>506.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>517.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But since the court's decision in Lwazidu, it has developed a consistent approach that arises in circumstances similar to the one before the court today based on sound principles of law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>517.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>530.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The northern Cyprus cases, Ilashku, and now Ivantok, all provide firm guidance to this court on the appropriate legal principles to apply in its consideration of this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>530.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>549.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the application of those principles to the facts of the present case, the incidents the subject matter of these proceedings took place primarily between 2002 and 2004, with the majority of incidents occurring in 2004, the same year as the Ilashku decision was delivered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>549.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>560.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has, therefore, already examined in detail the factual circumstances giving rise to its finding that the Russian Federation had jurisdiction over the territory of Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>560.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>571.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It examined a military, political, and economic support provided by the Russian Federation and found that the MRT was established and continued to survive as a result of this support.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>571.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>575.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Ivantok, the former fourth chamber made a similar finding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>575.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>587.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It held that since 2004, and at least up until June 2007, the Russian Federation continued to provide military, economic, and political support to the MRT.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>587.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>604.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is, therefore, a clear line of authority from this court establishing as fact that from the establishment of the MRT administration in 1991 until at least June 2007, the Russian Federation had jurisdiction over the territory of Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>604.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>609.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The facts underlying this application occurred during this period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>609.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>616.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that these findings are applicable to the facts of this case and that there is no good reason to depart from them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>616.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>625.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Notwithstanding this, the court has raised a number of questions concerning the Russian Federation's military, economic, and political influence over the MRT.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>625.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>634.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While these have been fully addressed in the applicant's written observations, I would like to briefly highlight just some of the facts that indicate the extent of that influence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>634.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>653.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the question of military support, despite its commitment to withdraw all of its troops at the 1999 OSCE Istanbul Summit, the Russian Federation continues to have a significant armed presence in Transnistria and continues to maintain a stockpile of weapons on the territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>653.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>658.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, there is no longer even any public commitment to withdrawal of troops from the territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>658.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>673.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is borne out by the 2009 agreement between the Russian Federation, Moldova, and the MRT that Russian troops would be replaced by an OSCE peacekeeping mission, but only once a political settlement had been reached.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>673.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>685.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if the military presence has reduced to some extent, the fact that it remains alongside the weapons stockpile has what the Alaskan judgment described as a dissuasive influence in the region.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>685.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>713.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It represents the specter of Russia exercising its control in a more overt fashion in the future, consistent with the true purpose of its military presence in Transnistria, which is not, as is suggested in its written submissions, to carry out peacekeeping duties and guard armaments, but rather to maintain control over the territory, to retain the capacity to react to events, and to consolidate the position of the MRT in Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>713.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>726.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards political influence, the Russian Federation dismisses the court's detailed findings of fact in Alasku on its role in the establishment of the MRT administration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>726.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>739.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While we would refer the court to those findings, we would also like to highlight some recent examples of political influence that illustrate the role Russia continues to play in the life of that administration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>739.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>750.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thousands of Russian passports have been granted to citizens of Transnistria since 1992, including over 70,000 since 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>750.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>768.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian parliament, for its part, describes Transnistria as a zone of special strategic interest, while statements by the Duma have been openly supportive of independence, with the former speaker of the Duma going so far as to describe Transnistria as an outpost of Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>768.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>779.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While the Russian Federation asserts that it has provided no economic support, the court in Alasku found that economic support provided to the MRT was essential to its continued existence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>779.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>788.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court noted the supply of gas to the MRT on favorable terms at paragraph 156 of the Alasku judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>788.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>804.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian Federation denies it has any involvement in facilitating the supply of cheap energy and characterizes the activity of Gazprom, the main supplier of energy in the territory, as that of a public corporation engaged in complex commercial transactions in difficult circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>804.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>807.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But Gazprom is not independent of the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>807.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>811.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian Federation is the majority shareholder in Gazprom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>811.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>821.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the MRT administration owes over $2 billion to the Russian Federation for the supply of energy, but that debt is regarded as owed by the Moldovan government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>821.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>828.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No attempt has been made by the Russian state to recover that debt from the MRT administration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>828.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>834.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian Federation also provides large sums of money to fund business and even pay pensions to the Transnistrian residents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>834.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>840.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They characterize this classic exercise of state authority as humanitarian aid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>840.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>846.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whatever you want to call it, its effect in terms of Russian economic control is clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>846.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>856.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has asked about a resolution in the Duma in February 2005 requesting the introduction of sanctions against Moldova with the exclusion of the region of Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>856.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>871.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the government seeks to dismiss the significance of this, the Duma took it seriously enough to follow up that resolution with a further resolution just one month later, inquiring as to the measures taken on foot of the original resolution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>871.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>886.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we note in our written submissions, economic sanctions were introduced by the Russian Federation shortly after that, according to a report from the IMF, had serious consequences for the Moldovan economy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>886.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>899.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian Federation's involvement in and influence over the MRT administration is incompatible with its assertion that it is an honest broker, an assertion that is completely at odds with its historical involvement in the territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>899.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>927.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would ask the court to consider why the Russian ambassador to Moldova attends 20th anniversary festivities purporting to celebrate Transnistrian independence, why that same ambassador insists the presence of Russian troops in Transnistria is in Russia's best interests, why Russia continues to provide passports to individuals resident in Transnistria, and why so many Russian nationals are members of the MRT administration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>927.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>935.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The MRT administration enjoys extensive military, economic, and political support, such that it survives by virtue of that support.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>935.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>940.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit the threshold for jurisdiction is more than convincingly met in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>940.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>949.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Russian responsibility in this case, in our submission, flows from the relationship of dependence and control it has generated with the MRT.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>949.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>970.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Where the state has effective control of an area through a subordinate administration, the court has emphasized, most recently in paragraph 138 of the Al-Skhini judgment, and I quote, that it is not necessary to determine whether the contracting state exercises detailed control over the policies and actions of the subordinate local administration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>970.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>994.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rather, as the court went on to make quite clear, and again I quote from that judgment, Responsibility flows also from its failure to take measures to protect the rights of people in an area under its effective control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>994.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>999.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has asked about the positive obligations of Russia to ensure respect for the applicant's rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>999.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1011.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court's consistent approach has been to hold that once it is established a state has effective control, that state owes human rights obligations to individuals that come within its jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1011.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1027.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The contracting state with effective control must take necessary, appropriate, and feasible measures to protect the individuals from such violations, even where they are committed by private individuals with whom the state has no formal relationship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1027.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1040.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That duty does not impose an absolute obligation of result, but it does impose a due diligence obligation to do all within the state's power to prevent violations from taking place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1040.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1047.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the court should ask itself, what has the Russian Federation done to prevent the violations complained of?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1047.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1053.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is beyond doubt that Russia knew what was happening and how the applicant's rights were being violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1053.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1063.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is demonstrably the case, in light of its extensive control and influence, that there were steps reasonably available to the Russian Federation to prevent those violations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1063.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1070.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it has failed to take any meaningful measures to protect the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1070.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1074.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now turn to the question of Moldova's jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1074.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1084.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Transnistria is part of the territory of the Republic of Moldova, and Moldova is responsible for securing to everyone within its jurisdiction the rights and freedoms set out in the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1084.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1092.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We acknowledge in our written submissions, and repeat again today, that Moldova does not exercise control over the territory of Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1092.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1100.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is perhaps tried to note that aspects of its sovereign functions are curtailed, that the options at its disposal are more limited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1100.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1107.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, that does not absolve it of its obligations towards individuals within its national territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1107.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1121.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are not advocating for the application of a novel, strict responsibility standard, but of the well-established obligation to take all possible and feasible measures to restore the rule of law generally and to prevent and respond to violations specifically.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1121.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1131.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moldova had at its disposal considerable means to affect the circumstances of the applicants in this case, including taking diplomatic, economic, judicial, and other measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1131.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1173.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not enough to simply rely on the monitoring and documenting of serious human rights violations in order to ensure the right to return to the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1173.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1185.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Moldovan government could also have sought to bring the criminal law to bear on those responsible for crimes committed in the course of, and associated with, the violations of the applicant's rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1185.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1196.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Where the Moldovan government failed to take measures reasonably available to it, it is, we submit, in breach of its positive obligations to secure the applicant's rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1196.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1209.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court has repeatedly affirmed that it must have regard to the Convention's special character as a human rights treaty, and that its provisions must be interpreted and applied so as to be practical and effective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1209.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1218.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants in this case are entitled to the protection afforded by the Convention, notwithstanding the establishment of the self-proclaimed MRT administration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1218.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1228.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, it is precisely in situations that threaten the rule of law and democratic principles underpinning the Convention that such protection is most important.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1228.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1239.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court has urged to ensure that there is, to use the Court's own phrase in the Cyprus versus Turkey case from 2001, no regrettable vacuum in the system of human rights protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1239.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1248.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants ask the courts to find they come within the Article I jurisdiction of both respondent states in respect of violations on which my colleague, Mr. Plastika,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1248.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1248.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>will now address the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1252.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1253.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Hughes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1253.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1253.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Postică.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1256.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1257.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1257.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1260.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I would like to begin by illustrating to the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1260.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1269.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>court how some of the applicants were affected by the action of the MRT by highlighting their experiences from the witness statements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1269.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1276.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the way home, we were stopped at random by the Transnistria militia, who searched forcefully our bags.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1276.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1284.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When these men found books written in Latin script, they tore them apart and told us to go to study to the Russian schools instead.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1284.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1290.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to quote from the state of Christina Bulgak, one of the child applicants in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1290.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1295.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When the school year had to start, we were unable to go to school.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1295.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1302.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We had to stay alone at home almost like in a home arrest when our parents had to go to work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1302.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1314.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We couldn't even play in the yard with the other children because they pretended not to understand us and would call us homeless, or Romanians, says Alisa Safonova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1314.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1321.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We were dismissed from their jobs only because their children studied at a Romanian language school, says Diana Gas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1321.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1328.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a brief sample of what the applicants have endured at the hand of MRT.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1328.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1333.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case is not about a forgotten conflict in an obscure region of the world.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1333.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1346.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These events took place mainly between 2002 and 2004 and continue happening right up to the present day in an otherwise peaceful southeastern European country, a member of Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1346.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1357.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The breakaway administration of the Transnistria region in the Republic of Moldova punishes in these ways the applicants, children, parents, and teachers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1357.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1370.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their only crime is the desire to speak freely and study in their native language, the official language of their state, and to provide a meaningful education for their children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1370.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1383.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is even more troubling, honorable judges, to see this anomaly raised to the rank of an official regulation of this breakaway region, which in itself is a contradiction in terms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1383.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1398.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the MRT have introduced a so-called law on languages that requires anyone who wants to avoid criminal prosecution to use a Cyrillic script when writing in Romanian.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1398.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1406.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, in a bitter irony, an illegal administration forces ordinary law-abiding citizens into a situation of illegality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1406.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1417.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have an impossible choice between educating in this linguistic anomaly or breaking the law and living under the constant threat of criminal prosecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1417.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1422.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This abnormal regulation is an MRT administration patented invention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1422.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1433.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nowhere else in the world has such an anomaly been introduced, but it serves to graphically illustrate the goals of the MRT.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1433.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1442.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They include further isolating Transnistria from the rest of Moldova and the ethnic Moldovans from full participation in public life in Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1442.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1446.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the breakaway administration of the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1446.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1454.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>unrecognized Moldovan separatist region of the Transnistria have systematically infringed the applicants' fundamental rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1454.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1462.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants' right to private life, education, and freedom from discrimination have been violated on a regular basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1462.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1465.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will deal with this violation in turn.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1465.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1480.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With respect to Article 8, the right to private life is undoubtedly central to a normal life of a modern person, and language is undoubtedly central to exercising meaningfully this right to private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1480.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1489.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is clear to everybody that one's mother tongue should be spoken and written in the script in which it was designed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1489.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1497.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not only is it unnatural to write in Russian with French characters, or in English using Cyrillic script.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1497.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1505.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Forcing Romanian speakers to use this anomaly grossly violates their right to live a normal life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1505.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1515.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Language is clearly linked to ethnic identity and to relation with others, all of which are protected by Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1515.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1519.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This Court, in the case of Cibotaro v. Moldova, has held</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1519.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1525.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that refusing to recognize one's identity can amount to an interference with private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1525.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1540.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, prohibiting pupil applicants from studying in the script of their own language, an essential aspect of their linguistic, ethnic, and cultural identity, is in direct interference with the right under Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1540.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1565.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the harassment, intimidation, and insults suffered by the pupils for attending the schools of their choice, where teaching took place using the Latin script, and of parents for trying to ensure that their children are educated according to their cultural and linguistic traditions, also amounts to a serious interference with their private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1565.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1577.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The targeted closure of the Moldovan schools by the MRT and continued harassment for teaching the Romanian language with the Latin script has interfered also with the private life of the applicant's teachers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1577.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1595.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has had a detrimental impact both on their ability to freely pursue their profession without arbitrary interference, protected under Article 8 on their own cultural and linguistic identity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1595.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1608.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Living under the constant threat of prosecution constitutes further interference with the right to private life, as the Court has recognized in the case of Norris v. Arlan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1608.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1622.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable Court, the applicants submit that the various interferences with their rights are neither in accordance with the law nor necessary in a democratic society as required by Paragraph 2 of Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1622.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1635.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The acts committed against the applicants described in the application form and in the statement and access to the case have no basis in either Moldova or Russian law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1635.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1643.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither of the governments has ever offered a possible justification for the interferences, and there can be none.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1643.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1646.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1646.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1658.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to further support the applicants' claims, allow me to remind the Honorable Court that the MRT did not stop at violating the applicants' present private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1658.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1663.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They purposefully attempted to jeopardize the applicant's future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1663.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1667.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The administration attacked their rights to education.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1667.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1676.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A primary aim of education is to enable children to maximize the child's ability and opportunity to participate fully in society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1676.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1689.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Conversely, education which fails to achieve these aims can hinder a child's access to opportunities both within the education field and in the future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1689.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1700.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Studying in an artificial language, Romanian written in Cyrillic, a language that doesn't exist outside of Transnistria, means the end of education after school years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1700.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1711.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nowhere in the world can the pupil go on to study on university with the language anomaly that the MRT forces upon them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1711.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1718.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The facts of this case also involve other direct interferences with the right to education.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1718.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1744.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, school closure, the besieging and storming of premises by the militia, the arrest and detention of teachers, the cutting off of basic utilities and food supplies, seizure and destruction of Latin script materials, repeated acts of vandalism, harassment, intimidation, and verbal abuse against the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1744.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1752.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such acts are the antithesis of the sort of environment in which the goals of effective education might be realized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1752.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1776.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The deliberate interferences by the MRT administration also include thwarting access of pupils of all three schools to adequate facilities, forcing the pupils and teachers to use substandard premises and restricting physical access to their existing schools, thereby forcing pupils in some cases to travel up to 70 kilometers per day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1776.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1802.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such distances imposed artificially in a region without proper roads and public transportation mean for some pupils being unable to attend classes, being late for classes, being unable to take part in extracurricular activities, burdening them with unaffordable expenses, and overall resulting in a wholly inadequate standard of education.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1802.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1808.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, I will turn to consider the violation of the right to equality under Article 14.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1808.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1818.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The policy implemented by MRT targeted the applicants because of their ethnicity and language and was plainly discriminatory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1818.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1826.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As explained, the education imposed on the applicants was as useless education in no functional language at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1826.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1839.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For those who insisted on education in the latent script, they were eventually subjected to intolerable conditions in inadequate premises with onerous travel requirements and timetables.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1839.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1846.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This imposed great burdens and pressure, forcing many to renounce this path or leave.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1846.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1860.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is in stark contrast to the position of pupil-speaking Russian and Ukrainian in Transnistria, who received up-to-date modern materials used in other countries such as Russia and Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1860.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1868.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, as the Russian government recognized, the Russian authorities supplied the Russian schools with the needed materials for study.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1868.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1881.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were placed at a severe disadvantage in comparison to their Russian and Ukrainian-speaking pairs, who had access to superior education and superior instruction facilities, superior books and resources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1881.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1894.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the discrimination against Romanian speakers in providing proper education amounts to a gross violation of Article 14 of the Convention taken with Article 8 and Article 2 of the Protocol 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1894.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1901.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable Court, the resolution of the case in favor of the applicants remains important today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1901.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1912.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Violation at the heart of this case dates back to 2002 and 2004, but violation also continues to the present day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1912.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1918.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants submit that it would be a grave injustice not to find violation of the applicants' rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1918.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1929.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We invite the Court to confront directly the actions of the illegal administration within the territory of Moldova and fine against the respondent states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1929.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1940.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not to do so would deny the applicants, including among them some of the most vulnerable members of society, the right to the protection of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1940.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1949.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This would leave the applicants with no avenue for address, no remedy in face of serious violation of their rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1949.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1949.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1951.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1953.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Postika.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1953.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1957.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then I give the floor to Mr. Grosu on behalf of the Republic of Moldova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1958.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1960.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1960.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1962.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable judges of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1962.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1970.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>distinguished audience, different representative of the applicants, your excellency, the representative of the government of Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1970.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1982.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me at the outset express my gratitude for the distinguished high forum, in face of which I have been appointed to represent the government of Republic of Moldova in this particularly complex case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1982.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1995.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, through observations filed at the different stage of procedure, the Moldovan government tried to convey the court and the applicants to a conclusion that they did their best for securing the applicant's rights in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1995.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1998.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Moldova still continues doing so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1998.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2010.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would not reiterate the general background of the case that was thoroughly described in the Ilashko and Vyatsov cases, which has already assessed by the court from a legal perspective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2010.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2018.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the issue of the mind they are still maintaining their actuality, especially for the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2018.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2030.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber adopted the same approach in its admissibility decision, where it examined the events that had been already established in the Ilashko case, and the developments which occurred afterwards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2030.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2033.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber approach was based on two criteria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2033.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2044.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first criteria regards the events of general nature, and that denote the developments of a transnistrian conflict in time, after the findings in the Ilashko case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2044.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2054.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second criterion relies on particular events linked with the applicants, which would be appropriate to define as measures of individual nature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2054.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2062.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Moldovan government never declined to acknowledge that the population and territory from the transnistrian region belong to Moldova as such.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2062.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2067.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nor the obligations under the convention the Moldovan government do not reject.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2067.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2079.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So concerning the cases that imply the transnistrian issue, Moldova acknowledged their jurisdiction, but dispute their responsibility under the convention for the potential violations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2079.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2090.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What the Moldovan government always pleaded for is that they are effectively unable to exercise their powers on their territory and over transnistrian regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2090.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2101.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This would include difficult task for Moldova to secure respect for human rights within their territory, which is out of their effective control and legal authority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2101.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2117.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Long since in the Ilashko case, it was set up that as a consequence of this lack, the Moldovan government actually cannot efficiently exercise their authority over the part of its territory under the effective control of the so-called Moldovan Transnistrian Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2117.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2130.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, Moldovan responsibility could not be engaged under the Article I of the convention on account of a wrongful act within the meaning of international law, paragraph 105 of events of judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2130.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2142.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the above-mentioned Ilashko case, the court has also established the principles that shall govern the assessment of the jurisdiction issue in respect of both responded states, Moldova and Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2142.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2159.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Ivancso case, the court proceeded to the same approach and noted that in respect of Moldova, it should be assessed only one aspect concerning the jurisdiction, namely the question whether or not the Moldovan government has discharged their positive obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2159.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2165.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court reiterated that this question should be examined on the following two aspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2165.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2175.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, general, and the second, individual measures which Moldova has to undertake in order to fulfill its requirements set up in the Ilashko case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2175.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2178.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is to say, I would emphasize the wording of both judgments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2178.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2198.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are within the jurisdiction of the Republic of Moldova, but that its responsibility for the acts complained of committed in the territory of the so-called Moldovan Transnistrian Republic, of which it's exercised no effective authority, is to be assessed in the light of its positive obligations under the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2198.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2213.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moldova's positive obligations relate both to the measures needed to reestablish its control over Transnistrian territory as an expression of its jurisdiction, and second, to measures to ensure respect for the applicant's rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2213.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2221.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to general measures needed, it's not for the court to indicate precisely what kind of measures Moldova must take.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2221.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2240.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the court distinguished that, firstly, Moldova has to refrain from supporting the separatist regime of the so-called Moldovan Transnistrian Republic, and secondly, to act by taking all the political, judicial, and other measures at its disposal to reestablish its control over that territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2240.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2247.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the government moving forward in the present pleadings would start at first by the following statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2247.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2264.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They fully discharged their positive obligations under the both aspects, taken generally and individually, having done what was their best for ensuring effective resolution of the Transnistrian situation or for securing the applicant's rights under the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2264.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2271.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, the government note that they do not challenge the facts established by the admissibility decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2271.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2284.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, in the government's opinion, since the present case involves the assessment of Moldova's positive obligations, such a legal test would be partial if it would be limited in time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2284.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2293.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, they insist on the inclusion of new facts and recent developments incurred after the serving of the chamber's decision as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2293.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2300.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, the jurisdiction issue in this case involves not only the question concerning Moldova's solitary positive obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2300.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2308.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case involves another question, whether the applicants fall into the jurisdiction of the second responded state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2308.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2316.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our opinion, this question is also closely related to the assessment of the Moldova's correlative positive obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2316.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2328.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is because of the court's previous legal assessment that concerns Moldovan government's obligation to refrain from supporting the separatist regime of the so-called Moldovan Transnistrian Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2328.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2339.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since Moldova still abstains from supporting the Transnistrian regime, then someone might reasonably ask, how and why this regime subsists, however?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2339.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2349.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this sense, it would be reasonable to take into consideration the second responded party's actions concerning the resolution of the same Transnistrian issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2349.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2359.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would be also fair to assess the extent of interference by the second responded party's action and Moldova's positive obligations exercise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2359.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2376.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How these actions or omissions, which would belong exclusively to the second responded state, would contribute, delay, or impede Moldova in reaching a positive resolution of the conflict and therefore finding a redress for the applicant's rights?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2376.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2393.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, as it might be concluded from readmissibility decision reasoning, the assessment of the general measures which Moldovan government have to undertake as positive obligations imposes an examination of the military, economic, political, diplomatic, and other aspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2393.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2402.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not least, we bear in mind the sustainability of the Transnistrian regime and its dependence from either or both responded states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2402.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2406.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So now I will proceed to the assessment of the above aspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2406.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2416.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government noted in their previous submissions that they do not have even a clear image about the bulk of arms store within the Transnistrian territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2416.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2423.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, Moldova can declare undoubtedly that there is still military presence of the Russian Federation in Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2423.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2428.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither of the parties in the present proceedings would dissent on this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2428.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2436.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the Moldovan government, all data in this respect are scrappy, and the image of real situation is disjointed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2436.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2442.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It might be about 19,000 tons of ammunition that still stand within the Transnistrian territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2442.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2446.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it cannot be counted properly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2446.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2452.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moldovan authorities are not admitted to visit the Russian military stores in Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2452.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2459.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second responded state would be in a better position to provide the court with real information about their military presence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2459.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2468.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in their last submitted documentary, the second responded state confirmed the information about the presence of military equipment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2468.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2474.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The last known significant amount of military equipment was withdrawn in 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2474.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2483.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since then, what would prevent to leave such ammunition in possession of so-called Transnistrian officials, as it happened to be in the Ilashko case?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2483.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2496.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this sense, the Russian ambassador to Moldova declared of several occasions the military equipment removal from Moldova's territory was stopped because of the Moldova's refusal to sign the Cossack memorandum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2496.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2505.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the other side, Russia claimed that the removal was temporarily stopped because of the strong opposition from so-called Transnistrian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2505.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2516.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This could be interpreted by a neutral observer as a kind of political influence casted on Moldova and a kind of implicit support for the so-called Transnistrian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2516.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2532.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's rather questionable how the Transnistrian opposition would prevent such a power as Russian Federation from removal of its own military goods from the territory of internationally non-recognized and non-constitutional entities such as Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2532.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2539.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the government would recall that they always pleaded for removal of that military presence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2539.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2548.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, they are in favor of replacement of the existing peacekeeping military forces by a civil mission of international observers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2548.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2561.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This lack of real information and prohibition to have access to military stores would lead any objective observer to a conclusion that a part of Moldova's territory is under the military control of another foreign state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2561.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2570.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, this idea was expressed by Lord Justice Brooke when he assessed the jurisdiction issue in the Altskene case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2570.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2582.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was stated that the situation in Altskene's case contrasts starkly with the situation in northern Cyprus and in the Russian-occupied part of Moldova, which feature in Strasbourg case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2582.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2594.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In each of those cases, part of the territory of a contracting state was occupied by another contracting state, which had every intention of exercising its control on a long-term basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2594.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2604.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The civilian administration of those territories was under the control of an occupying state, and it deployed sufficient troops to ensure that its control of the area was effective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2604.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2607.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Paragraph 80 of Altskene judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2607.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2612.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are a lot of other aspects of military nature that could be addressed in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2612.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2623.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, the issue of Taraspo airport, or an eventual enrollment of the so-called Transnistrian nationals and the Russian army due to their Russian citizenship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2623.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2640.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian government in their last submitted documentary have expressly acknowledged that they used the Taraspo airport for displacing their special equipment in the Transnistrian territory after a trolleybus explosion occurred in Taraspo in August 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2640.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2646.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The airport was used without consent from the Moldovan authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2646.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2652.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, for a proper examination of a present case, some recent events cannot be neglected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2652.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2662.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, there was a killing of a Moldovan civil national by a peacekeeping soldier at the very beginning of January this year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2662.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2667.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This event was widely commented and strongly condemned by the Moldovan government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2667.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2672.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It must be noted that the peacekeeping soldier has a so-called Transnistrian citizenship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2672.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2685.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Simultaneously, that soldier is a Russian national as well, who after the killing had left Transnistria and apparently, according to mass media, set himself in Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2685.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2689.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These facts do not advance the resolution of the tragic incident.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2689.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2705.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the present moment, the consequences of the foreign military presence and the peacekeeping forces within the Moldovan territory raise many questions concerning the sovereignty, the possibility to control the region, and to ensure the respect for human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2705.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2712.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's practically impossible for Moldova in this situation to impose their rule of law on that territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2712.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2722.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moldova was considered, since the Ilashko case, as being under the positive obligation to ensure the rule of law and respect for human rights and the territory concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2722.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2728.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it will be very difficult to discharge such obligations because of that foreign military presence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2728.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2743.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, as the court concluded in the Ilashko case and continued most recently in both Al-Skhinian and Al-Jaddah cases, a foreign military presence within territory of another state creates a clear jurisdictional link.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2743.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2773.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite the fact that the reasons of the Judge Bonello expressed in his concurring opinion to Al-Skhinian judgment have not been shared by the majority of the court, the Moldovan government consider relevant his statements that once a state is acknowledged by international law to be an occupying power, a rebuttable presumption ought to arise that the occupying power has authority and control over the occupied territory, with all the consequences that fall from a legal presumption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2773.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2779.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, this link is between the Transnistrian territory and the Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2779.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2791.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the military presence might develop in time and become a kind of designation of a foreign authority on another territory, or even in a kind of partial substitution thereof.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2791.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2818.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This logic is derived from the Al-Skhinian judgment, when the court stated that the UK assumed the exercise of some of the public powers normally to be exercised by a sovereign government, and soldiers engaged in security operations exercised authority and control over individuals killed in the course of such security operations so as to establish a jurisdictional link.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2818.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2823.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Paragraph 149 of the Al-Skhinian judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2823.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2831.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In time, the military presence would threaten any peaceful resolution, and it might be used as a trump card in political disputes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2831.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2836.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, this was the case when Moldova refused to sign the Cossack Memorandum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2836.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2844.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The withdrawal of the military presence from their territory would create more chances for successful settlement of Transnistrian dispute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2844.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2849.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The entire European and international community would benefit from this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2849.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2857.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With due diligence, all difficulties which appeared in such removal process would be surmounted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2857.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2865.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At least due diligence is merely on the part of the Russian government that assumes such responsibility for military removal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2865.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2873.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another condition imposed by Alashko judgment was that Moldova should abstain from supporting the Transnistrian regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2873.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2880.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that no political or economic assistance would come from Moldova, so the regime would be unable to resist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2880.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2884.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government declared that they approached very carefully this standard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2884.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2891.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the regime still exists and continues to cast its influence on people on that territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2891.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2899.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, as the Russian government acknowledged in their written observations, they still support financially the Transnistrian regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2899.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2908.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This financial support is provided either by means of waiving of debts for gas consumed, which actually amounts to a sum of about $2.9 billion</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2908.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2914.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>US dollars, or by affording Transnistria with non-refundable money aid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2914.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2922.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The financial humanitarian aid usually takes form of non-refundable credits and investments in the Transnistrian economy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2922.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2927.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The examples of such financial support were produced by all parties in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2927.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2943.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the second responded state, in their finally submitted documentary, had acknowledged expressly that Russian commercial entities made investments in Transnistria, and therefore Russia has clear economic interests there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2943.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2954.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this sense, the government note that the financial aid provided by the Russian Federation for the Transnistrian region are subjected to vote for supervision from the Russian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2954.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2967.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, the Russian prosecution authorities initiated a number of criminal proceedings against the son of a former leader of Transnistria and against several officials from the Transnistria financial institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2967.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2973.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These criminal proceedings concern the alleged embezzlement of the Russian humanitarian aid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2973.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2979.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The political aspect is the most difficult to describe because of the continuous development thereof.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2979.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2989.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What the government wished to declare in this respect is that they never supported, by no means, so-called Transnistrian politicians and officials.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2989.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2997.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Moldovan government have even attempted to develop a new diplomatic language for use in discussions with so-called officials.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2997.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3006.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This language must avoid any official acknowledgments of a Transnistrian status, but without affecting the negotiation process either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3006.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3018.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From another point of view, we can observe that the entire Transnistrian policy is based on opposition towards Moldova, but with strong political commitments to Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3018.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3029.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The latest example would serve as an evidence for a strong political support expressed during the so-called presidential elections held in Transnistria in late 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3029.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3037.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A lot of direct implications were cast in the Transnistrian electoral process from the very powerful Russians politicians and parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3037.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3044.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All so-called Transnistrian candidates for elections claim to have strong relations and support from Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3044.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3056.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, on the government's opinion, must be mentioned the recent Russian parliamentary elections where certain ballot boxes were opened within the territory of Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3056.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3063.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ballot box of the ballot process was held despite of a strong and official opposition from the Moldovan authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3063.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3069.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The candidates for Russian Duma electoral campaigns had been widely held in Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3069.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3075.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These facts are also relevant for the assessment of the jurisdiction and its political aspect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3075.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3084.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the same line of ideas, the government rely also on many mutual official visits of different political figures between Russia and Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3084.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3089.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This would prove strong political relations among these politicians.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3089.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3101.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the Transnistrian conflict resolution, after the end of the 1992 military phase of the conflict, the Moldovan authorities were always committed to the peaceful solution of the dispute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3101.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3111.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have unconditionally accepted the assistance and cooperation of international partners like OSCE, European Union, and even from the United States of America.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3111.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3120.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such international actors always sustain the Moldovan government's effort in a political settlement of the dispute and in country reintegration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3120.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3129.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government may assume that because of their approach to the Transnistrian problem, several serious violations have been settled and at least were partly redressed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3129.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3136.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, the Vardanyan and the Kazakh cases have been widely disseminated for the attention of the international community.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3136.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3140.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These cases were basically sated by the Moldovan government's engagements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3140.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3148.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both persons were released from custody of the so-called Transnistrian authorities with the support of international community.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3148.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3150.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government had also afforded Mr. Kazakh</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3150.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3156.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a financial redress for medical care in a house in Chisinau, the capital of Moldova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3156.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3167.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, we conclude and declare that Transnistria regime has never been sustained and it will never be supported, nor directly, nor implicitly, by the Moldovan government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3167.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3174.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In all political disputes, the Moldovas' only will is to settle the issue and to gain their control over the territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3174.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3180.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They wish to serve up the rule of law and respect for human rights within the region.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3180.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3188.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The individual measures performed by Moldova in respect of the applicants must be also taken into account in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3188.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3192.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government rely on the facts established in the admissibility decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3192.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3201.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There had been noted then the Moldovan government had effectively performed active measures and somehow to redress the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3201.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3208.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Recalling those findings, the government emphasized they had paid for rent and for refurbishing of school buildings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3208.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3214.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They still pay the teachers salaries and provide with educational materials, buses, and computers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3214.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3226.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Moldovan law and education, the pupils and graduates from Transnistrian schools have special facilities and applying for domestic universities and higher education system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3226.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3233.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government had raised the Transnistrian school issue before the international community of several occasions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3233.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3240.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They sought the assistance and intervention of international organizations for mediation of the school crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3240.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3263.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Among other things, the school crisis has also been discussed at the high-level conference held in Bad Reichenhall, Germany on 9 September 2011 under the auspices of the OCE and European Union as an example of a recent policy promoted by the Moldovan government for building confidence between the two banks of the Dniester River.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3263.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3269.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a final point, the government would like to consider a legal assessment which is required for the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3269.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3277.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Among many relevant principles instituted by the Court in respect of jurisdiction concept, the government would note as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3277.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3288.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Alskene judgment, the Court surrounded the notion of public powers that were exercised by the state extraterritorially, paragraph 149, Alskene judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3288.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3299.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This led the Court to find a clear link established between an individual and the responding government by exercising their powers throughout their agents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3299.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3308.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Actually, in the government's opinion, the Court held in the Alskene that the military presence may engage the exercise of public powers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3308.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3322.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, sharing the Court's opinion in the way mentioned above, the government would consider that these reasons do engage the Russian government's jurisdiction due to their continuous military presence in the region.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3322.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3330.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What distinguishes the present case from Alskene judgment is that in the present case, there are two responded states engaged in dispute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3330.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3339.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moldova claims territorial applicability, but they insist on the lack of their authority on the absence of any means to gain the effective control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3339.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3351.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From another point of view, despite of the military presence, the Russian government argue the absence of any public powers over their territory and therefore the absence of effective control either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3351.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3360.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, given the Alskene judgment reasons, the military presence could be understood as an exercise of a sort of public powers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3360.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3375.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Long ago, in Loya Zidu judgment, we saw that when as a consequence of a military action, whenever a lawful or unlawful, a contracting state exercise effective control of an area outside its national territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3375.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3388.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The obligation to secure in such an area the convention rights derives from the fact of such control whether it be exercised directly through its armed forces or through a subordinate local administration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3388.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3392.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same principles were at the core of Alskene judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3392.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3405.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the government may assume that in terms of Loya Zidu and Alskene judgments, the Russian Federation would be considered as having jurisdiction that may engage its responsibility under the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3405.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3414.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the jurisdiction of Moldova, the government recognize the existence of corresponding positive obligations, as stated in the Lashko judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3414.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3418.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But their obligations were discharged in their present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3418.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3423.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same exemption of responsibility was found in the Ivan Sok case as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3423.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3433.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the government invite the court to assess the Moldova's positive obligations and the light of the corresponding positive obligations of the Russian government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3433.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3444.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's necessary to examine how Moldova's obligations can be fulfilled in this situation where the concurring or even a conflict of jurisdiction still persists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3444.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3461.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government consider that the Loya Zidu judgment derived the reasoning that any particular extent of the positive obligations to secure conventional rights would be proportionate to the level of control, in fact, exercised.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3461.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3469.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the merits of the present case, the government of Moldova acknowledge that they are in a very difficult legal situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3469.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3476.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's uneasy for Moldova to assess whether there has been a violation of the applicant's rights or otherwise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3476.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3487.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government of Moldova always, in the present case, gave their support to the applicants, having attempted to secure their rights and appropriate redress.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3487.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3497.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this sense, Moldova's actions would lead to a conclusion that they acknowledged, at least implicitly, that the applicant's rights were actually breached.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3497.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3504.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this situation, it would be inappropriate for my government to argue against the finding of a violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3504.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3519.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in this situation, the government wished to emphasize that it's for the court now to assess the legal issue to what extent the applicant's rights were or not actually breached by other of both responding states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3519.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3527.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On behalf of my government, I constantly vote how to conclude duly the present oral pleadings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3527.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3541.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Beyond many opportunities, like two years ago during the hearings before the chamber, I found it most appropriate to quote again the dissenting opinion of the distinguished Judge Lukaidis from the Ilashko case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3541.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3545.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That opinion proved to be very topical, even after the lapse of time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3545.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3550.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same conclusions the court has reached in its reasoning in the Ivancso case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3550.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3575.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the Judge Lukaidis noted that to conclude that there is jurisdiction over certain persons simply because the government concerned has failed to take judicial, political, diplomatic, and economic measures or any other measures, even though actual authority over the persons, so the applicants on the part of the government was lacking, would be stretching the concept of jurisdiction to an unrealistic and absurd extent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3575.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3582.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the Moldovan government invited the court to build a realistic concept of positive obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3582.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3596.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, the government now considered that the present case is rather of general interest, and it certainly can be considered as a case that might move forward the process for Moldova's territorial reintegration from the dead point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3596.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3612.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the government kindly invite the court to discharge the Moldovan government of any responsibility under Article 2, Protocol Number 1 of the Convention, and under Article 8 of the Convention, taken separately or in conjunction with Article 14 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3612.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3618.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These eventual findings would not stop the Moldovans' efforts to fulfill their positive obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3618.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3630.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the court will rather urge the Moldovan government to keep their efforts and to move straight ahead into securing the applicants' rights and the rights of all the population within the Moldova's territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3630.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3630.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3632.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3634.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Grosu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3634.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3636.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then I give the floor to Mr. Matyushkin</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3636.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3638.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on behalf of the government of the Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3650.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3658.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Власти РФ выражают несогласие с изложением фактов в решении Европейского суда от 15 июня 2010 года по вопросу приемлемости.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3664.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3674.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Европейский суд взял за основу трактовку фактов, касающихся Молдавско-Преднестровского конфликта в период с 1991 по 2003 год, изложенного в деле Илашко и другие против Молдавии и России.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3679.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3683.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Изложение фактов начинается за 11-13 лет до предполагаемого нарушения прав заявителей по данному делу, то есть с 1991-1992 года, и соответственно за 3-4 года до вступления Конвенции в силу в отношении Российской Федерации.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3683.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3689.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В то время как обжалуемые события в настоящем деле имели место в 2003-2004 годах.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3705.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3709.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Такое изложение фактов является ретроспективным.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3709.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3715.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В случае Море против Франции и Городи против Франции суд указал, что он должен по возможности воздерживаться от высказывания взглядов по историческим вопросам, не подпадающим под его юрисдикцию.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3722.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3730.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Во-вторых, доводы заявителей о продолжающемся до настоящего времени нарушении их прав не подтверждены доказательствами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3730.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3736.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Так, исходя из информации, представленной заявителями в Европейский суд, предполагаемые нарушения их прав давно устранены.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3736.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3744.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В делах Катаны, Калдары и других школьники возобновили обучение в сентябре-октябре 2004 года.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3744.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3748.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В деле Черкасские и другие в 2002-2003 годах.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3748.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Кроме того, как следует из требований заявителей по справедливой компенсации, практически все школьники уже закончили обучение в школах и поступили в университеты.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3762.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В-третьих, анализ меморандума в заявителе власти Республики Молдова позволяет сделать вывод, что эти материалы не только содержат недостоверные сведения, но и целенаправленно извращают суть проблемы.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3772.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3774.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Обвинительный антироссийский уклон очевиден.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3774.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3788.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Прежде всего, речь идет о намерениях обвинить власти РФ военной, политической и экономической поддержки Приднестровского режима и тем самым предоставить ситуацию как длящееся осуществление юрисдикции над регионом.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3788.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3800.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>При этом искусственно упускаются из виду факты активного российского содействия урегулированию молдавско-преднестровского конфликта в составе международного посредничества формата 5 плюс 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3800.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3826.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В настоящем деле, в отличие от дел Альскения, ИСА и другие, Лашку, Банкович, Бехроми и Бехроми, Саддам Хусейн против коалиционных сил, Асанидзе против Грузии, заявители не смогли сформулировать, какой экскретариальный акт был совершен властями РФ и какова юрисдикционная связь между предполагаемыми жертвами и РФ.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3826.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3850.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Как указано в параграфе 95 решения по делу Минас Арксян против Азербайджана, а также в решении по делу Джиби и 361 родитель против Швейцарии и Италии, система индивидуальных жалоб, гарантированная статьей 34 Конвенции, исключает жалобы, заявленные путем акция о популяриз.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3850.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3853.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Заявители должны доказать, что они прямо пострадали от обжалуемой меры.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3853.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3859.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Показательным в этой связи также является решение по делу Саддам Хусейн против коалиционных сил.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3859.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3872.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Суд отметил, что коалиционные силы оккупировали Ирак в марте 2003 года, по большей части при участии сил и поддержке со стороны США и Соединенного Королевства.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3872.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3878.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Суд предположил, что коалиционные силы получили поддержку от каждого из договаривающихся государств, указанных в жалобе.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3878.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3888.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В то же время суд отметил, что Саддам Хусейн не указал на роль и ответственность каждого из государств-ответчиков, существующих между ответчиками США.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3888.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3900.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Дополнительно он не указал, какой из государств-ответчиков, кроме США, имело влияние и причастность к его аресту, содержанию под стражей и передаче властям.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3900.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3911.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Соответственно суд пришел к выводу, что отсутствовала юрисдикционная связь между Саддамом Хусейном и договаривающимися государствами по смыслу статьи первой конвенции.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3911.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3936.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В решении по делу Бехрами и Бехрами, несмотря на то, что страны-участницы миротворческой операции в рамках мандата ООН осуществляли военный контроль над территорией Косово, контролировали внутренние коммуникации и перемещения людей, осуществляли контроль над обширной территорией Косово, Европейский суд не признал экстратериальную юрисдикцию государств-участников Кейфор над подконтрольной им территорией.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3936.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3960.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Настоящие дела также существенно отличаются от дела Аль Саадун и Мауди против Соединенного Королевства, в котором военнослужащими сил Международной коалиции, вторжившись в Ирак в марте 2003 года, заявители были арестованы за убийство британских военнослужащих, содержались в местах лишения свободы, контролируемых британскими военнослужащими, а затем были выданы иракским властям.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3960.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3973.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Европейский суд установил, что власти Соединенного Королевства имели тотальный и исключительный контроль над местом содержания, где находились заявители, и поэтому суд установил, что заявители находились под юридикцией Соединенного Королевства.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3973.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3990.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Утверждение заявителей в параграфе 91 дополнительных замечаний о том, что школы имени Александру Челбун и школы имени Штефана Челмары находятся в зоне безопасности, охраняемой российскими миротворцами, не соответствует действительности.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3990.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4024.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В соответствии со статьей 3 соглашения о принципах мирного регулирования вооруженного конфликта в Приднесровском регионе Республики Молдова от 21 июля 1992 года, город Бендеры, как место пребывания контрольной комиссии и в силу особой сложности обстановки, объявлен районом с повышенным режимом безопасности, который обеспечивается воинскими контингентами сторон, участвующих в выполнении данного соглашения, то есть его контролируют не российские миротворцы, а военнослужащие совместных миротворческих сил.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4024.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4050.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>При этом ближайшим постом к лицею имени Александру Челбун, город Бендеры, является двусторонний молдавско-российский пост номер 3, расположенный на удалении 2 километра от лицея, на удалении 7,2 километра от лицея имени Штефана Челмары, в селе Дородское, находится трехсторонний российско-молдавско-преднестровский пункт номер 8, левый.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4050.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4059.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Таким образом, двусторонние и трехсторонние посты совместных миротворческих сил располагаются в нескольких километрах от школ заявителей.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4059.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4073.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Контроль в соответствии с мандатом действий миротворцев в зоне безопасности исключает полицейские функции, разбирательство, гражданско-правовых конфликтов, хозяйственных и имущественных споров.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4073.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4083.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Российские миротворцы не имеют какого-либо отношения к проблемам школ, так как данное учебное заведение находится далеко за пределами участков ответственности постов.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4083.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4102.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В деле ИСА и другие против Турции суд принял во внимание заявление правительства Турции о том, что убийства родственников заявителей в 10 километрах от места дислокации турецких войск за пределами зоны проведения операций не могут быть вменены государству ответчику.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4102.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4115.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В соответствии с действительностью также параграфы 13, 17, 91, 93 и другие дополнительных замечаний заявителей, где речь идет о школе в селе Дородское.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4115.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4126.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Заявители жалуются, что ученикам ежедневно приходится проделывать путь в 35 километров до школы, а школьные автобусы задерживают и подвергают тщательному досмотру.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4126.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4142.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В параграфе 13 заявители указывают, что этот участок дороги контролируется молдавскими властями. В параграфе 17, что обыски проводятся должностными лицами Приднестровья. В параграфах 91 и 93, что эта территория охраняется российскими миротворцами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4142.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4166.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>На самом деле на маршруте следования учеников в лице из Штефана Чалмары и вблизи данного участка местности отсутствуют какие-либо посты совместных миротворческих сил. Ближайшие контрольно-пропускные пункты номер 8, левый, расположен в 7,2 километрах и номер 9, левый, расположен в 14 километрах соответственно.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4166.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4188.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В параграфе 13, что контроль и досмотр транспортных средств и лиц в них следующих представителями совместных миротворческих сил не производится. Предполагаемые нарушения прав заявителей, если таковые имели место на самом деле, могут быть причинены органами власти и должностными лицами Приднестровской Молдавской Республики, а не российскими миротворцами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4188.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4216.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В этом заключается существенное отличие настоящего дела от дела Аль-Скейни. По своему существу, дело Аль-Скейни и другие является исключительным и в корне отличается от рассматриваемого дела. В Соединённое Королевство его партнеры по коалиции сместили прежнее иракское правительство, что являлось целью их вмешательства. Затем они взяли на себя обязательства по формированию правительства, которые были предназначены для того, чтобы внести в правительство правительство.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4216.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4238.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Они взяли на себя обязательства по формированию нового правительства и установлению гражданского порядка, а также взяли на себя роль правительства Ирака под названием Временной Власти Коалиции. Временная Власть Коалиции передала правление Южным Ираком в руки британских вооружённых сил. В указанных районах Ирака никакого другого гражданского правительства не существовало.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4238.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4261.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Важно, что в параграфе 150 постановления по делу Аль-Скейни суд также уделяет особое внимание тому, что смерти родственников заявителей были вызваны действиями британских солдат. По мнению суда из этого следует, что во всех этих случаях присутствовала юрисдикционная связь в целях статьи 1 Конвенции между Соединённым Королевством и умершими.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4261.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4275.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В этом случае, в указанном постановлении не содержится никаких аргументов в поддержку позиции заявителей властей Молдавы.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4275.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4295.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Большая Палата признала, что юрисдикция в соответствии с Конвенцией в первую очередь является территориальной, кроме исключительных случаев. Таким образом, заявителям в отношении данной жалобы необходимо доказать, что обстоятельства настоящего дела являются в своём роде исключительными, что оправдывает отступление от стандартных правил.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4295.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4314.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В качестве исключения суд отметил такое основание, как осуществление государством фактического контроля над территорией иностранного государства. Однако признание наличия фактического контроля в деле Айскени было сделано на основании действий государства, выходивших далеко за рамки военной миссии и прямо направленных на создание нового правительства.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4314.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4334.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Возвращаясь к обстоятельствам данного дела, следует отметить, что Российская Федерация никогда не признавала независимости Приднестровского региона Республики Молдова, а также, в отличие от дела Киборг против Турции, не признавала действия самопровозглашённых властей, не признанных международным сообществом.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4334.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4361.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>По словам Айскени, Российская Федерация никогда не смещала местную администрацию Приднестровского региона и, тем более, никогда не устанавливала там временное административное управление, не издавала какие-либо инструкции для местного населения, никакой деятельности по вооружению, обучению, совместному оперативному планированию оперативная группа российских войск с военными силами Приднестровья никогда не проводила и не проводит.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4361.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4370.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Россия не соответственно соблюдает международные договорённости, выполняет взятые на себя обязательства государства-посредниковы в регулировании конфликта.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4370.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4374.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В соответствии с статьёй 4 соглашения строго соблюдает нейтралитет.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4374.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4394.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Россия не оказывает политической, экономической, финансовой, военной, образовательной и иных видов поддержки Приднестровью. Размещение на территории Приднестровья российского воинского контингента в составе совместных миротворческих сил, которые переданы в подчинение Объединённой контрольной комиссии, строго соответствует международным соглашениям.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4394.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4419.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В своих собственных делах отсутствует юрисдикционная связь с заявителями и Российской Федерацией по смыслу статьи 1-й Конвенции. Власти России категорически возражают против дискриминационного подхода к России, когда только в отношении одного государства, России, в делах Илашко и других, были применены критерии решающего влияния и тесных взаимоотношений путём военной, экономической, финансовой и политической поддержки.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4419.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4443.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Эти критерии по своей природе уникальны и применяются избирательно только в отношении России. Ни в одном другом деле Европейского Суда по делам об экс-территориальной юрисдикции они не использовались. Неизвестны данные критерии и никакому другому Международному Суду, ни Международному Суду ООН, ни Международному трибуналу по бывшей Югославии.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4443.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4470.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Относительно юрисдикции Республики Молдова. В параграфах 63-70 решения по делу Минас Архсян против Азербайджана Европейский суд признал недействительными заявления Азербайджана и Республики Молдова о нераспространении их юрисдикции на Горный Карабах и Приднестровский регион, сделанные при ратификации Конвенции.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4470.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4489.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>По аналогии с делом с Архсян бесспорно, что правительство Республики Молдова действует в границах своей международно признанной территории. Вследствие этого негативные и позитивные обязательства сохраняются у Республики Молдова даже в тех случаях, когда осуществление государственных полномочий ограничено частью территории.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4489.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4506.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Следует отметить, что за 2011 год состоялось три прямых контакта премьер-министра Молдавии Филата с бывшим лидером Приднестровья Смирновым. Обсуждались вопросы в сфере экономики, железнодорожного сообщения, обеспечения прав человека.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4506.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4521.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Однако проблема школ и взаимодействие двух министерств образования, Молдавского и Приднестровского, не затрагивалась и не была выделена в отдельную тему для рассмотрения в рамках экспертных групп по выработке мер доверия.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4521.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4542.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Относительно отсутствия военной поддержки. Обвинения во всем происходящем российских миротворцев являются явно необоснованными. Миротворческие силы в зоне безопасности состоят из воинских контингентов трех сторон – Молдавии, Приднестровья и России, а также группы наблюдателей от Украины.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4542.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4558.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Все контингенты подчинены Объединенной контрольной комиссии, принимающей коллективные решения по каждому инциденту, имевшему место в зоне безопасности и требующего вмешательства Объединенной контрольной комиссии миротворческих сил.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4558.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4574.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Подписанное на уровне президентов Российской Федерации и Республики Молдова соглашение о принципах мирного регулирования вооруженного конфликта в Приднестровском регионе Республики Молдова от 21 июля 1992 года остается в силе.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4574.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4595.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Удивительно, в договоре о дружбе и сотрудничестве между Россией и Республикой Молдова от 19 ноября 2001 года зафиксировано участие России в качестве сопосредника и гаранта будущих договоренностей на основе соблюдения суверенитета и территориальной целостности Республики Молдова.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4595.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4606.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Существующие власть и правительство, исследованные судом в деле Илашко, существенно изменились. Возьмем для примера массовый вывод войск бывшего СССР с территории Республики Молдова.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4606.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4635.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В том году численность личного состава 14-й армии, застигнутой на территории Молдавии к моменту распада СССР, а не специально введенной в порядке оккупации, составляла чуть более 11 тысяч военнослужащих. На основании протокола о количественном составе и размещении миротворческих сил от 28 июля 1992 года было предусмотрено присутствие на территории Молдавии шести российских батальонов.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4635.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4663.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В рамках мотива России российский воинский контингент в составе совместных миротворческих сил в Приднестровском регионе Республики Молдова, переданный в подчинение Объединенной контрольной комиссии, в одностороннем порядке был сокращен с шестим атострелковых батальонов и подразделения обеспечения всего 3100 человек в 1992 году до одного батальона 418 человек в 2003 году.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4663.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4679.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4679.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4699.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4699.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4719.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4719.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4743.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4743.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4771.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4771.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4799.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4799.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4827.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4827.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4849.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4849.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4873.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4873.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4893.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4893.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4913.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4913.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4933.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4933.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4951.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4951.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4971.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4971.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4995.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4995.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5015.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5015.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5037.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5037.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5059.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5059.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5079.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5079.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5099.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5099.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5119.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5119.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5139.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5139.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5167.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5167.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5187.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5187.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5209.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5209.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5237.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5237.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5265.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5265.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5285.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5285.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5313.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5313.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5333.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5333.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5353.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5353.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5373.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5373.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5393.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5393.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5413.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км в длину и в ширину от 12 до 20 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5413.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5433.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5433.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5459.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5459.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5479.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5479.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5499.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5499.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5519.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5519.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5543.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженностью 225 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5543.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5563.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженности 225 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5563.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5587.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Время личной состава батальона выполняет возложенные на него задачи в зоне безопасности протяженности 225 км, расположенные между конфликтующими сторонами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5587.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5589.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>в наших письменных заключениях.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5589.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5589.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Спасибо за внимание!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5593.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5599.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Matyushkin. So we have come to the end of the first round of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5599.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5606.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>addresses. The Court put a number of questions in advance of the hearing, which the parties</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5606.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5618.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>have incorporated, the answers of which the parties have incorporated in their oral submissions already. I would like to ask whether judges have additional questions which they wish</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5618.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5630.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to put to any of the parties. That does not seem to be the case, so I think we do not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5630.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5645.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>need a break and I will give the floor at once to the applicants to make short replies if they wish to the submissions of the other two parties. Mr. Hughes, do you wish to reply?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5648.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5658.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President, members of the Court. I'll just briefly respond to what was outlined by the Moldovan government in relation to its positive obligations,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5658.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5671.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then address some of the issues raised by the Russian Federation. With respect to the Moldovan submissions regarding what they've done in relation to this issue,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5671.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5689.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>how they've attempted to prevent these violations from taking place, what steps they've taken to influence the course of events, we would simply say to the Court, we're not expecting an unreasonable or impossible burden to be imposed on the Moldovan state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5689.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5702.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We've recognized on a number of occasions that the situation with respect to Transnistria is such that Moldova doesn't exercise control over Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5702.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5730.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But again, we reiterate that there were certain things it could have done that it didn't do that could have had an influence on the way in which the applicants' situation was unfolding in Transnistria during that crucial period between 2002 and 2004, and also the situation either side of those dates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5730.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5751.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say that those positive obligations include the bringing of criminal proceedings, for example, against members of the MRT administration, which would have had the effect of curtailing their travel through Moldova and also internationally.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5751.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5756.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is just one brief example of what the Moldovan government could have done.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5756.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5774.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A second example, we say, would have been to introduce this matter on a more robust basis at international meetings concerning the discussions around the future of Transnistria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5774.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5781.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In terms of the Russian submissions to date, we'll simply say this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5781.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5804.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian position is that the circumstances in Issa, Loizidu, cases similar to that involving the situation of Turkish troops in Iraq, of Turkish troops in northern Cyprus, is entirely compatible with the facts of this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5804.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5810.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not a question of the number of boots on the ground.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5810.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5825.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in Cyprus, the Russian Federation states that there were a significant number more troops there exercising control over the area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5825.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5831.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The circumstances of this particular case are, in many respects, unique.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5831.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5841.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decision of this court in Alashku found that the MRT administration has been established, not just supported, but established by the Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5841.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5845.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And since its establishment, it has been supported.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5845.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5862.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The effect of Russian troops being present on the ground in Transnistria is that they maintain the ability to react to events and maintain the ability to ensure control continues over the region.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5862.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5870.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relation to political support, again, we simply say the statements from the Juma speak for themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5870.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5885.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The actions of the Russian government with respect to the sanctions introduced and that had serious consequences, as noted by the IMF in 2006, speak for themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5885.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5899.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is clear political support for the MRT administration, but we would ask the court to consider political, economic, and military support as having a cumulative effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5899.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5907.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not a question of taking each particular type of engagement or involvement of the Russian Federation on its own.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5907.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5917.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is a cumulative effect to the way in which they exercise control over the territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5917.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5937.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the specific questions raised by the court in advance of the hearing, on the airports we would simply say that our understanding is that there is an agreement from 1994 between the Russian Federation and Moldova giving control of the airport to the Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5937.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5959.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the question of the teachers coming within Article 2 of Protocol 1, the teachers we refer to in our application are also parents, and it is in their capacity as parents we say they come within Article 2, Protocol 1 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5959.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5959.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those are my submissions. Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5963.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5964.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5964.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5967.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr Grosu, would you like to reply shortly?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5969.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5970.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5970.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5996.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je vais parler en français.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6000.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6020.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le Moldovan authorities did not pursue certain measures taken previously, particularly investigations in respect of persons involved in the applicant's conviction and detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6020.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6034.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the court considers that in the absence of control over Transnistria territory by the Moldovan authorities, any judicial investigation in respect of persons living in Transnistria or linked to the offences committed in Transnistria would be ineffectual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6034.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6038.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is confirmed by the witness evidence on that point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6038.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6058.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans ce cas, même si j'ai cité l'affaire Hilashko, dans ce cas je ne vois pas aucun raisonnement pourquoi on dépare de ce que la cour a constaté il y a 7 ou 8 ans avant, parce que la situation, si on parle du contrôle des autorités constitutionnelles de Kishinev sur le territoire de Transnistria, n'a pas changé.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6058.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6069.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le caractère effectif des autorités de droit, cela veut dire le parquet général et les autorités judiciaires sur le territoire de Transnistria, n'a pas devenu plus effectif de 2004 jusqu'à présent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6069.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6082.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quant aux problèmes qui ont été invoqués par la partie russe et le gouvernement russe, je vais mentionner le suivant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6082.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6111.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Premièrement, sur l'aspect militaire, je vais mentionner très courtement que même si vraiment le contingent militaire de la Russie dans la Transnistrie n'est pas comparable que celui dans le cas d'Oezidou ou dans les autres cas, dans les autres situations, cela veut dire qu'il ne se chiffre pas par des dizaines de milliers de soldats, mais ce n'est pas à mon avis le principal point à quoi il faut donner l'attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6111.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6116.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et ici je partage l'idée qui a été invoquée par les recueillants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6116.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6135.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pour le gouvernement moldave, c'est très important qu'aucun soldat étranger ne se trouve pas sur le territoire moldave sans son consentement, surtout si on parle d'un état neutre comme l'état de la République de Moldova concernant conformément notre constitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6135.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6144.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc la présence même d'un seul soldat, cela pose des problèmes de la souveraineté de l'intégrité territoriale de la République de Moldova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6144.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6149.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>De notre parti et de notre point de vue sur l'aspect militaire, je voudrais invoquer le suivant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6149.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6180.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Après les actes de vandalisme qui malheureusement ont eu lieu au mois d'avril 2009, après les élections parlementaires dans mon pays, dans la République de Moldova, la délégation de Transnistrie dans la commission unifiée de contrôle, cela veut dire sur le contrôle desquels se trouvent les forces pacificatrices, donc la délégation de Transnistrie, elle a sollicité d'élargir le contingent militaire russe jusqu'à 2700 personnes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6180.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6193.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc le contingent russe actuellement qui compte à peu près 1100, 1200 selon les dires du gouvernement russe, ils ont sollicité de l'augmenter jusqu'à 2700, cela veut dire plus que le doublé.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6193.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6214.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ici, mon commentaire, même si la fédération de Russie ne considère pas le contingent de 1100 soldats comme très grand qui sera capable de contrôler ce territoire, c'est très important de donner attention à comment apprécie la partie transnistrienne ce fait.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6214.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6228.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc la partie transnistrienne considère que même un tel contingent de 1000 ou 2000 personnes est comme une garantie pour eux très sérieuse dans la réglementation définitive du conflit transnistrien.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6228.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6235.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et c'est indébitable que pour la partie transnistrienne, ça c'est un facteur très important qui est dans leurs mains.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6235.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6244.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sur le fait, ce qu'a invoqué le gouvernement russe, c'est sur l'aide humanitaire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6244.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6253.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le gouvernement russe soutient qu'il accorde de l'aide humanitaire quant à la partie transnistrienne, quant à la Moldova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6253.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6266.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La république de Moldova ne peut pas nier vraiment la fédération russie avec des différentes occasions à offrir de l'aide humanitaire et d'autres types d'aide à la république de Moldova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6266.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6273.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pourquoi on est reconnaissant? Mais quand même, je vais me référer à l'aide humanitaire</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6273.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6276.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>qui a été accordée à la région transnistrienne.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6276.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6307.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La partie russe, dans ses derniers commentaires du mois d'octobre-décembre 2011, il stipule à la page 13 que « the current procedure of providing humanitarian aid to foreign states is governed by the regulation of the government of the Russian Federation and is taken by the government of the Russian Federation based on the request for assistance by the officials of the sovereign state ».</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6307.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6320.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, dans ce règlement, je constate que c'est la base juridique d'accorder une aide financière ou humanitaire de la partie du gouvernement russe à un État étranger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6320.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6358.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, même par ce fait, ce que le gouvernement russe a comme fondement juridique ce règlement qui réglemente la modalité d'accorder de l'aide financière à un État étranger, si on compare avec la situation, on transpose la situation de la transnistrie, si les leaders de la transnistrie, ils ont fait comme ça, ils ont sollicité de l'aide financière à la partie russe, ils ont accordé de l'aide financière ayant à la base ce fondement juridique, ces réglementations, cela veut dire qu'on implicitement reconnaît la souveraineté de la transnistrie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6358.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6372.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, cela ne marche pas dans le même pied avec les déclarations de la souveraineté, de l'intégrité territoriale de la partie de la fédération russe envers la République de Moldova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6372.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6394.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ce qui concerne la dernière question, pas la dernière, mais la question en ce qui concerne l'aéroport militaire de Tiraspol, je ne veux pas conclure qu'avec les arguments qui dérivent des derniers documents qui ont été attachés par le gouvernement russe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6394.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6429.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans ces documents qui ont été attachés au dossier au mois de décembre 2011, le ministère des Affaires étrangères russe expressement reconnaît que, après l'explosion terroriste dans un trolleybus à Tiraspol qui a eu lieu, selon nos informations, au mois d'août 2006, donc un avion avec un équipement spécial a atterri sur l'aéroport de Tiraspol sans avoir un consentement de la partie moldave.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6429.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6436.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est la réponse qu'on voit dans la réponse de la partie russe de son ministère des Affaires étrangères.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6436.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6465.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En parlant de la question sur le fournissement de gaz par Gazprom à la MoldovaGaz, sur le fait de clarifier certaines choses avec le paiement de la Transnistrie pour le gaz, selon nos informations, moi je peux affirmer qu'au moins depuis 2008, la partie Transnistrie ne paye pas pour le gaz qui a été livré de la partie de Gazprom à l'adresse de la Moldavie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6465.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6469.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On va le dire, à peu près quatre ans, elle ne paye pas pour le gaz utilisé.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6469.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6486.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sur la dernière question que je vois ici, « Can the applicants in the present case quote teachers invoke a right under Article 2 of Protocol No. 1? » In my opinion, no,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6486.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6495.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>but the allegations I think should be properly addressed under Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6495.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6500.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6500.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6502.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I answered all the questions addressed by the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6506.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6509.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Grosu and Mr. Matyushkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6513.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6530.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Уважаемые господини председатели, уважаемые судьи Большой Палаты, я кратко также хотел бы отреагировать на ряд утверждений, которые прозвучали в сегодняшних устных выступлениях моих уважаемых коллег.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6530.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6554.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Что касается поставок гуманитарной помощи, то такие поставки были, это только что признал уважаемый представитель правительства Республики Молдова, эти поставки были Республику Молдова, были в частности в Приднестровский регион.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6554.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6561.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Они осуществлялись только в случаях стихийных бедствий в соответствии с международной практикой.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6561.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6571.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В частности, в 2003-2004 годах поставлялось зерно в Молдову, которое пострадало от засухи.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6571.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6582.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В 2006 году в Приднестровье гуманитарная помощь поставлялась для населения, пострадавшего стихийного бедствия.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6582.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6593.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>И в 2008 году в результате наводнения пострадавшего населения, в результате наводнения также поставлялись гуманитарные грузы.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6593.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6596.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Оказание гуманитарной помощи не выходит за рамки международной практики.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6596.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6615.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В частности, в Приднестровье гуманитарная помощь одновременно с Российской Федерацией поставлялась властями Соединенных Штатов Америки, Европейского Союза в том числе.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6615.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6633.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Я хотел бы еще раз обратить внимание сюда, что с моей точки зрения есть определенный глубокий водораздел между фактическими обстоятельствами настоящего дела и обстоятельствами дела Илашко.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6633.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6650.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>И если мы увидим те факты, на которые ссылаются уважаемые представители заявителей, мы, мне кажется, способны эти факты оценить и понять различия.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6650.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6656.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>В соответствии с принципами, принятыми в доказывании, каждая сторона обязана доказывать то, на что она ссылается.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6656.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6670.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Тем не менее, мы увидели, что ряд информаций, которая представляется заявителями, в частности, не подкреплена какими-либо доказательствами.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6670.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6694.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Касаемо использования аэропорта в Тирасполе, действительно власти Российской Федерации после теракта, который произошел в Тирасполе в 2006 году, запросили молдавские власти разрешение использовать аэропорт в Тирасполе, получили отказ.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6694.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6705.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Аэропорт использован не был и больше, собственно, властям Молдовы по этому поводу мы не обращались.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6705.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6745.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Также я хотел бы кратко сказать об утверждении, которое прозвучало в выступлении уважаемого представителя Республики Молдова и которое касалось этого печального инцидента, который произошел в январе 2012 года, когда был застрелен на посту гражданин Республики Молдова российским миротворцем.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6745.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6776.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Обстоятельства этого инцидента были расследованы представителями Объединенной контрольной комиссии с участием властей Республики Молдова и действия российского военнослужащего были признаны соответствующими необходимым процедурам и требованиям устава несения службы.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6776.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6822.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Да, это суверенитет Республики Молдова, да, в дальнейшем, по-видимому, будет расследование властями Республики Молдова, судебная процедура, возможно, это остается за рамками, но непосредственно этот инцидент не может быть вменен властям Российской Федерации, во-первых, он находится вне рамок настоящего дела, само собой разумеется, но и во-вторых, предварительное расследование состоялось представителями совместно всех сторон, сразу после того, как этот инцидент произошел.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6822.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6842.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>И последнее, о чем я хотел сегодня сказать, это о том, что несколько раз в своем выступлении уважаемый представитель молдавского правительства назвал оккупирующей силой миротворцев, которые находятся на территории Республики Молдова в Приднестровском регионе.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6842.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6856.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Я бы хотел сказать, что этот термин абсолютно противоречит целому ряду международных соглашений, которые были подписаны и признаются молдавской стороной.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>ru</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6856.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6856.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Спасибо большое!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6861.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6863.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr Matyushkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6863.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6868.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now then come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6868.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6876.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to thank the parties for their interventions and their answers to the court's questions put in writing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6876.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6880.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6880.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6882.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6882.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6886.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6886.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6892.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I declare closed the hearing in the case of Khatun and others against Moldova and Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
