<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>4488309_23062015</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>203.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>204.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>242.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>243.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>251.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>259.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case of Nasr and Ghali versus Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>259.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>275.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on 6th August 2009 under Article 34 of the Convention by two Egyptian nationals, Mr. Osama Mustafa Nasr and Mrs. Nabila Ghali.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>276.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>284.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the fourth section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>285.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>291.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on 22nd November 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>292.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>299.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The defending government are represented by their co-agents, Mrs. Accardo and Mr. Pellegrini,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>300.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>304.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Mrs. Incutti, advisor,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>304.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>309.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Giannuzzi, counsel, and by Mr. Di Taranto,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>309.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>313.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>expert of the Ministry of Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>313.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>317.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mr. Bauccio, counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>317.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>322.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and assisted by Mr. Scambia and Mr. Favero, counsels.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>322.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>326.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>326.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>330.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, I wish to welcome the visitors of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>330.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>340.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representatives of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>340.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>344.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Incutti and Mr. Giannuzzi for the government</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>344.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>349.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>will speak first, and then Mr. Bauccio for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>349.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>363.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, I have authorized the applicants representatives to plead in Italian.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>363.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>363.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then I call Mrs. Incutti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>371.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>372.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>372.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>394.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Madam President, distinguished members of the court, ladies and gentlemen, before getting into the matters set by the questions posed by the court, which concern the merits of the application, this government wishes to reiterate its inadmissibility claim for non-exhaustion of domestic remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>394.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>407.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This honorable court often states that the rule of exhaustion of domestic remedies is an expression of the principle of subsidiarity and an indispensable part of its functioning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>407.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>425.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, if it is so, then the assessment of the respect of the rule under Article 35 should be considered of utmost importance and should be examined very closely, attentively, and strictly applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>425.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>433.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in the present case, the non-exhaustion of domestic remedies by the applicants emerges per tabulas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>433.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>454.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It cannot be easily disregarded that the application was lodged before this court on August 4th, 2009, while the first instance trial was still pending and mostly way before the rendering of the first instance decision by the judge of the criminal court of Milan on November 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>454.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>466.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the application was lodged at the very beginning of this judicial history and was communicated to this government only in the year 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>466.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>494.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that the criminal proceedings has only recently terminated in the year 2014, and especially that this court has concretely waited for the domestic case to be completed, clearly shows that the respect of the rule of exhaustion was even more necessary to be fulfilled in this present case for the purpose of Article 35 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>494.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>536.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the government deeply feels that the time elapsed from the lodging of the application to this court in the year 2009 to the present time, 2015, that is almost six years in all, and mostly the acceleration that this proceedings has had after the delivery of the final domestic decisions in February and March of 2014, is an evident confirmation that the court needed to wait and see how the domestic criminal proceedings would have ended up.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>536.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>552.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In doing so, however, with all due respect to this court, the government believes that the rule under Article 35 of the Convention has been in the practice, overlooked, and not strictly applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>552.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>566.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whereas this precise case deserved an immediate declaration of inadmissibility in consideration of the greatly evident, premature nature of the application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>566.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>583.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, it is here recalled that, according to this court's case law, the requirement for the applicant to exhaust domestic remedies is normally determined with the reference of the date in which the application is lodged with the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>583.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>593.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also, that the appeal to the court of cassation is one of the remedies that should be, in principle, respected in order to comply with Article 35.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>593.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>609.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This government has abundantly contested in its previous written observations the applicant's exemption claim on the basis of a purported ineffectiveness of the domestic remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>609.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>630.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this regard, the government draws the attention on the fact that, according to this court's teaching, the applicant's claim of ineffectiveness of domestic remedy and right to be exempted from the rule of exhaustion should be assessed by the court with an ex ante evaluation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>630.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>640.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, at the time the application was lodged by the applicants, on the basis of the facts and circumstances present at that time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>640.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>658.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, at that time, the applicants based their exception claim for ineffectiveness of the domestic remedy exclusively on the issuing of the Constitutional Court decision No. 106 of 2009,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>658.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>670.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which established the legitimacy of the state secret opposed by the executive branch to some of the evidence acquired by the investigating office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>670.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>686.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, contrary to what the applicants assert, this decision did not bring, from the start or even after, to a total dismissal of the trial or to denial of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>686.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>702.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the contrary, the facts show that the final outcome of the trial as a whole has terminated with a judgment in favor of the applicants despite the state secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>702.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>709.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this regard, this party draws the attention of the court on the applicants' contradictory behavior.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>709.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>727.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is frankly striking that the applicants had from the start invoked the ineffectiveness of the proceedings for the purpose of lodging this application and then continued to use the alleged ineffective domestic remedies until their full termination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>727.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>742.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lastly, for the purpose of the government's non-exhaustion plea, it is also maintained that at the time, August 2009, the domestic remedies had not been exhausted even under the civil point of view.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>742.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>758.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be noted that with the first instance decision of November 2009, the applicants were awarded considerable sums as provisional compensation of damages, €1 million to Mr. Nazar</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>758.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>762.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and €500,000 to Mrs. Ghali,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>762.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>772.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>immediately enforceable and assisted by a prejudgment conservative seizure on one of the defendant's assets.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>772.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>797.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, it has never been demonstrated by the applicants to have concretely filed a civil suit first to obtain the payment of the provisional compensation amounts immediately payable, and now that the criminal proceedings is over to have final settlement of the damages to which they are entitled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>797.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>828.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the light of the above, the government believes to have accomplished the burden of proving that the applicants have not used all domestic remedies available under domestic legislation and strongly insists on its non-exhaustion plea, specifically requesting the court to carefully examine this issue autonomously on the basis of an ex ante criteria of assessment of such plea.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>828.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>863.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government believes that if the court were to examine the inadmissibility issue jointly to the merits of the application that is in connection of the procedural aspects of violations under Article 3 and 5 of the Convention, then it would be shifting the assessment criteria from an ex ante evaluation of the assessment plea to a post evaluation which involves the final outcome of the domestic remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>863.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>882.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Passing on now to the questions posed for the purpose of this hearing, it is noted that the first three questions concern the substantive aspects of the alleged violations of Article 3 and 5 of the Convention and may be dealt with at the same time in order to avoid unnecessary repetitions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>882.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>915.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to evaluate if, in the present case, the Italian State can be held responsible for the alleged violations to the Convention, it is necessary to carefully verify if the facts as definitely established by the national courts lead to a clear and undisputable involvement of the Italian authorities in the offenses endured by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>915.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>934.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the seriousness of the violations charged to this government, it is here recalled that the assessment of a State's responsibility for violation of core human rights as these are in issue must be effected with a standard of proof beyond the reasonable doubt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>934.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>961.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now regarding the assessment of the factual circumstances of this case, the government also recalls that the court discharges competence to establish the facts of a case and to question the findings and conclusions of national courts with regards to the acquisition, the admissibility, the utilization of evidence in a trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>961.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>998.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, as it will be further explained, on the fundamental premise that there has been no violation also of Article VI of the Convention, as a consequence of the assertion and opposition of the State's secret to some of the evidence of the domestic criminal proceedings, the court, accordingly to its jurisprudence, should rely on what definitely established by the national courts, including the Italian Constitutional Court on the State's secret issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>998.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1002.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What was then assessed by the domestic trial?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1002.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1020.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Preliminarily, it should be noted that the Office of the Public Prosecutor was able, on the basis of the circumstantial facts of the material time, to initiate an investigation only with respect to the illegal kidnapping of the applicant, Nazar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1020.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1036.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If appearance of other offenses had resulted at that time, it would have been a precise obligation by law for that office to extend the investigation to other possible committed crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1036.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1047.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it should be noted that the Milan Prosecutor Office has carried out this inquiry with its usual diligence and particular attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1047.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1053.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a matter of fact, the alleged acts of physical and psychological violence suffered by Mr. Nazar</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1053.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1066.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>during the phases of the execution of the illegal abduction and after experienced in Egypt have remained unsubstantiated during the Italian criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1066.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1075.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nor has the applicant demonstrated any injury or distress causally connected to the unlawful acts recounted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1075.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1083.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, for the crime of an aggravated abduction officially prosecuted, 26 U.S. defendants were convicted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1083.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1092.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the basis of a material evidence that had not been covered and could not be coverable, according to the law, with the state secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1092.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1095.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is factual evidentiary material.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1095.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1101.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While the Italian defendants were ultimately dismissed from trial, since, unlike the U.S. defendants,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1101.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1121.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>all the evidentiary material collected and brought against them was found to be inadmissible in the trial, as legitimately falling within the scope of the state secret as defined and established by law 2007, number 124.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1121.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1145.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That said, it should be considered as definitely established in the facts by the domestic judicial authorities that there is no judicially verified evidence of the involvement in the abduction crime of the Italian authorities, namely the Italian defendants or others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1145.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1187.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the Italian state cannot be held responsible beyond the reasonable doubt that is on the basis of strong, clear, verified and concordant elements for any of the alleged violations of the human rights here examined, that is, of the unlawful abduction, the rendition, unlawful detention and submission to acts of torture, inhuman or degrading treatment, occurred at any time or anywhere, neither in terms of direct participation and complicity, active conduct, nor in terms of acquiescence and connivance, omissive conduct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1187.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1210.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In answering the Court's questions, it is expressly asked to make reference to this Court's previous case law on similar matters, specifically to the El-Masri, al-Nashiri and Husayn cases, while this government strongly contests that this present Nazar and Ghali case be compared to these three other cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1210.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1227.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Aside from the fact that all four cases deal with the matter of extraordinary renditions, operation, occurred around the same period of time, there are profound differences between those cases and the one here in issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1227.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1255.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, with respect to the substantive aspect, in the El-Masri, al-Nashiri and Husayn cases, the Macedonian and Polish states have been found by the Court on the basis of specific external evidence acquired al-yumde by the Court to have been actively and directly involved in the wrongdoings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1255.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1273.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, as known to this Court, in these three cases, Macedonian and Polish state agents had been actively involved in the victims' capture and unlawful detention on their premises, as well as in the subsequent rendition to the CIA.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1273.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1289.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, Polish territory was found to host CIA black sites and to have assured in several occasions special transit procedures to CIA rendition aircrafts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1289.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1294.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, these three cases are also very different from the present one under the procedural aspect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1294.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1306.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As known, in the El-Masri case, the criminal complaint was very rapidly, in two months and a half, rejected by the public prosecutor's office as being unsubstantiated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1306.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1315.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the other two cases, on the contrary, the investigation on the unlawful facts was deemed by this Court as unreasonably too long.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1315.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1320.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Things are very different in this present Nazar case, in the Nazar and Ghali case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1320.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1329.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under the substantive aspect, it must be considered that, one, the applicant Nazar was captured exclusively by CIA agents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1329.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1346.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two, the applicant Nazar was never not even for one moment in the hands of Italian authorities, nor has he been unlawfully detained for some time by Italian authorities, and this is also admitted by the same applicant Nazar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1346.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1360.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Three, the applicant Nazar was immediately removed by the CIA from Italian territory the same day of the kidnapping, and flown first to Germany, and later that same day with a different aircraft to Egypt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1360.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1378.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Four, the airport from which the applicant departed is a Yusuf military airport, thus not accessible to Italian authorities, and has never revealed itself to be a regular transit site for the purpose of U.S. Extraordinary Rendition Program.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1378.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1383.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case is also completely different from the others under the procedural aspect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1383.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1400.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As said, the Italian state has promptly initiated an investigation on the applicant's disappearance, and performed and concluded criminal proceedings for the crime of illegal abduction, which includes the arbitrary detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1400.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1425.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, despite the assertion and opposition of the state secret, once again to some, not all of the evidence of the trial, the domestic criminal proceeding was indeed capable of leading to the assessment of the crime, to the identification and punishment of those responsible, 26 subjects, as well as to grant the victim elevated compensation of damages suffered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1425.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1433.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The domestic criminal proceedings was thus complete and effective within the meaning of this Court's definition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1433.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1440.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Italian state has not yet been able to make a decision on the execution of this Court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1440.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1472.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Conclusively, the government responds to the Court's questions regarding the state's responsibility by firmly affirming, no, there is no evidence that proves beyond the reasonable doubt that the Italian authorities have been actively and directly involved in the applicant's unlawful abduction under any account, and the Italian state cannot be held accountable of any of the purported violations of human rights deriving therefrom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1472.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1474.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now my colleague, Mr. Giannuzzi,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1474.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1478.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>will address the Court with the responses to the last questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1478.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1478.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1480.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1485.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mrs. Incutti and then I call Mr. Giannuzzi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1485.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1512.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regards to the question regarding the procedural aspects of Article III of the Convention, firstly, it must be remarked that the introduction of the law number 124 of 2007, which has replaced the law number 801 of 1977, has not substantially changed the previous rules regarding the state secret privilege.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1512.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1518.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The new law has not changed the definition of the state secret and its object.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1518.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1532.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The scope of the state secret was also maintained with the only difference that it now refers to the safeguard and protection of national security of the Republic instead of the democratic state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1532.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1559.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The responding governments observed that the Parliament, in regulating the matters of the state secret privilege, has complied with the well-established case law of Italian Constitutional Court, according to which the rules concerning the matter in question, as stated in its Judgment Number 106, 2009, invoked the supreme interest of the state's security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1559.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1581.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The continuity between the rules contained in the law of 1977 and those introduced by the law 124, 2007, can be appreciated also from the point of view of procedural regulation of the acquisition, assessment, and utilization of the evidence covered with the state secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1581.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1586.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The outcome of the state secret assertion opposition procedure is also the same.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1586.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1603.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the Prime Minister confirms the state secret and the evidence sealed is essential for the decision-making process, then the judiciary authority must dismiss the defendant from trial for the existence of a state secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1603.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1611.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be noted that the new law has increased the powers of the judiciary and framed those of the executive power.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1611.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1637.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, it has expressly introduced by Article 40, modifying Article 202 of the procedural code, that the judiciary can always proceed with investigation on the criminal offense on the basis of other evidentiary materials which are autonomous and independent from those covered with the state secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1637.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1647.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was a principle established by the case law of Constitutional Court and now explicitly stated in the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1647.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1658.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the new law provides expressly, and this is an absolute novelty, that the state secret can never be opposed to the Constitutional Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1658.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1683.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, in the light of this evident continuity between the two regulations of the state secret while the criminal proceeding initial spending, the introduction of law of 2007 has in any way affected the rules regarding the taking, assessing, and using of that evidentiary material covered or to be sealed with the state secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1683.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1692.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the new state secret regulation has really non-affected in any way the relevant investigation trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1692.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1711.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the change in legislation has not in any way impeded, hindered, or obstructed the criminal proceedings, and therefore it cannot result in a violation of the duty under Article 3 of the Convention to ensure an effective investigation into the applicant's allegation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1711.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1736.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As for the question regarding the consequences of the Constitutional Court judgment number 106 of 2009 and number 24 of 2014, the responding governor recalls entirely what already affirmed in its previous observation and letters to the Court regarding the development of the criminal domestic case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1736.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1746.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first decision of the Constitutional Court has set out the principle on the state secret issue that should have applied and respected in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1746.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1780.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This ruling established that two prime ministers, two presidents of the Council of Ministers, had lawfully covered with the state secret not the material abduction of the applicant in itself, but the relationships between the Italian Secret Service Agency and the foreign Secret Service Agency, as well as the Italian Secret Service Agency's internal organizational structure and its operational directives, interna corporis, even if connected in any way to the abduction of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1780.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1792.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this regard, it must be highlighted that the Constitutional Court has definitely excluded the opposition of the state secret had retroactively overwhelmed the previous investigation activity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1792.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1816.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It explained that the official opposition of the state secret at a certain time didn't imply an automatic demolition of all the previous investigation activity, but implied that from that moment onwards, the judicial authority had to behave differently with respect to information sealed with the state secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1816.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1837.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, it is underlined that the alleged massive circulation and publicity of the secret information affirmed by the applicants was in any case subsequent to the opposition of the state secret by the executive branch, and therefore no consideration of purported unjustified exercise of the state secret can be affirmed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1837.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1870.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Constitutional Court decision number 24 of 2014 criticized the interpretation given by the Court of Cassation and subsequently by the Court of Appeal Milan to its previous ruling number 106-2009, and very explicitly affirmed that it is not for the judicial authorities to trace margins of the state secret different from those set by the executive power. Therefore, despite the decision of the Constitutional Court on the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1870.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1887.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>issue of the state secret, the outcome of the criminal proceedings concerning the applicants' abduction in its entirety did not deprive the applicants of their right to access the court under Article 6, paragraph 1 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1887.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1902.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also strongly affirms that the Italian state has not violated its duty under Article 3 of the Convention to ensure and effect investigation of the crime of abduction and also on all other applicants' allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1902.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1923.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government's claim that this Court, applying its well-established jurisprudence on this point, should assess the effectiveness of internal criminal proceedings with reference to the entirety of the remedy and not to a specific procedural issue. It is here also, once again, strongly emphasized that this assertion and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1923.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1948.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>opposition of the state secret by the executive branch on some of the elements, which has been found legitimate by two decisions of the Constitutional Court, as well as the introduction of law number 124 of 2007, did not affect the outcome as a whole of the criminal proceedings and thus the applicants' right to a fair trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1948.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1968.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As this Court has affirmed in its well-established case law, where the investigation may involve issues of national security, evidence should be disclosed to the party in the proceedings without compromising national security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1968.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1976.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If disclosure is not possible, the difficulties that disclose it should be counterbalanced in such a way that the party can effectively defend its interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1976.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1982.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, this is our case. Most of the defendants, on the basis of the evidence</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1982.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1992.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>not covered with the state secret, were punished, and the right to get compensation of damages was granted to the victim. It is to be noted that Italy is actually</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1992.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2001.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the only State that has thoroughly investigated and prosecuted the case of unlawful abduction and arrived to a conviction of the offender.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2001.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2010.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the responding government reiterates the claim that Italy has fulfilled the procedural aspect of Article III of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2010.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2025.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Coming to the execution of the sentence imposed on the convicted SIA agents, the government highlights that the statement that the Italian State did not seek execution appears to be somehow equivocal and misleading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2025.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2044.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Insofar, it is implied the idea of an arbitrary decision of the Italian authorities aimed at ensuring that de facto impunity of agents who have been judged to be guilty of aggravated abduction. On the contrary, the Italian authority acted in full respect</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2044.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2048.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of domestic law provisions regulated the execution methods.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2048.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2065.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, it must be both pointed out that for all the convicted, order for the execution of the sentence within the domestic territory were issued by the General Prosecutor's Office in Milan. Moreover, European arrest warrants were</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2065.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2074.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>issued by the Italian judicial authorities and were circulated among the EU member States through the Schengen information system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2074.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2081.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These Italian execution orders and European arrest warrants are still in force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2081.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2095.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, whenever any of the convicted SIA agents should enter the territory of a member State of the European Union, that member State would be obliged to arrest that person and to surrender him or her to the Italian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2095.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2111.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as the search of convicted SIA agents outside the European Union is concerned, the MEPRA implies the recourse to the extradition procedure and deserves a different consideration. The extradition procedure is a really</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2111.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2116.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>significant and time-demanding form of judicial cooperation between States.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2116.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2133.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so it is perfectly understandable that States tend to regulate it carefully so to ensure the recourse to such a form of cooperation when it appears to prove really effective and justified by the circumstances of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2133.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2149.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, the Italian Criminal Procedure Code in Article 720 leaves the last decision to the Ministry of Justice on whether to submit or not a request for extradition. The relevant decision is therefore of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2149.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2153.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>political nature. On this ground, in the year 2000, long</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2153.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2159.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>before the SIA agent's conviction for Mr. Nassar's abduction was ever ruled, the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2159.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2174.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Italian Ministry of Justice released some guidelines providing that the request for extradition should not be submitted in case the penalty to be applied did not exceed four years of imprisonment. The rationale behind this rule is that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2174.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2201.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it would not be worthy to have recourse to the complex extradition procedure, which usually takes months for its completion, to obtain the surrender of a person who, taking into account the tension for extradition purposes suffered, could shortly be admitted to alternative measure to prison when a penalty still to be served in Italy would not exceed three years of imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2201.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2207.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It must be noted, then, that the above-mentioned guidelines are still enforced as of today. As far as the present case is</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2207.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2226.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>concerned, all the convicted SIA agents were granted a formal pardon according to law number 241-2006, which provided for a pardon of three years applying to all crimes committed before May 2, 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2226.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2231.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, all of them had their sentence reduced by three years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2231.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2243.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having all of them been sentenced to seven years of imprisonment, the final effective sentence once granted the pardon was of four years of imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2243.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2254.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The sentence did not meet the requirements set forth in the minister's decree adopted in 2000 for launching the extradition procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2254.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2262.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards Mr. Robert Seldenledi, who had been convicted to nine years of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2262.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2282.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>imprisonment, reduced to six years because of the formal pardon, on December 12, 2012, the Minister of Justice ordered the issuing of an international arrest warrant aimed at ensuring his arrest. Robert Selden, having been traced out by</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2282.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2296.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Panama's authorities, the Minister of Justice issued a request for provisional arrest on July 18, 2013. And once Mr. Leldi was arrested, the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2296.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2311.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Italian Minister of Justice signed those same authorities a letter of request for extradition on September 19, 2013. This request was not fulfilled since Leldi</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2311.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2317.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was released by Panama's authorities and let go back to the United States.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2317.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2332.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>United States officer, Colonel Joseph Romano, has a different position since he was granted the clemency, grazia in Italian law, by the President of the Italian Republic. The presidential clemency is a typical act left to the fully</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2332.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2336.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>discretionary and contestable decision of the head of state himself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2336.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2355.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Conclusively, the responding government strongly affirms that the Italian state has not violated its duty under Article 3 of the Convention to ensure and affect the investigation of the crime of abduction and also on all other applicants for probation of torture and secret detention. Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2358.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2360.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Giannuzzi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2360.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2363.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then I call Mr. Bauccio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2363.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2363.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2365.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2372.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Onorevoli giudici, buongiorno. Per rispetto anche dialettico nei confronti</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2372.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2389.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>dei rappresentanti del Governo italiano vorrei subito entrare nel vivo delle loro osservazioni e smentirle tutte punto per punto. Il Governo italiano afferma che il ricorso sarebbe inammissibile</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2389.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2396.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>perché presentato prima dell'esaurimento dei mezzi interni. Mi sembra un'affermazione</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2396.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2427.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>incompleta, peraltro contraddetta da quanto da ultimo affermato dagli stessi rappresentanti del Governo, ossia che le due sentenze della Corte Costituzionale hanno da subito imposto un ostacolo insormontabile al proseguimento del processo nei confronti degli imputati agenti dei servizi segreti italiani. Non possiamo che concordare con questa affermazione.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2427.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2445.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>È vero, le sentenze della Corte Costituzionale e prima ancora il segreto apposto dal Presidente del Consiglio italiano hanno in effetti costituito, eretto un muro invalicabile. È stato chiaro</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2445.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2453.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>subito tutto questo. Anzitutto al Tribunale, al giudice di primo grado, che con rassegnato</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2453.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2480.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>sconforto ha preso atto nella sentenza, con toni davvero inusuali nella letteratura giuridica e giurisprudenziale italiana, ha denunciato il sipario nero che era stato calato sul processo, sulla verità, sul giudizio. Siamo uomini civili di un'Europa civile, siamo cittadini di un</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2480.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2487.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Paese civile, non possiamo accontentarci di soluzioni intermedie. Non possiamo accettare</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2487.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2516.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>come ricorrenti che la verità sia mezza verità, che i colpevoli non siano tutti colpevoli e che ci sia qualcuno meno colpevole degli altri, non perché lo decide un giudice, un regolare processo, ma perché lo decide dall'alto qualcuno che tiene i fili del sipario nero, qualcuno che decide di far calare il buio sul processo. Allora il nostro ricorso non</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2516.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2531.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>è affatto inammissibile, perché il nostro ricorso si radica nel momento in cui è stato chiaro tutto questo. Nel momento in cui abbiamo preso atto che giuridicamente la Presidenza</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2531.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2552.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>del Consiglio e la Corte Costituzionale italiana avevano abbassato il sipario nero, abbiamo dovuto prendere atto che il processo nei confronti degli imputati italiani non era più possibile, non avrebbe più avuto un futuro. Abbiamo continuato nel giudizio, ma con questa consapevolezza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2552.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2572.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il Tribunale di Milano ha ratificato con la sua sentenza questa presa d'atto e penso che oggi, dopo aver udito il Governo italiano, possiamo concludere che siamo tutti concordi su questo. La prima sentenza e la seconda sentenza della Corte Costituzionale hanno</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2572.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2587.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>impedito la valutazione delle prove, ma prima ancora della sentenza della Corte Costituzionale la Presidenza del Consiglio, che reiteratamente ha apposto il segreto di Stato. Non siamo</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2587.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2595.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>un quarto grado di giudizio, è vero. Anche su questo concordiamo col Governo italiano</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2595.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2608.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>e non siamo qui per decidere se gli agenti del servizio segreto italiano sono colpevoli o sono innocenti. Non è questo il nostro compito e nel ricorso non leggerete mai affermazioni</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2608.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2623.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>da parte dei ricorrenti che volessero in qualche modo spingervi ad una valutazione di questo tipo. Noi siamo qui per il motivo opposto. Siamo qui perché non è stato possibile giudicare</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2623.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2631.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>quegli agenti. Ancorché imputati, nonostante fossero imputati, non è stato possibile pronunciare</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2631.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2635.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>nei loro confronti una sentenza definitiva di condanna.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2635.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2646.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allora il ragionamento che il Governo italiano svolge è un ragionamento circolare, non logico.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2646.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2661.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Non c'è la sentenza definitiva di condanna perché le prove sono state interdette allo sguardo dei giudici italiani. Non possiamo conclamare una prova universalmente certa</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2661.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2668.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>di colpevolezza perché quella prova è stata segretata. Allora il ragionamento che noi</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2668.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2708.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>dobbiamo fare, e mi sarei aspettato delle considerazioni da parte del Governo italiano, è proprio su questo punto capire se l'essenza del segreto di Stato, la sua funzione, la sua proiezione finalistica, sia stata rispettata e se il segreto di Stato è stato davvero interpretato in modo compatibile con i principi democratici e con i principi giuridici espressi della Convenzione europea, con la vostra giurisprudenza. E' su questo punto che noi siamo qui chiamati</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2708.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2708.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a ragionare.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2708.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2750.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Corte di Cassazione ha dovuto prendere da ultimo atto con la sentenza del 2004, con sconforto e anche con una leale e dignitosa polemica nei confronti della Corte Costituzionale, di doversi fermare per rispetto istituzionale, di non poter giudicare, di dover accogliere i ricorsi degli imputati solo per questo motivo, cioè solo perché qualcuno ha fermato la Suprema Corte di Cassazione. Che cos'è il segreto di Stato in un regime democratico,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2750.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2757.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in uno Stato di diritto? Che cos'è il segreto di Stato in un Paese che aderisce alla Convenzione</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2757.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2765.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>europea dei diritti dell'uomo? Non intendiamo intaccare questo istituto, ma vogliamo ribadire</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2765.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2782.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>che il segreto di Stato ha un senso se anzitutto viene utilizzato per mantenere segreto qualcosa che è segreto. L'essenza, il senso che autorizza un Paese civile, una comunità civile, a derogare</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2782.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2812.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>il dovere, di esibire le prove, di accertare la verità, di andare fino in fondo nell'accertamento delle responsabilità, questa deroga può essere ammessa solo se da un lato, anzitutto, ci si trova di fronte a qualcosa che è segreto e che, se svelato, potrebbe intaccare la sicurezza dello Stato, potrebbe mettere a rischio l'incolumità dei cittadini, l'integrità dello Stato.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2812.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2815.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allora sono questi i due capisaldi sui quali noi dobbiamo ragionare.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2815.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2823.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il primo. Erano segrete le prove? Che sono state segretate? Il Governo italiano ha espresso</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2823.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2834.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>una volontà aborigine di inibizione, di interdizione di queste prove? Si è comportato coerentemente</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2834.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2840.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>per il rispetto di questo principio, di questo elemento costitutivo del segreto di Stato?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2840.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2849.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La risposta è no. Anzitutto i comportamenti degli imputati e del Governo. 5 novembre 2006</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2849.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2864.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>il Governo comunica all'autorità giudiziaria che non c'è nessun segreto, che si può indagare, che il Governo è straneo al sequestro, che non opporrà nessuna resistenza. E gli imputati</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2864.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2872.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>non collaborano con le autorità giudiziarie. Confessano. Come ricorda la Corte di Cassazione,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2872.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2881.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>gli imputati producono prove della propria colpevolezza. Un imputato produce un atto</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2881.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2895.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>di indagine condotto dal proprio difensore, nel quale è depositata la prova della propria colpevolezza. Le autorità giudiziarie applicano delle misure cautelari, che vengono eseguite</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2895.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2901.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>e validate, confermate dai tribunali che hanno controllato quei provvedimenti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2901.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2920.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allora questo è un primo elemento, è definitivo, che ci consente di affermare che il Governo ha consentito la pubblicizzazione di questi elementi, ne ha consentito l'uso. Gli stessi</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2920.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2927.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>imputati hanno consentito i sequestri nella sede del Sismi, hanno ammesso le proprie responsabilità.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2927.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2951.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Onorevoli giudici, sulla base di queste prove la Corte d'Appello di Milano, con una prova di grande coraggio civile e di attaccamento alla legge, ha condannato gli imputati, prima che giungesse l'ennesimo segreto di Stato e la seconda sentenza della Corte Costituzionale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2951.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2957.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Li ha condannati perché ha accertato la loro responsabilità. Ma questa condanna non ha</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2957.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2959.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>avuto un futuro, come abbiamo denunciato.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2959.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2976.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allora il problema qui è capire se noi possiamo oggi ritenere il segreto di Stato compatibile con una situazione in concreto, in cui gli elementi di prova sono stati resi pubblici.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2976.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2982.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Questi elementi di prova non sono stati divulgati solo all'interno del processo. Li trovate</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2982.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2990.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>sul web, su internet, nelle tesi universitarie, sui libri, negli articoli di giornale. Noi</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2990.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2996.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>nel ricorso abbiamo documentato tutto e nei giudizi abbiamo documentato tutto. Non una</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2996.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3017.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>parola da parte della Corte Costituzionale su questo elemento che pure voi avete considerato nella vostra giurisprudenza fondamentale per capire se viene rispettato di volta in volta, in concreto, il principio di proporzione, il principio di adeguatezza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3017.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3026.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il segreto di Stato non può essere usato, interpretato, manovrato in termini astratti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3026.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3033.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ha bisogno di essere calato nella realtà, nel caso concreto. Ebbene quei verbali, quelle</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3033.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>intercettazioni, le attività difensive degli imputati sono pubbliche dalla prima ora. Pubbliche</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3056.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>nel processo, pubbliche perché non sono state impedite dal Governo e pubbliche nell'opinione pubblica mondiale. Allora io ripeto una domanda retoricamente, perché ormai è troppo tardi</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3056.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3062.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>per rispondere. Cosa ha fatto il Governo italiano per impedire anche successivamente questa</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3062.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3073.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>divulgazione? Quali azioni ha compiuto per sottrarre alla conoscenza pubblica? Nulla.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3073.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3088.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ancora oggi il Governo italiano si è mostrato e ha fatto sfoggio di indifferenza nei confronti di questo aspetto della vicenda. È come se la segretezza di quelle prove interessasse</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3088.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3098.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>solo nel processo e interessasse solo per impedire che quegli imputati venissero condannati sulla base di quelle prove.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3098.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3108.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il secondo elemento costitutivo nel segreto di Stato è il bilanciamento. Siamo di fronte</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3108.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3118.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>al comportamento fuori legge di alcuni individui. Non è indispensabile stabilire un coinvolgimento</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3118.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3124.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>del Governo italiano perché noi non abbiamo una sentenza definitiva dei tribunali italiani.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3124.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3139.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Non è indispensabile fare i nomi e i cognomi dei governanti che eventualmente sono stati complici con questa azione. Quello che possiamo affermare in termini di certezza è che i</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3139.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3154.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>governanti italiani, il Presidente del Consiglio, hanno impedito che si accertasse la verità rispetto a un comportamento illegale, fuori legge. Non c'è una legge italiana che autorizzi</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3154.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3159.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>i servizi segreti italiani a compiere un sequestro di persone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3159.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3194.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allora, se questo fatto è un fatto ontologicamente escluso dal comportamento di uno Stato, se questo reato è incompatibile con l'essenza democratica, con l'essenza costituzionale di uno Stato e della Convenzione, allora qual è la relazione tra il segreto di Stato e la copertura globale di quelle prove? Noi in questo caso, in questo processo, non abbiamo</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3194.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3213.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>avuto alcuna collaborazione da parte del Governo italiano e il divieto di utilizzare quelle prove è un divieto assoluto, un divieto che si è esteso a ogni parte, a ogni proposizione, a ogni elemento di prova che pure emergeva da quei documenti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3213.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3241.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I giudici non sono stati messi nelle condizioni, e lo hanno denunciato, di poter selezionare, da un lato salvaguardare eventualmente gli interessi dello Stato, ma dall'altro sanzionare, giudicare i comportamenti dei singoli, delle persone che a titolo personale o in nome dello Stato, che importanza ha, che rilevanza può avere, hanno commesso un sequestro di persona.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3241.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3255.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ecco, il segreto di Stato non è il segreto di un reato. Il segreto di Stato è uno strumento</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3255.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3263.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>per difendere lo Stato, non per difendere l'imputato. Il segreto di Stato è, e possiamo</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3263.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3278.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ammetterlo in un regime democratico, per difendere una Costituzione, non per offenderla e per mortificarla. Il segreto di Stato non può essere utilizzato per regalare l'impunità</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3278.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3286.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a degli imputati. E' questo che è successo nel processo Abou Omar. Il segreto di Stato</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3286.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3301.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ha regalato agli imputati un privilegio, il privilegio di non essere giudicati. Ecco,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3301.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3308.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>si è parlato del reato di tortura, onorevoli giudici. È singolare che il Governo italiano</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3308.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3317.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>anche su questo elemento cada in una contraddizione. Nei processi non hanno accertato la tortura.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3317.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3324.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ne siamo consapevoli, lo sappiamo anche noi. Siamo qui anche per questo. Non lo hanno accertato</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3324.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3341.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>perché i capi di imputazione dovevano essere privi di questo reato, perché l'ordinamento italiano non ha una norma che vieta e punisce la tortura. Quindi non possiamo che prendere</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3341.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3354.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>atto che anche le argomentazioni del Governo italiano confermano un vuoto intollerabile e ingiustificabile. Un Paese che aderisce alla Convenzione europea dei diritti dell'uomo</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3354.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3363.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ancora oggi non ha una legge che vieta la tortura. Il sequestro di persona subito dal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3363.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3379.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>cittadino egiziano Abu Omar è anche il sequestro di persona subito da un uomo che meritava e doveva avere dal Governo italiano una protezione rafforzata. Era un rifugiato, cioè una persona</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3379.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3388.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in una condizione di particolare pericolo. Afferma la difesa del Governo di aver fatto</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3388.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3399.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>tutto quanto era il suo dovere per assicurare i responsabili alla giustizia italiana. Ritiene</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3399.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3413.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>il Governo italiano che un mandato di cattura europeo nei confronti di cittadini statunitensi, stati negli Stati Uniti, sia sufficiente per ritenere assolto questo dovere. In realtà</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3413.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3421.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>il Governo italiano non ha mai chiesto un'estradizione degli imputati, anche quando erano indagati.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3421.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3430.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>E nessuna misura è stata possibile applicare perché il Governo non ha collaborato. E ancora</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3430.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3436.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>oggi sono tangibili ed evidenti i segni di questa mancata collaborazione.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3436.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3449.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Afferma il Governo che i ricorrenti avrebbero potuto e potrebbero agire in sede civile e ottenere in quella sede giustizia. Mi chiedo sulla base di quale considerazione giuridica</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3449.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3455.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>venga fatta questa affermazione. Il Segreto di Stato ha impedito per due volte alla Suprema</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3455.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3471.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Corte di Cassazione di utilizzare le prove della colpevolezza degli imputati, ma il Governo italiano pensa che invece in sede civile sarebbe possibile accertare una responsabilità. Non</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3471.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3485.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ci dice però in base a quale norma e non ci viene detto sulla base di quale procedura ciò sarebbe possibile. In verità, nessun processo, nessun accertamento in nessuna sede</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3485.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3499.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>penale e civile sarà mai possibile e non lo sarà mai più in Italia, perché le sentenze della Corte Costituzionale hanno impedito e impediranno per sempre questo accertamento.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3499.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3509.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I ricorrenti hanno subito un danno ingente, onorevoli giudici. Un uomo è stato sequestrato</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3509.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3516.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>nel centro di una città, una delle più grandi città d'Europa, Milano. Il fatto del suo</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3516.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3524.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>sequestro non è opinabile, è un fatto certo. La sua detenzione all'estero è un fatto</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3524.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3534.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>certo. L'uso della base di Aviano sul territorio italiano è un fatto certo. E se non ci fosse</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3534.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3547.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>stato il segreto di Stato, sarebbe un fatto certo anche il coinvolgimento di molti altri imputati italiani funzionari del Sismi. Così è stato per la Corte d'Appello di Milano.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3547.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3558.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Un sequestro non è un atto che prevede il consenso della vittima. I processi penali</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3558.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3567.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>hanno accertato il danno ingente subito da Buomar e dalla Consorte. Abbiamo delle testimonianze</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3567.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3575.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>acquisite, non siamo qui per giudicarle. Quegli accertamenti sono ormai definitivi. La sentenza</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3575.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3584.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>di condanna nei confronti degli agenti statunitensi è definitiva. Non c'è una quantificazione</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3584.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3599.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>definitiva perché dopo la sentenza della Corte Costituzionale, la Corte d'Appello italiana ha dovuto sospendere la provisionale concessa dal Tribunale in primo grado. Ma</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3599.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3618.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>il Tribunale, accertando l'entità in via provisionale, ha già dato una misura della gravità di quel danno. Ecco, onorevoli giudici, mai più Buomar e Nabila Ghali potranno ottenere</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3618.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3625.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>neanche una parte di quel risarcimento. È per questo motivo che io sono qui a chiedervi</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3625.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3632.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>di valutare anche questo aspetto. Valutare cioè come il vostro intervento oggi, nella</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3632.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3640.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ipotesi di un accoglimento del nostro ricorso, ponga lo sguardo anche su questo aspetto.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3640.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3656.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il danno fisico, il danno morale, il danno psicologico subito da Buomar e da Nabila Ghali è un dato di fatto per i Tribunali italiani e per le Corte italiane. Ed è un fatto pacifico.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3656.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3662.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ed è pacifico che questa quantificazione è ormai vanificata. La quantificazione del</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3662.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3671.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>vostro danno, vi chiedo, tenga conto di questa lesione. Vi chiedo a voi di tenere conto</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3671.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3678.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>della gravità della violazione e dei suoi riflessi anche sugli interessi dei ricorrenti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3678.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3688.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Onorevoli giudici, io ho terminato. Non credo che sia necessario aggiungere altro. Il segreto</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3688.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3694.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>di Stato retroattivo, così come lo chiede il Governo italiano, è un controsenso. Il</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3694.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3701.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>segreto di Stato di ciò che è pubblico è un controsenso. Il segreto di Stato applicato</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3701.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3719.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a chi ha commesso un reato incompatibile con la Costituzione, con l'articolo 3 della Convenzione, con l'articolo 5, con l'articolo 6, con l'articolo 13, tutto questo non è oggetto di un segreto di Stato. Uno Stato non compie sequestri. E uno Stato non può</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3719.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3719.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>concedere segreti e immunità a chi compie sequestri.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3728.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3730.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your interventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3730.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3736.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would now like to invite the churches of the chamber to ask any questions they may have to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3744.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3744.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maybe one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3745.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3746.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Raimondi, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3747.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3750.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Madam President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3750.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3766.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question on the civil claims of the applicants, question which has just been mentioned by Mr. Bauccio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3766.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3777.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as far as the proceedings vis-a-vis the American agents are concerned, there are two proceedings which went on in parallel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3777.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3790.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are decisions in the final judgments which are relevant, which concern also the civil claims of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3790.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3805.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in one of them, there are also sums which are granted on a provisional basis, waiting for the final determination in a separate civil proceedings in favor of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3805.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3814.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So my question is, which are the perspectives of recovery of these sums currently?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3814.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3814.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3814.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3815.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3816.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3817.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Other questions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3817.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3820.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no other questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3820.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3836.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then the court will rise for 15 minutes, following which the parties will return for the second round of short pleadings to respond to the submissions in the first round and to the judge question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3836.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3840.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we resume at 20 past 10.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3993.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3993.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4027.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4029.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4029.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4038.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is now resumed and I call the government's representative, Mrs. Incutti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4039.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4042.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Madam President, members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4042.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4046.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will be very brief.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4046.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4054.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And first, I will start with the question of Judge Raimondi on the execution proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4054.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4089.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government reiterates what has been said in its written observations and highlights that the applicants have been awarded considerable sums as immediately payable as compensation of damages, provisional sums, which are guaranteed by an asset which has been confiscated or actually seized in a prejudgment, with a prejudgment measure, a measure of conservative seizure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4089.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4102.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the applicants could have attacked this assets in order to have paid these considerable amounts of provisional damages.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4102.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4115.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to highlight that the decision against the US defendants is final from the year 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4115.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4133.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, the applicants could have initiated an executive proceedings for the enforcement of the provisional compensation of damages starting from the year 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4133.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4139.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I will reply very briefly to some of the considerations affected by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4139.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4150.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, the government maintains that there has been no black blanket lied over this proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4150.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4155.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, the proceedings has been initiated, completed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4155.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4157.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>People were convicted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4157.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4161.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Compensation of damages were awarded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4161.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4170.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so this is really not the case of complete concealment or hindering or obstruction of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4170.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4182.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also highlights that the particular position of the applicants is that of a civil party to the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4182.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4202.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is frankly quite striking that the applicants are so interested in the conviction of all when they are interested in specific positions of the defendants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4202.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4213.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After all, the state secret issue is a relevant issue, but it is a issue that attains to the admissibility of the evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4213.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4216.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is not only the state secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4216.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4219.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are many other types of secrets.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4219.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4227.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there are many other types of issues that may concern evidence that cannot be utilizable in a trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4227.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4271.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And sometimes, even if it's not a state secret, other secrets, which can be professional secrets, which can be a religious secret, may obviously seal certain information and not allow this information to be used in the trial, as long as we know, according to this Court's law, that the problems of inadmissibility of the overall outcome of the trial does not cause an insurmountable substantial disadvantage to the applicants to such an extent that the very essence of the right be impaired.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4271.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4282.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, this has not happened in this case, as 26 people were convicted and amounts were liquidated in favor of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4282.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4303.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As for the dialectic that has been present in the judicial history, it is normal that, obviously, within the domestic proceedings, there may be a dialectic between courts, national courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4303.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4305.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This has been the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4305.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4325.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it is totally normal that, in case of overruling of a lower court's decision, there may be considerations that are, obviously, formulated by the lower judge, in this case, the court of cassation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4325.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4347.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As for the extraditions, the government would like to highlight that extradition requests were not issued during the investigation because of the delicate nature of the investigation and also because, as we have heard, it is a very time-demanding procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4347.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4357.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was important to see how the domestic judicial proceeding would have ended up.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4357.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4383.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whereas, contrary to what has been affirmed by the applicants, once the conviction decisions had become final, the European arrest warrants, which are mandatory surrender procedures, had been issued by the judicial authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4383.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4428.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whereas, as we heard, the extradition procedure outside of the territories has obeyed to political discretional criteria of the Minister of Justice, according to the regulation that my colleague Giannuzzi has cited, which is a regulation that dates back to the year 2000, thus way before this case, and which, as said, actually makes it more transparent, makes this extradition procedure more transparent and certain and not so discretional.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4428.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4441.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because all those cases in which the penalty is higher than four years are obviously, the extradition procedure is worth initiating.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4441.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4472.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whereas, for all those cases in which the penalty is below the four years, the time consuming and the efforts to have an extradition procedure with the suffering of detention for extradition purposes may vanify, once the person is surrendered, may vanify the extradition, the surrender of the person, and obviously, the final outcome of this proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4472.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4487.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the regulation that the state has posed, the regulation of the year 2000, actually guarantees a fairness of this, of the way that political discretion on extradition is exercised.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4487.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4491.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One last brief comment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4491.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4500.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There should be no question on the constitutional court's decision and on the way how the state secret has been exercised in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4500.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4522.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There has been a political check on the state secret by a special parliamentary commission, which unanimously found the state secret as lawful, as well as two decisions of the constitutional court that affirm the lawfulness of the state secret applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4522.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4532.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court, the constitutional court, as you all know, is an independent court, the highest in the national system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4532.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4543.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is independent both from the executive, from the legislature, and from the judicial normal courts, the ordinary judicial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4543.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4555.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is the court that is entitled to the protection of the fundamental rights and to perform a fair balance among conflicting interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4555.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4557.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Giannuzzi will proceed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4559.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4572.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, I would like to briefly reply to some objections of the counterpart about the alleged retroactive nature of the opposition of the state secret.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4572.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4587.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think that these objections can be overcome by a careful examination of the one of the two sentences, the two judgments of constitutional court we have mentioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4587.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4625.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment number 106-2009 is clearly pointed out that in this case, there has not been a retroactive opposition of the state secret because the fact that the information document and acts which are related to the relationships between Italian secret service and foreign secret service were considered to be under the scope of the state secret even before, before since the year 1985.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4628.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4650.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a note of the president of the council of ministers of the time that sealed with state secrecy the information, the record, the documents related to the relationships between the Italian foreign, Italian secret service and foreign secret services agency.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4650.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4658.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a clear point explained, very, very clear explained by the constitutional court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4658.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4681.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as the alleged publicity of these, of the information covered with the state secret, it's also, it's also being explained by the constitutional court that the massive circulation of news was not prior to the opposition of the state secret, but was due to the proceedings itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4681.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4694.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so it cannot be in in equitable to the, to the government, which has also stated, that's also affirmed and confirmed the decision taken by president governments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4699.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4704.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the representatives of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4704.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4706.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Bauccio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4710.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4718.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Onorevoli giudici, poche parole per ribattere a quanto sostenuto dal Governo italiano.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4718.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4725.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Anzitutto rispondo all'equisito posto dall'Onorevole giudice Raimondi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4725.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4733.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'azione civile in Italia è pregiudicata per sempre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4733.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4738.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I ricorrenti non potranno mai più agire in Italia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4738.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4752.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dove agissero nei confronti degli agenti del Servizio segreto italiano imputati nel procedimento, quella azione troverebbe lo stesso esito del processo penale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4752.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4767.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quanto invece all'azione nei confronti degli imputati condannati agenti della CIA, questa azione andrebbe svolta negli Stati Uniti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4767.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4781.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ma gli Stati Uniti hanno sempre eccepito, anche durante il processo, che l'azione dei suoi agenti era un'azione coperta dal segreto di Stato.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4781.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4794.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La possibilità concreta per i ricorrenti di avere un esito favorevole, ma anche di poter introdurre l'azione civile negli Stati Uniti, è pari a zero.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4794.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4813.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Devo aggiungere che dal punto di vista del risarcimento, il Governo italiano non ha mai nemmeno provato la strada del risarcimento nei confronti delle parti civili, le quali non hanno mai ricevuto alcuna offerta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4813.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4824.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le parti civili e i ricorrenti odierni non hanno mai anticipatamente subordinato questa possibilità a termini e condizioni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4824.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4849.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il Governo italiano, alla stregua del Governo canadese, ma devo dire alla stregua di qualunque Governo responsabile, non ha mai pensato di comporre il conflitto, la lesione di un diritto fondamentale subito da due persone residenti in Italia con un'offerta di qualunque valore.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4849.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4859.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il Governo italiano si stupisce del fatto che i ricorrenti si accaniscano nei confronti di alcuni imputati.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4859.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4872.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Siamo noi stupiti, perché noi siamo qui perché non vogliamo rinunciare ad un'idea di giustizia piena.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4872.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4885.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vogliamo conoscere, volevamo conoscere i nomi e i cognomi di coloro che hanno provocato, consentito l'esito tragico di questo sequestro di persone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4885.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4893.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Una rendition che, forse, se avesse trovato un muro invalicabile nelle nostre autorità non sarebbe mai accaduta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4893.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4906.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ma non occorre nemmeno addentrarsi nello spiegare vicende e fatti che, purtroppo, per responsabilità del Governo italiano, non possono essere predicati in termini di certezza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4906.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4911.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La responsabilità del Governo italiano è tutta in queste conseguenze.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4911.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4928.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Aver neutralizzato con il suo comportamento la possibilità di rendere cogente, effettiva, la tutela di cui è l'articolo 3 della Convenzione, di cui è l'articolo 5 e 6 della Convenzione e 13 della Convenzione.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4928.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4931.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>E questa è la responsabilità del Governo italiano.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4931.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4960.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Noi siamo qui perché ci riteniamo privati di un diritto alla giustizia, di un diritto alla verità e anche un diritto alle conseguenze del proclamare giustizia, che si risolvono anche nel risarcimento del danno, che è per fizio, ma anche per necessità civile e democratica, il momento di composizione tra il cittadino e lo Stato.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4960.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4970.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Se lo Stato rinuncia a questa funzione, ma addirittura se lo Stato impedisce questa funzione, lo Stato cessa di essere a servizio dello Stato.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4970.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4985.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La casa sequestrata all'agente americano Seldon Lady. Abbiamo documentato, ed è un</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4985.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4999.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>fatto pacifico e notorio, che quella casa era per metà di proprietà della moglie di Seldon Lady e solo per metà di proprietà di Seldon Lady. L'intero ricavato della vendita</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4999.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5019.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>forzata di questa metà è andata a coprire il mutuo che aveva un privilegio e quindi un diritto di precedenza su tutti gli altri creditori, perché la casa non era mai stata pagata. L'argomento usato dal Governo ancora oggi è davvero incomprensibile.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5019.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5034.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Afferma il Governo che il segreto di Stato non avrebbe agito retroattivamente. Sono contento</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5034.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5045.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>che il Governo abbia accolto la mia provocazione. È vero, onorevoli giudici, non agisce retroattivamente.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5045.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5061.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ha agito retroattivamente negli effetti, perché ha impedito dopo ciò che non poteva più essere impedito. Ha reso per fizio, per finzione, segreto ciò che era pubblico. Ma è vero</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5061.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5069.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>che non può ontologicamente, nella sua essenza, agire retroattivamente. Sono d'accordo con</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5069.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5078.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>loro. Ma è proprio questo che fa esplodere la contraddizione e lo scandalo di una reiterazione</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5078.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5115.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>del segreto di Stato nei confronti di un materiale probatorio che non era stato segretato, che è stato acquisito e che è stato utilizzato dalle istituzioni italiane, dalla Procura di Milano che ha condotto un'indagine encomiabile, dai giudici che hanno avuto tra le mani quei documenti, dagli avvocati, dalle parti, dai giornalisti che hanno assistito a tutte le udienze del dibattimento senza che mai il Governo o gli imputati chiedessero che quelle udienze venissero celebrate a porte chiuse. Mai un comportamento che denotasse una reale</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5115.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5122.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>volontà di segretare quei documenti. Il segreto di Stato non può agire, aggiungo, non può,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5122.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5127.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>non deve agire retroattivamente. Ciò che è pubblico rimane pubblico.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5127.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5136.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quindi la pubblicità va valutata come un dato di fatto. La pubblicità del materiale</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5136.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5147.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>probatorio è un dato di fatto che non può essere cancellato da una semplice formula giuridica, da una semplice formula politica.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5147.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5162.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In ultimo, il Governo dice che la richiesta di estradizione è un atto politico, è un atto discrezionale. È il Governo che valuta, in determinati casi, l'opportunità di chiedere</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5162.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5170.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>l'estradizione. Ancora una volta, questa affermazione rende manifesta la posizione</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5170.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5179.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ingiustificabile ed in manifesto conflitto con la Convenzione. Una facoltà non è arbitrio</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5179.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5185.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in uno Stato di diritto. La possibilità o il margine, lo spazio di valutazione politica</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5185.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5200.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>non vuol dire arbitrio, non vuol dire un'opzione individuale, fuori da uno schema di legalità, di giustizia, di coerenza con i principi costituzionali e della Convenzione. Se non è in un Paese</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5200.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5223.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>democratico obbligatorio chiedere l'estradizione nei confronti di chi ha realizzato un terribile sequestro, che cosa dobbiamo attenderci per ritenere quell'articolo 3 violato, offeso, sfregiato? È su questo che noi vi abbiamo chiesto di intervenire e di dare la vostra</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5223.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5231.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>valutazione. Non può la facoltà trasformarsi in arbitrio, non può una valutazione discrezionale</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5231.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5245.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>essere un manto calcolato, essere un mantello studiato per proteggere singole persone, per motivi inconfessati, per motivi che non possiamo conoscere. Ma la non conoscenza di questi</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5245.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5255.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>motivi non può imporci che noi tutti si chiuda gli occhi sulla realtà, si chiuda gli occhi sulla verità, sulla esigenza di giustizia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5255.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5286.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ecco, e concludo, perché i ricorrenti, io sono qui oggi, noi siamo qui per rappresentare i ricorrenti, ma dopo questa vicenda così unica, così straordinaria, io mi sento di parlare a nome di quei giuristi, di quei giudici, di quei pubblici ministeri, di quei giudici della Suprema Corte che hanno esattamente denunciato queste violazioni e che non si sono voluti fermare finché un obbligo istituzionale ha reso insormontabile il loro cammino.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5286.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5286.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Grazie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Päivi Hirvelä</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5291.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5293.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Bauccio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5293.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5304.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we have now come to the end of the hearing, and I thank the parties for their interventions and their answers to the court's question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5304.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5317.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the court will now deliberate on the admissibility and the merits, and the judgment will be delivered later, and the parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5317.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5320.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5320.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5320.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
