<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>4489810_01072015</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>9.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>10.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>57.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>59.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>59.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>68.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case of Jeronovičs against Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>68.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>78.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on the 26th of July, 2010, under Article 34 of the Convention by Latvia National, Mr. Viktors Jeronovičs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>78.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>85.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to a section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>85.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>90.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on the 9th of October, 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>90.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>99.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 3rd of February, 2015, a chamber of the fourth section decided to relinquish jurisdiction in favor of the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>99.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>114.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 7th of April, 2015, the president of the Grand Chamber granted leave to the Helsinki Foundation for Human Rights of Poland to submit written comments as a third party by virtue of Rule 44, Paragraph 3 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>114.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>120.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The governments are represented by their agent, Ms. Kristīne Līce, assisted by Ms. Renāte Rūse</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>120.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>122.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. Alēns Mickevičs, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>122.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>126.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Ms. Inese Nikuļceva,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>126.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>127.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>127.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>131.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>131.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>137.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome a delegation of Serbian judges who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>137.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>145.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>145.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>147.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Līce for the government will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>147.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>151.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Ms. Nikuļceva for the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>151.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>163.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting into Serbian has been authorized for the benefit of the judges from Serbia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>163.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>172.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>172.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>174.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Ms. Līce.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>177.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>179.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President of the Court, distinguished judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>179.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>193.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ladies and gentlemen, the present case originates from the refusal of the Lasven authorities to reopen discontinued criminal investigation into the ill-treatment of the applicants that happened 17 years ago.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>193.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>204.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the following statements, I will therefore offer general comments on the notion of reopening, and I will then apply these general comments to the facts of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>204.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>213.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But first of all, I would like to briefly restate these facts and recall the course of the events in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>213.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>222.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In April of 1998, that is 17 years ago, the applicants allegedly was ill-treated by the police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>222.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>231.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the conclusions of the forensic medical experts, the applicants sustained minor bodily injuries, mainly scratches.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>231.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>236.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following this incident, a criminal investigation against the police officers was launched.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>236.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>249.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in 2001, that is three years later, the investigation was discontinued at the pretrial stage due to the lack of corpus delicti in the actions of the police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>249.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>256.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From now on, I shall refer to this investigation as the discontinued criminal investigation against the police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>256.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>266.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In November of 2001, the applicants submitted a first application to this court invoking a violation of Article III of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>266.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>270.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants alleged that he had been ill-treated by the police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>270.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>291.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And he also alleged violation of procedural aspect of Article III, stating that the excessive delays that occurred during the discontinued criminal investigation clearly revealed a lack of will of the investigative authorities to find out the truth, and if necessary, punish the responsible police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>291.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>297.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From now on, I shall refer to this application as the first application to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>297.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>302.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This first application was communicated to the government in 2007.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>302.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>321.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having examined the facts of the case on 30th of April 2008, the government submitted the unilateral declaration where it's acknowledged inter alia the violation of Article III and Article 13 of the Convention in respect of the discontinued criminal investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>321.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>328.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also proposed to the applicant compensation in the amount of 4,500 euros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>328.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>340.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 10th February 2009, the court accepted the government's unilateral declaration and decided to strike out the applicant's complaints under Article III and Article 13.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>340.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>354.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following this decision of the court, that is to strike out the applicant's complaints, the applicants requested the latter authorities to reopen this continued criminal investigation because of newly discovered circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>354.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>362.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant argued that the unilateral declaration submitted by the government constitutes such newly discovered circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>362.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>369.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the same grounds, the applicant likewise sought reopening of the criminal proceedings that led to his conviction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>369.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>372.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both these requests were refused.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>372.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>396.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In April of 2010, the applicant submitted a second application to this court alleging that by refusing to reopen both the discontinued criminal investigation and the criminal proceedings that resulted in the applicant's conviction, Latvia has failed to fulfill its obligations under Article III, Article VI, and Article 13 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>396.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>414.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 9th of October 2012, the court rejected as manifestly ill-founded the applicant's complaints about alleged violation of Article VI with respect to the refusal to reopen the criminal proceedings resulting in applicant's conviction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>414.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>428.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for this reason, the present case concerns only the discontinued criminal investigation into the applicant's ill-treatment and only alleged violation of procedural aspect of Article III and 13 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>428.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>434.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In light of these facts, the applicant's present complaint can be summarized in the following terms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>434.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>453.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant alleges that the government's unilateral declaration accepted by the court should be regarded as newly disclosed circumstances within the meaning of the relevant domestic legislation and that refusal to reopen criminal investigation constitutes violation of procedural aspect of Article 13.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>453.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>470.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the applicant's complaints that despite the acknowledgment by the government of the breach of his rights under Article III of the Convention, the state authorities, contrary to Article 13, have failed to properly investigate his ill-treatments, depriving the applicant of the remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>470.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>478.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the applicant's claims that the government was obliged to reopen the discontinued criminal investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>478.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>481.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government disagrees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>481.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>489.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now that I have established the facts of the case and the scope of the applicant's complaints, I will proceed with outlining the government's position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>489.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>499.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the author find it necessary to recall that under the Convention, there is no right to reopening of the proceedings where the final decision exists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>499.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>502.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I refer you to the decision in the case of Eder versus Germany.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>502.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>506.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's 13th of October, 2005.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>506.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>528.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, in the Convention system, reopening of proceedings is addressed in the context of the execution of court's judgments, where the state parties are free to choose the means to ensure full and effective execution, to remove the negative consequences of the violation, and to prevent similar violations from reoccurring.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>528.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>537.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wish to particularly emphasize that even in the context of execution, the reopening is regarded as an exceptional measure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>537.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>543.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer you to the recommendation by the Committee of Ministers, number R, 2002.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>543.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>569.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in this regard, recall that for the purposes of execution of court's judgments, reopening has to be decided on a case-by-case basis, taking into account the gravity of the violation and possible negative consequences of such reopening, considering that any reopening of a case where a final decision exists is, in fact, an exception to the principle of legal certainty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>569.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>583.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, a state cannot be obliged to reopen the domestic proceedings in every case where the court has found violation of the Convention in respect of state concerns.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>583.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>593.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Stating otherwise would negate negotiation of exceptional measure and would disproportionately interfere with the rights of others under Article VI of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>593.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>606.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before proceeding further, however, I wish to underline that the Latvian legislation clearly permits reopening of criminal proceedings following both the court's judgments and decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>606.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>629.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pursuant to the relevance provision of the criminal procedure law, one of the grounds for reopening of criminal proceedings in connection with newly disclosed circumstances are, and I quote from the law, findings of an international judicial authority that the domestic ruling which has entered into force does not comply with international law abiding for Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>629.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>648.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is nothing in the criminal procedure law that would limit which facts or circumstances could be declared a sufficient basis for reopening, provided these facts or circumstances are of legal nature and significance as required by the criminal procedure law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>648.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>675.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, I wish to draw the court's attention to the applicant's written observations of 8th May of this year, where he essentially agrees with the government's stats, and I quote, the grounds for reopening of criminal proceedings in connection with newly disclosed circumstances are rather broad, and that the relevant provisions of the criminal procedure law should be interpreted in a way that it provides for reopening of criminal proceedings following the government's unilateral declaration, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>675.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>689.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me repeat, there is nothing in the Latvian domestic legislation that would prevent reopening of proceeding following the court's decision where the court accepts unilateral declarations submitted by the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>689.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>692.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The domestic practice supports this conclusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>692.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>706.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just last year, following the court's judgment finding Article VI violation in the case of Cezniks versus Latvia, the competent authorities reopened their respective criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>706.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>714.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the framework of these reopened proceedings, the facts concerning alleged ill-treatments of the applicants are also examined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>714.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>725.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wish to emphasize that ill-treatments of the applicants in the Cezniks case was the subject of unilateral declaration the government submitted under Article III of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>725.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>735.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, to suggest that the government submits unilateral declarations merely to avoid responsibility is inappropriate, to say the least.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>735.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>739.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But now I wish to emphasize the following arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>739.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>770.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The criminal proceedings can be reopened if the finding of the violation, be it in a court's judgment or in a decision, is of such a nature that it contains new substantial information, that is new facts or evidence that could and should be examined, and therefore the most appropriate form of redress would be reopening of proceedings and their conduct in accordance with the requirements of the convention should the applicant so request.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>770.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>780.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With these considerations in mind, let us look briefly at the cases where the reopening of proceedings following establishment of a violation has been deemed necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>780.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>787.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And let us compare these sample cases with the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>787.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>807.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The courts, although it clearly does not have jurisdiction to order reopening of proceedings, under certain circumstances has indicated that reexamination of the case or reopening of proceedings would constitute the most efficient, if not the only means of achieving restitutio integrum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>807.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>822.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in majority of the cases where the court has acknowledged that retrial or reopening of the case would be an appropriate way of redressing the violation, concern the proceedings that entail breaches of requirements of Article 6 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>822.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>830.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in any case, they concern proceedings that were decisive for the status of the applicant concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>830.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>837.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, such proceedings would be those that resulted in the applicant's conviction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>837.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>846.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as I emphasized a moment ago, the complaints related to these proceedings have been declared manifestly ill-founded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>846.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>853.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the present case concerns only the discontinued criminal investigation into the applicant's ill-treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>853.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>875.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also wish to emphasize that in the present case, unlike for example, the case of Cesnik's that I mentioned a moment ago, in the present case, there's no question about the impact the applicant's ill-treatment might have had on the fairness of the proceedings determining the charges brought against the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>875.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>883.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, the present case bears resemblance to those Article 3 cases, such as Sapoškovs v. Latvia,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>883.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>888.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Timofejevi v. Latvia, Vovruško v. Latvia,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>888.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>901.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>where the court has found that investigation into the applicant's ill-treatment by the police was ineffective, including due to significant delays and thus a violation of procedural aspect of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>901.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>914.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In none of these Article 3 cases, the question of reopening of the respective proceedings has ever been raised during the proceedings before the court or in the context of the execution of court's judgments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>914.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>931.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I wish to underline that the present case is also clearly different from the cases that reveal continuing violation, most notably a disappearance of a person, as for example, in the cases against Turkey, such as Toktul v. Turkey, CA v. Turkey,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>931.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>933.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Taksin Açar v. Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>933.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>942.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In such cases, reopening, even after considerable time, could indeed ensure restitutio in integrum to the applicant's concerns.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>942.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>956.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, however, the applicant has failed to submit any arguments showing that he continues to suffer very serious negative consequences as a result of this continued criminal investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>956.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>973.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It cannot be denied that this continued criminal investigation could have created some disappointment to the applicants, but to claim that such disappointment is anywhere near the grief and anguish suffered by the families of the disappeared persons is to manifestly misrepresent the issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>973.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>976.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the above considerations clearly show</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>976.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>995.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that irrespective of the form in which the violation of the convention has been established, unilateral declaration or judgments of the court, the reopening of proceedings is an exceptional measure that in no way can be regarded as a right a person can seek protection of.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>995.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1011.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The mere fact of the existence of the courts finding a violation of the convention, or in this case, a decision accepting unilateral declaration cannot per se be considered as newly disclosed circumstances necessarily leading to the reopening.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1011.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1024.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me reiterate once again that the reopening of proceedings is an exceptional measure to be used when because of the facts of the particular case, no other form of redress is sufficient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1024.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1039.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, any claims to the effect that under procedural aspect of Article 3 of the convention, there is a general obligation to reopen proceedings following finding of a violation are manifestly inadmissible, ratione materia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1039.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1055.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Considering the facts of the present case I outlined just a moment ago, I once again wish to note that there is nothing in the present case that would qualify as exceptional circumstances warranting reopening of the discontinued criminal investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1055.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1070.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also wish to refer to the applicant's observations where he expressly seeks reopening of discontinued criminal proceedings, and I quote, in order to recognize the responsibility of the police officers and to punish them, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1070.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1087.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This clearly illustrates that the applicant aims not at elimination of continuing negative circumstances if such existed at all, but at punishing third parties, which in itself, of course, is incompatible with the provisions of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1087.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1102.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To summarize, there is nothing in the convention or the court's case law that creates an obligation for the domestic authorities to reopen proceedings whenever there's a violation of the convention established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1102.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1112.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Reopening is and remains an exceptional measure, and in the present case, there are no exceptional circumstances that would justify this measure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1112.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1129.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now turn to the government's unilateral declaration of 30th April, 2008, in order to establish whether there is something to suggest that the government undertook obligations that go beyond those stemming from these general considerations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1129.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1140.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is to say, the question is whether the government, in the context of the first proceedings before the court, undertook to reopen this continued criminal investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1140.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1154.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, I must emphasize that the purpose of the unilateral declaration submitted in 2008 was to acknowledge a violation, to offer compensation, and as a result, to terminate the proceedings before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1154.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1164.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason for the unilateral declaration was the fact that there were indeed significant shortcomings that occurred during the investigation of the applicant's ill treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1164.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1177.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Notably, the investigation was not effective, since there were unsubstantiated periods of inactivity, and the medical evidence about the actual origin of the applicant's injuries was contradictory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1177.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1195.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It turned out that the applicant had underwent the medical examination two days after his apprehension, when it apparently was no longer possible to determine the exact time and origin of the minor, I recall, minor bodily injuries sustained by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1195.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1206.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, already at the time of investigation, it was impossible to determine whether they had been sustained before or during the apprehension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1206.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1215.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It must be stressed that the nature of these shortcomings are such that they cannot be remedied through repeated investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1215.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1225.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is to say, so many years after the incident, it is no longer practically possible to establish how the applicant sustained the injuries and the persons responsible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1225.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1233.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, recognition of the violation and offer of the compensation in a unilateral declaration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1233.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1248.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the government has never acknowledged that any of the actions by the police officers following the applicant's apprehension in 1998 had been incompatible with the provisions of the criminal procedure law at the material time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1248.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1265.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, contrary to the applicant's allegations, neither the domestic authorities during the investigation nor the government in the unilateral declaration had ever acknowledged the guilt of the police officers because it was not established during the investigations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1265.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1283.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, having regards to the context, purpose, and contents of the government's unilateral declaration, the said declaration in no way can be interpreted as government's commitment to reopen the discontinued criminal investigation after the court had accepted this declaration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1283.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1318.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to be very clear, the reason the domestic authorities in the present case refused the reopening was not because the violation of the convention was established in the unilateral declaration, but because the unilateral declaration did not and, due to the nature of the shortcomings just described, could not contain any new facts or evidence that were unknown at the moment of termination of the investigation, but that could be useful in the investigation de novo to remedy these shortcomings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1318.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1333.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this stage, I wish to recall that, despite the fact that the criminal investigation was discontinued, the applicant still had the right to seek compensation for the alleged ill-treatment by the police officers in the course of civil proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1333.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1340.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wish to further emphasize that the court has, on several occasions, acceded to the findings of the Latvian Supreme Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1340.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1350.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's, and I quote, a decision to discontinue criminal proceedings due to the lack of corpus delicti exercises no prejudicial effect in civil proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1350.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1352.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>End of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1352.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1362.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer you to the court's judgment in the case of Y versus Latvia of 21st October, 2014, as a source of relevant case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1362.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1382.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, a civil court could adjudicate the applicant's claim for compensation of damages in the absence of a judgment in the criminal case against the police officers, as the threshold for awarding damages in civil proceedings, of course, is lower from the one required for the establishment of criminal responsibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1382.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1400.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, this remedy has never been used by the applicants, despite even the fact that the court, this court, in the decision accepting the government's unilateral declaration striking the applicant's complaints, itself has expressly recalled this possibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1400.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1406.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before concluding, I will make few remarks concerning the applicant's claim for just satisfaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1406.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1417.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant, in his claim of just satisfaction, requests, and I quote, compensation for non-pecuniary damage in the total amount of 50,000 euros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1417.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1424.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I note that the applicant has failed to submit any additional requests for compensation of costs and expenses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1424.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1441.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I maintain the government's observations of 24th of April, 2013, and I wish to emphasize that the applicant has failed to provide a single argument that would substantiate any causal link between non-pecuniary damage he might have suffered and the possible violation at question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1441.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1451.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the government invites the court to reject the applicant's claim for compensation of non-pecuniary damage as manifestly ill-founded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1451.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1460.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have come to the conclusion of my statement, and will now summarize the government's position and will restate the most important points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1460.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1481.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, under the convention, there is no general obligation to reopen proceedings whenever there has been a violation of the convention, because reopening is and remains an exceptional measure that in no way can be regarded as a right a person can seek to enforce.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1481.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1500.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, in the present case, the government's unilateral declaration cannot per se be considered as newly disclosed circumstances, as it contains no new facts or any other substantial information that would serve as a basis for the reopening of discontinued criminal investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1500.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1517.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is to say, the reason for the refusal to reopen the discontinued criminal investigation was not the form in which the violation of the convention was established, that is, unilateral declaration, as opposed to court's judgment, but the contents of the documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1517.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1526.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the fact that this particular finding of a violation did not reveal anything that could be material in the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1526.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1537.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the applicant does not continue to suffer very serious or other negative consequences as a result of discontinued criminal investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1537.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1549.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, the reopening of criminal investigation about minor bodily injuries sustained by the applicants 17 years ago could not reasonably ensure restitutio in integrum to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1549.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1559.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This purely formal reopening would be impractical and would contravene the core aims of convention to secure rights that are effective and practical.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1559.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1563.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, currently, the reopening is time-barred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1563.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1574.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another effective and accessible remedy, that is, request for compensation for the alleged ill-treatment in the course of civil proceedings, has never been used by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1574.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1594.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the light of the above mentions and taking into account the arguments contained in its written submissions, the government invites the Grand Chamber to conclude that applicants' complaints are inadmissible or, alternatively, that in the present case, there has been no violation of procedural aspects of Article 3 and Article 3.13 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1594.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1594.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1599.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1601.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1601.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1604.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call now Miss Nikuļceva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1611.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1618.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable members of the Grand Chamber of the Court, on my opinion, there</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1618.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1623.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>are two very important following questions in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1623.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1637.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the member states, whether the member states of the Convention, in the cases if the Court has already found a breach of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1637.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1662.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If they have only obligation of payment of some sum of money, or also a legal obligation to provide individual redress, individual justice for the applicant for the consequences of the breach of his rights so far as possible in the practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1662.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1689.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And secondly, if the states have this obligation, does it extend only to the cases if the Court has adopted a judgment, or also to the cases when the states itself recognized breach of the Convention and submitted unilateral declarations?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1689.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1698.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally I would like to say some words about facts, in addition as was mentioned by the government agent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1698.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1706.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The present case really is closely linked with the previous case, Yerenovich v. Latvia,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1706.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1712.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with application number 547-02.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1712.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1736.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In that case, the applicant claimed inter alia, among many other violations, that in April of 1998, following his arrest, he had been beaten by the police officers, and that the investigation into his compliance had been ineffective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1736.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1753.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to mention that in that case, firstly the government submitted a proposal for friendly settlement, but the applicant decided not to accept it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1753.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1765.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And one of the reasons was that the investigation of the alleged violations had not been carried out by the Latvian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1765.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1787.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then the Latvian government submitted the unilateral declaration, as was already mentioned, and the Court adopted its decision of 10 February 2009, and struck out the application of its list of cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1787.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1803.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following the decision of the Court and unilateral declaration, the applicant submitted to the prosecutor's office an application and asked to reopen both criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1803.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1818.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The criminal proceedings in which he had been convicted, and the criminal proceedings against the responsible police officers about his physical ill treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1818.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1835.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the prosecutor's office refused to reopen criminal proceedings, and what I would like to underline is that the prosecutor's office refusal was on the formal grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1835.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1839.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They performed no investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1839.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1858.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They explained that the unilateral declaration of the government cannot be considered as findings of an international judicial body, as mentioned by the criminal law of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1858.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1862.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then the applicant applied to the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1862.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1868.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I would like to say some words about excursion of domestic remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1868.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1875.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant, in this case, in the present case, had only one possible domestic remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1875.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1887.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is to ask to reopen the relevant criminal proceedings in connection with so-called newly disclosed circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1887.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1901.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And those newly disclosed circumstances in the present case are the unilateral declaration and the decision of the Court of 10 February 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1901.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1917.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No other mechanisms exist in the Latvian law in this case for providing an investigation into the applicant's complaints about ill treatment of him by the police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1917.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1926.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there are no disputes that the applicant has exhausted this domestic remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1926.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1938.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I cannot agree with the opinion of the government that the applicant had the right to lodge a civil claim in order to seek compensation for damages caused by the state police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1938.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1951.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the criminal proceedings are decisive for determination of responsibility of the police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1951.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1959.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There cannot be investigation about physical violence against the applicant in civil proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1959.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1983.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And secondly, what is also very important, on 10 February 2009, it's when the court adopted the decision, the statutory limitation period for lodging a civil claim has already elapsed because the statutory limitation period is 10 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1983.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1986.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's according to the civil law of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1986.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1998.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it's counted from April 1998 when the applicant had been beaten by the police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1998.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2005.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I would like to speak about Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2005.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2029.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think that there are no disputes that Article 3 requires that there should be an effective, independent, impartial, prompt, and subject to public scrutiny, official investigation where an individual makes a credible assertion that he has suffered ill treatment at the hands of agents of the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2029.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2040.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in this case, the Latvian authorities never performed such official and effective investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2040.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2068.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the question is, was there the fact that the government in their unilateral declaration has admitted the breach of Article 3, means that Latvia, Latvian authorities, are set free from obligation to investigate the applicant's complaints about physical ill treatment on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2068.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2082.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And here I would like to refer to Article 1 of the Convention, which provides an obligation of the states to secure to everyone the rights and freedoms defined in the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2082.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2104.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And from this article, and also from the very essence of the Convention, on my opinion it follows that the investigation of the applicant's complaints on the merits may not be replaced only by money and only by recognition of the breach of the applicant's rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2104.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2143.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, from Article 3, Article 3 of the Convention still enshrines an obligation of Latvian authorities to provide effective investigation, and the opposite conclusion would make the Convention rights illusory and ineffective, and in the present case, as we speak about Article 3, the general legal prohibition of torture and inhuman and degrading treatment would become ineffective in practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2143.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2149.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I mentioned the obligation to provide an investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2149.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2155.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not the same as reopening of the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2155.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2167.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I can agree that in general it's up to the government to choose a remedy, but nevertheless the government should provide at least one remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2167.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2177.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A remedy should be there, and this remedy should be effective in law and in practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2177.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2188.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as I already mentioned, in the present case there are no other mechanisms except of reopening of criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2188.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2199.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To some extent, I can agree about exceptional nature of reopening of the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2199.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2211.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reopening of criminal proceedings is an exceptional measure from the domestic viewpoint, in domestic legal system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2211.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2222.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But a judgment of this court and also unilateral declarations are in any case exceptional situations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2222.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2242.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I cannot agree that criminal proceedings, if this is the only possibility to investigate physical violence against the applicant, should be reopened not in all cases, but also in some or exceptional cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2242.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2254.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, if this is the only way, the criminal proceedings should necessarily, mandatory, be reopened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2254.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2276.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No, unfortunately I cannot agree also with the opinion of the government that only new facts or evidences that could be used in the investigation may be considered as being grounds for reopening of the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2276.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2290.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Obviously not only new facts or evidences, but also wrong interpretation of the law are grounds for reopening of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2290.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2316.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it's also to the Latvian law, the criminal procedure law of the Latvia establishes that grounds for reopening of the criminal proceedings are also decisions of the Constitutional Court of Latvia, judgments of this court, and these courts do not find any new facts or evidences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2316.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2359.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, I also would like to say some words about the government opinion expressed in writing in their memorial, that reopening of the criminal proceedings against the police officers, in the present case is regulated not by section 655 of the criminal procedure law, that's a norm that actually was applied by the prosecutor's office, but by another norm, by section 393 of the criminal procedure law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2359.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2385.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to draw attention that this section includes very broad formulation, namely the criminal proceedings may be reopened if it has been determined that lawful grounds for decision to terminate proceedings did not exist, or if new circumstances have been disclosed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2385.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2431.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the unilateral declaration in the present case admits that the physical treatment of the applicant by the police officers and the effectiveness of the investigation of the applicant's complaints did not meet the standards enshrined in Article 3, thus this unilateral declaration suggests that lawful grounds for adoption of the decision to terminate the criminal proceedings had not existed in the present case, so it corresponds with section 393 of the criminal procedure law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2431.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2445.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So although the Article 3 in the present case requires an official investigation of the applicant's complaints, in practice it never took place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2445.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2491.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we know that firstly the police office on 19 March 2001 had terminated the criminal proceedings against the responsible police officers due to the lack of corpus delicti, and following the unilateral declaration and the decision of the court of 10 February 2009, the Latvian Prosecutor's Office refused to reopen investigation, stating that the unilateral declaration could not constitute a ground for reopening of the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2491.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2505.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And no other, any other mechanism to remedy the breach of the applicant's rights was offered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2505.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2522.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also would like to mention briefly that the Prosecutor's Office refused also to reopen the criminal proceedings in which the applicant himself had been convicted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2522.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2529.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the applicant's view, these criminal proceedings were based on evidences that had been acquired using violence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2529.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2537.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, in the applicant's view, these criminal proceedings also should be reopened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2537.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2557.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to sum up, the refusal of the Prosecutor's Office to reopen the relevant criminal proceedings in the present case constitutes a violation of the state's procedural obligation enshrined in Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2557.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2565.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I would like to draw attention also to one another case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2565.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2569.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's case of Alexej Svobodrushko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2569.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2580.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant in the present case, Viktor Sieranovich, was arrested and tried together with another individual, Alexej Svobodrushko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2580.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2591.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the terminated criminal proceedings concerned physical violence against both these individuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2591.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2601.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's the same decision to terminate the criminal proceedings against the responsible police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2601.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2628.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alexej Svobodrushko applied to the Strasbourg Court as well, but in that case, the Court adopted not decision, but judgment of 11th December 2012 and found that the investigation of the ill-treatment of Alexej Svobodrushko had not been effective and independent, and there had accordingly been a violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2628.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2644.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, firstly, there are not any doubts that the investigation in this case against Viktor Sieranovich was not effective, because it's the same investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2644.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2676.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And secondly, I would like to draw attention that Alexej Svobodrushko is entitled, according to the Latvian law, the Latvian criminal procedure law, to renewal of criminal proceedings against the responsible police officers and criminal proceedings in which he had been convicted in connection with the Court's judgment, what is so-called newly disclosed circumstance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2676.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2691.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant in this case, Viktor Sieranovich, is in similar situation, but he is not entitled to reopening of the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2691.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2729.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to say that Article 46 of the Convention, from this article, it follows that a judgment in which the Court finds a breach imposes on the respondent state a legal obligation not just to pay the sum awarded by way of just satisfaction, but also to choose general and also individual measures to put an end to the violation found by the Court and to redress so far as possible the effects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2729.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2736.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think that the situation of the applicant cannot depend on purely procedural matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2736.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2776.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whether a breach of the rights of the applicant is recognized by the Court's judgment or by a unilateral declaration of the government, I cannot see reasons to put applicants in the cases where the Court, where the government submitted unilateral declarations in different situation in comparison to the applicants in cases where the Court adopted judgments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2776.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2797.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like also to draw the attention to the terms of the Latvian government's unilateral declaration, which suggests that the government undertakes to adopt all necessary measures in order to provide an effective remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2797.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2814.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the decision of the Court of 10 February 2010 also recognizes the right of the applicant to exercise other appropriate remedies to obtain redress.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2814.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2824.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in the applicant's view, there is a corresponding obligation of the government to provide this appropriate individual remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2824.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2858.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also would like to say that if the Court makes a conclusion that states have legal obligation to put an end to the breach in individual case and make reparation for its consequences, only if the Court has adopted a judgment that it unfortunately would considerably diminish the role of the unilateral declarations, which in general is a good mechanism.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2858.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2866.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I would like briefly to say some words on Article 13.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2866.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2880.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I agree that Article 13 of the Convention does not provide that the state shall necessarily reopen the relevant criminal proceedings in all cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2880.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2891.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But there should be a relevant mechanism, a relevant procedure for examination of an individual case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2891.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2899.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In an individual case, of course, the principle of legal certainty might prevail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2899.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2907.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It might be situations that statutory limitation period has elapsed already.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2907.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2913.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it might be established only if the relevant proceedings take place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2913.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2919.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At least this is so in the Latvian legal system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2919.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2934.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's said explicitly by the Latvian criminal procedure law that the existence of the newly disclosed circumstances shall be determined by an investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2934.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2954.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I also would like to explain that according to the criminal law of Latvia, a person may not be held criminally liable in most cases if two to 15 years, depending on severity of a crime, has elapsed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2954.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2973.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the length of the statutory limitation period may be established only after investigation and after conclusion as to what crime is performed, because statutory limitation periods are different for different crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2973.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3003.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in the present case, the prosecutor's office refused to reopen both criminal proceedings, stating that the government's unilateral declaration are not grounds for reopening the criminal proceedings, and they do not try to perform investigation to find this right balance between legal certainty and rights of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3003.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3028.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And besides, if we speak about statutory limitation period, then it's only concerning the criminal proceedings against the responsible police officers, because there are no statutory limitation periods for criminal proceedings in which the applicant himself can be convicted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3028.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3036.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, I would like to touch briefly also the competence of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3036.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3065.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant considers that nothing prevents the court to examine the merits of his application under Article 3 to decide whether the refusal to investigate the applicant's complaints lead to a situation that general legal prohibition of torture and inhuman and degrading treatment becomes ineffective in practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3065.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3090.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the court is also competent to review the merits of application under Article 13 of the Convention to examine whether the applicant had an effective remedy before a national authority, in order to obtain reparation of consequences of the breach of his rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3090.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3108.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's true that the text of decision of 10 February 2009 of the court does not suggest that the court considered whether the applicant might need to claim reopening of the relevant criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3108.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3139.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But had the court in its decision drawn attention to whether the Latvian law, namely the criminal procedure law, sections 393 and 655, provided the right of the applicant to reopen the criminal proceedings, the court probably would come to the positive answer, because the law actually provides this right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3139.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3173.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I said already, section 393 has a very broad formulation, and the meaning of section 655 of this law is also to provide reopening of criminal proceedings in all cases when the circumstances indicate that a convicted person is not guilty or testify on guilt of another person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3173.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3182.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And here the unilateral declaration of the government recognizes guilt of the police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3182.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3201.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a warning that the police officers acted not according to Article 3 of the Convention, and also raises doubt that the applicant's guilt in the relevant proceedings was not proved by reliable evidences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3201.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3235.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, if the court considers that it is prevented by reason of its decision of 10 February 2009, to examine the merits of the current application, the applicant would like to ask the court to restore his application in case number 547-02 to the list of cases of the court under Article 37, paragraph 2 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3235.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3254.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that the government refuses to improve the consequences of the breach of the applicant's rights, contrary to their commitment in the unilateral declaration, to adopt all necessary measures in order to provide an effective remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3254.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3266.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the applicant's view constitutes exceptional circumstances, I'm sorry, mentioned in Article 37, paragraph 2 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3266.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3266.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3274.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3275.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3275.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3281.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce qu'il y a des questions de la part des juges?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3281.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3291.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tel n'est pas le cas, alors je propose qu'on continue tout de suite avec la représentante du gouvernement pour la réplique.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3291.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3291.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous avez la parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3296.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3304.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I fear that to some extent the arguments of the government have been misrepresented.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3304.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3314.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me reiterate once again, at no point we suggest that there is a difference between judgments and decision when it comes to reopening.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3314.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3317.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no difference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3317.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3326.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Domestic proceedings can be reopened either when the finding of violation is in the judgment or in decision accepting declaration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3326.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3331.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What matters is not the form, but the content.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3331.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3342.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't have to remind this court or the distinguished counsel for the applicant, there are numerous judgments of this court finding violation of procedural aspect of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3342.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3352.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are very few category of cases out of these Article 3 cases where reopening is deemed necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3352.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3375.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is highly regrettable that the number of Article 3 violations, procedural aspect violations, including in the Latvian cases, including the case of Vovruško mentioned by the applicant's representative, but unfortunately the reason for the violation of Article 3 are ineffective investigation that took place and that cannot be remedied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3375.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3382.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the evidence was not gathered in 1998, is there any chance an evidence could be gathered in 2008?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3382.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3385.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I highly doubt it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3385.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3401.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore as regrettable as it is, there are cases where a recognition of a violation or finding of a violation in a court judgment, in addition to the monetary compensation, is a measure to remedy the violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3401.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3418.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In those exceptional circumstances where finding of a violation either in a judgment or a declaration provides new information, either on the interpretation of the law or the new facts, the proceedings are reopened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3418.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3426.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again I can recall that in the Latin practice there are several instances where proceedings have been reopened following the finding of a violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3426.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3434.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In one case this court found that a court trying the applicant was not independent and impartial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3434.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3444.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Obviously that is an exceptional circumstance that has direct impact on the status of the applicant and the proceedings was opened in the case of Lovens v. Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3444.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3450.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in the case of Baltinč v. Latvia, this court indicated that the domestic court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3450.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3455.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>had failed to examine a certain claim by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3455.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3465.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore this court indicated, clearly indicated something lacking in the examination of the domestic court, that the domestic court should re-examine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3465.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3469.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore the domestic proceedings were reopened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3469.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3483.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of Česniks I mentioned today, it's not only the facts and the violation contained in the judgments of the court, it's also the facts contained in the unilateral declaration that are re-examined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3483.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3494.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So to reiterate, nothing in our position or the domestic legislation of Latvia suggests that reopening is only possible when there is a judgment of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3494.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3496.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is not the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3496.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3504.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Reopening is also possible where there is a decision and the examples we offered I hope clarify that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3504.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3523.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second point I'd like to address at this stage is that it is clear and there's no doubt about that, that reopening is an exceptional measure in the course of execution of the court's judgments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3523.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3541.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore to claim that there is an obligation in all cases of violation to reopen domestic proceedings is manifestly misinterpreting what this conventional system is all about.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3541.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3559.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I once again repeat that reopening can be required in those particular cases where the consequences for the applicants are extremely negative or where there are obvious new information or evidence or interpretation of the law that can be examined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3559.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3563.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this present case is not such a case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3563.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3574.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I once again refer to the case of Vavruško that yes indeed he was co-accused of the applicants in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3574.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3577.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No reopening in Vavruško case either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3577.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3586.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Vavruško case is very well under the examination by the committee of ministers on the measures the Latvian government has taken to execute the judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3586.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3597.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At no point the question of reopening has come up for the simple fact that reopening can serve no practical purpose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3597.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3606.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore in our statement we refer to the need to ensure rights that are practical and effective, not theoretical and illusory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3606.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3616.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Reopening in these cases would in our opinion be this illusory and theoretical approach to the rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3616.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3625.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just to conclude, the government maintains that in the present case there are no exceptional circumstances warranting reopening.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3625.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3635.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I once again recall that the present case is only about discontinued criminal investigation into the applicants ill treatment and not about the conviction of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3635.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3641.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I respectfully request the court to find that either the application is inadmissible or that there has been no violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3641.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3641.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3646.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3647.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Miss Nikuļceva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3651.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3652.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3652.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3681.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, I am very happy that the government and I, we are on the same opinion about the Latvian criminal procedure laws, that actually it allows reopening of the criminal proceedings, not only in the case of the judgment of the court, but also in cases of unilateral declarations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3681.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3696.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But here I would like to draw attention that the government's agents' opinion cannot replace what was really done by the Latvian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3696.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3735.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if we look into the decision of the Latvian prosecutor's office of 20 December 2010, then the prosecutor's office refused reopening of the criminal proceedings just because the unilateral declaration is not findings of an international judicial body, and not because of other reasons as it's explicitly said in this decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3735.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3758.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like also to draw attention that the fact that evidence cannot be got ahead after 17 years, that it might be difficult to perform investigation now, that maybe statutory limitation period has elapsed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3758.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3784.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's also just opinion of the government agent, because what the applicant required, applicant requires the prosecutor's office to open this investigation and to decide on these questions, to evaluate, are there any new evidences, is it possible to find any new facts during investigation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3784.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3786.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And no.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3786.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3790.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are there statutory limitation period or no?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3790.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3807.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it never was performed, and it may not be replaced by evaluation of the agent, because the agent is not in the position to perform investigation in criminal cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3807.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3846.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I also would like to mention that I cannot agree that the question is about minor bodily injuries of the applicant, and that the statutory limitation period has elapsed already, because the criminal case against the police officers was on exceeding of official powers, and it's absolutely another case, maybe in connection with violence or connection with torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3846.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3869.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And secondly, I would like to say about some words on negative consequences to the applicant, and here I would like again to remind that the applicant actually asked to reopen two criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3869.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3884.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I guess that for everybody it's clear that if we speak about the criminal proceedings in which the applicant himself had been convicted, that they concern him directly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3884.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3896.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it's of paramount importance for the applicant also to receive investigation in this case against the police officers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3896.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3906.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even at the end, maybe it really might be situations that the statutory limitation period already had elapsed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3906.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3917.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, it's very important for the applicant to know who did it and the recognition of their responsibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3917.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3917.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3920.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3924.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3924.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3926.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3926.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3933.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits, and the judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3933.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3939.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery, and I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
