<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>4647011_18062014</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>72.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>73.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>118.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>119.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Veuillez vous asseoir.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>119.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>130.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je déclare ouverte l'audience publique sur la recevabilité et le fonds de l'affaire Parrillo contre l'Italie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>131.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>144.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'affaire a été introduite devant la Cour le 26 juillet 2011 par une ressortissante italienne, Mme Adelina Parrillo, en vertu de l'article 34 de la Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>145.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>151.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Elle a été attribuée à la 2e section de la Cour conformément à l'article 52, paragraphe 1 du règlement de la Cour.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>152.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>162.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La requête a été communiquée au gouvernement le 28 mai 2013 sous l'angle des articles 8 de la Convention et 1 du protocole numéro 1 de la Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>162.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>169.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le même jour, la Cour a déclaré irrecevable le grief tiré de l'article 10 de la Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>171.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>177.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le 28 janvier 2014, une chambre de la 2e section a décidé de se dessaisir au profit de la grande chambre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>178.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>182.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Aucune des parties n'a s'étant opposée à ce dessaisissement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>183.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>236.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quatre tierces parties, à savoir le Centre européen pour la justice et les droits de l'homme, les associations Luca Cossioni, Amica Cigogna Onlus, L'Altra Cigogna Onlus et Cerco Un Bimbo agissant conjointement, les associations Vox, Osservatorio Italiano Sui Diritti, SIFES, Society of Fertility, Sterility and Reproductive Medicine et Città Dinanzativa agissant conjointement, ainsi que les associations Movimento per la Vita, Scienza e Vita e Forum delle Associazioni Familiari agissant conjointement, ont soumis des observations écrites en vertu de l'article 44, paragraphe 3 du règlement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>237.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>246.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le gouvernement est représenté par sa co-agente, Mme Paola Accardo, assistée de M. Gianluca Mauro Pellegrini,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>246.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>255.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>co-agent du gouvernement, ainsi que de Mme Assunta Morresi et de Mme Deirdre Fehily, conseillère.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>255.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>260.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La requérante est représentée par M. Nicolò Paoletti,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>260.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>263.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>M. Claudia Sartori,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>263.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>266.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>M. Natalia Paoletti, conseille,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>266.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>270.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assistée de M. Michele De Luca, conseiller.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>271.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>275.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je salue les comparants au nom de la Cour.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>276.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>290.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je salue également le groupe de magistrats et avocats azerbaïdjanais, ainsi que le groupe de juges et membres du greffe de la Cour suprême de la République de Moldova en visite d'études à la Cour.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>291.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>301.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ayant consulté la co-agente du gouvernement et les représentants de la requérante, j'ai fixé ainsi l'ordre de parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>302.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>314.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nous entendrons successivement Mme Paola Accardo et Mme Assunta Morresi pour le gouvernement, puis M. Paoletti, M. Natalia Paoletti,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>314.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>319.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>M. Michele De Luca et M. Claudia Sartori pour la requérante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>319.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>321.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La parole est à Mme Paola Accardo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>324.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>326.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci, Monsieur le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>327.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>347.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les gouvernements italiens, en adressant la Cour à ses juges ses meilleures salutations et les excuses de l'agent pour son absence, présentent de brèves considérations et la réponse aux questions qu'on récit par lettre le 2 mai 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>349.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>367.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tout d'abord, les gouvernements italiens désirent confirmer ces observations du 28 mars 2014 aussi bien sur les récivabilités de la requête au sens de l'article 35, paragraphe 1 de la Convention que sur les fonds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>368.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>378.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il attire notamment l'attention sur les faits que la requérante a attendu plus de sept ans pour saisir la Cour.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>378.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>398.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quant au fait que la loi 40 de 2004 l'empêchait de disposer de sang qu'un brione en cryoconservation était entrée en vigueur en mars 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>398.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>416.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ce fait est pertinent au sens de l'exception faite au sens de l'article 35, paragraphe 1 et suscite des doutes sur l'importance de l'intérêt enjeu pour la requérante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>417.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>443.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Une autre, il faut observer encore qu'elle demande à demander au centre où sont conservés les embryons donnés pour la procuration médicalement assistée d'en disposer pour les derniers à la recherche seulement le 14 décembre 2011, après avoir présenté la requête à la Cour le 23 juillet 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>446.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>459.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tout d'abord, les gouvernements italiens voient mal comment la plainte de la requérante pourrait rentrer dans les champs d'application de l'article 1 du protocole N.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>460.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>488.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quelle que soit la nature de l'embryon sur lequel la communauté scientifique, les juristes s'interrogent et donnent des réponses très controversées, il ne s'agit pas d'un embryon qui puisse appartenir séparément ou conjointement aux deux personnes du sexe opposé qui l'ont engendré selon les concepts traditionnels du droit des propriétés.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>490.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>503.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour, qui a déjà tranché des affaires concernant les embryons, n'a jamais reçu des plaintes envoquant la protection accordée au potentiel parent par l'article 1 du protocole 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>504.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>518.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La défense de la partie requérante s'appuie donc sur un arrêt rendu aux Etats-Unis qui aurait établi que l'embryon est soumis au régime de la propriété.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>519.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>529.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais aucun arrêt de la Cour ni d'autres des autres Cours européennes ou des pays de l'Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>531.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>540.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, dans les documents du Conseil de l'Europe, il ne ressort pas que l'embryon soit considéré comme n'importe quelle chose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>540.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>549.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Au contraire, il est à maintes reprises dit que l'embryon, l'effetus humain, doit bénéficier du respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>550.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>558.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est une protection quand même accordée, au moins dans l'essence du respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>559.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>570.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il ressort ainsi que l'approche est bien loin de celle envers une chose qu'on peut attribuer à un propriétaire dont il peut disposer librement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>571.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>582.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, à la lumière de la jurisprudence de la Cour, la question summise par la requérante pourrait seulement se poser sur l'angle de l'article 8 de la Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>583.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>589.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Compte tenu du vaste champ d'application qui lui est accordé.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>590.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>599.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais aussi, il faut même tenir compte des nombreuses limites justifiées qui y sont prévues au même article, au paragraphe D.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>601.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>623.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La requérante se plaint que l'article 13 de la loi 40 de 2004 l'empêche de donner à la recherche scientifique les embryons en cryoconservation qui faisaient partie d'un projet familial brisé par la perte tragique de son compagnon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>624.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>651.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pour évaluer s'il y a eu la prétendue ingérence injustifiée dans la vie privée, il faut bien considérer que l'embryon qui fait objet d'évaluations les plus disparates dans la communauté scientifique et du point de vue éthique et juridique fait sans aucun doute l'objet d'une protection par les durées européennes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>651.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>682.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pour se retenir aux sources provenant du Conseil d'Europe, la Convention d'Oviedo, la Convention invoquée par la requérante en appui à sa prétention de donner les sangs aux embryons à la recherche scientifique, n'impose certainement pas aux étudiants et non pas aux États qui adhèrent de permettre la recherche scientifique destructive sur les embryons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>684.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>691.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sur la base de l'article 18, les États sont libres de l'autoriser ou de l'interdire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>693.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>715.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais s'ils la permettent, ils doivent se conformer aux limitations établies par ces mêmes articles 18, notamment, ils ne peuvent pas produire des embryons expressement dirigés à la recherche destructive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>717.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>735.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans ce contexte, le choix d'interdire ou de permettre la recherche sur les embryons, si on la permet, en suivant les limites imposées pour sa protection, au moins pour son respect, fait partie de la marge de l'appréciation des États.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>736.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>772.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est la Cour même qui nous dit que pour se prononcer sur l'ampleur de la marge d'appréciation devant être reconnue à l'État dans une affaire soulevant des questions au regard de l'article 8, il y a lié de prendre en compte un certain nombre de facteurs lorsqu'un aspect particulièrement important de l'existence ou de l'identité d'un individu se trouve en jeu, la marge laissée à l'État est d'ordinaire restreinte.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>774.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>804.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais par contre, lorsqu'il n'y a pas de consensus au sein des États membres du Conseil de l'Europe, que ce soit sur l'importance relative de l'intérêt en jeu ou sur les meilleurs moyens de le protéger, en particulier lorsque l'affaire soulève des questions morales ou éthiques délicates, la marge d'appréciation est plus large.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>805.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>819.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ce que je viens de lire, c'est le paragraphe 94 de l'arrêt des Grandes Chambres S.H. contre Trich du 30 novembre 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>820.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>852.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et quelques mots encore, parce que les mêmes paragraphes continuent, grâce à leur contexte direct et constant avec les forces vives de leur pays, les autorités des États se trouvent en principe mieux placées que les juges internationaux pour se prononcer non seulement sur les contenus précis des exigences de la morale, mais aussi sous la nécessité d'une restriction destinée à y répondre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>854.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>872.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans cette perspective, la Cour, par lettre du 20 mai dernier, a assigné au gouvernement italien la tâche de fournir tout document concernant les travaux préparatoires et les différentes réflexions, commissions d'espérance, etc.,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>873.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>880.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>qui ont accompagné la rédaction de l'article 13 de la loi 40 de 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>881.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>887.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le gouvernement italien a versé aux actes tout...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>889.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>896.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>d'une façon informatique, parce qu'il s'agit de travaux préparatoires très lourds, très...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>897.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>906.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et donc, il a adressé à la Cour les sites Internet, les lignes Internet, pour tout décharger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>907.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>917.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, il ressort de l'examen de ces actes versés, qui sont à disposition de la Cour, sur lesquels on peut même demander des renseignements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>918.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>934.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et donc, on a fait le choix de partir même dans les actes plus anciens, pour démontrer comment les problèmes ont été abordés, quels étaient, au niveau national, les débats.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>935.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>960.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et donc, de ces dossiers, on peut voir même comment ont été prises en considération le rapport du comité directeur pour la biétique du Conseil de l'Europe, résolution du Parlement européen, des différents documents qui concernent les problèmes de l'Assemblée parlementaire du Conseil de l'Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>961.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>970.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et bien sûr, le plan de départ a été l'article 18 de la Convention d'Oviedo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>971.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>994.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, ici, je laisse les considérations à faire, seulement en attirant l'attention qu'il s'agit vraiment d'un grand travail qui a tenu compte des opinions opposées des problèmes, soit au niveau scientifique, soit au point de vue éthique.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>995.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1023.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On peut donc observer que l'interdiction qui empêche à la récréante de destiner les embryons à la recherche est prévue par la loi et poursuit un but légitime dans une société démocratique en tant qu'expression des résultats majoritaires sur la base d'un vaste débat scientifique et éthique.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1025.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1054.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, à ces propos, je me réfère même à les textes de l'article 8 qui encadrent les limites du paragraphe 8 de la Convention, bien sûr, et qui encadrent les limites et les ingérences qui ont permis dans les droits au respect de la vie privée dans ces paramètres de l'évaluation d'une société démocratique.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1056.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1079.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il est bien significatif à ces propos que cinq référendums, lancés en 2005 pour l'abrogation de plusieurs dispositions restrictives de la loi numéro 40 de 2004, y compris l'article 13, qui était aujourd'hui le premier référendum, ont échoué.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1080.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1094.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Car la ligne de l'abstention du vote avait-il fait afin de ne pas s'attendre les quorums nécessaires pour la validité d'un référendum?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1094.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1095.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cette ligne...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1098.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1106.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'était la ligne qui avait été indiquée par les mouvements qui voulaient maintenir les limites proposées par cette loi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1109.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1151.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il faut encore considérer que suite à l'arrêt de la Cour constitutionnelle numéro 170 du 10 juin 2014, très récent donc, qui a déclaré illégitime l'interdiction de la fécondation hétérologue, l'interdiction prévue à l'article 4, l'INEA 3 de la loi 40 de 2004, le juridique italien permet à présent l'utilisation des embryons pour la fécondation hétérologue pour ceux qui n'ont pas la possibilité de procréer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1152.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1157.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il s'agit donc d'une autre possibilité non destructive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1158.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1201.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, on essaie de démontrer la cohérence du système, et pour les autres questions, ça serait Mme Morez qui va répondre, la cohérence du système dans la ligne pour célébrar une production hétérologue hétérologue et quand on a une psychedelie entièrement recouverte par le système cercle du système películique à l'avico, sur l'immeuble en deo adulte qui menace une flow de vitérals aussi symptomatiques que c'est dans un fěcondage hétérologue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1201.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1226.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>être saisie par la récréante si elle le souhaiterait, mais sans doute qui constitue un élément qui renforce la cohérence du système orienté à protéger et à favoriser l'exploitation du potentiel de vie humaine de l'embryon. Or à ces propos, vous avez trouvé dans les</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1226.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1270.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>conversations aux actes, un avis du comité national pour la boétique, on va expliquer tout de suite ce qu'il s'agit, s'il s'agit d'un comité des formations gouvernementales dans lesquelles font partie différents médecins, personnes des sciences et de l'autorité de la culture dans ces domaines. Et donc nous avons madame Morizi qui en fait partie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1270.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1301.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, s'il s'agit de cet avis du 18, une délibération qui est après la délibération du 18 novembre 2005, bien avant que le moment dans lequel est sorti l'arrêt de la cour constitutionnelle qui justement vient de sortir. Ce comité a considéré expressement l'adoption pour la</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1301.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1309.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>naissance. Adoption pour la naissance. Qu'est-ce que c'est donc que des couples stériles</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1309.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1329.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>pourraient adopter un embryon qui était, qui auparavant ça c'était pas possible au moment dans lequel étaient rédigés les documents parce qu'il n'y avait pas encore l'arrêt de la cour constitutionnelle. Mais il, maintenant c'est</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1329.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1335.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>possible, c'est ce qu'il a déjà souhaité dans ces documents. Et c'est-à-dire donc</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1335.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1358.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>l'adoption pour la naissance de l'embryon qui, comme ça, vient destiné à sa première destination naturelle donc faire surgir la vie humaine. Pour les autres questions, jusqu'à présent je me suis occupé</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1358.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1362.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>seulement de la première question, les premiers points de la lettre. Mais pour</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1362.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1375.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>les autres questions posées par la cour, Madame Moresi, membre du comité national des biotiques, va répondre. Ce comité a pour but d'étudier, formuler</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1375.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1401.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>les avis nécessaires à définir les réglementations plus appropriées pour matière difficile et complexe comme celle de la loi 40 et continue à étudier chaque aspect de l'existence de l'embryon humain dans le respect des principes éthiques et d'application, notamment du principe des précautions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1401.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1410.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>À ce moment-ci, je laisse Madame Moresi continuer. Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1410.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1414.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci. Je donne la parole à Mme Morresi, s'il vous plaît.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1418.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1441.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>About the second question of the court, the Italian government challenges the statement that the embryos of the claimant will in any case be destroyed because of the fact that they are cryopreserved, as well as the more general statement that cryopreserved embryos are destined to destruction insofar as such.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1441.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1451.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to current scientific knowledge, embryo cryopreservation, if correctly applied, does not have a time limit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1451.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1454.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is not an expiry date.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1454.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1457.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is not a shelf life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1457.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1466.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, the birth of a healthy child from an embryo frozen 20 years ago was recently reported in the literature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1466.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1501.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on the other hand, as previously observed by the study commission of cryopreserved embryos in art centers, a point pursuant to a decree of the Ministry of Labor and Health and Social Policies on the 25th of June 2009, today no scientific criteria exist to ascertain whether cryopreserved embryos are still viable during their cryopreservation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1501.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1513.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since their viability may be verified only if, after thawing, they are transferred to a uterus and manage to develop and result in a pregnancy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1513.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1530.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is therefore not possible to ascertain which cryopreserved embryos are still viable during their cryopreservation, a condition which is necessary both for transfer to the uterus and for researchers' purposes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1530.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1542.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If embryos, after thawing, are not viable, they cannot be used for any kind of experiment, just as they would not result in a pregnancy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1542.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1554.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And adding always about the second question, in Italy, it is not allowed to import embryos for research, it seems, from two questions of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1554.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1559.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is only possible to import embryonic stem cell lines.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1559.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1566.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Embryos, it must be clear that embryos are totally different from cultural embryonic cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1566.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1571.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A stem cell line is obtained from the destruction of an embryo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1571.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1586.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But a stem cell line is a collection of cells that multiply themselves infinitely and that conserve their fundamental properties, but without the potential to develop into a human being.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1586.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1593.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They can only become individual tissues, earth tissues, or bone tissues, and so on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1593.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1607.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The research carried out on these lines is consistent with the aims of the Italian legislation, that is to protect the human embryos, because they are produced irrespective of any Italian request.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1607.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1615.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That means that they are produced in countries where the legislation allow to destroy embryos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1615.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1620.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But they are not produced on the request of Italian researchers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1620.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1633.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are already more, there are already more than 300 certified lines in the world, all produced without any request from Italian researchers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1633.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1652.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two thirds of these lines are in the United Kingdom, Sweden, France, Spain, and in the United States, which are at the disposal of the scientific community, as confirmed, for example, by the International Stem Cell Registry of the UMass Medical School.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1652.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1668.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>About the question number three, from a scientific point of view, the condition of cryopreservation of embryos, even for long periods of time, is not comparable with their voluntary destruction for research purposes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1668.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1690.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The efficacy of cryopreservation processes depends on the freezing method, if slow or rapid, on the level of development of the embryos at the time of freezing, the addition of cryoprotectants, that is chemical substance that protect the embryos from the formation of the eyes, and so on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1690.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1705.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Scientific literature confirms a high level of survival of cryopreserved embryos, which were thawed and successfully transferred to women who later became pregnant, giving birth to healthy babies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1705.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1722.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cryopreservation process, when correctly performed, blocks the cellular metabolism, suspending the viability of cells and tissues, but does not necessarily compromise the vital functions that are restored after thawing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1722.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1739.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, the Italian government points out that the research on human embryos in Italy is subject to the same rules established by the European Union, both in the case of the Seven Framework Program, FP7, and in the case of Horizon 2020.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1739.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1753.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Italy, as I said before, the destruction of human embryos for research is not permitted, and human embryos may not be imported for scientific research, as stated by the court in its second and fourth questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1753.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1772.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Italy, it is, however, possible to import only human embryonic stem cell lines for research purposes obtained from human embryos previously destroyed in other countries, where laws permit their destruction, without any request from our researchers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1772.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1785.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Similarly to what happens in Italy, the European research programs under the FP7 and Horizon 2020 do not finance the research projects involving the destruction of embryos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1785.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1794.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regardless of whether these are embryos created in Europe or imported from other countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1794.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1813.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>FP7 and Horizon 2020 studies also implies the use of existing human embryo stem cell lines, where the embryos have already been destroyed, but not destroyed under research projects founded by the European Union.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1813.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1836.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Coherently, our country contributes to funding European scientific research projects, as it did recently for the FP7, and as it is doing for Horizon 2020, without excluding funds for research work on human embryonic stem cell lines.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1836.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1849.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Provided this does not entail the direct destruction of human embryos, according to the ethical principles adopted by the European Union.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1849.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1859.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And at the end, the Italian government has moreover explained that there are no general regulation applicable to scientific research in this field.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1859.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1865.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such research may be carried out in private, public, or mixed structures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1865.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1883.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the methods are established from time to time by the individual calls for research projects, which in the case of research on embryonic stem cell lines, must respect the provisions of the law in force, that is, do not destroy direct the embryos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1883.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1894.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any passage to ethical committees, or specific bodies, or any similar request are indicated and regulated by the research projects' calls.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1894.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1894.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1897.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1905.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci Madame Morresi, alors je donne la parole à Maître Paoletti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1919.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1925.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sì, volevo ringraziare il Presidente.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1928.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1929.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Qui veut prendre la parole?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1929.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1933.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maitre Politique.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1931.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1934.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maître Pauletti, s'il vous plaît.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1938.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1938.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je ne vous entends pas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1938.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1940.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous devez parler dans le micro.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1941.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1968.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sono poche parole, in effetti sarà anche l'esperto a dover intervenire e chiarire meglio di chiunque altro la situazione che è oggetto del presente ricorso.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1968.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1984.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due parole sulla prima risposta che vorrei dare al Governo e sulla sua eccezione che non avremmo seguito i medi interni previsti dalla legge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1984.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1997.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In effetti il Governo non tiene conto che nel nostro ordinamento giuridico la possibilità di adire la Corte Costituzionale passa attraverso la magistratura.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1997.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2001.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quindi noi abbiamo la magistratura che deve applicare la legge, qualsiasi essa sia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2001.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2008.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Se poi ritiene che il fatto sia incostituzionale, che la legge sia incostituzionale, deve rimettere gli atti della Corte Costituzionale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2008.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2015.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Questa Corte ha sempre ritenuto che questo passaggio non potesse essere considerato un rimedio interno.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2015.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2025.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Una delle ultime decisioni della Gnasciambria è quello del caso Scoppola, paragrafo 75, che testualmente dice questo, cioè il magistrato deve applicare la legge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2025.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2035.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allora dovesse ritenerla incostituzionale e rimetterà gli atti alla Corte Costituzionale, ma non può la parte privata adire direttamente alla Corte Costituzionale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2035.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2042.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Non potendo far questo non vi erano nel nostro ordinamento rimedi effettivi ed efficaci in Italia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2042.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2058.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Attualmente la Corte Costituzionale ha sospeso il giudizio analogo sulla utilizzazione di embrioni per la ricerca scientifica e ha rinviato l'udienza dell'8 aprile ad altra udienza in attesa che questa Corte decidesse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2058.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2075.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Questo è un osseto verso la Corte, ma è anche un discorso di carattere giuridico interno, in quanto la Corte Costituzionale giudica in relazione anche alle decisioni di questa Corte, ai sensi dell'articolo 117 della Costituzione.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2075.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2098.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Già c'è un precedente importante, la sentenza della Corte Costituzionale 348 in materia di espropriazione, che in relazione alle sentenze della Gran Chambre Scordino sulla indennità di esproprio ha deciso l'incostituzionalità, facendo riferimento a quello che aveva detto la Gran Chambre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2098.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2117.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Per quanto riguarda un'osservazione in linea generale, cioè su quella che è la posizione delle ricorrente, le ricorrente effettuano la fecondazione artificiale prima che il proprio compagno parta per l'Iraq, dove purtroppo poi trova morte nello strage di Nasrirah.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2117.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2127.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A questo punto la signora Parrillo si trova nella difficoltà di decidere se impiantare o non impiantare l'embrione.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2127.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2136.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In effetti la legge italiana glielo impedisce, perché è impossibile impiantare l'embrione solo e esclusivamente se la coppia si rivente entrambi, quindi se sono viventi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2136.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2144.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La signora Parrillo non può, anche se volesse, impiantare l'embrione.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2144.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2146.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'embrione quindi rimane crioconservato.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2146.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2162.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La signora Parrillo decide, in ricordo anche del proprio compagno, di donarlo per la ricerca scientifica e questo gli è impedito dall'articolo 13 della legge 40.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2162.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2167.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'inconcruenza, e non la coerenza, come diceva la dott.ssa Cardo, del nostro ordinamento</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2167.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2168.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>è plese.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2168.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2197.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Da una parte noi abbiamo un embrione che viene tutelato prima dell'impianto, quindi ancora un insieme di cellule essenzialmente, e poi successivamente con la legge 194 che prevede l'aborto, quello stesso embrione impiantato può essere poi distrutto con l'aborto, che è legale in Italia e ormai direi che in tutti i paesi del mondo occidentale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2197.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2211.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Altra incongruenza, non si può effettuare la ricerca scientifica in Italia sull'embrione e sulle cellule staminali estratte da questa embrione, ma si possono importare dall'estero le cellule staminali per effettuare la ricerca.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2211.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2213.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Insomma, mi sembrano incongruenze.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2213.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2215.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Abbiamo degli embrioni, utilizziamoli.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2215.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2226.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Non sono embrioni italiani che non possono essere utilizzati, mentre embrioni di altri paesi, magari di altre religioni, possono essere utilizzati.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2226.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2231.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'è un'incongruenza, non si capisce nemmeno cosa desidera il Governo a questo punto.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2231.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2241.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nel nostro ordinamento questo embrione rimarrà crioconservato in eterno, perché in effetti la signora Parrilla, e qui la materia del contendere, non può disporre dei propri embrioni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2241.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2248.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A mio avviso è in violazione del primo protocollo addizionale, in ogni caso è in violazione dell'articolo 8 della Convenzione.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2248.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2260.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Un'interferenza grave da parte dello Stato sulla possibilità per la signora Parrilla di disporre di cose che le appartengono, anche eticamente e moralmente, indipendentemente da tutto quello che può dire il Governo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2260.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2269.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Può essere una cosa straordinariamente eticamente legata all'uomo che può rientrare in diritto di proprietà.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2269.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2277.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Un diritto di proprietà necessariamente deve essere collegato ai quattrini, all'aspetto economico, può essere collegato a un'ordinata cosa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2277.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2294.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Se io voglio donare un rene e mi fosse impedito di donare il rene, è una lesione del mio diritto, in quanto consapevole del fatto dell'aiuto che posso dare a un altro essere umano, ho il diritto di donare il rene.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2294.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2304.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>E così il diritto di non vedere marcire questi embrioni, come diceva Umberto Veronesi, gettati nel lavandino dopo un certo numero di anni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2304.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2309.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ricordiamoci che in Eghiterra gli anni che sono postati in posti come Libi sono dieci anni, in Francia cinque anni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2309.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2313.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cioè sarà lo stesso legislatore a stabilire per quanto tempo potranno essere crioconservati.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2313.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2323.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In ogni caso, il diritto alla ricerca scientifica, il diritto di donare, quindi di disporre di embrioni per la ricerca scientifica, è uno dei diritti fondamentali.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2323.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2327.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Grazie per il seguente.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2333.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2345.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Avvocato Natalia Paoletti, mi soffermo brevemente sullo stato della normativa italiana che riguarda gli embrioni in questione, ritornando un attimo sulle sue contraddittorietà.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2345.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2364.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quindi abbiamo l'articolo 5 della legge 40 del 2004 che stabilisce che non possono essere impiantati quando uno dei componenti, la coppia, è deceduto, quindi nel caso di specie la signora Parrillo non avrebbe potuto cedere al suo impianto, motivo per il quale si è determinata a donarli.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2364.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2376.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Non possono essere utilizzati per la ricerca scientifica, vietata appunto dall'articolo 13 che la sanziona penalmente, e sono destinati a rimanere crioconservati.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2376.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2395.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Riguardo le contraddittorietà, inutile tornare sul fatto che il nostro ordinamento prevede appunto che non possa essere utilizzato e distrutto un embrione, laddove invece riconosce il diritto della gestante di abortire sino al termine del terzo mese.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2395.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2414.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Codessa Corte è già entrata nel merito, ed ha riconosciuto che la legge ha delle contraddittorietà, con la sentenza Costa-Pavanne, nella quale, con riferimento all'esame diagnostico preimpianto, ha stabilito testualmente, è giocoforza constatare che in materia il sistema legislativo italiano manca di coerenza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2414.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2426.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Da un lato, esso vieta l'impianto limitato ai soli embrioni, non effetti dalla malattia di cui i ricorrenti sono portatori sani, dall'altro autorizza i ricorrenti ad abortire un feto affetto da quella stessa patologia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2426.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2448.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'altra contraddittorietà è quella riguardo il fatto che, come ha messo sia dal Governo al paragrafo 75 della sua memoria che nell'intervento della professoressa Morresi, nel nostro ordinamento si possono importare cellule staminali embrionali prodotte all'estero.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2448.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2456.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quindi, in estrema sintesi, in base alla nostra normativa, si possono distruggere gli embrioni purché ciò avvenga all'estero.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2456.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2476.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mi soffermo ulteriormente su ciò che stabilisce il protocollo addizionale alla Convenzione di Oviedo sulla ricerca biomedica del 2005, che all'articolo 2 stabilisce testualmente che tutti i divieti all'attività di ricerca sugli umani non si applicano alla ricerca sugli embrioni in vitro.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2476.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2482.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Altro punto importante è quello di tenere conto che si tratta di embrioni in vitro, non di embrioni impiantati.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2482.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2502.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Così come la Corte Interamericana dei diritti dell'uomo, con sentenza del 20 dicembre 2012 resa nel caso Murillo e altri contro Costa Rica, ha stabilito testualmente che l'embrione non può essere inteso come persona agli effetti dell'articolo 4.1 della Convenzione americana,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2502.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2508.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in quanto il concepimento ai sensi dell'articolo 4.1 avviene dal momento in cui l'embrione</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2508.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2516.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>si impianta nell'utero, ragionque il cui, prima di quest'evento, non può aver luogo l'applicazione dell'articolo 4 della Convenzione.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2516.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2531.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A questo punto, nell'insistere affinché il ricorso venga accolto, passo la parola al professor Michele De Luca, professore universitario, tra i massimi esperti mondiali di ricerca sulle cellule staminali e direttore del Centro di Medicina Rigenerativa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP4</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2541.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2549.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will obviously address mainly scientific issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2549.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2557.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm not my role to get into this legal stuff that I barely understand, obviously.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2557.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2561.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But there are a few things I would like to say.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2561.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2564.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is in vitro fertilization?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2564.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2571.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In vitro fertilization is the union of a sperm cell with the nocites.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2571.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2576.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that give rise basically to a cluster of cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2576.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2579.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's what is originating in in vitro fertilization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2579.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2585.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Which is basically the same thing that occurs in vivo when you have natural fertilization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2585.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2594.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now this cluster of cells that are generating during vitro fertilization are not individuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2594.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2596.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is a cluster of cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2596.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2599.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they are all identical.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2599.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2600.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Each other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2600.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2602.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are all alike.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2602.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2605.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are not specialized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2605.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2610.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is not the heart, a leg, a trunk, a brain, or a heart.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2610.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2613.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is a group of cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2613.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2615.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those are the embryonic stem cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2615.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2619.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So what is called the in vitro embryo?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2619.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2625.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is basically a group of pluripotent stem cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2625.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2635.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That have the potentiality of becoming a fetus or a human being after implantation in the universe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2635.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2643.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But you can easily judge this by yourself because you can freeze down a cluster of cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2643.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2645.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do this all the time in the lab.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2645.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2652.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But try to freeze down a human being or to freeze down a fetus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2652.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2654.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2654.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2667.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in fact actually what has been said that there is a difference between the embryo and the embryonic cell lines that are derived from the embryo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2667.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2673.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is basically not true because the embryo in vitro embryo itself is a cluster of cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2673.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2678.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Each of these cells have the potentiality of becoming an embryo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2678.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2690.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This has been shown in animals and recently has been also shown that you can take one of these embryonic stem cells and make another cluster of embryonic stem cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2690.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2697.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore what we are talking about is embryonic stem cells which are not different from the embryo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2697.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2701.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are the embryo that we are talking about.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2701.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2704.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Which is not an individual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2704.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2711.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It becomes an individual only after implantation and only after development.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2711.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2713.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Become then a fetus and then a human being.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2713.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2722.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is true for each of these all alike identical clusters of cells that we have in vitro.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2722.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2726.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now are these cells useful?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2726.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2736.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These cells are tremendously useful because the embryonic stem cells, and I'm not working with them so I have no interest in working with embryonic stem cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2736.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2738.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm working with different cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2738.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2756.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I can tell you that embryonic stem cells are essential for research because those are the only pluripotent stem cells we have in nature and they're the only cells that in principle can make tissues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2756.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2763.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then can help people with severe invalidating or deadly disease.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2763.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2779.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a matter of fact, there are clinical trials done by excellent scientists, not by quacks, by excellent scientists like Lawrence Studer, by Anders Bjorklund.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2779.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2791.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are using in clinical phase one and two clinical trials those embryonic stem cells derived tissues for spinal cord injury, for retina disease, and for Parkinson's.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2791.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2803.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if we don't do research, basic research, we will never be able to show that those cells would help many people with untreatable disease.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2803.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2819.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is why the donation of embryos or I call it better clusters of cells that are frozen down and they will lose viability by definition is crucial, is important.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2819.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2833.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because only with the donation and with the science we can go to those clinical trials that eventually will show one day that it is useful for clinical benefit for the entire world population.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2833.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2837.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is what people are doing in countries where this is allowed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2837.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2849.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I tell you more, there is this possibility of getting pluripotent embryonic, embryonic cell-like stem cells from in vitro reprogramming.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2849.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2854.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's the famous IPS or the Yamanaka protocol.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2854.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2856.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course this is important.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2856.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2863.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is important for one specific reason, because those cells would be autologous, would be made by cells from the same patients.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2863.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2886.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we will never know whether those cells can be used at the clinical level, can do the same tissues, can do the same job that an embryonic stem cell, a natural embryonic stem cell can do if we cannot work on the embryonic stem cells, if we cannot compare those embryonic stem cells with the IPS.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2886.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2887.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And only research will tell this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2887.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2890.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's why donation is important.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2890.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2899.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donation which is allowed in many other countries other than Italy and a few others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2899.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2906.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I heard somebody speaking about respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2906.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2919.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now in your mind, what is more respectful for a cluster of cells that is frozen down and has never been used, will never be used?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2919.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2928.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that we don't know officially what will be the cell viability in the long term.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2928.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2929.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We need to do this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2929.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2934.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a matter of research.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2934.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2941.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If we don't touch this, we will never know how long it will be viable in the liquid nitrogen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2941.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2953.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the current tendency of most of the people that do in vitro fertilization is that they will not use it anyway after a certain number of months or years that it has been frozen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2953.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2954.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2954.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2965.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is more respectable for a cluster of cells, not a human being, a cluster of cells, assuming that the cluster of cells need respect, what is more respectful for a cluster of cells?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2965.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2973.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To let them lose viability slowly and progressively during years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2973.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2974.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And don't use them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2974.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2975.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just leave it then.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2975.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2982.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are then at a certain point, 20 years later, take and put in the sink.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2982.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2998.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or to use them to do something that can be useful for the entire population of people, for all the people with the macular dystrophy, all the people with Parkinson's, all the people that could benefit from the research.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2998.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3002.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't know what is more respectable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3002.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3017.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I just want to point out just two things that have been already said, so it will be very brief.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3017.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3018.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Think about it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3018.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3026.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Parillo cannot, in any case by our law, cannot implant the embryo in his uterus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3026.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3043.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What has been suggested that she could donate this embryo to a third party, to people that cannot generate procreate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3043.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3054.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If she does that, in principle, that couple could make abortion three months later and decide to kill the fetus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3054.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3069.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But Parillo cannot donate the cluster of cells to do a fundamental research for all the human beings, for all the humanity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3069.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3077.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as scientists in Italy, it is not true that in Italy we cannot make research on embryonic stem cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3077.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3089.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We can make it as long as the embryo, from where the cells are derived, is not produced in our country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3089.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3092.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't know what the logic of this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3092.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3099.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is a Danish or a Swedish embryo needs less respect than an Italian embryo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3099.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3104.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we can do, because any embryonic stem cells must come from an embryo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3104.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3116.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if I can take an embryonic stem cell coming from a Swedish embryo or English embryo, I can use it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3116.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3120.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is basically nonsense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3120.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3120.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm going to stop there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3127.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3129.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3129.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3129.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3133.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3150.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mi collego a quanto detto dal professor De Luca, che ringrazio molto per il suo intervento di grandissimo interesse, per parlare della recentissima decisione della Commissione europea del 28 maggio scorso, con la quale è stata rigettata l'iniziativa dei cittadini europei, denominata Uno di noi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3150.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3161.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Iniziativa che chiedeva all'Unione europea di introdurre un divieto e porre fine al finanziamento di attività presupponenti la distruzione di embrioni umani.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3161.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3192.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ebbene, la Commissione europea con tale decisione in primo luogo ha affermato dei principi, ha dimostrato l'erroneità, questa decisione dimostra l'erroneità di quanto ha sostenuto il Governo italiano nella sua memoria, in relazione alla sentenza della Corte di giustizia, la nota sentenza nel caso Brustle, contro Greenpeace, nella quale secondo il Governo italiano si sarebbe affermato un divieto di ricerca scientifica che utilizzi gli embrioni umani.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3192.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3217.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Commissione invece afferma nella sua decisione, l'ha cito testualmente, la cosiddetta sentenza Brustle della Corte di giustizia dell'Unione europea dichiara che la direttiva Biotech non è intesa a disciplinare l'utilizzazione di embrioni umani nell'ambito di ricerche scientifiche, essa ha ad oggetto esclusivamente la brevettabilità delle invenzioni biotecnologiche.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3217.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3225.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La sentenza non verte sulla possibilità di fare ricerca in questo ambito né sul relativo finanziamento.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3225.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3247.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>E in effetti la sentenza della Corte di giustizia, affermando il divieto di brevettabilità dei risultati della ricerca scientifica sugli embrioni in quanto ciò implicherebbe un loro sfruttamento industriale e commerciale, ammette che tale ricerca possa essere fatta, poiché come ovvio per esserci un risultato vi deve essere una ricerca.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3247.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3290.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In secondo luogo, la decisione della Commissione europea del 28 maggio scorso definitivamente chiarisce che la ricerca scientifica che utilizzi gli embrioni umani è libera e sono vietate esclusivamente tre attività di ricerca, anche qui cito testualmente l'attività di ricerca vietate sono quelle finalizzate alla clonazione umana a fini riproduttivi, le attività di ricerca volte a modificare il patrimonio genetico degli esseri umani che potrebbero rendere ereditabili tali modifiche e le attività di ricerca volte a creare embrioni umani soltanto a fin di ricerca o per l'approvvigionamento di cellule staminali.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3290.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3322.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In terzo luogo, la Commissione europea nella medesima decisione del 28 maggio scorso ha sottolineato l'importanza fondamentale della ricerca scientifica sulle cellule staminali e embrionali che si ricorda è stata finanziata dall'Unione europea e viene effettuata nella stragrande maggioranza degli Stati membri, inizialmente in base al settimo programma quadro e ora in base al programma Orizzonte 2000. La Commissione ha affermato testualmente</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3322.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3348.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in questa decisione che la ricerca sulle cellule staminali e embrionali umane può potenzialmente contribuire alla prossima generazione di trattamenti sanitari sotto forma di cure o possibilità di cura per malattie incurabili e o letali come il morbo di Parkinson, il diabete, l'ictus, le malattie cardiache e la cecità. Questo l'ha ricordato giustamente anche in maniera</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3348.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3354.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>egregia il professor De Luca. E quindi occorre che venga riconosciuto il diritto della ricorrente</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3354.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3366.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a donare i propri embrioni a un laboratorio italiano che già effettua la ricerca sulle cellule staminali e embrionali importate dall'estero e che li possa utilizzare per tale ricerca.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3366.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3366.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Grazie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3373.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3375.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup pour vos développements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3376.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3383.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je me tourne maintenant vers mes collègues pour demander s'il y a des questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3383.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3383.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, la juge Keller.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Helen Keller</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3390.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3392.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3392.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3405.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question to the representative of the applicant, in particular to Maître Paoletti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3405.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3419.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Did I understand the facts correctly that our applicant never asked for an in vitro fertilization after her partner has died?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3419.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3435.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Did I understand it correctly that she never wished to pursue the pregnancy because she didn't want to become a single mother?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3435.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3440.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question concerns also the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3440.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3474.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Did the applicant receive, before she went into in vitro fertilization treatment, a contract by the hospital in which she was informed about the fact that the embryos created by in vitro fertilization could only be used for the fertilization, but not for anything else?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3474.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3474.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3475.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3478.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, le juge Casadevall.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3480.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3482.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci, M. le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3483.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3498.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je m'adresse aux deux parties pour leur demander si pourrait-elle nous donner son point de vue sur deux aspects moins scientifiques et plus techniques pour moi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3498.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3511.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le premier étant, quel est votre point de vue sur l'applicabilité de l'article 8 de la Convention au fait de l'affaire qui est présente devant nous.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3511.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3521.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et le deuxième point, d'une certaine façon lié au premier, sur la qualité des victimes de la requérante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3521.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3521.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3524.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3527.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, juge Sajó.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3532.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3534.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3534.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3540.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My questions are partly overlapping the questions which were already raised.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3540.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3561.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first question is, what was the legal system applicable in 2003 when the embryos were created concerning conservation and, in particular, research in Italy?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3561.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3572.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, it is argued by government that embryo is life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3572.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3583.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is this, assuming that you are right and this is life, is it a life comparable to that of the fetus?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3583.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3618.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is the in vitro embryo that was called a cluster of cells by Professor De Luca, is this entity, a person, in view of Italian law, having regard to the position of the Constitutional Court which said in 75, "persona che deve ancora diventare"?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3618.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3630.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the applicants, if I understand correctly, the in vitro entity is 11 years old.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3630.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3645.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is there any research advantage to use these cells for research purposes given the age and given the doubts expressed?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3645.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3662.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the government, is an Italian scientist subject to criminal prosecution if he or she carries out research abroad on in vitro embryo?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3662.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3662.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3664.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3668.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci, juge Sajó et la juge Karakaş.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Işıl Karakaş</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3673.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3675.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Oui, merci, Monsieur le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3675.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3700.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'aimerais que le gouvernement clarifie le but légitime de l'interdiction de l'article 13 de la loi 40 2004, tout en considérant que les laboratoires peuvent pratiquer des recherches sur les lignes embryonnaires importées de l'étranger, donc après la destruction de ces embryons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3700.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3703.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>D'après cela, j'ai une question plus simple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3703.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3710.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce qu'il y a une interdiction de destruction des embryons?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3710.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3714.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ça, on le sait, mais que devient-il s'il existe une interdiction?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3714.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3718.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, est-ce que les institutions gardent à l'infini?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3718.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3718.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est ma deuxième question. Merci beaucoup.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3721.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3725.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, la juge Yudkivska.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ganna Yudkivska</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3728.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3729.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3729.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3734.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have one question to the representative of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3734.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3736.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a factual question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3736.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3747.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is the applicant obliged to maintain contacts with the embryo storage bank whilst her embryos are cryopreserved?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3747.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3751.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For instance, should she still pay for cryopreservation of her embryo?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3751.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3751.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3752.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3756.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, le juge Pinto de Albuquerque.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3759.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3763.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This question goes to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3763.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3786.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to know if there is any available data on the number of sterile couples who have benefited from fertilization with cryopreserved embryos of third couples who did not want to become parents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3786.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3795.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do we have already any available data on these third couples who have benefited from this possibility?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3795.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3795.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3798.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3801.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, le juge Vučinić.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Nebojša Vučinić</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3804.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3805.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3805.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3810.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions for both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3810.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3824.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we saw from hearing, the main purpose and object of the law from 2004 is to protect the life of the embryo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3824.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3835.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this context, is there any, I would say, internal inconsistency or contradiction concerning this main object of the law?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3835.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3845.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mean, in any case, embryo will be extinct, will be perished after the lapse of some time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3845.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3861.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or more precisely, whether the holding embryo in cryopreserved status on the temperature absolute zero amounts also some sort of scientific experiment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3861.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3873.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question is whether the prohibition of scientific research is motivated by other reason, not only to protect the life of the embryo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3873.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3874.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3874.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3877.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, la juge Ann Power-Forde.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ann Power-Forde</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3878.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3881.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3881.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3891.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is of a philosophical nature, and I would like both parties to comment on the philosophical underpinnings of each other's submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3891.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3909.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If I understand correctly, the submission of the government is founded upon a philosophical understanding of the embryo as a value in itself under Italian law, that the embryo is the subject of rights or is a value in itself, an end in itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3909.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3924.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if I understand correctly, the submissions of the applicant, the embryo, or as Professor De Luca has put it, may be seen as a cluster of cells, that this entity, this embryo or cluster of cells, may become a value for others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3924.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3929.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So not necessarily an end in itself, but perhaps a means towards some other end.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3929.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3936.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you mentioned some of the types of research and benefits that can accrue from the research on embryos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3936.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3954.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would like each side to consider the philosophical underpinning in terms of value, means end, and comment on the correlation of each party's position with the rights protected under Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3954.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3954.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3956.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3957.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3957.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3971.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'aurais aussi une question qui rejoint celle qui a été posée par la juge Karakaş et qui concerne le gouvernement au regard de l'article 8 de la convention, paragraphe 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3973.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3991.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Au paragraphe 73 des observations du mémoire du gouvernement du 28 mars 2014, vous mentionnez, au titre du but légitime, celui de protéger la vie des embryons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3992.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4006.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Au regard de la terminologie, au regard de l'article 8, paragraphe 2, sous quelle rubrique des limitations est-ce que vous classeriez cette justification?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4008.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4023.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et au niveau de la question de la proportionnalité aussi, si vous pourriez développer votre argumentation qui est mentionnée au paragraphe 73 de votre mémoire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4024.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4024.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Voilà.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4025.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4029.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>S'il n'y a pas d'autres questions, je propose qu'on se revoie à 10 h 45.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4029.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4029.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4329.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4330.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4369.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4370.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'audience est reprise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4371.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4372.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je vous prie de vous asseoir.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4375.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4377.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Qui veut prendre la parole?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4377.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4378.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous avez la parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4379.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4382.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci, Monsieur le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4382.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4390.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, je voudrais avant tout bien définir l'EG de l'examen de la Cour.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4390.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4409.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je voudrais attirer l'attention sur les faits qu'aujourd'hui, la Cour n'est pas appelée à trancher des problèmes scientifiques, c'est-à-dire, elle ne doit pas dire qu'elle, théoriquement scientifique, doit avoir plus de crédits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4410.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4419.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et donc, il faut vraiment se concentrer sur les problèmes, qui est la cohérence du système.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4419.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4432.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je rappelle que la Cour a déjà déclaré irrécevable la requête pour ce qui concerne les champs d'application de l'article 10 de la Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4432.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4442.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bon, en même temps, je réponds à la dernière question, qui était celle posée du président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4442.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4447.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et particulièrement, elle a été adressée à la défense du gouvernement italien.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4447.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4462.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je dis, à part l'expression employée, je dois dire que les mémoires déposées en avril dernier n'étaient pas rédigées par moi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4462.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4467.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'étais chargée au dernier moment de la défense de l'affaire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4468.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4470.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, c'est seulement cette partie dernière.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4470.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4490.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais à part les problèmes employés, la ligne 7, celle-ci, en rapport à la question de la protection accordée par le système juridique italien, à l'embryon, si le commun le considère.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4490.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4496.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bon, il s'agit d'une protection en fonction de sa potentialité.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4496.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4512.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Si on regarde même les problèmes, la loi numéro 40, et la ligne directrice, c'est la potentialité des vies qu'a en soi l'embryon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4513.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4514.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il s'agit d'un embryon humain.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4514.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4521.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, sa naturelle destination est serrée de devenir une vie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4521.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4529.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le système italien fait le choix d'accorder cette protection en fonction de leur vie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4529.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4548.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cette précision permet même d'aborder une question qui ressort de l'intervention du professeur De Luca, que, franchement, j'ai bien appréciée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4549.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4556.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, il dit, mais il serait hypocrite d'utiliser des lignes cellulaires.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4556.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4563.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je précise maintenant qu'il s'agit des lignes cellulaires, des cellules souches, je crois.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4563.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4574.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les mots précis, c'est pas exactement l'embryon, des cellules qui sont dérivées des embryons qui ont perdu leur potentialité de vie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4574.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4577.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quand on utilise ces cellules souches.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4578.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4585.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, il dit, mais ça serait hypocrite parce qu'on permet de faire la recherche sur les cellules souches.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4585.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4620.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais je dis, alors, si on protège la potentialité des vies, et ça, c'est le choix, dans le sens du choix dans lequel va l'ordre juridique italien, alors si on utilise les cellules souches, on n'est pas en contradiction avec cette direction, c'est-à-dire de protéger la potentialité des vies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4620.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4633.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lorsque les cellules souches sont désormais des cellules qui ont des potentialités énormes de se développer, mais jamais elles pourraient donner origine à l'être humain.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4633.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4642.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bien sûr, l'ordre juridique considère la différence, les différentes tapes de ce développement de la vie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4642.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4648.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et donc, la protection accordée est différente.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4648.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4658.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En vue de cette potentialité de développement, on peut parler de protection ou de recherche.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4658.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4661.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On peut parler de protection ou de respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4661.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4688.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais après, quand il y a la grossesse, alors la question change, parce qu'il y a même à comparer la situation de la mère, l'intérêt de la mère, la future mère, et de l'être qui va naître et qui sera une fois né, il sera sûrement un sujet de droit à plein titre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4688.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4701.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On peut même prévoir que déjà, celui qui va naître peut être, je dis, entre guillemets, sujet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4701.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4703.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais tout est...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4703.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4713.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il s'agit d'une situation en attendant l'avènement de la naissance qui est protégée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4713.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4719.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais elle sera définitivement acquise seulement quand il aura la naissance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4719.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4732.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, c'est une ordre juridique qui se passe, se bouche les yeux sur les problèmes de différentes étapes du développement de la vie humaine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4732.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4742.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pour ce qui concerne les embryons, son choix est de protéger la potentialité des vies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4742.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4759.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est pour ça qu'utiliser des cellules souches pour la recherche, c'est autre chose, qu'utiliser un embryon dont on doit supprimer la potentialité des vies humaines.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4759.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4763.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est dans le point de vue de l'État.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4763.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4766.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est très, très différent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4766.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4773.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je viens maintenant à une question qui a été posée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4773.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4779.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Elle regarde l'article...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4779.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4786.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Elle regarde, au gouvernement italien, les champs d'application de l'article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4786.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4789.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Comment il les considère?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4789.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4795.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bon, auparavant, je dis qu'en effet, le premier protocole doit être exclu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4795.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4805.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Avec quelques efforts, on pourrait considérer les champs d'application de l'article 8 seulement de façon indirecte.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4805.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4826.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est-à-dire, lorsque la récréante avait ses projets de se faire une famille avec son compagnon, et malheureusement, son compagnon est décédé, d'un certain côté, ça est lié à ses projets qui ont échoué.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4826.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4830.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais c'est seulement dans un sens indirect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4830.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4849.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ce que je doute vraiment, et en répondant à la question qui a été expressement posée, je vais vous faire connaître mes doutes, c'est en effet de la qualité des victimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4849.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4850.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais pourquoi?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4850.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4870.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Si nous examinons comment s'est passée la chose, nous voyons que la récréante s'était soumise à des pratiques de procréation médicalement assistée en 2002.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4870.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4878.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Malheureusement, en 2003, elle a perdu son compagnon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4878.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4906.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jusqu'en 2004, c'est-à-dire jusqu'en mars 2004, avant l'entrée en vigueur de la loi numéro 40, elle pouvait en effet donner ses embryons à la recherche parce qu'il n'y avait pas une situation réglée en Italie sur ces sujets.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4906.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4912.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Elle ne l'a pas fait, on peut dire que c'est un choix qui doit mourir.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4912.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4920.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Si on l'a fait d'emblée tout de suite après cet événement terrible, on peut l'accepter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4920.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4941.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais moi, j'attire l'attention sur l'effet qu'avant le recours à la cour, c'est-à-dire en 2011, la partie récréante n'a rien fait pour manifester son désir de donner ses embryons à la recherche.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4941.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4950.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moi, je dis enfin, je laisse la parole à mon collègue qui va parler des autres aspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4950.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4968.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais j'insiste que nous sommes appelés à évaluer si nous voulons vraiment aller au fond de l'affaire parce qu'il y a des considérations qui pourraient arrêter l'examen à la phase de la récevabilité.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4968.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4987.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Parce que si nous avons vu, donc, il ne s'agit pas de voir la liberté de la recherche scientifique parce que la récréante n'est pas porteuse de cet intérêt directement, mais elle a seulement ses désirs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4987.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5002.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, la difficulté même de les lier à la ville, à le champ d'application de l'article 8, on pourrait bien conclure, pour la récevabilité de la requête.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5002.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5017.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais enfin, si la cour désirait trancher l'affaire dans les fonds, il faut vraiment considérer que l'OG c'est lui.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5017.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5040.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La cohérence avec les choix de l'Italie dans lesquels elle a un plein marge d'appréciation, comme je venais de le rappeler, sur la base de la jurisprudence de la cour.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5040.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5044.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Si ce choix est cohérent, il faut s'arrêter à ça.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5044.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5070.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il faut se rappeler qu'il n'y a pas une notion médicale sur la nature de l'embryon précis de laquelle les travaux préparatoires sont partis, sans doute pour arriver, celle qui était une solution des compromis dans des différentes opinions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5070.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5096.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mais le choix de privilégier la potentialité des vies de l'embryon, ça constitue un but légitime auquel le gouvernement italien peut attendre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5096.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5123.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je rappelle aussi que les situations de point de vue de la protection juridique de l'embryon, du fœtus et de l'enfant né, elles sont bien différentes, mais elles ne sont pas en contradiction avec cette protection que l'ordre juridique italien, à présent, va accorder à l'embryon dans ses potentialités de vie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5123.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5123.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, c'était un plaisir.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5133.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5136.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Good morning, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5136.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5140.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Good morning, Mrs. and Mr. Judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5140.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5148.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I've heard with great interest the intervention of Professor DeLuca before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5148.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5153.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He made us a very interesting lesson about regenerative medicine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5153.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5159.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He discussed about whether embryos shall be considered or not individuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5159.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5171.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He tried to demonstrate us that cell lines taken by embryos are fundamental for the scientific research.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5171.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5174.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is very interesting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5174.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5187.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But here, now, we are not discussing about the question whether the scientific research shall be protected or not in Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5187.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5189.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are discussing about something different.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5189.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5207.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The discussion today is whether the rights protected by the applicants, protected by Article 1 of Protocol 1 and by Article 8 of the Convention have been violated or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5207.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5228.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, I see from some question made by the court before that there is still some need to clear again, which is the difference between embryos and cell lines.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5228.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5230.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope to try.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5230.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5233.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I try to be as clear as possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5233.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5242.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I want to point out that the scientific research is made with cell lines.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5242.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5244.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not made on embryos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5247.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5261.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To produce cell lines, the destruction of an embryo is needed because cell lines are taken by embryos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5261.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5273.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once a cell line has been produced, the cell line may be reproduced without any limit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5273.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5278.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It reproduces automatically without any limitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5278.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5283.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we have thousands and thousands and thousands of cell lines.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5283.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5288.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I beg the professors if my technical language is not very precise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5288.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5298.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Italy, the research on cell lines is allowed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5298.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5303.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do make research on cell lines.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5303.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5321.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The research is made using cell lines produced abroad, produced in those countries where it's permitted to take cell lines from an embryo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5321.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5325.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this could seem incoherent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5328.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5332.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's why I have to point out one thing more.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5332.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5348.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The production of these cell lines used for research in Italy is not made on request of the Italian authorities or of the Italian scientists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5348.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5356.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cell lines are available for the scientific community all over the world whenever they are produced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5356.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5375.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if cell lines are produced by destroying an embryo in the country X, all the scientists of any other country of the world may have access to these cell lines and use it for the research.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5379.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5391.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this means that there is never a request from the Italian authorities to destroy embryos to produce cell lines for scientific research.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5395.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5401.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Monsieur Mauro Pellegrini, votre temps de parole est déjà largement expiré.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5401.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5403.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc je vous prie peut-être de conclure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5403.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5404.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5405.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5416.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I said this because there were two questions, as far as I remember, made by Judge Caracas and Judge Bucinich.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5416.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5429.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is to say, which are the aim pursued by Article 13 of the Italian legislation, Law 40 of 2004?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5429.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5439.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, the aim of the law is not to protect the embryo as it is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5439.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5446.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The aim is to protect the embryo in relation to its potentiality to become a human being.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5446.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5450.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The potentiality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5450.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5463.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant tries to convince us that the destiny of cryopreserved embryos is the extinction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5463.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5466.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is not true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5466.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5484.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since 2005, as already my colleague said before, the National Committee for Bioethics posed a problem of the destiny of the embryos cryopreserved and never more used by the couple who generated them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5484.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5492.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The solution proposed in 2005 by this committee was the so-called adoption for birth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5492.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5503.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is to say, the possibility of using this embryos, cryoconserved, for procreation of infertile couples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5503.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5510.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This possibility, so this solution, has now became a reality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5510.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5526.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since last week, there is this very important judgment made by the Constitutional Italian Court, which established that from now on it's possible in Italy the non-partner fertilization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5526.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5543.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is to say that the possibility of using this cryopreserved embryos for use of fertilization of couple non-fertile for procreation, sorry, for non-fertile couples is now a reality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5543.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5553.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the legitimate scope pursued by Article 13 of Law 40 of 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5553.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5558.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is the answer that we can give to the question number two of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5556.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5563.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Monsieur Mauro Pellegrini, je dois encore une fois vous rendre attentif que vous avez déjà dépassé le temps imparti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5563.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5568.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous êtes à 20 minutes. Normalement, c'est 10 minutes. Il y a eu des questions, c'est vrai, mais je vous prie de conclure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5568.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5568.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5568.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5576.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If you want, I have to answer to some question already made by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5576.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5578.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I try to do it briefly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5578.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5581.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What happened before 2004?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5581.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5586.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before 2004, there was no legislation in force concerning this matter in Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5586.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5589.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This matter was unregulated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5589.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5590.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So no rules, no monitoring.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5590.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5595.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a far west.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5595.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5597.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What else?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5598.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5607.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Monsieur Mahwapedi, je dois vous arrêter malheureusement maintenant parce que le temps est expiré largement et je donne la parole au requérant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5610.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5611.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous avez la parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5611.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5611.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Qui veut prendre la parole?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5615.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5621.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>20 minutes pour vous également, puisque le gouvernement a pu répliquer pendant 20 minutes, donc vous aurez 20 minutes pour faire vos développements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP4</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5625.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5627.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, I try to be very, very short, OK?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5627.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5635.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because the time will be very, because there will be lots of issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5635.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5641.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That the embryonic stem cell lines are different from the embryo is simply not correct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5641.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5648.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because the embryo, the in vitro fertilized embryo, is a cluster of cells, right?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5648.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5653.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if you take out one of these, you make a line, that's an ES cell line.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5653.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5660.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Each of these cells has the potentiality to become a human being.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5660.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5673.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As has been shown in a recent paper in Nature, where people have taken the in vitro fertilized cells, took one of the cells, and developed independently as something that could become a human being.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5673.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5681.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, you have to destroy so-called a cluster of cells to make an ES cell line.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5681.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5691.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if you do this in Switzerland, in England, or in Sweden, you can take the cells and use it in Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5691.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5693.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But you cannot use the embryos in Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5693.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5697.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is inconsistent, in my opinion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5697.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5701.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donation to a third party.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5701.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5707.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case, specifically in the case of Parillo, the heterologous donation become available since a few months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5707.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5720.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the time where the in vitro fertilization was done, all the tests that are needed for a donor to give rise to an embryonic stem cell to donate it to somebody were not done.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5720.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5726.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because for the autologous in vitro fertilization, they are not requested.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5726.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5735.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, in any case, Parillo cannot give its embryos to a third party.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5735.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5737.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's not possible to do it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5737.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5748.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One question was, what's the difference between the embryo in terms of in vitro fertilization and the fetus?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5748.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5749.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is a tremendous difference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5749.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5764.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I said at the beginning, the in vitro fertilization give rise to what is called an embryo, which is a cluster of cells which are identical to each other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5764.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5767.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no difference between those cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5767.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5770.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no development of any tissue or any organs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5770.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5777.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fetus is something that is much more similar to a human being than a cluster of cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5777.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5786.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the fetus, you can start to see feet, hand, trunk, probably a certain point the brain, and the heart.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5786.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5787.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So you cannot compare.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5787.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5791.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in fact, you cannot freeze down a fetus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5791.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5792.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But you can make abortion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5792.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5794.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's another inconsistency.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5794.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5799.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you can make abortion not in the interest of the baby, so of the fetus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5799.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5804.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You can make abortion in the interest of the mother that becomes, at that point, a patient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5807.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5817.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The other question that was raised, also from one of you, was the meaning of life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5817.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5822.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, if we go in the philosophy of the meaning of life, we can stay here for hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5822.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5823.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>OK?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5826.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5829.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would call these cells viable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5829.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5832.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the cells in our body are viable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5832.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5836.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even the embryonics themselves are viable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5836.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5839.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is life, from a philosophical point of view, I don't know.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5839.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5846.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is true, though, and this is exactly what they said, is they have the potential to become alive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5846.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5849.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is out of question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5849.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5857.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Think about what other cells have the potential to become alive in the sense of a human being.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5860.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5862.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The sperm cell, of course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5862.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5866.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The oocyte, they have this potentiality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5866.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5868.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have to manipulate them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5868.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5870.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You mix them together.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5870.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5872.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You make an in vitro fertilization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5872.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5878.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They acquire the potentiality to become a human being.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5878.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5880.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You just have to implant in the uterus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5880.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5889.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same thing, it happens with the in vitro reprogramming, with the autologous IPS, the Yamanaka cells.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5889.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5900.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If you take a skin, for instance, cell, which is viable in vital, and you make another type of manipulation, which is different from the in vitro manipulation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5900.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5902.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's another type of manipulation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5902.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5907.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You make exactly a pluripotent stem cell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5907.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5909.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Embryonic-like.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5909.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5915.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Embryonic-like, they're not identical because in terms of the biology, there are differences that people should address very carefully.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5915.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5922.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that cell implanted into a uterus will become a human being.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5922.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5929.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, also the IPS have the potentiality of becoming a human being and alive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5929.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5948.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if the IPS have the potentiality of becoming a human being in IPS, also my skin cell have the possibility and the potentiality to become a human being if manipulated and if implanted into uterus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5948.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5955.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So all these cells, after manipulation, they have the potentiality of becoming life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5955.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5958.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can work on the adult cells, yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5958.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5963.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can make science on the IPS, yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5963.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5966.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can I work on, can I make research on the in vitro fertilization?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5966.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5967.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5967.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5974.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is inconsistent because all of them have the potentiality to become life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5974.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6003.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of parrillo, in the case of many of these donated or sovereign numerare embryonic or embryos that are in the fridge, that are frozen down, in practical terms, because nobody's going to insert in the uterus of any woman one of these embryos that are there for four or five years or whatever.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6003.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6010.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is the potentiality of this cluster of cells that are in the fridge?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6010.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6012.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have two potentiality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6012.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6017.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One is to lose their viability with time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6017.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6025.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or even if they don't lose, they can stay alive, whatever, or viable forever.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6025.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6028.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we finally got immortality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6028.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6030.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But they would never be used for anything.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6030.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6033.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They just lay down in the fridge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6033.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6053.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or the other potentiality of those cells is to make research to find out a way to help all the humanity to find a solution for a certain number of disease, like other countries are doing this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6053.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6061.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that we have cell lines all around the world because we are still in a situation of research.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6061.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6074.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the moment those cells will become really useful from a clinical point of view, as Lawrence Studer, Bjorklund, and other people are showing around the world, we will need that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6074.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6085.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We will need to develop this in each country to help our people with the Parkinson's disease, our people with retinal blindness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6085.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6090.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, we need to have access to this and to use as a donation those embryos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6090.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6094.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm not talking about making embryo on purpose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6094.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6098.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm not talking about this, even though you could do this for therapeutic cloning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6098.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6100.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But forget about it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6100.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6107.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm talking about those embryos that are lying down in the fridge and can be, should be donated for research.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6107.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6129.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because the potentiality, I said again, the potentiality of those specific embryonic stem cells, a cluster of cells, is either to die out during time and never be used for any reason, or to be used to do research and science that can be useful for the entire community.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6129.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6134.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Avoid this, not allowing donation in my mind.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6134.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6136.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Paton is wrong, but it's not ethical.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6136.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6139.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It goes against the human rights, from my point of view.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6147.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6149.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci, professeur De Luca.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6149.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6153.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce qu'il y a quelqu'un d'autre qui veut encore prendre la parole?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6153.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6155.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ou non, la requérente?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6155.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6158.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous avez la parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6160.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6175.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Presidente, volevo rispondere alla domanda riguardante il fatto se la ricorrente aveva scelto di non avere impiantati gli embrioni per non essere una madre singola. In realtà i tempi in cui sono avvenute le cose non le hanno</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6175.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6179.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>proprio permesso neanche di prendere in considerazione questa scelta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6179.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6190.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il compagno della ricorrente è morto nell'attentato a Nassiria presso la base italiana che è avvenuto il 12 novembre 2003. La legge del 19 febbraio 2004 è</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6190.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6203.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>entrata in vigore il 10 marzo, quindi sono intercorsi meno di quattro mesi tra la morte del compagno e l'entrata in vigore della legge che le vietava tale eventuale impianto, quindi non è stata proprio presa in considerazione.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6203.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6222.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Colgo l'occasione, visto che si tratta di questioni temporali, di precisare una cosa riguardo la risposta del centro dove sono crioconservati gli embrioni riguardo il fatto che non possono essere utilizzati, risposta successiva alla proposizione del ricorso. In realtà è una mera formalità, l'avremmo anche</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6222.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6230.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>potuta non produrre, abbia stata formalizzata una risposta scritta a quella che era stata un'istanza orale e comunque c'era una legge che precludeva il tutto. Grazie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6237.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6247.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vorrei rispondere alla domanda se esisteva un contratto o meno fra il ricorrente e il centro che ha effettuato la fecondazione assistita.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6247.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6271.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A quell'epoca in effetti non era entrata ancora in vigore la legge 40 e quindi tutto questo, l'eventuale contratto non c'è stato, c'è stato un accordo di tipo medico per effettuare questa fecondazione assistita che era libera a quell'epoca, come era libera anche la ricerca scientifica sugli embrioni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6271.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6300.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La domanda conteneva anche un'altra richiesta, cioè la signora è sottoposta a un pagamento, attualmente non paga, non ha mai pagato, però proprio in questi periodi molti centri che hanno presso di loro gli embrioni priori conservati stanno chiedendo, mettendo fatture e chiedendo pagamento ai titolari di questi embrioni e quindi potenzialmente la ricorrente potrebbe essere debitrice di questo centro.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6300.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6305.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Attualmente però non ne è stata fatta alcuna richiesta di pagamento.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6305.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6328.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Per quanto riguarda la normativa precedente al 2003, l'ha già detto anche il Governo, c'era massima libertà, non c'era nessuna limitazione e successivamente con la legge 40 sono intervenute tutte le varie limitazioni che sono state in gran parte eliminate dall'ordinamento giuridico con la decisione della Corte Costituzionale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>it</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6328.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6344.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>È rimasta ancora la possibilità di donare gli embrioni per la ricerca scientifica, ma qualcosa è pendente di fronte alla Corte Costituzionale e, come ho detto all'inizio, è stata rinviata l'udienza che era stata fissata per l'8 aprile proprio in attesa della vostra decisione.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6357.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6358.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6358.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6359.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce qu'il y a encore des...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6359.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6363.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La requérante veut encore faire d'autres développements ou vous avez terminé?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6363.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6365.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vous avez terminé.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6367.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6369.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nous en arrivons alors au terme de l'audience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6370.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6377.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je remercie les comparants qui ont assisté la Cour par leurs interventions et leurs réponses à ces questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6377.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6381.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour va maintenant délibérer sur la recevabilité le fonds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6382.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6387.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les partis seront informés de toute décision que la Cour prendra sur l'affaire en objet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6387.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6389.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'audience est levée.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
