<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>4728715_18042018</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>15.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>16.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>52.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>53.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>66.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>74.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Ilyas and Ahmed versus Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>74.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>89.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on 25 September 2015 under Article 34 of the Convention by two Bangladeshi nationals, Mr. Ilyas Ilyas and Mr. Ali Ahmed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>89.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>97.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was allocated to the fourth section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>97.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>103.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on 7 October 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>103.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>113.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 14 March 2017, a chamber of the fourth section declared it partly admissible and adopted a judgment on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>113.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>130.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 14 June 2017, the government requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention, and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on 18 September 2017.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>130.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>147.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent government are represented by Mrs. Aranka Lőrincz Director, Office for Immigration and Asylum, Ministry of the Interior, Mrs. Zoltán Tallódi, Government Agent, and Mrs. Mónika Weller, Government Co-Agent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>147.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>162.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mrs. Barbara Pohárnok, Counsel, assisted by Mrs. Grusa Matevzic, lawyer at the Hungarian Helsinki Committee, Advisor, and Mrs. Nuala Mole from the AERI Center, Advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>162.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>167.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>167.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>179.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome the delegation of judges from the Court of Cassation of Greece, including the President and Madam Prosecutor General, and the delegation of Greek prosecutors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>179.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>184.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I furthermore welcome the following groups who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>184.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>205.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The group of Turkish judges and prosecutors, the group of judges and prosecutors from Serbia, and the judges and prosecutors participating in the joint JUFREX program, coming from Serbia, Montenegro, Albania, the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia, Bosnia and Herzegovina, and Kosovo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>205.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>214.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>214.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>220.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Pohárnok for the applicants will speak first, and then Mrs. Zoltán Tallódi for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>220.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>238.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting into four other languages, Turkish, Serbian, Albanian, and Macedonian, has been authorized for the benefit of the groups of judges and prosecutors attending this hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>238.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>246.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>246.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>247.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mrs. Pohárnok.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>247.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>248.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor, please, Madam.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>256.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>260.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Members of the Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>260.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>265.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>allow me to bring you back to September 2015 with a quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>265.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>275.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It all began at half past 11 in the morning when they let us in and said that they will take our fingerprints and then give us refugee status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>275.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>283.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We were inside until half past five when they brought us the decision that they do not give us refugee status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>283.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>287.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then they told us we either leave or they put us in jail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>287.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>292.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We wanted to appeal, but they told us that it won't do any good.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>292.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>294.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's better for you to leave.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>294.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>297.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I did not want to come to a prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>297.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>299.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I could have done it in Syria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>299.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>304.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, these are the words of a Syrian</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>304.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>315.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>asylum seeker interviewed on the 17th of September 2015, right after he left the transit zone on the Serbian-Hungarian border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>315.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>332.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His testimony, annexed to our written submission, gives a truthful account of what was happening to asylum seekers admitted to these transit zones at the material time of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>332.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>346.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is in light of this context that the government's allegations denying procedural shortcomings and that Hungary returned genuine asylum seekers to Serbia should be assessed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>346.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>365.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Except for families with minor children, all asylum seekers, regardless of nationality or vulnerability, were subjected to summary procedures concluded within a day without the minimum safeguards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>365.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>369.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What makes the case of Mr. Ilyas and Mr. Ahmed special</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>369.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>381.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is that, unlike most asylum seekers, other asylum seekers, they refused to leave the transit zone and to withdraw their asylum claim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>381.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>386.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a consequence, they ended up in detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>386.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>393.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They trusted the system and hoped that, in the end, they would be protected from injustice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>393.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>395.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it did not happen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>395.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>401.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now they have come to this court to find justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>401.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>404.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>404.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>407.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the case of Mr. Ilyas and Mr. Ahmed</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>407.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>426.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is a case about Hungary's, Hungarian government's, disregard of the essential procedural safeguards that ensure that no one is subjected to a risk of torture or inhuman treatment and no one is deprived of the right of an effective remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>426.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>443.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case is also about extrajudicial deprivation of liberty of two already traumatized human beings for three and a half weeks without any review by a competent court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>443.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>454.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As opposed to the government's allegations, the applicants did not come to this court to have a ruling on the merits of their asylum claim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>454.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>464.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They do not claim that asylum seekers should be granted an unconditional right to enter and remain in Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>464.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>474.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their claim is merely that if detention is used, it should be based on law and respect the necessary procedural safeguards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>474.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>477.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What they request you, Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>477.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>480.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is to find the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>480.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>498.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, that their expulsion, which lacked both rigorous scrutiny and access to effective judicial remedy, exposed them to a real risk of inhuman treatment and thus led to the violation of Article 3 and Article 13 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>498.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>511.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, that their arbitrary detention in Hungary, which lacked any legal grant and any possibility of judicial review, breached Article 5 and 5.4</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>511.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>512.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>512.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>530.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, that inhuman conditions during their arbitrary detention in Hungary, against which there was no opportunity to seek any remedy, breached Article 3 or Article 8 and Article 13 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>530.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>534.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why did the applicants stay in the transit zone?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>534.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>543.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because they wanted to find international protection and safety, despite the government's allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>543.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>546.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For instance, Mr. Ilias is an extremely vulnerable orphan</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>546.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>548.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>since the age of eight.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>548.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>558.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Most of his life, he lived undocumented outside of Bangladesh in precarious conditions, often exposed to extreme hardship, from arbitrary detention to child labor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>558.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>565.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even in Bangladesh, during the short period he could spend there, he was destitute, undocumented, and homeless.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>565.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>572.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He faced abuse and harassment from the ruling party for being involved with the political opposition party.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>572.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>577.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was also under constant harassment by the Bangladeshi police.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>577.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>583.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Eventually, he was expelled from his own country for being an undocumented migrant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>583.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>598.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While he was detained in the Hungarian transit zone, Hungary granted refugee status to another asylum seeker from Bangladesh for risk of persecution due to his political affiliation, which was the same as Mr. Ilias's.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>598.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>608.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During their journey to Europe, both applicants had been vagrant and victim of forced labor whilst at the mercy of gangmasters and smugglers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>608.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>619.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then in Greece, they again became victims of forced labor in human treatment and conditions at the infamous Manolada farm.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>619.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>630.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They shared the fate of the Bangladeshi fruit pickers of this farm, who this court had found to be victims of violation of Article 4 of the Convention in the Chaudhry case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>633.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>644.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court is best placed to know of the deficiencies of the asylum system in Greece, unchanged in 2015, for which Greece was also held responsible for in MSS.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>647.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>661.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Medicare reports, while the applicants were detained in the Hungarian transit zone, both applicants were diagnosed with post-traumatic stress disorder.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>661.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>667.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Ilias had signs of past treatment on his body.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>667.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>669.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Ahmed also had depression.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>672.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>674.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, in our submission this morning,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>674.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>679.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will address three issues in relation to the merits of our complaint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>682.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>692.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first, I will demonstrate the arguability of Article 3, why and in what form the applicants were facing risk of retreatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>692.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>702.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, I will demonstrate why the applicants' expulsion to Serbia led to the breach of Article 3 and Article 13.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>702.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>713.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third, I will demonstrate why the transit zone was the detention, why it was unlawful and arbitrary in breach of Article 5 and 5.4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>718.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>725.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I will start with the first point, the arguability of the applicant's claim with respect to Serbia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>725.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>748.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All major international organizations, UN bodies such as the UNHCR, UN Committee Against Torture, UN Human Rights Committee, the EU Commission, reputable NGOs, and even other EU member states like Germany, Austria, and Belgium stated at the material time that Serbia was not safe for asylum seekers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>748.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>749.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>749.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>762.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mainly because of the serious deficiencies of the asylum system, including lack of access to the procedure, the absence of reception conditions, and the risk of chain refoulement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>762.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>779.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unlawful pushbacks and expulsions from Serbia to former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia, FIROM, and further on to Greece and Turkey, or even to countries of origin such as Syria, took place as routine practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>779.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>794.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As admitted by Serbian state representatives in the evidence submitted, Serbia was automatically applying its own safe third country list, which included FIROM and all its neighboring states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>797.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>812.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court granted interim measures against Serbia, preventing returns to FIROM and Montenegro, initially in June 2015, again in 2016, and in 2017.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>812.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>824.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, even the Hungarian asylum office stopped issuing safe third country inadmissibility decisions regarding Serbia in the middle of 2017 entirely.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>827.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>830.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But Mr. Ilias and Mr. Ahmed's situation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>830.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>835.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was special, and even worse at the material time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>835.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>836.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>836.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>843.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because they were rejected asylum seekers expelled by Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>843.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>861.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was a well-known fact that asylum seekers rejected by Hungary did not have the right to lawfully enter Serbian territory, to apply for asylum, or to receive any kind of reception conditions in Serbia, not even basic food and shelter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>861.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>881.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under domestic law, Hungary had to apply the readmission agreement and had to ensure that Serbia officially takes back rejected asylum seekers, including the applicants, and grants them access to the asylum procedure and reception conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>881.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>886.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the absence of this, Hungary could not expel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>886.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>892.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, had to continue and examine the asylum applications on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>892.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>900.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In reality, by September 2015, readmission procedures were already suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>900.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>916.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Serbian state officials stated in the media that Serbia would stop Hungary returning rejected asylum seekers with all its powers involving the army and not accept anyone Hungary attempts to return under duress.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>919.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>936.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a fact that in the applicant's specific case, Hungary never initiated the readmission procedure, never contacted the Serbian authorities, although their expulsion was based on the readmission agreement with Serbia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>936.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>951.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also a fact that the exit area of the transit zone where rejected asylum seekers were forced to leave to is Hungarian territory outside the state border of Serbia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>951.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>963.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, it was of utmost importance that Serbia officially takes back the applicants as asylum seekers and grants them access to the asylum procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>963.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>973.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, as the evidence show, on 8 October 2015, the applicants were forced to leave the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>973.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>982.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then the Serbian officials did not let them enter Serbia despite them asking for it with the assistance of UNHCR.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>982.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>985.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then they had to enter irregularly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>985.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1010.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By their expulsion, the applicants either faced destitution on the border of the two countries or because of eventually entering Serbia irregularly without the right to apply for asylum, they were left destitute, facing harassment and abuse by the Serbian police, risk of arrest, misdemeanor procedures, fines, and deportation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1010.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1020.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They faced the risk of automatic chain refoulement to FIROM and Greece, where the risk of Article 3 violation was unanimously established by the chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1024.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1026.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, at the material time,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1026.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1034.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hungary did not reject the applicants' asylum claim and expelled them due to the lack of persecution in Bangladesh.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1034.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1043.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hungary chose not to examine their asylum claim on the merits, but decided that Serbia should do it for them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1043.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1048.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is why they were expelled from Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1048.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1057.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Publicly available evidence that laid before the Hungarian authorities showed that Mr. Elias and Mr. Ahmed had arguable claims under Article</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1057.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1059.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>3 with regard to Serbia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1065.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1077.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This brings me to the second point of today's submission, which is why Hungary violated Article 3 and Article 13 in relation to the applicants' expulsion to Serbia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1077.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1085.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the core of the complaints is that Hungary expelled the applicants without examining with rigorous scrutiny.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1085.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1094.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And by denying the basic procedural safeguards, the applicants clearly argued their claims with regard to Serbia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1094.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1097.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the applicants fully</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1097.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1106.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>accept that the existence of the government decree entailing the safe third country list did not in itself violate Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1106.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1119.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was the manner of implementation that rendered the domestic proceedings to be in breach of convention standards, despite the applicants' clear, arguable claim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1119.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1130.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The complaint deficiencies have been observed by multiple bodies, including UN bodies, the CPT, the Commissioner for Human Rights, EU Commission and NGOs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1130.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1138.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Eventually, these were the primary basis for the chamber to find unanimously the Article 3 violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1138.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1147.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under this second point, now I will present the two most flagrant violations from our written submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1147.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1158.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, Hungary failed to apply the convention standards in relation to the subject and scope of Article 3 risk assessment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1158.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1167.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hungary simply did not examine the relevant facts, which I listed under the first point today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1167.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1183.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It unlawfully required the applicants to prove that they had individually suffered past ill treatment while transiting through Serbia, instead of examining the future ill treatment, the risk of future ill treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1183.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1201.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hungary ignored the evidence described in the publicly available country information reports, including UNHCR's findings, on which the applicants specifically relied, which alone was against domestic law and this court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1201.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1208.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That the authorities' conclusion on this report was biased, superficial, and distorted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1208.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1214.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That the burden of proof placed on the applicants was far too excessive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1214.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1223.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second most flagrant violation is the ineffectiveness of the domestic judicial remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1223.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1237.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Domestic law explicitly prohibited the competent Hungarian court to conduct an ex-nunc judicial review and to examine the applicant's submissions, facts, and evidence in the second procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1237.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1243.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For instance, the medical opinion, the country information, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1243.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1245.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1245.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1257.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>now I will turn to our third point of today's submission, the extrajudicial detention of Mr. Elias and Mr. Ahmed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1257.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1261.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under this third point, I will address three issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1261.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1268.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, I will argue that the transit zone placement was deprivation of liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1268.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1272.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, that it was unlawful and arbitrary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1272.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1279.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third, that there was no judicial remedy available for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1279.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1282.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first issue is the definition of detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1285.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1292.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What did the place look like at the time when Mr. Elias and Mr. Ahmed, two traumatized asylum seekers,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1292.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1297.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>were staying there for 3 and 1 1 weeks?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1297.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1307.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, the place resembled a cage in the middle of nowhere, fenced in with high barbed wire fence and rows of razor blade wire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1307.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1315.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were constantly controlled and monitored by armed police, border guard officers, security guards, and cameras.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1315.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1320.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Elias and Mr. Ahmed lived in a container</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1320.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1330.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with not more than one to two square meters free space and a narrow strip as an outside area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1330.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1341.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No privacy, total isolation from the outside world, with no possibility of communication and no meaningful activities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1341.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1347.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants could not leave the place towards Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1347.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1364.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And contrary to the government's allegation, it would not have been their free choice to leave in the direction of Serbia, because leaving would have meant abandoning their asylum claims, asylum procedures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1364.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1370.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They could not re-enter the transit zone and feared ill treatment upon exiting the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1373.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1378.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is the legal definition of the deprivation of liberty?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1378.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1383.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Your court has already given a definition in many cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1383.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1390.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The legitimacy of which the government, in fact, have explicitly accepted in their written submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1390.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1410.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Deprivation of liberty is to be assessed in light of a wide range of factors, such as the type, duration, effect, and manner of implementation of the restrictive measures, the degree of supervision and control, extent of isolation, availability of social contacts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1410.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1420.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The theoretical possibility to leave the place of confinement is only one among the several factors in this definition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1420.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1424.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court has already found the applicability of Article 5.1</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1424.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1440.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in transit zone cases in Amur, in Shamshen, and in Riyadh and Lidiab, despite the fact that it was possible for the applicants to voluntarily leave the country where they wished to take refuge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1440.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1451.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the arguability of the non-reformant claim is not a decisive factor whether the deprivation of liberty falls within the scope of Article 5.1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1454.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1456.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quite the opposite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1456.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1467.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such attempts from governments were explicitly rejected by this court as early as Amur, more than two decades ago.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1467.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1475.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, lack of acceptance of the asylum seekers by the receiving country was a relevant fact in these cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1475.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1480.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, according to this court, findings in Casparov detention may violate Article 5.1,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1480.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1491.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>even though the person concerned has agreed to it, or as had in HL or Stanov, if given himself up to be taken into detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1491.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1505.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the specific facts of the present case, the court will recall that the transit zone was and still is a place of detention, according to several UN and Council of Europe institutions, as well as academics and NGOs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1505.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1513.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Importantly, the CPT itself has always considered the transit zone as a place of detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1513.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1523.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Recently, even Hungarian courts started issuing judgments in which they define placement in the transit zone as deprivation of liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1525.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1534.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, it is against this backdrop that the government still insists on saying that the applicants were not detained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1534.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1544.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They argue that the Amur principles and your consistent case law do not apply to the specific facts of this case, of Mr. Ilyas</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1544.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1547.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. Ahmed's present case, because</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1547.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1550.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the lack of risk of persecution in Serbia and Bangladesh.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1550.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1569.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Related to this argument, the Hungarian and the Russian governments are implying that Habas corpus rights should only be granted to those who can prove before any decision on that issue that they face ill treatment upon leaving the country where they seek refuge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1569.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1572.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is fundamentally wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1572.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1585.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is undisputed that every person has the right to ask for international protection, as most recently reinforced in AEA versus Greece, and be protected from ill treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1585.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1619.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our submission is that every person entitled to be guaranteed Habas corpus rights by the state which has jurisdiction over them, as long as this person is waiting for the decision on their asylum claim or for a decision on their return, no person, regardless of their nationality or merits of their claim, of their asylum claim, should be accepted to renounce their Habas corpus rights and return to ill treatment for the sake of regaining their personal liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1621.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1635.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Every person should be granted at least the chance to show the arguability of their claim under Article 3 in a procedure that satisfies the convention before any remover can take place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1635.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1640.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the government is wrong about the facts of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1640.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1649.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In light of the report and other evidence, the applicants had an arguable claim with respect to Serbia and onward to Greece.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1649.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1651.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, it is based on these considerations</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1651.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1655.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that Mr. Elias and Mr. Ahmed were actually</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1655.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1672.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>deprived of their liberty while waiting for the outcome of their asylum proceedings, in which Hungary was supposed to examine their arguable claim, despite the exit gate in the direction of Serbia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1672.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1678.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I will turn to the second issue of why the applicant's detention was unlawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1684.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1687.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will address three points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1687.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1690.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the lack of legal basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1690.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1697.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the lack of individualized assessment as regards necessity and proportionality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1697.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1705.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third, the inapplicability of the government's argument concerning border procedures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1705.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1712.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first point is that the applicant's detention was unlawful within the meaning of Article 5.1</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1712.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1719.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because it was not in accordance with national law and had no legal basis in national law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1719.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1724.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Elias and Mr. Ahmed never received a decision</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1724.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1737.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>nor information on the fact that they were detained under what law, for what reasons, on what conditions, for exactly how long, and with what remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1737.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1773.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Grand Chamber reinforced its consistent case law in Claifia, the lack of specific legal provision underlying detention, the absence of a decision on detention, and the absence of judicial authorization, contrary to the principle of legal certainty, and these deficiencies should alone suffice for the conclusion that the applicant's detention was devoid of legal basis and arbitrary under national law and consequently under Article 5.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1773.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1802.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our second point is that the applicant's detention was arbitrary because the Hungarian authorities failed to carry out an individualized assessment and examine whether detention was necessary and proportionate in the applicant's individual case, despite the clear legal obligations under domestic law on detention of asylum seekers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1802.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1816.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This alone should also suffice for fighting a violation of the convention, as it was established by this court in the case of OM versus Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1816.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1827.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our third point concerns the government's allegation that the national rules on border procedure should be considered sufficient legal basis for their detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1827.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1830.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government is wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1830.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1853.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if this piece of law would be acceptable in the first place, the quality of the law is not compatible with the general convention principles, the rule of law, legal certainty, proportionality, and the principle of protection against arbitrariness, the very aim of Article 5.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1853.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1866.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today, I would like to emphasize in the following five points why the government's stance is totally unacceptable in the applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1866.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1881.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the border procedure provisions suggested by the government exclusively concerned the asylum procedure process at the border transit zones, but not the issue of persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1881.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1887.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But not the issue of personal liberty detention in the transit zones.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1890.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1904.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is clear that this law simply did not say a word about detention, about related judicial remedy, or about assessing vulnerability, as it was confirmed by the chamber judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1904.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1915.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second point, the government cannot possibly state that Mr. Ilyas and Mr. Ahmed were not detained</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1915.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1921.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and state at the same time that they should have known what the legal basis was for their detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1924.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1937.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Three, the two educated applicants could not possibly foresee anything about their detention without ever receiving any decision or adequate information on their detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1937.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1948.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is more, none of the documents issued in the Hungarian proceedings concerned their placement in the transit zone as such.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1948.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1973.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Four, the applicants whose mother tongue is Bangla and who are illiterate in Urdu language were only given written information leaflet in Urdu language, which did not contain anything about detention and which was of insufficient quality, as stated by the witness statement, which we submitted to the chamber on 28th of March.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1976.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1998.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Five, as opposed to the government, the fact remains that the applicants who were diagnosed with post-traumatic stress disorder remained detained despite the medical evidence and their written requests to be released based exactly on the border procedures exclusion clause.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2001.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2007.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, I address our third point about the applicant's detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2007.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2012.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants on lawful detention was also in breach of Article 5.4,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2012.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2027.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>given the fact that there was no opportunity either in law or in practice for the applicants to have their detention reviewed by any authority, let alone a judicial one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2027.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2047.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As opposed to the government, domestic law on border procedure did not allow the court in the applicant's case to review the lawfulness of their stay in the transit zone, not even the applicability of the border procedure itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2047.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2052.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was explicitly stated in the final court decision in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2055.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2057.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2057.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2068.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the government explicitly acknowledged the legitimacy of your consistent case law applied unanimously by the chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2068.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2089.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government was not correct about the relevant facts of the case and did not present any persuasive or legitimate reason that could justify for the Grand Chamber to reverse from the consistent case law on detention in transit zones and on standards of the necessary procedural safeguards in Article 3 cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2092.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2102.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we request the Grand Chamber to find that Hungary violated Mr. Ilyas and Mr. Ahmed's rights</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2102.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2108.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>under Article 3, Article 13, Article 5, Article 5.4,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2108.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2110.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2110.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2111.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2116.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2119.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mrs. Pohárnok.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2119.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2121.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I call Mr.Tallódi, have the floor, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2128.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2130.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2130.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2143.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable members of the court, ladies and gentlemen, it's a privilege and a pleasure to have the opportunity to appear before the court to present the oral submissions on behalf of the government of Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2143.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2151.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has directed the government to react to the applicants' observations in their oral pleadings at this hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2151.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2169.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although this method is not appropriate to correct each and every false presentation of facts, or flawed arguments in the applicants' submissions, to point out their irrelevance to the present case, the government considered that the court should not be lost in those details anyway.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2169.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2181.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those details would be relevant only if the court decided to endorse a universal right to free movement of persons across borders, which I hope I can dissuade you from.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2181.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2194.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, however, let me note that the applicants' observations didn't reveal any meaningful information about their present legal status in Germany and Spain, respectively.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2194.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2212.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have presented a moving story of their sufferings as a result of their bad decisions made in their quest for a better life in the course of their journey to Europe, but they still have not submitted a credible story of their persecution in their home country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2212.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2220.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second applicant still claims to have left Bangladesh because of his poverty and loss of family caused by a flood.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2220.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2234.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He stated that he resided in Spain with a new identity, new name and date of birth, but he had not applied for asylum there, and he is not known to the Spanish immigration authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2234.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2251.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first applicant's story has become more refined and sophisticated, possible for the benefit of the asylum proceedings in Germany, but it is still not credible enough to have convinced the German authorities of his need for international protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2251.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2266.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's request for asylum having been rejected, he was ordered to leave Germany by the 7th of December, 2017, but it seems that he was overstayed his welcome and he's still in Germany.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2266.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2282.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It appears that he can enjoy a tolerated status in Germany as long as his home country refuses to take him back, or until he decides to leave voluntarily, because otherwise the German authorities have no means to remove him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2282.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2316.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the court can satisfy that the applicants are all well, happily defying the law in Europe, and that the Hungarian authorities being very much aware of the realities of the process of migration in Europe were right in concluding that the applicants didn't face the risk of ill treatment or chain refoulement in Serbia, in spite of all anxiety and concerns raised by the NGOs or the UNHCR wanting to facilitate migrants' access to the country of their chosen destination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2316.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2347.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the applicants in the present case are formally two Bangladeshi nationals who have a real stake in the present proceedings for a compensation claim of 15,000 euros each, the real stakeholders in this case are the NGOs acting as representatives for the applicants or intervening as third parties, which are advocates of the recognition of the right to asylum shopping and of the universal right to free movement of persons across borders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2347.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2370.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me remind you that these purported rights are not yet recognized in international law, and even if the honorable members of this court consider such development of international law desirable, that decision is not for a judicial authority to make, not even under the pretense of interpretation of the Convention as a living instrument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2370.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2393.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For such interpretation only means the adaptation of the vague notions used in the provisions of the Convention to the actual changes in society, to social reality, and not making society adapt some political goals not envisioned by the drafters of the Convention or by the states which have later acceded to that instrument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2393.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2397.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2397.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2414.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>this leads us to the real issue raised by this case, whether there is a right to have access to the country of chosen destination, whether there is a right to asylum shopping in international law, or a universal right to free movement of persons across borders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2414.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2434.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can any of those purported rights be derived from the Convention by way of interpretation, or do they constitute political goals formulated in human rights language whose achievement needs a political decision by the lawmakers, both in international and national law?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2434.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2479.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While the NGOs acting as representatives for the applicants or intervening as third parties, as well as the UNHCR advocate the recognition of the right to asylum shopping and of the universal right to free movement of persons across borders with a view to facilitating access to European standard of living for as many people as possible, and thus strive to have the notion of liberty under Article V be defined as the freedom to go wherever you want, the court must keep to the presently applied notion of personal liberty, allowing the inherent legal restraints without requiring individual judicial decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2479.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2495.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should we accept the applicant's definition of liberty, we would need a fully reasoned judicial decision every time we denied anyone entry to our home, or to mention a close example, to the building of this court or to the premises of any public offices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2495.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2502.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What difference does it make if the gates of that office are at the border or inland of a state?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2502.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2508.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What difference does it make if it is our private home or the common home of a community?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2508.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2517.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Denial of entry is a restriction of liberty only if the person denied entry clearly has a legal entitlement to enter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2517.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2528.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do asylum seekers have an automatic right to enter the country, simple on account of a claim for asylum, irrespective of the well-foundedness of that claim?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2528.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2532.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is an issue for the national legislator to regulate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2532.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2536.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under Hungarian law, the applicants did not have such a right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2536.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2544.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, their liberty was not restricted when they were not allowed to enter the territory of Hungary beyond the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2544.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2555.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or if a broader notion of liberty is applied, their freedom to do as they wished was subject to an inherent limitation stemming from the lack of the right to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2555.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2565.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, no issue of restriction of liberty arose in the present case, which should have been the subject of a judicial decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2565.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2575.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To conclude otherwise, it would be tantamount to a judicial recognition of an unconditional right to enter the country, a right to free movement across borders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2575.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2607.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this point, it must be noted that when the third party submissions are concerned about the restriction of the asylum seekers' freedom of movement, it is to be understood as a reference to a purported freedom of movement across borders, since freedom of movement, as provided for in Article 2 of Protocol Number 4 to the Convention, is well known to be a liberty of movement within the territory of a state, restricted to those lawfully within the territory of a state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2607.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2613.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, those who already have been granted leave to enter and stay in the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2613.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2626.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No mention is made in the Convention of a freedom of movement across borders, thus the legal basis for the third party's concerns in this respect is completely lacking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2626.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2658.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Considering the additional protocols have never restricted, only specified or supplemented the rights enshrined in the Convention, we cannot conclude that the scope of Article 5 is broader in respect of the liberty of movement than that of Article 2 of Protocol Number 4, and thus Article 5 cannot be interpreted to include a right to free movement across borders, as claimed by the applicants and the third parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2658.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2663.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no universally recognized right to free movement across borders either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2663.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2677.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Free movement is recognized by some regional arrangements, such as in the European Union, as a privilege accorded to the citizens of the states taking part in a special form of international cooperation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2677.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2683.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This privilege cannot be extended as a universal human right by judicial interpretation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2683.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2696.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is the court-settled case law that, in accordance with well-established international law, contracting states have the right to control the entry, residence, and removal of alliance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2696.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2708.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also know from the jurisprudence of the court that the rights enshrined by the Convention must be interpreted in a manner so as not to make them illusory or theoretical.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2708.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2712.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That should apply to the rights of the contracting states too.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2712.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2714.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why is that so?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2714.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2719.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You could ask, since states' rights are not human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2719.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2752.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because the states, contrary to the picture painted of them by human rights NGOs and some advocates of supranational global governance, are not to be regarded as an abstract entity with the power of repressing human freedom and to be eliminated as a leviathan, but the community of people exercising their right to self-determination within the framework of a social contract, creating an institutional structure for the protection of their well-being and achieving their common goals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2752.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2773.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this sense, states' rights necessary to fulfill their tasks conferred upon them by the social contract are to be protected from attempts of elimination the same way as human rights, as it is enshrined in both UN covenants as the people's right to self-determination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2773.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2794.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the devastating fate of people living in failed states and the inability of the United Nations to ensure the universal protection of human rights show, states, defined by the territory, borders, and population, cannot yet be eliminated from international law for the sake of globalization and global governance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2794.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2808.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, none of the provisions of the convention can be interpreted in a manner making the states' right to control the entry, residence, and removal of alliance illusory or theoretical.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2808.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2821.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Granting a right to freedom of movement across borders or an unconditional right to entry upon the mere submission of a claim for international protection would have exactly that effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2821.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2841.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then a request for asylum would substitute for any passport or visa requirements the preventing an unauthorized entry, part of Article V, Paragraph 1F of the convention, would become meaningless for all entry would be automatically authorized by the decision of this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2841.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2849.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there would be no stopping of anyone, refugee or not, from reaching their desired destination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2849.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2864.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You might find that a desirable development in a global village, but it is certainly not so until the effective institutions of a comprehensive and democratic global governance of the global village will be put in place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2864.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2879.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it is demonstrated by the German authorities' inability to remove the first applicant after rejection of his asylum claims, the state's right to control the removal of alliance has already become theoretical.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2879.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2885.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is therefore even more important not to render the right to control the entry of alliance illusory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2885.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2896.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same effect of making the state's right to control immigration illusory can be achieved by the interpretation of Article III as proposed by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2896.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2920.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the standards of protection of individual rights are set as high as to make it practically impossible to apply any restriction in the interest of the community, or public interest if you prefer, and as high as to make individual interests prevail under any circumstances, it makes the protection of the rights of the community illusory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2920.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2952.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the threshold for the applicability of Article III is set so high that its standards can be reasonably met only by the richest states, and if the risks of refoulement and the adequacy of procedural safeguards in the asylum proceedings are determined by the opinion of organizations which are committed to the realization of a right to asylum shopping, it is tantamount to recognizing a right to choose a country of asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2952.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2960.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it has been shown by the government in their memorial, that right is not recognized in international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2960.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2973.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An explicit recognition of that right by the court would be obviously ultra-virous, and the government considered that the implicit endorsement of that right is also contrary to the object and purposes of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2973.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2989.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The principles of international law, for instance, the state's consent being necessary to create new obligations for them, and the principles of democratic government, for instance, division of competencies between the legislator and the judiciary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2989.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2993.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2993.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2998.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it is the above considerations in the light of which you should examine the applicants' complaints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2998.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3006.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article V is not applicable in the present case because the applicants were not deprived of their personal liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3006.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3031.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They did not have the right to enter Hungary without the necessary travel documents, and therefore they had to wait for the determination of their request for leave to enter, made in the form of an asylum application, at the gates of the border fence in the transit zone, where they were offered food and shelter to cater for their most basic human needs while waiting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3031.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3037.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were not in confinement or detention in the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3037.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3045.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The definition of confinement is the state of being forced to stay in a place which you cannot leave.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3045.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3051.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants entered the transit zone of their own free will and were free to leave any time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3051.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3086.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They exercised the perpetrated right to asylum shopping, a right to choose a country of asylum, and thus it was their own choice to apply for asylum in Hungary with all the consequences it entailed, including their accommodation in the transit zone, just as it was their own choice not to apply for asylum in other countries, but to avoid the authorities of the transit states because they did not like the terms under which asylum was obtainable in those countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3086.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3110.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Naturally, the applicants would have preferred the terms of obtaining asylum to be more favorably in any of the transit states, including Hungary, but nevertheless they accepted the terms of the word available in Hungary and submitted their asylum application there, even if only with a view to obtaining the right of passage to Western Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3110.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3119.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If they were in confinement in the transit zone, as some consider, the applicants had validly consented to it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3119.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3147.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also referred to the judgment of 16th of March 2017 of the German Federal Court of Justice, in which it found that the accommodation at the airport transit zone, which the asylum applicant was free to leave any time, did not constitute deprivation of liberty, at least until up 30 days, and thus didn't require judicial supervision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3147.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3165.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government know that the applicants in this case stayed at the transit zone only for 23 days, and they were not even in an airport transit zone, but at the border, which they could leave with even less financial or practical difficulties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3165.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3188.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This judgment is also significant because it proves that the chamber misunderstood the provisions of EU law governing deprivation of liberty in asylum proceedings, and in fact, as it was argued by the Hungarian government, accommodation in transit zones pending border proceedings were to be distinguished from asylum detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3188.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3198.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should the grand chamber uphold the chamber's judgment, it would render EU law, and apparently German law too, contrary to the convention's requirement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3198.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3223.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this point, I would like to briefly point out that the Hungarian judicial decisions filed by the applicant's representatives in annexes number five and six of the latest submissions concern a different legal situation, not governed by the rules of border proceedings applied in the applicant's case, and thus cannot disprove the government's argument in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3223.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3232.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Contrary to the chamber's findings, the applicants were not compelled to stay in the transit zone by a fear of forfeiting their right to seek asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3232.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3247.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After leaving the transit zone, they remained free to apply for asylum in Serbia, to resubmit their claims in Hungary, or, as the first applicant did, apply for asylum in Germany or any other state they chose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3247.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3264.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the finding that the applicants were deprived from the possibility to pursue a procedural aimed to shelter them from the risk of exposure to treatment in breach of Article 3 of the convention is wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3264.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3273.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Contrary to the applicant's allegations, they were not deported to Serbia but left the transit zone voluntarily when they were ordered to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3273.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3281.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Had they not left voluntarily, they would have been deported and handed over to the Serbian authorities as a measure of enforcement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3281.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3297.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the last thing the applicants wanted was to be handed over to the Serbian authorities that they had chosen to avoid since an application for asylum in Serbia could not bring them closer to reaching their chosen country of destination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3297.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3323.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since they were not handed over to the Serbian authorities in readmission proceedings but left voluntarily, they were in the same legal position in Serbia, entering illegally from Hungary, as those asylum seekers who entered illegally from other states, thus they were not prevented from requesting asylum in Serbia by the mere fact that they had returned from Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3323.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3342.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the applicants clearly stated that they had had no intention of seeking asylum in Serbia, their counsel argues that they were denied an effective remedy in Serbia in respect of their claims under Article 3 or that they did not trust the Serbian authorities to give them proper treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3342.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3354.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, according to the jurisprudence of this court, the prejudices invoked by the applicants' counsel cannot serve as a justification for not having recourse to an effective domestic remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3354.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3360.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When there are doubts about the effectiveness of a domestic remedy, that remedy must be tried.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3360.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3372.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no cases in the jurisprudence of the court finding that Serbia was in violation of its obligations under Article 3 and 13 in respect of asylum proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3372.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3377.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants' counsel refers to some strikeout decision to prove the contrary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3377.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3400.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, had those cases truly revealed any structural problem in Serbian law and practice, the court would not have struck those applications out of its list of cases for whatever personal solution of the matter, but would have continued the examination of the application as required by the general interests of human rights protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3400.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3406.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, cases post-dating 2015 are irrelevant in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3406.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3421.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we must conclude that irrespective of the counsel's allegations, it was the applicants who told the truth that they had not intended to all seek asylum in Serbia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3421.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3428.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, all the alleged deficiencies of the Serbian asylum system are irrelevant in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3428.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3462.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the government reiterates that in accordance with the court's jurisprudence, the issue under Article 3 is not whether and how the states, including the safe Serb countries, honor their obligations under the Geneva Convention, whether they effectively grant asylum to asylum seekers, even if not requested, as they are called to account for by the reports of the UNHCR, but whether the asylum seekers face a real risk of refoulement to the country which they have fled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3462.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3478.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Irrespective of Serbia, even the UNHCR acknowledged that it was general practice to allow asylum seekers, even readmitted ones, to continue their journey towards Western Europe instead of taking any measures of deportation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3478.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3491.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, contrary to the applicants' arguments, it is not chain return to a safe Serb country, which is prohibited by Article 3, but the chain refoulement to the country of persecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3491.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3528.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although we cannot even speak of a risk of chain refoulement when there is no country of persecution at the end of the chain, as in the applicants' case, the government point out that even the UNHCR acknowledged that since June 2015, adequate guarantees have existed in Macedonia against the risk of refoulement, and therefore no risk of chain refoulement from Serbia to Greece via Macedonia existed in September 2015 for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3528.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3547.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the complaint concerning the alleged shortcomings of the procedural safeguards in the asylum proceedings in Hungary, under Article 13 in conjunction with Article 3, please note that it was not communicated to the government and therefore cannot be reintroduced before the ground chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3547.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3564.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber chose to assess the perceived deficiencies of the asylum proceedings in the context of Article 3 alone, but that assessment was based on a set of erroneously established facts, as it was explained in detail in the government's written pleadings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3564.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3571.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, I would like to add only a few remarks in light of the applicants' observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3571.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3577.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants complain about the inadequacy of the information they were given about the asylum proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3577.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3624.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government considered that apart from the generally required information, which the applicants were always given at the adequate time by the asylum authority, such as information about issues that needed clarification in the proceedings, like what happened to them in Serbia, or about available remedies, the applicants could have obtained any further information or clarification in the framework of free legal assistance provided by the state, which they did not avail themselves of, but chose the assistance offered by the lawyers commissioned by the Hungarian Helsinki Committee, the same organization which provides for the representation in the present proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3624.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3637.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, if the applicants had insufficient information about the asylum proceedings, it was not attributable to the Hungarian government, but to the counsel of their own choice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3637.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3654.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the language and quality of interpretation, the government point out that contrary to the applicants' claims, in the present proceedings they were given interpretation in a language they claimed to understand and by interpreters whom they claimed to properly understand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3654.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3666.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither the applicants nor the legal representative complained before the domestic authorities of the quality or language of the interpretation, not even on a direct question from the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3666.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3679.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the interpretation was indeed inadequate, we cannot but conclude that the applicants and the representatives misled the Hungarian authorities in order only to be able to complain before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3679.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3700.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the short procedural deadlines complained of by the applicants, as well as by the UNHCR, the government submit that those deadlines are the guarantees for keeping the duration of asylum applicants' legal uncertainty as regards their right to enter to the minimum possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3700.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3712.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The deadlines in the case did not affect the effectiveness of the work of the applicants' legal representatives, as it is proven even by the fact that their first request for judicial review was successful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3712.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3722.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The procedural deadlines set by Hungarian law are adequate to the nature and complexity of the legal issues to be clarified in the course of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3722.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3732.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants did not need more than three days for giving account of their personal experience concerning the Serbian asylum system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3732.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3740.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the submissions of the UNHCR, the government note that its analysis is inaccurate, incomplete, and biased.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3740.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3744.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As an example, in paragraph 2.2.6</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3744.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3761.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of its third-party submissions, the UNHCR alleges that as a result of the difficulties hindering access to judicial review, in 2015 only nine rejected asylum seekers registered requests for judicial review in the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3761.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3769.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And later, withdrawals left only two asylum seekers to pursue judicial review proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3769.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3778.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, withdrawal of a request cannot be reasonable, seen as a proof of being hindered in submitting that request.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3778.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3804.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the UNHCR submissions contradict its own findings, stated in paragraph 27 of the same report, cited as a source of information, that between the 15th of September, 2015, and the 31st of March, 2016, 114 of 118 rejected asylum applicants submitted requests for judicial review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3804.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3833.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government submit that even if the number of requests for judicial review in the transit zones were to be regarded as low, it was not due to difficulties in filing such requests, but to the fact that about 90% of all asylum seekers in the relevant period qualified as persons with special needs who did not fall under the rules of border proceedings applied in the applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3833.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3849.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government must also point out that the concerns of the UNHCR, an organization with a mandate to improve the protection of refugees, seem to be misplaced with economic migrants abusing the asylum and welfare systems in Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3849.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3887.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As an organization concerned about the improvement of the effectiveness of the asylum proceedings, the UNHCR should be quite satisfied with the measures introduced by the Hungarian government in 2015 and 2017, discouraging and later curtailing abuses by economic migrants and asylum shoppers, which have resulted in an ever-increasing rate of recognition of refugee status and granting of international protection in Hungary to those who are in real need of it, as it was shown in the government's written pleadings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3887.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3890.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3890.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3901.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>when you deliver your decision in the present case, you must also bear in mind that in accordance with Article 46 of the convention, your judgment will be binding only in respect of Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3901.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3926.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should you succeed in forcing Hungary to grant a universal right to freedom of movement across the borders, demolish the border fence and the transit zones at the border, you may soon find the border fence rebuilt on the borders of Austria and Hungary, right where the iron curtain dividing Europe used to be with the new so-called Kali jungle and the western borders of Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3926.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3946.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then, by not following the court's wisdom in the Bankovic case, in an effort to protect human rights universally, you may cause the destruction of the rights of the people living in the legal space of the convention, including the right to free movement across borders, as it is recognized today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3946.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3949.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, that concludes what</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3949.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3950.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wish to say at this stage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3950.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3953.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I thank you, Mr. President and members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3953.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3957.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for listening to me so patiently and attentively.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3957.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3957.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3962.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3969.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mr. Tallódi and I thank both parties for their submissions and now</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3969.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3977.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I invite my colleagues, the judges of the Grand Chamber who wish to do so, to put their questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3977.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3977.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Kjølbro, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Jon Fridrik Kjølbro</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3981.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3982.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3982.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3986.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I do have one question to the applicants and three questions to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3986.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3992.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question to the applicant, the applicants are from Bangladesh and requested asylum in Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3992.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4000.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The basis for their request must be, I assume, the risk of ill treatment in their country of origin, which is Bangladesh.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4000.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4011.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In their observations before the court, the applicants have provided the court with some information about their personal situation and the alleged risk of ill treatment in Bangladesh.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4011.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4018.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But my question is, did the applicants also explain to the Hungarian authorities the basis for their fear of ill treatment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4018.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4021.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If so, when and to whom did they do so?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4021.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4026.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More specifically, were they given a chance to do so by the Hungarian authorities?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4026.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4030.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And were they also questioned by the authorities on this issue?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4030.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4045.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When I listened to the representative's intervention addressing the question of arguable claim and fear, if I did not misunderstand it, it was only with reference to Serbia and Greece, but not in relation to Bangladesh.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4045.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4050.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first question to the government concerns Serbia as a safe third country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4050.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4059.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants did submit a request for asylum in Hungary, but the Hungarian authorities relied on Serbia as being a safe third country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4059.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4076.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it correct to conclude that Hungarian authorities never assessed the applicants' request for asylum under merits, that is, the risk of ill treatment in a country of origin, but limited its assessment to Serbia being a safe third country?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4076.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4083.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If so, why was their assessment limited to Serbia?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4083.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4088.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was it the result of a legal prescription or a standard practice?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4088.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4097.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, were the applicants asked by the Hungarian authorities about their fear of ill treatment in Bangladesh, and if so, when and by whom?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4097.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4105.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question to the government concerns the possible consequences in case the applicants had left the transit border area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4105.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4119.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of the issues of dispute between the parties is the question of the possible consequences in case the applicants had decided to leave the border transit zone before having received a final decision on the request for asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4119.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4138.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to section 62, paragraph 2, subparagraph D of the Asylum Act, the authorities may discontinue the proceedings of a request in case the asylum seekers leaves his place of accommodation for more than 48 hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4138.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4150.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, according to section 66, paragraph 6 of the same act, an asylum seeker may, within the time limit of nine months, request the continuation of a request for asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4150.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4162.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, my question, is it correctly understood that if the applicants had left the border transit zone, the processing of the request would have been discontinued?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4162.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4175.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And are there any examples in practice where the authorities have decided, on the basis of a request from an asylum seeker, to continue the processing of a request that has been discontinued?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4175.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4177.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My last question to the government is the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4177.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4182.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Hungarian authorities relied on Serbia as being a safe third country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4182.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4194.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the government, the authorities did so on the basis of a general assessment of the situation in Serbia, as well as an assessment of the applicant's individual situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4194.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4213.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is, are there any examples in practice, in particular during the relevant period in 2015, where Hungarian authorities exceptionally have reached the conclusion that Serbia was not a safe third country, or was Serbia, in all cases, regarded as being a safe third country?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4213.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4214.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4214.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4216.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4216.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4217.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now Judge Bianku, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ledi Bianku</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4220.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4221.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4221.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4227.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question follows the last question of my learned colleague, Judge Kjølbro.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4227.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4235.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is directed to the government, but the applicants can, of course, provide information and opinion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4235.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4249.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question is, section 2 of the government's decree 191, 2015 provides for a list of countries to be considered safe for purposes of removals of asylum seekers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4249.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4264.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then the question is, how safe is this consideration as safe countries, especially if we consider that the Balkan route, including Serbia, was facing very high migrant fluxes in the summer, autumn 2015?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4264.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4273.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I invite you to consider as well paragraph 48 of the EU procedures directive as to the update of this information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4273.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4288.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question, this court in Sufi and Elmi has defined the sources of information for the purpose of qualifying a safe country of destination, being third or original country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4288.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4304.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In conducting their assessment, should national authorities and eventually this court rely in other sources of information on the country of destination situation, such as, for example, credible media reports?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4304.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4304.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4305.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4307.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4307.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4308.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Vučinić, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Nebojša Vučinić</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4310.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4312.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4312.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4315.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have short questions, better to say comments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4315.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4339.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to hear comments of both parties concerning the concept of so-called inherent limitations on personal freedom and liberties introduced by the government, Hungarian government in their written submissions and in the presentation of this morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4339.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4356.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More precisely, in the course of the legal qualification of the measures on which applicants had been subjected in the transit zone, government is invoking the concept of inherent limitations of personal liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4356.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4370.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can you say a little bit more precisely what does it mean, specifically in the context of the court's jurisprudence, court's case law regarding the Article 5 of the convention?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4370.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4370.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4371.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4373.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4373.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4373.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Spano please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4375.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4376.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4376.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4386.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just, I have one follow-up question, which is prompted by the pleadings of the government this morning and follows one of the questions posed by my colleague, Judge Kjølbro .</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4388.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4396.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is a crucial element in this case, and that is the implementation by the Hungarian authorities of the safe third country concept.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4398.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4413.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2009, the Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe issued guidelines on human rights protection in the context of accelerated asylum procedures, where the safe third country concept is developed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4413.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4427.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of the criteria mentioned for the appropriate application of that concept is that the third country, in our case, Serbia, will admit the asylum seeker.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4428.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4433.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, this seems to be, and now here comes my question, and I would like your comment on this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4433.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4444.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In section 51A of the Asylum Act of 2007, which was in force at the time of the proceedings, it stated as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4444.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4463.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the safe country of origin, which we're not dealing with here, or the safe third country refuses to admit or to take back the applicant, the asylum authority shall withdraw its decision and shall continue the procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4463.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4471.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, my question is, Mr. Tallódi, you said this morning that the readmission procedure had not been triggered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4471.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4488.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So may I ask, on what basis were the Hungarian authorities in conformity with 51A of your Asylum Act?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4488.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4512.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To what extent were there assurances made that Serbia would, in fact, readmit the applicants on the facts of this case, and therefore, to what extent, if your answer is that no such readmission was made explicitly by the Serbian government, how that would conform with the implementation of this safe third country concept.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4512.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4513.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4513.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4533.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. If there are no more questions the court will now withdraw for 20 minutes. Following which, the parties will be able to submit brief observations in reply to each other's submissions and reply to questions from the judges. The hearing is suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4728.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4729.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4763.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4775.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4775.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4781.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I call Mrs. Pohárnok.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4781.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4781.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4785.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4786.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4786.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4790.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So now, first, we will answer the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4790.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4793.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I will answer the first question of Judge Kjorbros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4793.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4796.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then I give the floor to my colleague.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4796.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4806.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So Judge Kjorbros, if we understood well, asks whether the applicants had the chance to explain the basis for their asylum claim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4806.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4826.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And our answer is, we respectfully submit that the procedure, which was done over and done with in a couple of hours' time on September 15 of September, after the applicants entered the transit zone, exclusively focused was a border transit zone procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4826.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4843.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By its nature and under Hungarian law, this procedure was an inadmissibility procedure within the asylum procedure, which means that it clearly exclusively focused on the issue of the safe third country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4843.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4856.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, as it can be seen from the case files of the Hungarian authorities, if you see the minutes of the case files, it's clear that the questions were centered around this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4856.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4870.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The asylum office informed the applicants during the interview that the Hungarian authorities consider Serbia as a safe third country, and this procedure is about this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4870.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4880.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So anything that was said, or what is in the minutes about the possible reasons for fleeing Bangladesh is said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4880.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4884.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If anything was said, it was by incident.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4884.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4887.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no examination of the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4887.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4899.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not the Hungarian authorities' obligation, and they did not do this in the asylum interview, which was in the asylum procedure, in the entire asylum procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4899.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4909.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicants did not have any legal assistance or information before their first asylum procedure was concluded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4909.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4910.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4913.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4919.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court, I will now try to answer the remaining questions</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4919.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4922.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then conclude our submission today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4922.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4942.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First I will answer to Judge Bianco's question regarding the application of governmental decree on safe third country, despite the media knowledge of influx of migrants coming through the Balkan states at the material time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4942.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4959.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would like to submit that as this court found in MSS case, it is incumbent to inform itself as to the realistic of the situation and not just rely on the fiction that the country is safe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4959.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4973.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Belgian authorities could not merely assume that the applicant would be treated in conformity with the convention standards, but to verify how the state would act in practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4973.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4978.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was in paragraph 359 of MSS case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4978.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5008.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the question of Judge Vucinic, what is the meaning of the inherent limitation of personal liberty, we believe that definition of this inherent limitation is for the government to answer, but we would like to submit that article 5 spells out very precisely the situations in which the deprivation of liberty is permitted and procedural safeguards are complying it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5008.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5014.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would like to stress that we do not claim that Mr. Islias and Mr. Ahmed had an unconditional</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5014.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5033.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>right to enter the remaining territory of Hungary, but we do believe that while they were kept waiting there, they had rights to have all procedural standards that are guaranteed by that convention in regard to their deprivation of liberty in place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5033.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5039.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally I would like to have a remark on Judge Spano's question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5039.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5070.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that Judge Spano in his question exposed one of the key issues in the present case, which is that under Hungarian law it was the Hungarian authorities' obligation to make sure that the Serbian authorities would readmit the applicants and process their asylum claim, as it is provided for in paragraph 836 of the Council of Europe guidelines to which Judge Spano referred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5070.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5078.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is clear from the files of the case that this was not the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5078.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5084.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the Court, I would like to conclude with the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5084.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5096.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the case about the rule of law, a concept which runs like a golden thread through the whole convention and is articulated in its preamble.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5096.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5108.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The rule of law requires to have in place the appropriate laws to safeguard convention rights from arbitrariness and to observe these laws in practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5108.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5134.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those essential procedural safeguards should ensure that no one is arbitrarily deprived of his or her liberty, that mechanisms exist about both in law and in practice for challenging detention and conditions of detention, and that no one is expelled to face a risk of prohibited ill-treatment directly or by chain refoulement without rigorous scrutiny being given to their claims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5134.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5146.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is the applicant's case that the Hungarian government failed to have in place and comply with essential procedural safeguards required by the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5146.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5170.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What the Hungarian and some of the intervening governments in essence argue is that you should sidestep the convention and your consistent case law regarding Article 3 and Article 5 in asylum cases to be able to control their borders and to ensure security of their people under heightened migration pressure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5170.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5181.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They contend that the Court's case law has generated the systematic abuse of asylum and has facilitated the blooming business of human smugglers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5181.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5185.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This position is fundamentally incorrect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5185.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5198.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No doubt that states are obliged to guarantee national security and to control their borders, which is of utmost importance as confirmed by the Grand Chamber in Sadi, Hirsi, and Klaifia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5198.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5208.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also clear that the convention does not guarantee anyone the right to refugee status nor the right to enter unauthorized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5208.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5215.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the Court, please be confident that contracting states are perfectly</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5215.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5230.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>capable to lawfully reject, detain, and remove those who have no legitimate claim for asylum or residence, even in times of mass influx, without human rights violations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5230.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5243.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their security concerns can and should be brought in line with existing human rights obligations, as confirmed most recently by the Grand Chamber in Klaifia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5243.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5253.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Subjecting human beings to arbitrary detention, to summary procedures, or to inhuman treatment does not make Europe a safer place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5253.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5260.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today we request you to uphold these standards in the case of Mr. Ilias and Mr. Ahmed, who</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5260.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5263.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>were seeking international protection in Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5263.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5263.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5266.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5271.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, madam. Now I call Mr. Tallódi, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5275.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5280.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5280.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5301.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before I react to the concrete questions, I would like to make some remarks concerning the allegations by the applicants, or the representative of the applicants, concerning the language or the quality of the language or the translation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5301.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5307.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both the applicants claim to speak and understand Urdu and never requested a Bengali interpreter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5307.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5309.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is very important.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5309.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5318.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In respect, it must be noted that neither the Convention nor EU law provides for the right to interpretation in the Asylum Seekers' Modern Tongue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5318.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5326.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is sufficient if interpretation is provided in a language that the applicant understands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5326.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5345.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The story of the applicants lives presented before this Court makes it more likely that they had a sufficient understanding of Urdu and of the other languages they had claimed before the Hungarian authorities to understand that they spoke only Bengali, as they claim in the latest submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5345.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5355.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, I draw your attention to annex number 2 attached to the applicant's written observations submitted on the 18th of December, 2017.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5355.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5371.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The counsel asking the applicant in English if she can call him with an Urdu interpreter – moreover, the first applicant's statement signed on the 12th of December, 2017, also says that it was translated to him in Urdu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5371.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5379.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The power of attorneys signed by the applicants in the Hungarian proceedings also indicated Urdu as a language of communication.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5379.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5388.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the video interviews deposited by the applicants with this Court were also conducted in Urdu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5388.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5413.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as a comment on the applicant's opening argument citing a Syrian refugee, let me inform you that in the period between 15th of September, 2015, and 27th of March, 2017, 11,038 persons submitted asylum applications in either of the border transit zones in Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5413.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5430.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More than 90 percent of them – more than 9,000 asylum applicants were found to fall in the category of persons with need for special treatment, who didn't fall under the rules of border proceedings and were granted leave to enter Hungary immediately.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5430.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5439.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Most of them left Hungary towards Austria and their earliest convenience without awaiting a decision on the merits of their asylum application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5439.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5461.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Hungary cannot reasonably be expected to prevent secondary movement of asylum seekers towards Western Europe without the measures introduced in 2017, bearing in mind that the Geneva Convention on the Status of Refugees obliges the states to provide refugees not less favorable treatment than to their nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5461.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5475.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A country where nationals enjoy higher standards of welfare services and a higher standard of living will always be more attractive to asylum seekers if they are given a choice than countries with a lower standard of living.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5475.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5490.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In response to the question of Judge Kjellbro, I can confirm that the focus on the applicant's asylum proceedings was on Serbia as a safe third country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5490.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5497.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It followed from the nature of the border proceedings dealing with the admissibility of the application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5497.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5512.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the applicants were briefly questioned on their reasons for seeking asylum, and their statements were sufficient to reveal that their applications were also manifestly ill-founded on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5512.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5529.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The consequences of their leaving, as we saw, that they could continue their journey to Western Europe by alternative routes, and they could submit or could have submitted asylum in other states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5529.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5540.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have been examples in the jurisprudence of Hungarian courts when the presumption of safe third country was successfully refuted by the asylum applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5540.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5546.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We know of at least two such cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5546.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5565.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Continuation of asylum proceedings after first absconding them by the applicants is typical in the context of Dublin proceedings, which means that they didn't return Hungary voluntarily, but they were forced, so-called forced, to come back to Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5565.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5586.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the question of Judge Spanu, I can repeat that the applicants left voluntarily after the decision on their expulsion, which was communicated then without waiting for the measures of enforcement, which would have involved seeking admission by the Serbian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5586.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5597.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As they were not in detention, the government could not retain them with such as admission was made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5597.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5627.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the method, by the update of the list of third safe countries, I can assure that the Hungarian law was eliberated in conformity with Article 38 and 39 on the concept of the third safe countries, enshrined by the Directive 2013, 32 EU Directive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5627.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5660.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is very important also that even the Hungarian asylum authorities' decision used their reports, which included media reports, for instance, the Serbian B92 television broadcast about the upcoming of an asylum center with a capacity of 300 people in Pressebo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5660.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5685.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning the inherent limitation, the question of inherent limitation, I would like to pay your attention that according to the principle of marginal appreciation, the state has the right to control and also stop the entry into the territory of the relevant state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5685.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5694.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under Hungarian law, the applicants didn't have a right to enter the state of Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5694.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5703.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, their liberty was not restricted when they were not allowed to enter the territory of Hungary beyond the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5703.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5726.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the notion of inherent limitation, a plus information, I would like to repeat that we cannot regard the situations when the right to do something is excluded by law as calling for individual judicial decisions or restriction of liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5726.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5733.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The lawfulness of that limitation can be assessed only in the context of the measure they are inherent in.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5733.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5754.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, the question is whether the applicants had the right to entry, and therefore the lawfulness of the limitation of the right to entry cannot be assessed independently of the merits of the case as the applicants claim. Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5756.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5758.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Tallódi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5758.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5761.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5761.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5766.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their submissions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5766.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5770.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5770.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5777.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered at a later stage, and the parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5777.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5779.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
