<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>4762113_01072020</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>17.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>18.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>60.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>61.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>77.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>88.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Good morning, I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case of Vavřička versus the Czech Republic and five other applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>88.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>113.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were lodged with the court between 23 July 2013 and 31 August 2015 under Article 34 of the convention by six Czech nationals, Mr. Pavel Avrička, Ms. Markéta Novodna,Mr. Pavel Ornič, Mr. Adam Brožič, Mr. Vrado Mirdubčí, and Mr. Prokop Roleček.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>113.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>122.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were allocated to the first section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the rules of court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>122.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>127.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were communicated to the government on 7 September 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>127.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>136.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 17 December 2019, the chamber decided to relinquish jurisdiction in favor of the grand chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>136.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>163.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The governments of France, Germany, Poland, and Slovakia and the Association of Vaccine Injured Persons, the Association Rosalio, the European Center for Law and Justice, and the European Forum for Vaccine Vigilance were all granted leave under Article 36, paragraph 2 of the convention, and Rule 44, paragraph 3 of the rules of court to make written submissions to the court as third parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>163.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>182.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Rwandan government are represented by their agent, Mr. Vít Alexander Schorm,assisted by Ms. Eva Petrová, Kateřina Radová,Ms. Dana  Prudíková, Mr. Tomáš Suchomel, Mr. Roman Prymula,and Ms. Hana Cabrnochová, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>182.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>200.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Ms. Zuzana Candigliota,counsel, assisted by Mr. Dan Petrucha, Mr. Karel Lach,Mr. David Dušánek, and Ms. Janíčková, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>182.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>200.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Barbora  Rolečková, the mother of one of the applicants,is also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>200.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>205.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>205.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>212.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the counsel for the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>212.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>219.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Schorm and Mr. Prymula for the government will speak first, and then Ms. Candigliota for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>219.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>220.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Schorm.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>231.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>244.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished judges, representatives of the applicants, once again it is a great honor for me to appear before the Grand Chamber and present my government's position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>244.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>253.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants in these cases complain about legislation on compulsory vaccination of children and its consequences for those who refuse to comply.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>253.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>264.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The compulsory vaccination scheme in the Czech Republic consists of vaccines against nine diseases to be administered to children according to a set calendar within their first years of life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>264.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>272.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no direct enforcement of the obligation, but noncompliance may result in a fine and non-admission to nursery school.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>272.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>280.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Specifically, five applicants in their preschool age were not admitted to nursery school for failure to undergo or require vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>280.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>285.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the sixth applicant, in fact, the first applicant, Mr. Wawrzycka,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>285.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>291.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was as a parent fined for refusing to have vaccinated his children aged 13 and 14 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>291.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>294.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants invoke three convention rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>294.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>299.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They all allege an interference with their private and or family life under Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>299.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>305.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, five of them also rely on the rights to education safeguarded by Article 2 of the first protocol.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>305.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>316.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, three applicants contend having refused the prescribed vaccination on the grounds of their beliefs and convictions within the meaning of Article 9 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>316.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>323.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me suggest at the outset, assessing the cases at hand exclusively under the scope of the right to respect their private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>323.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>328.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In previous cases, the court dealt with the issue of vaccination from this very angle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>328.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>341.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, and as elaborated on in our written observations, the facts under scrutiny do not trace new issues under other provisions, but appear as restatements of the applicants' complaints under Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>341.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>350.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the court itself posed some questions regarding the applicants' conscience and non-admission to nursery school with reference to this provision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>350.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>357.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This clearly warrants the conclusion that the applicants' claims fall, in fact, under the sole perspective of private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>357.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>363.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That being said, my government finds compulsory vaccination in principle compatible with the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>363.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>375.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After all, with the exception of arbitrary interferences or manifest errors, it is not the task of an international court to dispute expert conclusions or domestic authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>375.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>392.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, I will mainly focus on showing that the Czech vaccination scheme, to the extent it may interfere with convention rights, is proportionate to the legitimate aim pursued, namely to protect not only the individual obliged to get vaccinated, but the health of the members of the society as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>392.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>403.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This concerns, in particular, vulnerable persons who cannot be vaccinated due to their state of health or those who have not developed antibodies against the disease in spite of previous vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>403.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>419.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In line with their positive obligations under the convention itself, states are bound to put in place effective public health policies, making it possible to combat serious and contagious diseases and to protect the life and physical integrity of those in their jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>419.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>425.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>States can hardly expect that the court would discourage them from performing these vital tasks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>425.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>433.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After all, the recent global health crisis has demonstrated that these considerations are more relevant than ever.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>433.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>440.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While vaccinations are voluntary in some countries and compulsory in others, the aim of the respective authorities in each country is the same.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>440.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>456.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, according to the World Health Organization, as well as the European Commission, vaccination is the most cost-effective and safe way to prevent diseases, and vaccination refusal belongs amongst the 10 listed threats to public health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>456.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>464.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me note in this context that the court has never considered the compulsory vaccination itself to conflict with the rights protected by the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>464.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>467.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is one essential fact which I would like to put straight.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>467.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>472.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were filed by parents on behalf of their children, with the exception of Mr. Wawrzycka.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>472.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>474.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why does this matter?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>474.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>485.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parents mostly point out the implications of their refusal of vaccination for themselves, for example, in terms of not being able to take a job due to non-admission of their children to nursery school.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>485.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>490.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Most of their claims seem, therefore, incompatible razione, persone, with the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>490.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>496.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the interests of the parents and their children may not necessarily be aligned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>496.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>506.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, it is highly questionable whether not having the children vaccinated is in their best interest, especially when there is no substantiated reason for such a refusal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>506.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>525.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a matter of fact, under Article 24 of the Convention on the Rights of the Child, as developed by General Comment Number 15, issued by the competent UN treaty body, the child has the right to enjoyment of the highest attainable standard of health, including immunization against common childhood diseases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>525.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>535.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, by refusing vaccination in the knowledge of the legal consequences, the parents de facto deprive their children from enjoying the company of their peers in nursery school.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>535.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>543.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the scope of the applicant's complaints, the period to be considered by the court started in 2003 and ended in 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>543.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>547.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Inevitably, the vaccination policy has undergone some changes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>547.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>554.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, an act on compensation for damage to health caused by compulsory vaccination has entered into force this year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>554.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>564.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court, however, has to examine the complaints raised in the initial applications and not subsequent events or events totally unrelated to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>564.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>571.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court should also be mindful that vaccination policy is a health policy that usually lies on the shoulders of experts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>571.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>584.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the light of the Green Chamber judgment in Ljubljana and Kosovo versus the Czech Republic, if the case requires from the national authorities an assessment of expert and scientific data, the state's margin of appreciation is broader.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>584.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>589.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To determine the scope of compulsory vaccination requires, indeed, a high degree of expertise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>589.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>596.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is why our written observations are supported by a number of opinions from the relevant expert societies in the Czech Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>596.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>609.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In line with their opinion and also with the intervention of France, all the diseases for which the Czech legislation lays down compulsory vaccination are very serious and highly contagious.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>609.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>615.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me now bring our attention to issues of admissibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>615.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>620.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, after all, the reason for which the government speaks first.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>620.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>625.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are a number of objections with regard to several applicants which my government raised in writing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>625.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>628.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will not linger on them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>628.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>640.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today, let me only comment on an argument newly mentioned in the applicants' written submissions to the Green Chamber concerning non-exhaustion of domestic remedies in the cases of applicants Brozik and Lupski.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>640.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>649.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unlike the other applicants, these two filed neither a cassation nor a constitutional appeal in the proceedings concerning their admission to nursery school.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>649.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>657.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They contend that judicial proceedings would have offered reasonable prospects of success only had an interim measure been imposed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>657.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>676.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The national courts responded to this argument that since there is no entitlement to preschool education, and indeed, many children do not attend nursery school simply because of lack of capacity of these kind of facilities, one cannot perceive a risk of serious harm to the applicant's subjective rights that could justify implementing an interim measure in their case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>676.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>688.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An opposite outcome would, in fact, enable all unvaccinated children whose parents go to court to oppose the vaccination policy to enter preschool facilities for the duration of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>688.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>692.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That could jeopardize the legitimate aim of compulsory vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>692.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>701.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the code of administrative justice makes it possible to ask, on serious grounds, the national court to give a priority to a case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>701.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>711.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government, therefore, maintain that the proceedings on the merits did represent an adequate and effective domestic remedy in these cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>711.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>726.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning now to the merits of cases examined by this court, as I have already said, I will take the applications mainly from the perspective of private life and devote only a couple of words to issues seemingly raised under the angles of the other rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>726.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>732.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The relevant legislation apparently affects the right to respect for family life only marginally, if at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>732.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>742.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The obligation to get vaccinated on pain of fine or of non-admission to a preschool facility may amount, generally speaking, to an interference with the right to respect for private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>742.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>752.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to whether the interference was in accordance with the law, the impact of the parents' decision not to have their children vaccinated was not surprising.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>752.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>754.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The law was accessible and foreseeable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>754.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>761.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The obligation to undergo a series of vaccinations is set out in the 2000 Act on Public Health Protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>761.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>770.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Its relevant provision specifies that details, including the extent of compulsory vaccination, shall be provided for in secondary legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>770.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>781.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I cannot agree with the applicants that the Ministry of Health decree on vaccination against infectious diseases is not law in the sense of Article 8, paragraph 2 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>781.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>787.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The notion of law is an autonomous concept, and the structure of the national legal order is not decisive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>787.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>794.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The rules of obligatory vaccination are accessible to the general public and apply in the same way to the specified groups of persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>794.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>804.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the relevant legislation has been repeatedly reviewed by the Constitutional Court and the Supreme Administrative Court in the proceedings initiated by the applicants themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>804.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>811.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The domestic courts explicitly concluded that the legislation was in compliance with the Czech Constitution and the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>811.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>820.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Ministry of Health has established the scope of compulsory vaccination based on recommendations of its advisory boards of epidemiologists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>820.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>838.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This board was superseded in 2010 by the National Immunization Committee, which is an advisory body composed of leading experts in the field of vaccinology and meets all the criteria set by the WHO for a functional national advisory committee on immunization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>838.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>844.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I must oppose the applicant's argument that the compulsory vaccination scheme is not sufficiently supported by expertise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>844.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>850.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Publicly available serological surveys have been performed in my country since 1960.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>850.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>858.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are highly praised at the international level and meet the requirements of the European seroepidemiology network.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>858.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>866.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They monitor levels of antibodies against selected infections and provide information about susceptibility and collective immunity of the population.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>866.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>877.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The surveys are used to evaluate the overall effectiveness of vaccination programs and provide major grounds for important modifications in immunization schemes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>877.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>890.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As an example, the surveys have led to a recent modification of the vaccination calendar with respect to the second dose of compulsory vaccination against measles, rubella, and mumps, which has been postponed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>890.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>897.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under these circumstances, the applicant's objections based on lawfulness are hardly defensible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>897.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>904.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will not dwell upon legitimacy and will turn to the essential question of proportionality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>904.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>911.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are nine important points that I will mention on the necessity of the compulsory vaccination in the Czech Republic in abstracto.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>911.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>920.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, international commitments, including the Convention on the Rights of the Child, place a positive obligation on the state to protect the health of people within its jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>920.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>925.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vaccination is planned, organized, and controlled by experts of the public health sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>925.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>930.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vaccines for compulsory vaccination are provided free of charge by the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>930.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>938.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants allege that if all other children are fully vaccinated, there is practically no possibility for the applicants to potentially infect other children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>938.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>953.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They further allege that the aim of protecting the health of other children could be achieved by a less intrusive way, subsequent exclusion of unvaccinated children from the collective in case of an actual threat or outbreak of a disease.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>953.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>954.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I cannot agree.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>954.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>958.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The legislation seeks to prevent spread of the respective diseases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>958.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>967.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is aimed at the minors, as they are especially vulnerable to the risk of infection, and in that regard can face serious consequences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>967.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>977.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Czech Vaccinology Society, newborns and infants are very susceptible to infections because their immune system is not fully mature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>977.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>982.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They also suffer from higher frequency and complication rates of some infections.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>982.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>985.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is why an early vaccination is necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>985.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>990.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is also why the condition of vaccination for entry applies to preschool facilities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>990.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>999.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The idea behind is that all children are sufficiently protected when newcomers enter a collective people where the risk of infection is automatically higher.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>999.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1008.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also a tool to motivate parents to let children vaccinate in order for the society as a whole to achieve the necessary herd immunity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1008.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1023.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We talk about herd immunity when most of the population is immune to an infectious disease, and this provides indirect protection to those who have not, in spite of previous vaccination or due to their health condition, acquired individual immunity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1023.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1026.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The herd immunity is fragile, however.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1026.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1030.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The more parents refuse vaccination, the greater is the risk of disease spreading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1030.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1041.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the number of such parents has been on the rise, and the applicants' allegation that diseases are almost non-existent in my country is irrelevant in an era of increased migration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1041.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1050.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is more, the applicants are making benefits of solidarity of other people who bear the burden, the responsibility for the health of the society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1050.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1059.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I may sound rough, but from this point of view, the applicants place themselves in a position of fair judges in the public health system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1059.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1071.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, compulsory vaccination does not refer to a coercive administration of a vaccine, but rather to an obligation to be vaccinated against nine diseases according to a schedule determined by experts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1071.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1083.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The enforcement scheme is very limited, and it usually follows a discussion between parents and pediatrician about the aim of compulsory vaccination and the consequences of its refusal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1083.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1087.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The sanctions are not of a criminal, but of administrative nature only.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1087.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1091.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The authorities can impose a fine, just like in Mr. Babrzycka's case, which</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1091.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1097.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>can only be applied once and in the maximum amount of some 380 euros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1097.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1103.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another consequence consists in non-admission of the child to nursery school, just like in the case of the other applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1103.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1114.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, with regard to the need for various types of vaccination, the respective legislation is subject to an ongoing review by the Ministry of Health and its National Immunization Committee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1114.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1120.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The content of our obligatory immunization schedule has fully corresponded to the recommendations of the WHO.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1120.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1125.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No new compulsory vaccination has been introduced since the applications were filed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1125.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1136.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The immunization scheme has not been rigid, though, as in 2010, vaccination against tuberculosis was dropped and started to apply only to selected groups at risk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1136.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1139.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourth, obligatory vaccination is not performed mechanically.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1139.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1147.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is preceded by a medical examination if a child is found immune to infection or health contraindication is discovered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1147.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1149.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The vaccination is not carried out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1149.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1156.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, the interest of the society in terms of public health is fairly balanced against the protection of the rights of individuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1156.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1160.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants cast doubt on the establishment of permanent contraindications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1160.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1166.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Czech Pediatric Society, such contraindications are rare, but nonetheless possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1166.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1174.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in case of severe oncologic diseases, immune depressive conditions, and severe allergic reactions to previous vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1174.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1185.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fifth, although the child must be vaccinated against all diseases and within the time limit set out in the respective legislation, parents have a choice between several vaccines available and dates of application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1185.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1192.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the choice must not burden the child with repeated administration of vaccines if combined vaccines are available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1192.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1198.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In practice, the antigenic combinations determined by the National Immunization Committee are deemed optimal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1198.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1208.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sixth, compulsory vaccination is the only way to achieve the protection of health as voluntary vaccination in the past did not lead to a necessary level of vaccination coverage of the population.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1208.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1213.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the vaccine hesitancy has been growing, the applicants being, after all, a perfect example.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1213.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1217.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Other countries have been introducing compulsory vaccination too.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1217.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1222.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For instance, Germany, with regard to measles since the 1st of March, 2020.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1222.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1227.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Seventh, the adverse effects of pharmaceuticals, including vaccines, are constantly monitored.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1227.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1231.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Each health care professional has the obligation to report them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1231.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1234.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And parents can do the same.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1234.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1242.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Eighth, imposition of a fine as a measure of last resort or decision on non-admission to nursery school must be reasoned and is subject to judicial review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1242.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1248.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the established case law of this court, this in itself constitutes an important safeguard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1248.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1255.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, under the court's case law again, states enjoy a wide margin of appreciation in matters of health care policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1255.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1261.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the more so as there is presently no agreement at the European level in respect of vaccination policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1261.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1271.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My country's policy, together with its consequences, is far from being unique within the Council of Europe member states, as also indicated by third party interventions of the various governments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1271.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1281.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To sum up this section of my speech, the system of obligatory vaccination in the Czech Republic as such is accompanied by due safeguards within the meaning of the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1281.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1285.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me now comment on the interference in Concreto.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1285.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1293.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unlike the applicants, I'm convinced that even in relation to them individually, a fair balance under Article 8 of the Convention was struck.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1293.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1294.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will make three points now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1294.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1300.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, none of the children was vaccinated against the parents' will.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1300.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1302.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The obligation of vaccination is not absolute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1302.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1309.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are exceptions based on immunization to infection or contraindication explicitly provided for in the domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1309.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1315.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is yet another case of exemption on the grounds of freedom of conscience established by the Constitutional Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1315.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1321.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the domestic proceedings, however, none of the applicants proved meeting conditions for exemption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1321.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1326.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Applicant Wawrzycka suggests that the applicable rules were laid down retrospectively in his case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1326.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1339.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, this court has already ruled that the fact that an applicant's case is the first of its kind does not render the domestic court's interpretation and application of the legislation arbitrary or unpredictable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1339.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1342.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, none of the applicants, including Mr. Wawrzycka's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1342.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1354.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>children, have suffered any damage to health in consequence of the vaccination, nor have any of them demonstrated the probability that in their particular case the relevant vaccine would cause serious problems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1354.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1358.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet the applicants could have claimed damages under the old civil code.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1358.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1365.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, it is true that applicant Nowotna's attendance of nursery school was first allowed and later terminated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1365.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1374.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This may look odd, but we cannot disregard that the applicant was admitted in 2006 as her parents submitted a false medical report.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1374.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1381.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next year, however, the hygiene authority during an inspection found out that the applicant had not actually been vaccinated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1381.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1386.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, her parents signed a declaration in 2004 refusing the child's vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1386.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1396.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even though instructed afterwards that an incompletely vaccinated child whose health conditions allow for vaccination cannot attend nursery school, the parents remained inactive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1396.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1404.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, the director of the nursery school concerned was left with no other option and put an end to the applicant's attendance in 2008.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1404.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1414.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also appears that someone falsely amended applicant Hornick's medical report with a charmingly equivocal formula, playing with the concept of law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1414.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1425.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Curiously enough, in line with the applicant's arguments on lawfulness, I cannot help quoting it, the applicant is not lacking any regular vaccination prescribed by law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1425.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1436.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In sum, it seems that these two particular cases must be differentiated from the others due to some bad faith on the part of the parents who misled the authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1436.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1441.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, my next point, the last but one, in fact, concerns the right to education.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1441.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1447.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's complaints based on Article 2 of the first protocol are of the same nature as those claimed under Article 8 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1447.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1460.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, we deem these complaints incompatible ratione materie with Article 2 of the first protocol, for under the court's case law, the notion of education does not concern preschool education, or the more optional.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1460.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1472.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the relevant period, Czech nursery schools, as for example French nursery schools, did not accept non-vaccinated children unless they had been found immune to infection or showed health contraindication.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1472.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1480.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any case, I share the opinion of the German government that well-compulsory vaccination aims at facilities at this low educational level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1480.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1485.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This should at least be taken into account when assessing proportionality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1485.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1488.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I come to my last point, namely the freedom of consents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1488.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1498.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm convinced that, and the interventions filed to the game chamber by other governments support this view, that the issue of vaccination does not fall within the scope of Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1498.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1508.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, in Bofa and others versus San Marino, the commission refused to extend the protection of Article 9 to parents who wish to evade the legal obligation to have their children vaccinated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1508.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1513.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is yet another strong reason for the court not to consider the complaints under Article 9 separately.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1513.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1520.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None of the applicants made convincing arguments to grant exemption from obligatory vaccination on the grounds of their freedom of consents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1520.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1533.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Constitutional Court stated in the applicant Vavrzycka's case, it cannot accept cases that are only general and cannot be seen as attaining a certain level of cogency, seriousness, cohesion, and importance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1533.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1543.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My government cannot but agree with the Constitutional Court that there is no real reason why the applicant's personal views should prevail over the general interest of the society in the protection of public health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1543.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1549.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for all these considerations, I respectfully propose holding that there was no violation of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1549.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1553.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would conclude with a quote from our Constitutional Court judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1553.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1563.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vaccination in general is an immunization tool preventing selected infections, constitutes a social benefit requiring shared responsibility of the members of the society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1563.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1570.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is an act of social solidarity of those who take risk in order to protect the health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1570.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1571.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1571.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1583.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And let me now somewhat introduce Professor Roman Primula, chairman of the Czech Vaccination Society and chairman or member of various European scientific societies or platforms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1583.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1589.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He also chaired the Central Emergency Committee during the recent pandemic crisis in my country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1589.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1591.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I suggest giving him</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1591.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1592.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the floor for a couple of remarks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1592.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1592.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1592.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1592.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1593.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1594.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1594.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1596.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Prymula, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1602.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1604.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1604.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1614.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ladies and gentlemen, vaccination is one of the most useful tools for preventing infectious diseases and reducing morbidity and mortality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1614.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1621.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Availability of vaccine has had a substantial impact on rates of vaccine-preventable diseases across the world.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1621.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1626.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, achieving high vaccination rates is challenged by less than optimal acceptance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1626.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1641.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In countries such as United States and Australia and many European countries, vaccine mandates such as those requiring vaccination for entry into school have been used to increase and sustain vaccination rates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1641.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1659.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Multiple countries in Europe, including France and Italy, have recently faced outbreaks of vaccine-preventable diseases such as measles, and in response have changed their policies, whereas other countries are considering introducing immunization mandates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1659.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1667.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mandatory vaccination in EU countries was associated with higher prevalence of measles and pertussis vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1667.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1671.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mandatory vaccination was associated with higher vaccination coverage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1671.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1677.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, mandatory vaccination was associated with lower measles incidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1677.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1688.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While the vast majority of parents vaccinate their children, many parents are unfamiliar with vaccine-preventable diseases and hold misconceptions regarding vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1688.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1706.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maintaining public confidence in the safety and utility of vaccines is particularly challenging, as diseases have been effectively controlled, primarily by the sustained use of vaccines, resulting in public and media attention on vaccine safety rather than prevention of disease.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1706.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1709.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vaccine hesitancy has been growing worldwide.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1709.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1716.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The WHO has recently named vaccine hesitancy among the top 10 threats to public health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1716.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1729.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Czech Republic, vaccine refusal has been growing due to proliferation of vaccine misinformation on social media and growing perception that vaccination requirements violate personal liberties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1729.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1742.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Recent measles outbreak in the Czech Republic highlights the urgency of effective communication interventions with vaccine-hesitant parents to inform planning of future educational programs to boost parenter vaccine confidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1742.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1750.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In most developed countries, indecision to lay public opposition to vaccination is becoming a health and social problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1750.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1769.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to a survey conducted by the Vaccination Trust Project, Europe has the highest number of negative responses in terms of perception of the importance of vaccination, its safety and effectiveness, leading to the highest degree of hesitancy against vaccination in the population.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1769.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1779.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If vaccination is successful in a given country, this will significantly reduce the prevalence of the previously feared disease against which it is vaccinated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1779.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1781.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This disease becomes relatively rare.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1781.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1798.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This will bluntly lay public vigilance towards it and shift public attention to discussions about the level of risk involved in a given vaccination and discussions about why to vaccinate against it when it is almost no longer present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1798.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1808.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This erroneous attitude leads to a decreasing vaccination rate and the subsequent return of previously controlled vaccine-preventable diseases to the population.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1808.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1821.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The European Parliament noted that widespread and growing reluctance towards vaccination had already reached worrying proportions because of the large scale of the related health consequences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1821.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1839.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the usefulness of vaccination as a prevention tool, the European Parliament is asking member states to ensure that vaccinations are extended beyond early childhood and that it applies to all age groups to ensure lifelong protection from vaccine-preventable diseases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1839.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1848.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, weakening public confidence in vaccination worldwide is a cause for concern and a major challenge for public health professionals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1848.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1876.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the European Parliament called on member states to develop a comprehensive European Union-wide action plan to highlight the societal problem of vaccine hesitancy and strengthen member states' commitments to immunization as a priority public health measure, including priority and specific regional measures, and take into account the changing circumstances and specific problems facing individual member states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1876.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1882.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The position of the most expert on vaccination can be expressed as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1882.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1891.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is one of the most important achievements of public health, which enables the health and lives of citizens to be protected under health immunity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1891.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1903.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or also, vaccination has brought tremendous health and socioeconomic benefits for individuals, populations, and society as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1903.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1907.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is one of the most cost-effective public health interventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1907.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1907.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for listening.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1909.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1910.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1910.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1913.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the government for their submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1913.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1916.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now call the representative of the applicants, Ms. Candigliota, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1931.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1934.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dear Mr. President, honorable judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1934.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1963.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it's an honor to appear before you today on behalf of the children and parents in the case related to the system of mandatory vaccination in the Czech Republic, which disproportionately interferes with the rights of the children to education, the rights of the parents to care for their children following their opinions, conviction, and the conscience, and in the best interest of the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1963.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1969.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it also interferes with the right of the families to the protection of private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1969.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1972.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our main arguments are as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1972.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1983.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, denying the access of the children to preschool education cannot be the punishment for the child not being fully vaccinated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1983.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1997.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any restrictions on the access of the child to education resulting from the protection of public health must be convincingly reasoned and cannot be arbitrary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1997.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2018.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite the individual member states having a wide margin of appreciation in the matter of health care system, including the vaccination systems, such a system may not entirely ignore the right to freedom of thought and conscience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2018.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2028.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the contrary, it must take regard to such a right, and it must enable some exemptions based on this right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2028.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2038.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such a system cannot and may not force people to act contrary to their conscience and against the best interest of the child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2038.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2049.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, apart from that, the vaccination policy must include and reflect respect to the right to freedom of thought and conscience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2049.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2059.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It must be transparent, well-reasoned, proportionate, without the influence of persons who are in conflict of interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2059.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2069.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And last but not least, it must include fair compensation for those who suffer harm to their health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2069.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2075.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The gravest errors on the side of the government are the following ones.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2075.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2103.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, vaccinations are introduced as mandatory, and accordingly, repressive measures are adopted in a non-transparent manner without sufficient reasoning, disproportionately and irrationally with involvement and influence of people who share vested interests in the matter and are in a massive conflict of interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2103.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2127.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, despite one of the chambers of the Constitutional Court of the Czech Republic having adjudicating and exceptions from the blanket mandatory vaccination policy on the grounds of freedom of thought and conscience, the applicants were not given an opportunity of such an exemptions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2127.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2145.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, in the case of harm to person's health originating as a result of mandatory vaccination, even after the recent adoption of the compensation bill, the right to just satisfaction of the harm is not guaranteed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2145.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2158.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, I would like to address the first point, which is the lack of credibility, lack of reasoning, and disproportionality of the blanket mandatory vaccination policy in the Czech Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2158.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2167.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government refers to the approach and attitudes of the Czech medical professional societies in support of mandatory vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2167.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2173.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this forum, there is no room to debate and rebut their individual statements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2173.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2199.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But what must be mentioned is that if we uncritically followed the stance of the Czech professional associations and their call for repressions and repressive attitudes, regardless human rights, we would still conduct involuntary sterilization of Roma women and disabled women.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2199.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2204.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And up to this day, the psychiatric patients would be detained in cages.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2204.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2228.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is mainly because of this professional association that the Czech Republic is still actively reverting to such practices as placing newborns and infants in government care institutions, ill treatment of psychiatric clients, use of surgical castration or of sex offenders, and other similar inhuman practices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2228.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2236.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The very fact that an opinion is adopted by a Czech professional association is not a decisive one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2236.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2243.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is solely and merely one of the claims that needs to be approached critically.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2243.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2252.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mainly, it is necessary to take into consideration that medical professional associations used to cooperate with the former totalitarian regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2252.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2261.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They used to participate in breaches of human rights, and they continue dismissing and despising human rights and freedoms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2261.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2269.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They do not even respect the right to freedom of expression of their own members, doctors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2269.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2274.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the agreement among the doctors is only an illusionary one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2274.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2296.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those who harbor slightly different opinions, and they don't necessarily have to be opposed to vaccination, but merely do not promote repressive regimes and called for safer vaccinations, are being silenced and have to face threats of professional liquidation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2296.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2311.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Roman Primula and Hanna Caberno-Kovar, who have been invited by the government as consultants, definitely do not represent the experts who promote safe vaccination and the best interest of the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2311.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2319.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their excessive conflicts of interest are something we have informed this court about in detail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2319.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2334.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have submitted the analysis of the League of Human Rights from 2012, which describes the close ties of these persons and their professional association with producers of vaccinations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2334.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2339.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Roman Primula not only profits from his ties</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2339.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2348.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with pharmaceutical industry, but he was not able to obtain a security clearance for more than one year up to now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2348.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2355.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both of the mentioned persons and their associations lack professional credibility entirely.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2355.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2362.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They promote the interests of the vaccine producers and not the interests of the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2362.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2369.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite that, the government follows the opinions of such so-called experts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2369.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2379.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question I have to ask is, does the government really have no independent, impartial and professional credible experts?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2379.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2390.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This brings me to the most important points and arguments about what is that is significantly wrong with the blanket mandatory vaccination policy in the Czech Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2390.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2424.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, there is no well-reasoned report nor analysis that would, before the introduction of obligation of vaccination against each of the nine diseases, assess the necessity of such a measure for the protection of public health, and that would be for the introduction of the condition of vaccination against every one of the nine diseases for the access to pre-school education, assess the necessity of such a measure for the protection of public health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2424.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2445.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, such a reasoned report and analysis cannot, in any case, be replaced by an entirely one-sided and purpose-based, exposed, drafted opinion of the professional association of the here-presented consultants who entirely lack credibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2445.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2456.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such a report, in its entirety, not exceeding 15 pages and covering all nine diseases subject to mandatory vaccination, has been submitted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2456.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2471.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to stress that their opinion does not at all address the matter of necessity of the condition of vaccination against each of these diseases for access to pre-school education.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2471.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2496.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, although such an analysis has been made in case of vaccination against hepatitis B in the past, with conclusion that introducing blanket vaccination is not suitable, several years later, such a vaccination was introduced not only as a blanket measure, but immediately as a mandatory one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2496.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2504.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant, Pavel Vavrička, was subject to a penalty, inter alia, for failure to comply with this vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2504.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2532.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And fourth, since May 2020, the amended Act on the Protection of Public Health has come into effect, which broadens the prohibition of access of not fully vaccinated children, not only to the nursery schools and facilities with state subsidies, but also to any private, non-educational facilities for the children of pre-school age.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2532.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2552.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it has been affirmed by the response by the Ministry of Health to our application for information, the amendment of the Act was adopted without any scientific evidence or analysis that would reason such an oppressive measure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2552.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2565.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government is attempting to punish to the large extent and to complicate the lives of the families who do not obediently follow the state vaccination scheme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2565.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2568.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They do it because they can.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2568.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2578.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they do not at all bother to even pretend that they have any professional basis for doing so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2578.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2586.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither the government nor the Czech courts address the fact that the existing system of repressions is not rational.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2586.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2607.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It makes no sense whatsoever, and mainly that for the access of the child to pre-school facilities, even vaccination against diseases where the transmission among children is not a realistic threat, this includes, for example, tetanus and hepatitis B. The unreasonableness lies also</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2607.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2618.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the fact that the staff of the schools are not subject to mandatory vaccination and not even tested for the mentioned diseases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2618.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2650.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For more details, we would like to refer to the well-reasoned and accurately argued dissenting opinion of the Constitutional Court Judge Katerina Šimáčková, as well as to the public, as to the opinion of the former public defender of rights, Anna Šabatová, who were the sole officials in the Czech Republic to be interested in the question of proportionality of the blanket mandatory vaccination policy in the Czech Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2650.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2660.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their conclusion is that the Czech law is disproportionate, irrational, and constitutionally nonconforming.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2660.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2678.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both the constitutional judge and the former ombudsperson consider the denial of the pre-school education to a child to be a sanction for violation of the obligation to subject the child to the full list of the prescribed mandatory vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2678.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2706.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the opinion of the judge Šimáčková, the majority of judges of the Constitutional Court failed to meet their obligation to assess impartially and without prejudice the constitutionality of the legislation on mandatory vaccination and merely approach this legal test as the defense of the general suitability of a vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2706.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2711.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Judges, let me move on the second argument</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2711.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2716.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of my speech that is the argument of freedom of conscience and thought.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2716.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2732.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant Pavel Vavřička and the parents of the applicants are loving and caring parents for whom the interest of their children is an absolute priority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2732.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2748.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of applicants Proko Proleček and Markéta Novotná, their parents even hold a university degree in the field of biology and they do not fully dismiss and reject vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2748.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2762.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They even allowed their children to be vaccinated against the most serious diseases in cases where they assess the benefits of vaccination or overwhelmingly prevail over the risks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2762.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2768.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of the parents acted in line with their best conviction and conscience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2768.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2783.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2015, the Constitutional Court of the Czech Republic decided that there must be an exemption from the blanket policy of mandatory vaccination on grounds of the freedom of thought and conscience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2783.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2799.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its judgment, it stated that in case of the exemption, I quote, a public body must not subject to the obligation of vaccination or to a sanction or enforce it in any other way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2799.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2813.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the Constitutional Court found that the thought and conscience of the parents in certain cases shall override the obligation of vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2813.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2820.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants, however, were not given an opportunity to exercise this exemption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2820.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2832.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of applicant Vavrička, the court merely addressed the matter of freedom of religion, which was not the right relied on by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2832.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2843.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such an exemption based on the right to freedom of thought and conscience was not at all assessed in the cases of other applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2843.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2858.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government did not confer such an exemption within the law, and there is not another single case of a recognized exception apart from the mentioned case from 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2858.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2882.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that the medical authorities as well as the World Health Organization recommend a variety of vaccination, but contrary to the Czech professional organizations, it doesn't require the application of repressions, and it doesn't require disproportionate interference with human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2882.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2894.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Interference with human rights in the form of a refusal of education to the children who are not fully vaccinated and enforcement of vaccination via penalties and fines.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2894.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2902.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One thing is enforcing of the vaccination being available and the cost covered by the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2902.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2920.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it is a completely different question when we assess its blanket enforcement against everyone, even against a minority of people who are prevented from complying with the mandatory vaccination on the grounds of their conscience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2920.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2935.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is necessary to bear in mind that science is a tool for improvement of the quality of people's lives, but it is not and cannot be the only voice to be heard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2935.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2946.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, we would have to succumb to the dictatorship of professionals, or to put it more precisely, the dictatorship of the pharmaceutical industry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2946.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2954.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The findings of medical science, however, are limited and undergo continuous development.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2954.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2964.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>History has proven on many occasions that medical science had been wrong and that certain procedures were more harmful than beneficial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2964.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2974.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>History has also indicated that involuntary interference with the physical integrity of human beings threatens human dignity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2974.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2997.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With all due respect to the success of vaccination against serious infections, nowadays it cannot be stated without any reservation that the entire list of existing vaccinations and a high-tech overcrowded vaccination scheme is ambiguously beneficial for the health of all children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2997.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3029.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the government and other member states argue that the obligation to vaccinate is not related to forced vaccination to which a human being has to be subjected, but merely to penalization and exclusion from the preschool facilities, we would like to respond to that by insisting that this doesn't mean that this indirect way of enforcement is proportional.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3029.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3055.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whether it is direct physical enforcement of mandatory vaccination or indirect sanctions of the impact in the light of interference with the rights of children remain very similar, because some children will at the end be vaccinated as a result of the pressure placed on their parents contrary to their best interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3055.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3074.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The very fact that the applications have not been, sorry, the very fact that the applicants have not been vaccinated or fully vaccinated doesn't mean they were not under the threat on interference with their physical integrity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3074.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3089.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or would an imposition of a penalty in response to a legitimate exercise, for example, of the right to freedom of expression instead of physical silencing of the speaker be acceptable?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3089.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3104.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is substantial is the fact that the state forces the parents by imposing sanctions to act against their conscience and against what they consider best for the health of their children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3104.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3119.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is worth mentioning that driving a person to act against their will or conscience qualifies under the definition of degrading treatment prohibited by Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3119.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3132.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third argument I would like to address is the act on compensation for damage to health caused by compulsory vaccination that came into effect in April 2020.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3132.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3148.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our submission, we, among others, noted that this act was criticized by the experts in healthcare as it failed to provide sufficient extent of compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3148.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3162.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since then, in the course of legislative procedure, the situation has been substantially aggravated concerning the chances of the injured party to fair compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3162.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3180.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The compensation was limited solely to cases of, I quote, extraordinary grave harm on health of a person, which is the expression defined by the case law of the Supreme Court in a very restrictive manner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3180.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3214.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the judgment of the Supreme Court dated 27th June 2019, file number 25CDO4201, 2018, this term cannot be deemed to include internal injuries due to which the relevant person fell into a three-week-long unconsciousness and was better ridden for the period of six months without a possibility to move.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3214.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3229.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In line with the decision of the Supreme Court, the consequences of such harm have to be so grave as to permanently exclude the injured person from the majority of spheres of social life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3229.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3248.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the virtue of act on compensation, will the overwhelming majority of the injured parties not have a valid entitlement to compensation should the harm not to be extraordinary grave?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3248.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3279.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also know here that the injured parties who have suffered health damage as a result of vaccination in the period since 2014 until the mentioned act on compensation became effective will not enjoy a valid entitlement to compensation at all since this period the harm is not attributable to any provider of healthcare services nor to the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3279.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3296.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is therefore obvious that the act on compensation in the current form doesn't meet the requirements of the Convention on Biomedicine concerning the right to fair compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3296.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3302.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President and honorable judges, to conclude, I would like to mention</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3302.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3320.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that this very case is being addressed in our society at an unprecedented times of coronavirus pandemic that has represented and still represents many limitations, restrictive measures, but also many concerns.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3320.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3349.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But not even this fact and not even the significant concerns of some fraction of the public can lead to the conclusion that the state has the opportunity to interfere disproportionately with the fundamental human rights and freedoms, needless to say, with the physical integrity of a healthy human being without any symptoms of a disease.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3349.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3361.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here I would like to refer to the explanatory report accompanying the article on free and informed consent of the Convention of Biomedicine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3361.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3374.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no doubt that certain governments want to have the widest and unlimited authority to interfere with human rights in healthcare issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3374.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3386.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Equally, there is no doubt that from the side of the state and government experts, there might be other interests in play than the welfare of the society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3386.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3393.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are not seeking before this court to determine a common European health policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3393.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3405.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are merely pleading for our arguments to be heard as in the dissenting opinions of the Czech Constitutional Court Judge, Katerina Simáčková.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3405.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3422.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are pleading for this court to designate the limitations that at the moment have remained unrestricted of the arbitrary Czech repressive vaccination policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3422.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3438.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are seeking for this court to declare that the rights of the applicants conferred by the Article 8 and 9 of the Convention and Article 1 of the Additional Protocol were violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3438.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3438.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3441.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3444.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Ms. Candigliota.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3444.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3451.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to my colleagues on the bench, the judges who are wishing to put questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3451.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3452.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Wojtyczek.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3455.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3456.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3456.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3459.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have four questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3459.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3468.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first one is addressed to both parties and concerns the repartition of the burden of proof and the standard of proof.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3468.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3482.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to hear the view of both parties on the issue of the burden of proof in this case and of the standard of proof applicable to this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3482.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3498.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question is also addressed to both parties and concerns the judgments of the Czech Constitutional Court, which recognize the right to conscientious objection in respect of vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3498.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3507.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are these judgments self-executing, or do they require implementing legislation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3507.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3525.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to hear the view of both parties on this issue, whether this right can be asserted without implementing legislation, or does it require legislation which would enable to assert this right to conscientious objection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3525.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3532.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the third question is also addressed to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3532.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3537.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The policies in respect of vaccination vary from one state to another.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3537.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3541.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are states which introduce mandatory vaccinations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3541.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3548.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are states which base their policies upon positive incitements and recommendations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3548.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3578.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are there any statistical data which would enable us to evaluate the efficiency of both approaches and the spread of the different diseases in the context of mandatory vaccinations and the context of the opposite policy based upon incitements and recommendations?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3578.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3590.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, the fourth question, which is addressed mainly to the government, maybe the applicants would also like to comment on this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3590.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3611.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What are the precise targets concerning the immunization level among the population in percentage to eradicate the nine diseases which are on the list of diseases in respect of which there is an obligation to vaccinate?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3611.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3624.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are there precise numbers concerning the level of herd immunity which is necessary to be reached in order to eradicate the disease?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3624.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3633.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And are there differences among the nine diseases which are concerned by this obligation to vaccinate?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3633.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3633.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3635.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3636.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Chanturia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Lado Chanturia</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3643.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3645.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3645.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3652.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have one question for the government, one question for the applicants, and one question for both.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3652.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3674.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question, in its judgment, the Constitutional Court of Czech Republic, in its judgment of 3rd February 2011, decided that the protection of individual autonomy requires that, exceptionally, the persons concerned not be forced to undergo compulsory vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3674.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3676.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is follow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3676.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3692.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Have there been any concrete cases in which children were admitted to preschool facilities without having vaccinated according to existing law?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3692.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3698.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question, it relates to Article 9 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3698.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3712.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Had the children been vaccinated, what repercussions would this have had on their, on children's and their parents' beliefs under the Article 9 of the convention?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3712.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3722.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third question, you all know that vaccination could provoke some health complications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3722.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3731.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Who would be responsible for the costs of the treatment necessary in relation to those complications?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3731.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3731.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3732.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3734.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Harutyunyan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Armen Harutyunyan</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3739.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3741.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3741.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3744.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I have two questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3744.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3749.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One already my colleague, Judge Wojtyczek, asked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3749.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3760.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think, I hope that my questions for government and particularly for Mr. Prymula, maybe he as a medical expert will be able to spread the light on this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3760.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3778.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, of course, I would like, it will be interesting for me to know if there is some research comparing the situation in both situation, the countries where it is a mandatory duty in vaccination and in the countries where it is not mandatory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3778.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3790.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whether we have a research-based statistical data so that the mandatory duty in mandatory duty country, the situation is better.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3790.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3793.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And what is the result of that?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3793.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3809.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question, if how the children who are not vaccinated can infect the ones who are already vaccinated and they have immunity?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3809.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3818.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because when we are speaking about the interest of children who have to be vaccinated and the interest of others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3818.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3822.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would like to know you as a medical expert, can you explain us?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3822.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3829.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If they are vaccinated and already they have immunity, how the other ones who are not vaccinated can be dangerous for them?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3829.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3829.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3831.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3833.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Seibert-Fohr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Anja Seibert-Fohr</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3835.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3837.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3837.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3842.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to address both parties, the government and the applicant, concerning two issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3842.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3851.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The one is, the first one is about the best interest of the child, and the second one is about the question of necessity that you have already dealt with.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3852.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3860.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, with regard to the best interest of the child, I was wondering who decides on what is the best interest of the child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3860.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3866.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question means, to what extent do parents' rights play a role over here?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3866.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3881.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, what happens if the parents' attitudes divert from scientific evidence, including recommendations given by the World Health Organization?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3881.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3890.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, let me turn to the question of necessity, which is also relevant to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3890.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3902.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I was wondering, if I go through all of the different vaccinations, they have different mechanisms, and I'm sure that the expert will be able to elaborate on that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3902.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3912.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to ask the question, why is vaccination of young children against hepatitis B necessary or not?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3912.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3924.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After all, it seems to be transmitted via blood contact, a risk that does not seem to be that high in preschool.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3924.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3934.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would like to appreciate your comments on that, especially since the expert, Mr. Primolov,has referred to measles and pertussis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3934.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3948.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, we have seen that we have nine vaccinations over here, so I would be interested in hearing what are the reasons for the mandatory vaccination of tetanus and diphtheria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3948.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3955.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To what extent does it protect the health of others?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3955.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3973.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have referred extensively to herd immunity, so you may want to elaborate a little bit on to what extent the single vaccinations contribute to herd immunity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3973.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3983.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, with respect to the applicant, you have made the argument that the mandatory regime does not provide for any kind of exceptions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3983.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3988.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to hear...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3988.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3993.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You were questioning the necessity with regard to all vaccinations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3993.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3998.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So let's turn to poliomyelitis, for example, or measles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3998.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4009.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To what extent would allowing exception be contrary to the aim of providing protection against these kinds of diseases?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4009.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4009.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4010.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4011.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4011.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4012.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Bošnjak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Marko Bošnjak</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4014.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4016.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4016.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4025.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions for the government, but of course the applicants are very welcome to comment on this if they so wish.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4025.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4035.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first question refers to the list of compulsory vaccinations, namely how is this list actually drawn up?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4035.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4045.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, I'm interested in hearing what are the criteria to include or not to include a specific vaccination on the list.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4045.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4057.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this particular respect, my question is a little bit similar or continues the question of my colleague, Judge Seibert-Fohr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4057.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4064.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this particular respect, I'm also interested in the procedure of drawing up such a list.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4064.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4068.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, what is the role of experts?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4068.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4073.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How is their independence from conflict of interest guaranteed?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4073.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4085.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And how are any critical views taken into account when drawing up such a list?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4085.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4102.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question pertains to the issue of compensation of those children who suffer certain negative consequences from compulsory vaccinations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4102.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4111.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is my understanding that up to a certain point, the Czech law, the Czech legislation provided for such compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4111.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4115.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Later on, this was no longer the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4115.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4130.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, if I understand correctly, there have been some very recent developments which, according to the applicants, set very high threshold for such compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4130.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4161.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to hear from the government, but of course the applicants are also welcome to comment, what are or what were the reasons to first abolish such compensation in case of such consequences, to reintroduce it again, and what are the reasons to put a specific threshold in this particular respect?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4161.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4161.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you so much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4162.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4165.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very mutch. Le juge Pastor Vilanova, s'il vous plaît.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Pere Pastor Vilanova</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4168.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4171.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, M. le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4171.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4172.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'ai 3 questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4173.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4188.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La 1re dirigée à l'avocat qui représente M. Pavlichka, après, donc, une question dirigée au gouvernement et, finalement, donc, une question qui intéresse les 2 parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4189.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4198.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ceci n'obstant, rien n'empêche, donc, qu'il y ait des répliques, donc, à la question posée et aux requérants et au gouvernement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4198.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4204.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, venons-en, donc, à la 1re question, qui est celle dirigée, donc, aux requérants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4204.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4215.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pour autant que je sache, et ça intéresse, une fois de plus, M. Pavlichka, il s'oppose, donc, à faire vacciner ses enfants contre 3 vaccins, la poliomyélite, l'hépatite B et le tétanos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4215.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4222.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, il apparaît que M. Pavlichka a, dans le passé, fait vacciner ses enfants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4222.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4225.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce que cette démarche est complètement cohérente?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4225.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4231.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>2e question, celle dirigée, donc, au gouvernement et notamment, donc, à son expert.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4231.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4240.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce qu'on connaît le pourcentage d'effets secondaires graves, j'insiste, graves, dans le cadre de la vaccination obligatoire?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4240.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4244.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et enfin, donc, une question dont je veux agréer aux 2 parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4244.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4250.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il a été question de la Convention d'Oviedo et, notamment, ce qui intéresse les interventions médicales.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4250.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4258.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce que, à votre avis, la vaccination constitue une intervention médicale au sens de la Convention d'Oviedo?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4258.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4260.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je vous remercie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4262.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4263.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucup. President Lemmens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4269.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4272.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4272.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4279.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question primarily for the government, but of course the applicant can, or the applicants can also reply.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4279.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4299.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It refers to what the Constitutional Court held in its judgment of 2015, where it stated that vaccination represents an act of social solidarity, and each individual must undergo vaccinations in order to protect the health of society as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4299.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4315.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you ended your pleading by referring to this statement of the Constitutional Court and by adding that there is a shared responsibility, that is, including an individual responsibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4315.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4317.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4317.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4320.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first one is the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4320.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4326.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Convention protects individual rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4326.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4328.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's the system of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4328.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4338.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now how does social solidarity or a shared responsibility relate to those rights in the Convention system?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4338.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4352.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is that a sort of a fundamental duty that exists apart from the rights, or is it just an argument to demonstrate a justification under the Convention of limitations to rights?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4352.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4365.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second related question is how far does such an individual responsibility or an individual solidarity go?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4365.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4373.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What are limitations, if any, to such a responsibility of citizens in society?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4373.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4379.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you could apply that to what is at stake here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4379.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4389.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can individuals be expected or even be required to contribute to a system of general prevention of diseases?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4389.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4389.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4391.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4394.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4394.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4398.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I see no further request for questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4398.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4402.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now withdraw for 30 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4402.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4408.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We will reconvene at 11 sharp, as one of the parties needs to withdraw to an adjacent room.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4408.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4410.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is suspended until 11.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4410.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4410.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4493.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4494.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4533.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4534.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4534.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4543.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed and I call Mr. Schorm for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4549.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4550.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4550.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4554.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should like to thank the outset for all the questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4554.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4563.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are very many, and I hope we will be able, at least to some extent, to satisfy your legitimate curiosity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4563.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4576.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would nonetheless also like to refer to our written submissions that have been quite numerous as well during all these proceedings on the six applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4576.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4600.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to the issue of the conflict of interests, I would highlight as the first thing that in light of what our counterpart on the applicant side has said earlier, it looks like the problem were the people and not the situation, the problem of vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4600.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4611.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think this has to be borne in mind when thinking about the questions of the conflict of interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4611.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4622.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before every meeting of the National Committee on Immunization, members are obliged to declare any possible conflict of interest they could have with regard to any issue on the agenda.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4622.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4632.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it's also in line with the disclosure code adopted by the European Federation of Pharmaceutical Industries and Associations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4632.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4660.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also highlight that there are various National Immunization Advisory Committees according to the WHO standards, and the WHO has set six functionality criteria, such as the legislative or administrative basis, formal written terms of reference, et cetera, et cetera, and mandatory disclosure of any conflict of interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4660.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4683.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should also like to highlight that according to a study prepared some years ago in 2008 for the WHO, there are National Immunization Committees in 53 member states that comprise the Euro region, and the majority of them have no representation from public and or advocacy groups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4683.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4689.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All members are mostly representative of the governmental agencies and medical professional societies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4689.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4696.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think our approach is in conformity with the prevailing approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4696.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4712.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to the issue of the burden of proof, maybe I should put a question whether it is a matter of proving that it is necessary to vaccinate against certain diseases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4712.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4724.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well we consider this to be basically an expert question which is aimed at the national authorities, and they are the best placed to respond to these issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4724.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4735.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a question about the Constitutional Court's judgment which established an exemption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4735.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4741.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This judgment is self-executing and does not require any additional legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4741.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4750.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only the authorities must deal with objections based on this kind of exemptions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4750.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4773.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In practice, there are virtually no cases, but the courts always highlight that when something has happened to another child in the family, this could be a legitimate reason for an exemption based on conscience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4773.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4776.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this is constant in the courts' case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4776.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4784.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to highlight that no one from the applicants has been forced really to accept vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4784.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4790.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So when there was refusal from the parents, there was no vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4790.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4803.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we think that the people who refuse bear the consequences in the name of the health, of the public health, of the members of the society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4803.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4810.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fine is very low and the non-admission to a nursery school is not a sanction per se.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4810.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4818.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a measure in order to secure security and health of children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4818.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4835.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The best interest of the child, the interest really lies in the best protection, the highest attainable protection of health of children, which is mentioned in the Convention on the Rights of the Child.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4835.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4838.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have already referred to that in my speech.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4838.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4854.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, although this is a very generally expressed best interest of the child, it can always be assessed in light of the objections raised by parents in individual proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4854.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4858.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the Convention on the Rights of the Child is normally self-executing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4858.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4863.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course, there are not only administrative proceedings but also judicial review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4863.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4881.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to the issue of compensation for damage caused by compulsory vaccination, the truth is that up to the end of 2013, if I'm not wrong, under the old civil code, the liability was borne by the medical care provider.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4881.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4890.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was considered as inconsistent with the mandatory character of the obligation to provide vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4890.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4895.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But nonetheless, there was a gap in the legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4895.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4908.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would highlight nonetheless that there was still the possibility to refer to Article 20 of the OVA Law Convention, which establishes the possibility to ask for compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4908.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4915.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this convention is also a convention which has a constitutional standard in the Czech Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4915.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4924.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The today's conception of the new Act on compensation or on liability is based on the state's liability.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4924.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4942.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to the threshold of seriousness, by law, secondary legislation is under preparation which should really facilitate the burden of proof when there are typical corollary effects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4942.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4950.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There should be an independent expert commission which would assess each case individually at the administrative level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4950.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4953.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course, there would be judicial review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4953.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4969.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also consider that vaccination is a medical intervention under the OVA Law Convention, but we would refer to the exception provided for by Article 26 in the name of the protection of public health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4969.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4977.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, from the various legal perspectives, and then I would like you, Mr. President,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4977.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4980.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to give the floor to Professor Primula.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4980.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4993.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to the Act of Social Solidarity, well, we think simply that it's a matter of the protection of health, which is mentioned in the second paragraphs of various provisions of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4993.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5000.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, not in Article 2 of Protocol No. 1, but we know the mechanism of limitations</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5000.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5002.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>under this provision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5002.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5014.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would refer it's the protection of health with some exemptions and also with safeguards to which I have already alluded in my previous speech.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5014.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5020.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For this time being, thank you very much, and I would pass the burden of responding to your questions to Professor Primula.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5020.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5020.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5022.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5023.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, Mr. Prymula.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5027.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5029.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5029.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5037.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will address a couple of your questions towards medical issues and related epidemiological aspects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5037.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5050.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Basically, if you are talking about policies, so different countries may adopt different policies concerning mandatory immunization and voluntarily-based immunization in many countries is just combination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5050.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5081.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if we call for some proof of efficacy of such an approach, at least two papers have been published, and a recent one from previous year, I suppose, is showing that the mandatory immunization is better or increasing prevalence of measles vaccination by almost 4% and pertussis vaccination by about 2%.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5081.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5082.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this is a proof.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5082.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5102.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Speaking about the Czech Republic, we may compare our mandatory immunization with coverage, for example, for hexavalent vaccine, 98%, going down recently for 92%, and the measles coverage from originating 98% to 88%.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5102.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5120.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But if we compare just voluntary-based immunization in the country with this pneumococcal immunization or HPV immunization, in those we are much lower for HPV, 60%, for pneumococcal immunization, 64%.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5120.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5135.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Speaking about possible individual targets for individual diseases, what should be herd immunity level, it is complicated to explain because for each disease, it's a different figure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5135.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5143.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for some disease, we do not have herd protection like tetanus because this is just individual protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5143.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5146.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for tetanus, we do not have such a level, definitely.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5146.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5160.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But for measles, we need very high figures like 98%, and recently are going down in many European countries for vast majority of vaccines and diseases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5160.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5163.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In hexavalent vaccine, it's around 95%.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5163.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5170.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So those are figures, and in many European countries, just we are going down.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5170.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5177.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Speaking about...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5177.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5189.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>how may non-vaccinated children interfere with vaccinated children and how they can infect vaccinated children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5189.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5197.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So basically, as we are talking about herd immunity and herd protection, in those, we may reach about 95%.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5197.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5202.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if we are in school group, it's about 30 people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5202.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5209.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So one or two of them may be not immunized, and we do not have any troubles interfering with the others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5209.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5230.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But if we have more than this limited number of children unimmunized, we may interfere with the disease because our immunity may be overhelmed with exposure to higher proportion of agents and different bacterias.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5230.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5245.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this is the reason why we should keep certain fragile balance in the group, and this is the reason why we try to keep relatively high immunization coverage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5245.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5256.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another question, what are the different mechanism of action, why we are immunizing against hepatitis B in such small children?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5256.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5258.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's always a big discussion, why is that?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5258.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5265.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because you are right, the exposure to hepatitis B in such a younger age, it's quite limited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5265.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5285.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other side, it is a recommendation of WHO to immunize children as early as possible because if you are accidentally infected in such a young age, about 90% may develop chronic cirrhosis, and based on that, we may even die.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5285.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5323.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the major reason is probably that we have just long life immunization schedule, and if those children are immunized in early childhood with higher coverage, we may stay with that schedule till the entire life, and this is the reason why we are not willing to move it to upper ages and the situation is quite patient in the situation with hepatitis B immunization, even in the Czech Republic, and hepatitis B is step by step disappearing because we are immunizing the whole public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5323.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5354.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another issue, list of compulsory vaccinations, why we have those nine diseases and what are procedures, how it is developed, basically, the original list of diseases was based on our law since 1960, and step by step, this is considered by expert if it is necessary to keep the whole list or if it is necessary to change something in that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5354.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5392.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And after providing results of serological surveys, we are able to interfere with immunization schedule to postpone certain immunization and even to release some from the original list, and based on that, we have decided to move BCG immunization against TB because the risk of side effects was higher than the exposure to TB in the Czech Republic, so TB immunization, BCG immunization is not anymore mandatory for entire population but only for risk groups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5392.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5411.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So recently, we have nine diseases on the list, and it's necessary to say that it's a correct approach because if we just mandate one vaccine, and it is measles, we have three-valent vaccine, and mumps and rubella should be immunized together.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5411.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5415.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if we just declare one disease, we are immunizing, in reality, three diseases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5415.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5438.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And similar approaches to six diseases and hexavalent vaccine, definitely, we may go for pentavalent vaccine, but the reality is that it's better to declare all those than only one and using in a relatively different way the others, but on the other side, at the end of the day, we will immunize the similar figure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5438.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5446.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we have nine mandatory vaccines in the system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5446.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5455.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the last question concerning serious adverse events and possibility how to compensate them and how many do we have.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5455.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5464.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So basically, recently, we have a system of pharmacovigilance in which we are reporting side effects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5464.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5467.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These figures may be underreported.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5467.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5484.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is quite obvious, but the reality is now that for hexavalent vaccine, we have 226 adverse events per year in 2018, and for the MMR vaccine, 130.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5484.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5510.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Based on international data and from recalculation for the Czech Republic, we may expect that those serious cases, and this is based mostly on US adverse events and their Vaccine Injury Compensation Act, we may expect about six serious cases to be reimbursed or compensated per year in the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5510.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5510.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5511.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5513.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5513.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5518.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Schorm, has the government then concluded their observations in the second round?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5519.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5521.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, yes, I think so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5521.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5531.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I've just come to the fact that I've probably forgotten to respond to the question of who pays for treatment of effects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5531.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5535.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, it's usually borne by the public health insurance scheme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5535.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5544.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think this is provided for normally as any other diseases or health problems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5544.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5545.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this is probably all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5545.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5551.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I really apologize if we have missed to respond to any of your questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5551.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5554.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will give the judges the opportunity in a moment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5554.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5556.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Candigliota, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5569.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5573.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5573.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5579.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to address the question about the standard of proof.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5579.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5585.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm sorry I didn't understand well this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5585.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5619.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the standard of proof is meant in the sense of the proof that the vaccination system is safe and is necessary, so we think that there is the obligation of the government to show the proofs, to have analysis and studies for every of each nine obligatory vaccinations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5619.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5631.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because it's not the parents and the families, they have no possibility to perform such analysis and studies and so on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5631.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5640.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think that the government should be more active and should have some materials.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5640.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5648.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But even if we ask for such materials, they have completely nothing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5648.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5677.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the question was meant what are the criteria or standards for the exemption based on conscience, we think that there is different practice in different countries because there are countries, for example Canada, and there is this exemption based on conscience and there are criteria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5677.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5685.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But our Constitutional Court of the Czech Republic in its decision also formulated such criteria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5685.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5692.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first criteria, I will say more about it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5692.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5729.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first is constitutional relevance of the arguments included in the conscious objection, importance and necessity of the reasons that the objecting person uses to support their opinion, consistency and persuasiveness of the arguments of the objecting persons, and social consequences that may result from accepted exemption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5729.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5747.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we say that these criteria can be used also in other cases, not only in case of financial penalty, but also in case of access to preschool education.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5747.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5755.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the question about the...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5755.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5775.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was another question, if the exemption of conscience is self-executing or an implementation in law is needed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5775.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5798.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case I mentioned, the Constitutional Court concluded that the exemption of conscience is not a requirement and concluded that the exemption can be assessed on a base...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5798.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5817.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can be assessed in case of financial penalty because the authorities have possibility to take into account the belief or conscience of the person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5817.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5832.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We call it the material side of the offence and it means that the authorities can deal with the danger for the society of the offence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5832.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5845.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So according to the Constitutional Court, in case of financial penalties, there is no need to implement this exemption into the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5845.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5862.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the different situation is in the case of preschool education because the schools and the authorities have no legal basis for granting such an exemption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5862.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5893.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was an exceptional case of the Regional Court of Pilsen, Pilsen, and such an exemption was recognised also for the preschool education, but it was only one exceptional case that never happened again in other cases of other families.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5893.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5911.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it comes to the questions regarding statistical data, we claim that the countries with the voluntary system of vaccination protect sufficiently the public health and this is the proof.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5911.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5935.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, we don't have specific statistical data or analysis on this issue, but there is another very important and interesting question that in these countries with voluntary systems, the parent has no reason to cheat the system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5935.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5964.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the statistical data that are in these countries are more reliable than in, for example, Czech Republic because the parents are motivated, for example, to pay the doctor for the false medical certificate or to falsify the medical records.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5964.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5983.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would say that not only the voluntary systems protect well the public health, but they have also good information to take measures, other measures to protect public health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5983.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6009.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They know that all, what is the vaccination state of the children in, for example, kindergarten, but in Czech Republic we don't know because the parents are motivated to cheat in simply words.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6009.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6040.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would like to say that the protection of public health is illusionary in Czech Republic because when some epidemic arises, the authorities cannot know precisely if, for example, in a kindergarten really all children are vaccinated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6040.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6072.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I know that, for example, in Germany there is a case law that in case of measles, the children who are not vaccinated can be excluded from the preschool education or school education, I don't know, but only, not permanently, but only for a limited time when there is the danger for the public health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6072.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6088.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think that these measures are more effective than blanket mandatory vaccination with repression.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6088.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6117.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the best interest of the child, according to the Czech Constitutional Court and also I think according to the general interpretation, the best interest of the child is based on the parental decision making and we presume that the parents know better than anybody else what is best for the children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6117.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6130.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only in extreme cases the state can interfere in the parental rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6130.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6136.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then I would like to say a few words about the side effects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6136.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6156.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We claim that the side effects are not properly studied in the Czech Republic, but not only in the Czech Republic, there are no long-term studies comparing the state of health of fully vaccinated children and children who are not vaccinated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6156.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6168.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are some studies showing that vaccinated children suffer more of different chronical diseases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6168.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6176.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question, I would answer also to the question how to prevent polio and measles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6176.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6186.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I said before, I am convinced that the voluntary system of vaccination protects the public health well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6186.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6205.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This system is based on positive motivation of parents and as I also mentioned, there are other measures, for example, temporary exclusion of a non-vaccinated child from the collective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6205.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6221.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think that these are the measures that are proportionate and that can not only well, but better than the repressive system prevent infectious diseases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6221.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6233.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then I would like to answer the question about the consistency of Mr. Vavřička's conscience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6233.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6244.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was consistent during the whole procedure before the Czech authorities in the Czech Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6244.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6257.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is possible that he in his life changed his opinion that at the beginning he vaccinated his children and then he changed his conviction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6257.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6270.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But according to the Czech Constitutional Court, the consistency is required only during the procedure before the authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6270.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6280.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is accepted that the person before had another opinion and changed it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6280.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6307.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to compensation, I would like to mention another case of my client that is an infant who is permanently paralyzed in half of his face and according to his doctors, there is a causal link between the vaccination, obligatory vaccination and the harm he suffered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6307.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6320.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the government and the Czech courts refused any compensation arguing that there is no state liability for the negative impact of vaccination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6320.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6330.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, here present Mr. Primula elaborated record</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6330.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6350.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that there is no causal link between the damage and the vaccination and he has never seen the child and I think that it also shows the conflict of interest of this expert.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6350.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6368.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to conclude that I really appreciated the question how far can the solidarity or mandatory solidarity can go because it's very important question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6368.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6380.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government argues that there are some children that cannot be vaccinated and we need to protect them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6380.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6396.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the other people are obliged to undergo vaccination that can potentially harm their health and in some cases it really harms and very severely the health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6396.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6432.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think that the arguments of the government can be well used also for the obligation to donate a kidney to a sick person because the principle is the same and I think that we can recognize that it's not acceptable to give an obligation to a healthy person to donate his kidney because of public interest, because of interest of other people that unfortunately are not healthy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6432.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6451.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would like to hold the view that autonomy of the person must be respected and the person cannot be forced to be subjected to a potentially harmful intervention for the benefits of the others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6451.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6462.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think that there is the interest of public health but the obligation and repression is not acceptable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6462.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6462.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6464.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6467.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6467.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6470.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are there... Judge, Pastor Vilanova please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Pere Pastor Vilanova</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6473.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6474.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, M. le président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6475.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6477.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est une question que je veux...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6479.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6483.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Une question que je voudrais reposer à l'expert de la République tchèque.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6484.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6494.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A ma question de savoir quel était, plus ou moins, le pourcentage d'accidents graves alliçant donc avec la vaccination obligatoire...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6497.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6509.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il m'a répondu, il me semble avoir compris que, selon lui, il y avait à peu près 226 accidents graves, donc par an, en liaison avec la vaccination obligatoire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6510.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6514.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pouvez-vous donc confirmer ce chiffre-là?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6515.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6518.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pouvez-vous également dire qu'est-ce que vous entendez par accidents graves?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6519.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6531.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et également, c'était ma question principale, le pourcentage, donc 226 cas par an, mais par rapport à quel nombre approximatif de personnes vaccinées.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6532.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6536.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le pourcentage, et qu'est-ce que vous entendez exactement par accidents graves?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6536.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6536.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je vous remercie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6538.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6538.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6538.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6544.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are there other judges wishing to clarify or seek clarification?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6544.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6545.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6545.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6552.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Prymula, would you please provide an answer if you can?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6552.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6552.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6553.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6555.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, please, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6556.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6564.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Basically, in the Czech Republic, we have a cohort about 100,000 children, newborns.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6564.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6568.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What's a little bit higher in recent time, but we do not have full coverage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6568.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6573.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So let's suppose we have, per one shot, 100,000 kids.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6573.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6580.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have scheduled two plus one for hexavalent vaccine, what means 300,000 shots per dose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6580.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6591.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have those 228 adverse events, but it's necessary to say that many of them are very mild because those are reported to the system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6591.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6600.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some of them, it's a febrile reaction, 38.5, for example, without any consecutive events afterwards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6600.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6612.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So what I was referring to, we suppose that really serious adverse events will be about five to six with long-life possible sick relies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6612.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6612.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this was the figure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6617.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6621.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6621.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6626.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That then means that we are coming to a close in our hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6626.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6632.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to thank the parties for their submissions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6632.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6635.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6635.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6637.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered at a later date.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6637.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6641.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6641.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6642.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
