<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>4927011_26052021</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>10.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>11.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>21.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>23.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Good morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>23.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>36.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome all participants to this public hearing organized by the European Court of Human Rights with the use of video conferencing technology which has been made necessary due to the COVID-19 health crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>36.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>52.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wish to begin by thanking the applicants and the respondent government, as well as the third party intervener for their cooperation in preparing this hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case of Savickis and others versus Latvia, which I now declare open.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>52.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>62.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on 4 August 2011 under Article 34 of the convention by permanently resident non-citizens of the Republic of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>62.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>66.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Jurij Savickis, Mr. Gennadijs Nezdarovs,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>66.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>70.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Vladimir Spodokalo, Ms. Asia Zivicka,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>70.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>73.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as well as by Ms. Marzia Vagapova, who</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>73.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>76.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>now holds Russian nationality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>76.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>84.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the fifth section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the rules of court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>84.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>90.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on 22 June 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>90.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>98.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 1 December 2020, the chamber decided to relinquish jurisdiction in favor of the grand chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>98.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>114.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 5 February 2021, the Russian government expressed their intention to make use of their right to take part in the written and oral proceedings as a third party in conformity with Article 36, paragraph 1 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>114.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>118.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent government are represented by their agent, Kristīne Līce,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>118.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>122.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Ms. Elīna Luīze Vītola, Ms. Sandra</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>122.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>126.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kauliņa, and Ms. Baiba Felsberga, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>126.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>129.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Ms. Inese Nikuļceva,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>129.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>134.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>attorney at law, and Mr. Aleksandrs Kuzmins's advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>134.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>138.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian government are represented by Mr. Mikhail Galperin, representative</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>138.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>146.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the Russian Federation at the European Court of Human Rights, assisted by Ms. Alana Dzutseva, counsel, Mr. Sergey  Andreyev,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>146.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>150.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Sergey  Toropov, and Mr. Oleg Polokhov, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>150.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>154.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>154.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>165.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the respondent government and the representatives of the applicant and of the third party, I've determined the order of address as follows, Ms. Kristīne Līce for the Latvian government</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>165.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>168.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>will speak first, then Ms. Nikuļceva and Mr. Aleksandrs</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>168.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>173.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kuzmins for the applicants, and finally, Mr. Mikhail Galperin for the Russian government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>173.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>174.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Līce, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>178.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>183.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you and good morning. Mr. President, distinguished members of the Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>183.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>189.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in today's hearing, the Court is examining the case of Savitsky-Svendadas v Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>189.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>194.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court has asked a number of questions on various aspects of this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>196.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>211.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I address the admissibility and merits of the applicants' complaints, I will also provide the Government's responses to these questions, insofar as they have not yet been answered in the Government's written submissions. My statement today will likewise address</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>211.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>216.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the main arguments of the applicants and the third party intervener, the Russian Government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>217.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>224.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, I wish to note that the Government maintains its position, as submitted in its memorial on 5 February this year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>226.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>249.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before I turn to the Government's arguments regarding the admissibility and merits of the case, I wish to address two issues that repeatedly appear in the arguments of the applicants and the third party intervener, and that are crucial in the examination of the present case. The first issue is the scope of the applicants' complaints before the Court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>252.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>254.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the public international law principles relevant for determining this scope.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>254.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>271.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second issue is the unsubstantiated equation of the present case to the case of Andreeva v Latvia. As to the first issue, in other words, the scope of the case, it is important to bear in mind</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>271.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>279.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>what this case is not about. This case is not about the right to receive old-age pension,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>279.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>290.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as all applicants are insured and receive old-age pension. The case is also not about any difference</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>290.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>305.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>between the treatment of the applicants and the treatment of the Latvian citizens for the period since the restoration of Latvia's independence in 1990-1991. Instead, the dispute in the present</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>305.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>336.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>case is whether, in calculating supplements to the applicants' pensions as paid by Latvia, the Latvian authorities should take into account the periods of time the applicants have spent working or serving military service not in the territory of Latvia, which at the time was illegally occupied by the Soviet Union, but in another former USSR republic. In other words,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>336.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>357.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the dispute in the present case is whether Latvia is the state that must assume the obligation to compensate in a form of supplements to the applicants' pensions for the work and service carried out during Latvia's illegal occupation outside the territory of Latvia. For the ease</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>357.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>370.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of reference, in my statement I will use the term disputed years to refer to the periods of time when the applicants worked or served mandatory military service outside the territory of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>370.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>414.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, let me reiterate that the present case is not about the right to receive retirement pension, but about supplements for additional pension seniority accrued outside the territory of Latvia, which also means that the present case is about the limits to the obligations that, under international law, can be placed on Latvia, taking into account a lawful occupation by a foreign power for 50 years and also the wide margin of appreciation states enjoy when dealing with questions of economic and social policy. As to the second issue, that is to say the comparison</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>414.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>450.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the present case and the case of Andreeva versus Latvia previously decided by this Court, I wish to recall that in the Andreeva case the Grand Chamber found a violation of Article 1 of Protocol 1 in conjunction with Article 14 of the Convention, because the applicants in the Andreeva case resided in the territory of Latvia for all the years that constituted the disputed years and for that period of time forming legal and also actual ties only with Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>450.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>473.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, however, the disputed years consist of the time when the applicants worked or served the mandatory military service in Russia, Ukraine, Belarus, Turkmenistan, Tajikistan and Azerbaijan. Namely, during the disputed years relevance in the present case,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>473.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>488.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicants, unlike the applicants in the Andreeva case, did not reside in the territory of Latvia and had no legal ties with Latvia during the disputed years. This distinction</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>488.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>497.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is the crux of the present case for a number of reasons that I will emphasize during my statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>497.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>503.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, turning to the admissibility and merits of the case, I first wish to emphasize</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>503.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>514.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the case is set against complex historical backgrounds and raises a number of questions related to the obligations of states under international law. I will therefore begin</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>514.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>520.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>my statement with the assessment of the applicable principles of international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>520.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>539.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As noted by this court in the case of Zdanoka versus Latvia, following an ultimatum to allow an unlimited number of Soviet troops to be stationed in the Baltic countries, on 16th and 17th June 1940, the Soviet army invaded Latvia. The sitting government of Latvia at that time</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>539.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>554.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was removed from the office and a new government was formed under the direction of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union. From 21st July to 3rd August 1940, the Soviet Union completed</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>554.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>561.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the annexation of Latvia, forcing Latvia to become a part of the USSR. Thus, for 50 years</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>561.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>577.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>until 1990, when Latvia restored its independence, the entire territory of Latvia was under unlawful occupation and effective control by the USSR. This act constituted a violation of international law</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>577.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>595.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and in the light of the customary rules of state responsibility under international law, any legal obligations, including those related to payments of social security benefits, directly emanating from this occupation, fall on the occupying power. The International Court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>595.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>618.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Justice in its 1971 advisory opinion in the Namibia case, underlined that not sovereignty or legitimacy to title, but the physical control over the territory is the basis for state liability and for acts affecting other states. This principle has consistently been applied also by this court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>618.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>631.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in cases related to illegal occupation and exercise of effective and overall control over foreign territories. For example, in the cases of Cyprus versus Turkey, Catan versus Moldova and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>631.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>637.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Russia, and most recently in the decision in the case of Ukraine versus Russia regarding Crimea.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>637.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>658.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Considering that for 50 years of Latvia's occupation, including the disputed years, the USSR exercised effective control over the territory of Latvia, the same conclusions are equally applicable in the present case. In other words, the legal obligations in the field of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>658.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>677.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>social security that have a reason towards the former citizens of the USSR, under international law, fall on the state that exercised effective control and jurisdiction over those territories and persons during their respective years. Latvia did not exercise such jurisdiction</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>677.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>693.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>or effective control, therefore no obligation in the field of social security for the disputed years can fall on Latvia. Concluding otherwise, would lead to a situation where a legal benefit</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>693.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>708.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is derived from an illegal act, thus clearly going against the principle of ex injuria just non oritor. It would also lead to a manifestly unreasonable interpretation of the Convention,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>708.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>738.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as it would allow invoking Article 1 of Protocol 1 to the Convention to claim the obligation of any contracting party to provide social security benefits for years of work or service outside the territory of that contracting party and entirely unrelated to this contracting party in any other way. Furthermore, when assessing whether the applicants as non-citizens in the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>738.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>756.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>present case are a group of individuals that are in a similar or relatively comparable situation with Latvian citizens, the government submits that for this question as well the historical context of the creation of the status of non-citizens should be considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>756.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>776.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The statistics show that in 1935, five years before the occupation, 76% of Latvia's population were Latvians. But in 1989, that is to say a year before the restoration of independence,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>776.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>784.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>only 52% of the population were Latvians. The impact of Sovietization policies in the capital</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>784.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>790.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>figure was even bigger. It should be recalled that the International Court of Justice,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>790.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>811.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in its advisory opinion on the legal consequences of the construction of a wall in the occupied Palestinian territories, reiterated the prohibition of the occupying power to take measures in order to organize or encourage transfers of parts of its own population into the occupied territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>811.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>841.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the situation in Latvia, the extensive Sovietization policies carried out by the USSR during the occupation, whereby influx of workforce and military personnel in the territory of Latvia was artificially created, undoubtedly fall under the definition of measures prohibited under international law as defined by the ICJ. In 1990, Latvia restored its independence according</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>841.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>855.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the doctrine of state continuity, as Latvia considered and continued to exist de jure throughout the occupation, which was recognized by a number of other states. Therefore,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>855.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>870.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Latvian citizenship was not granted anew, but was restored to those individuals who held Latvian citizenship before the occupation and their descendants. As a result, a large number</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>870.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>883.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of persons present in the territory of Latvia were not automatically granted citizenship, and these are the persons who moved to Latvia during Latvia's illegal occupation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>883.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>911.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in order to protect those former USSR citizens who were brought to Latvia during the Sovietization process and who lost their USSR citizenship due to the collapse of the Soviet Union, to protect them from becoming stateless persons, Latvia, for humanitarian reasons, created the status of permanently resident non-citizen of Latvia. Therefore, the decision</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>911.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>924.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Latvia to introduce such a status has its roots in the doctrine of state continuity and, by extension, the general public international law. It must be emphasized that after the adoption</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>924.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>938.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the citizenship law in 1994, non-citizens were eligible to naturalize and acquire Latvian citizenship. In this context, it's important to underline that the status of non-citizen</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>938.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>953.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was intended as a temporary status, and individuals with non-citizen status were expected to naturalize or obtain a citizenship of another state if they so choose. It should also be added that the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>953.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>961.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>applicants could have naturalized and become the citizens of Latvia. Following the restoration of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>961.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>968.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>independence, Latvia created a pension system based on the principle of contributions. However,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>968.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>983.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>seeing that no pension funds existed at the moment of the restoration of its independence, Latvia decided to guarantee a minimal pension to all residents of Latvia. Therefore, as I noted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>983.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>998.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>at the beginning of my statement, the present case does not raise issues with regard to the basic pension that is awarded to all residents of Latvia, including the applicants. The only question in the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>998.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1030.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>present case is whether Latvia should pay supplements for additional pension seniority accrued during the disputed years, that is to say, for work and military service carried out in other former Soviet USSR republics outside Latvia's territory and before the restoration of Latvia's independence. Even though the obligation to pay pensions for work periods accrued during the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1030.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1052.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>occupation primarily falls onto the state that exercised jurisdiction over the persons during the disputed years, Latvia nevertheless decided to extend full pension advantages based on two criteria. First, the citizenship of the beneficiaries and second, the territoriality,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1052.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1067.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>meaning the employment or mandatory military service that was carried out in the territory of Latvia. Thus, a full pension benefits are awarded on the one hand to all Latvian citizens,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1067.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1096.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>regardless of where in the former USSR they were employed and resided, and on the other hand, to all other persons, namely non-citizens of Latvia, stateless persons, foreigners, whose work periods have been accrued within the territory of Latvia, thereby contributing to the development of Latvia's economy. Therefore, while the applicants in the Andreeva case worked</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1096.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1111.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the territory of Latvia and therefore fell in the latter category under the criteria of territoriality, the applicants in the present case do not. The applicants were not only physically</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1111.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1124.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>employed in the territory of another former USSR republic, but their residence was registered in the respective republic as well. Moreover, the central issue in the case of Andreeva versus</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1124.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1137.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Latvia was the definition of the concept of employment in Latvia, which is not the issue in the present case. In the present case, if compared to that of Andreeva versus Latvia,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1138.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1152.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>there is no dispute over the fact that the applicants did not live, did not reside in the territory of Latvia during the disputed years. Therefore, unlike the case of Andreeva versus</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1152.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1171.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Latvia, when it comes to the calculation of additional supplements to the pensions, the decisive factor is the territory in which the applicants were employed or served the mandatory military service and resided during the disputed years. To illustrate, one would hardly think of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1171.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1199.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a situation where a citizen of a former Yugoslavia, for example, having worked and resided for most of his or her life in one of the constituent states, decided to move to Latvia or France, and having done that, invoked responsibility of Latvia or France for the retirement pension entitlements for the employment carried out when residing in the former Yugoslavia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1200.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1228.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the government believes that the situation of the applicants in the present case is comparable to that of the applicants in the case of LV versus Austria, where the court held that the right to receive a pension in respect of activities carried out in a state other than the respondent state is not guaranteed under convention. Moreover, finding that the government</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1228.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1247.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the present circumstances has an obligation to grant full pension benefits to all individuals residing in the territory of Latvia would undermine the entire system of bilateral agreements of states in social security matters. Such a finding would render the bilateral social security</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1247.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1262.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>agreements already concluded between Latvia and Russia, Ukraine and Belarus meaningless and unnecessary. It should be noted that in the Andreeva case, the court explicitly recognised</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1262.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1282.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the importance of such bilateral agreements, and in paragraph 90 of the judgment stated that it, for its part, was fully aware of the importance of these agreements in the effective solution of the problems such as those arising in the Andreeva case. Thus, in reply to the court's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1282.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1300.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>questions regarding the relevance of the doctrine of state continuity in the present case and the difference of the present case from the case of Andreeva versus Latvia, the government draws two conclusions. First, as noted by the Constitutional Court of Latvia in its judgment of 17 February 2011,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1300.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1309.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Republic of Latvia is not the successor state of rights and liabilities of the former USSR.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1309.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1324.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pursuant to the doctrine of state continuity, a re-established state does not have the duty to undertake any liabilities that follow from the liabilities of the occupying power. Second,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1324.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1350.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the decision to grant full pension benefits to citizens regardless of their place of their employment and to non-citizens, foreigners and stateless persons who worked in the territory of Latvia is also a direct consequence of the doctrine of state continuity and the international law applicable in the present case. Moreover, as noted at the very beginning, the difference</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1350.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1383.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the present case and in the case of Andreeva versus Latvia, the differences are significant and the fact that the applicants in the present case were employed in another territory having created ties with the former USSR republics in the territory of which they carried out their work or military service, these differences are sufficient to establish that the conclusions of the court in the Andreeva case are not automatically applicable in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1383.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1390.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, turning to the question and visibility of the applicants' claims, I wish to</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1390.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1396.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>underline four arguments. First, the government reiterates that the applicants could not have had</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1396.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1410.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a possession or any legitimate expectation to receive from Latvia pensions for employment periods outside the territory of Latvia. Therefore, their claims ultimately fall outside the scope of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1410.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1420.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>article 1 of protocol 1 to the convention. Second, the government recalls that on 10 June 2019,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1420.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1428.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the first applicant, Mr. Savitsky, passed away and his heirs or other relatives have not come forward</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1428.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1434.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the case in this part should therefore be declared inadmissible. Third, the government</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1434.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1448.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>argues that four of the applicants have submitted their applications outside the six-month time limit, thereby failing to comply with article 35, paragraph 1 of the convention. And finally,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1448.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1462.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the government notes that the third applicant's complaint should be rejected due to the failure to exhaust domestic primitives. I will now elaborate these four arguments. With respect</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1462.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1488.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the first argument, I wish to recall that according to the well-established case law of this court, article 14 of the convention has no independent existence and its application can only be triggered if the complaint falls within the scope of one or more of the substantive rights guaranteed by the convention. In the present case, the applicants claim that they had a right to</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1488.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1504.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>receive retirement pension from Latvia in respect of the disputed years when they worked or served mandatory military service in other former USSR republics. In the case of Andreeva versus Latvia,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1504.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1523.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the court concluded that the applicants in that case had a pecuniary interest based on the domestic law, which created a system providing for the payment of pension in respect of aggregate periods of employment in the territory of the former USSR but outside Latvia to its citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1523.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1539.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the government strongly believes that such an assessment is inseparable from the facts and particular circumstances of the Andreeva case. I once again wish to reiterate that the applicants</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1539.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1553.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the present case are not in a similar situation with that of the applicants in Andreeva case, who during the disputed years worked and resided in the territory of Latvia. This is furthermore</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1553.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1581.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>supported by the fact that for a considerable time, the applicants in the present case themselves did not claim that they should receive pensions for employment periods outside the territory of Latvia and did not argue against the decisions of the domestic authorities refusing to pay old age pensions for periods worked outside the territory of Latvia. I recall that in the cases of Stek and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1581.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1605.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Datas versus United Kingdom and Tarkoyev and Datas versus Estonia, the court concluded that the relevant test is whether, but for the condition of entitlement about which the applicants complain, applicants would have had the right to receive the benefit in question. However, while this test</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1605.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1632.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in most cases would be sufficient, in the present case, the historical and geopolitical background of Latvia, the occupation of the USSR, the vast sovietization policies during the occupation and the restoration of Latvia's independence according to the doctrine of state continuity cannot be set aside. Otherwise, the test would fail to apply international law principles</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1632.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1651.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that are relevant for the case at hand and would create a rule that both undermines the system of bilateral agreements and social security matters and completely disregards the violation of international law that was committed during and following the occupation of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1651.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1681.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government draws the court's attention that if compared to both non-citizens who in the case like Andreeva versus Latvia worked in the territory of Latvia and citizens of Latvia in the particular circumstances of the present case, the situation of applicants is manifestly different from both these categories of persons. Consequently, unlike the applicants in the case of Andreeva versus</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1681.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1708.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Latvia who objectively had legitimate expectations that she would receive pensions for work carried out within the territory of Latvia, the applicants in the present case would not have had legitimate expectations that they would be granted social benefits for employment periods outside the territory of Latvia. Accordingly, the government is of a strong belief that the present case should</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1708.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1720.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>be dismissed because the applicants in the particular circumstances of this case could not have had legitimate expectation that they would receive pension for the disputed employment periods.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1720.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1741.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the second argument on admissibility, the government notes that since the first applicant's death for almost two years, none of his relatives or heirs have come forward to pursue his initial application. Therefore, in the light of the court's case law, the application in this part should be</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1741.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1749.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>found inadmissible due to the loss of victim status. Turning to the third argument regarding</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1749.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1766.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the admissibility, the government submits that the first, second, fourth and fifth applicant submitted their complaints outside the six months' time limit, contrary to Article 35, paragraph 1 of the Convention. While the Constitutional Court initiated proceedings in the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1766.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1785.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>applicant's case, noting that they did not have other remedies against alleged discrimination, this decision was taken following the request of the applicants to reopen proceedings before domestic administrative courts. In this regard, the government submits that according to the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1785.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1810.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>court's case law, as illustrated, for example, by the cases of Pechteina v Latvia, Iksandada v Latvia, the submission of the applicants to reopen proceedings at the domestic level and the subsequent constitutional complaints must be considered as extraordinary remedies and therefore cannot be taken into account for the calculation of the six months' time period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1812.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1838.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, even if this could be considered a continuing situation, it still remains unexplained why the first, second, fourth and fifth applicants were inactive for a period ranging from one and a half to 10 years before once again raising their complaints before domestic authorities and then before the court. This court, even in cases relating to investigation of missing persons,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1838.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1850.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>has concluded that where there has been excessive or unexplained delay on the part of the applicants, their applications can be rejected as submitted out of time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1850.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1864.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, as regards the third applicant's complaints, the government underlines that the third applicant has not exhausted domestic remedies available to him. Namely, the applicant</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1864.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1879.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>has not used the opportunity to seek recalculation of his pension based on the agreement concluded between the government of Latvia and Russia on social security matters. Therefore, if the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1879.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1890.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>applicant served his military service in Russia prior to the restoration of Latvia's independence, he should have relied on the bilateral agreement concluded between the two states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1892.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1895.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will very briefly address the merits of the applicant's complaints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1895.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1907.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As noted previously, the doctrine of state continuity is at the core of the restoration of Latvia's independence. Thus, the decisions made with respect to the creation of the status</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1907.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1912.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of non-citizen of Latvia are also based on this doctrine. Following the well-established</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1912.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1937.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>principles of international law and the case law of the ICJ and this court, the responsibility for payments of social benefits that the applicants accrued during the occupation should in principle fall onto the state that exercised effective control and jurisdiction over the persons and territory concerns. However, considering the special ties of its citizens</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1937.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1943.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with the state, Latvia undertook additional responsibilities with regard to its citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1944.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1967.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to non-citizens, Latvia decided to compensate those individuals who contributed to the development of the national economy of Latvia, that is, those non-nationals who were employed and resided in the territory of Latvia during the occupation. Seeing that the applicants</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1967.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1997.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the present case complain about the disputed years that they lived and worked or served military service in another former USSR republic, they are in a manifestly different situation compared to the applicants in the case of Andreeva versus Latvia, who, I repeat, worked and resided her entire life in the territory of Latvia during the disputed years. Also, it must be emphasized</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1997.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2011.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the applicants are not in a similar or relevantly comparable situation with Latvian citizens for the following reasons. As noted previously, the status of a non-citizen was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2011.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2019.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>created for humanitarian reasons. Non-citizens enjoy several rights ex lege, however, in the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2019.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2032.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>light of violation of international law, these rights, including the right to receive supplements for additional pension seniority, are not applicable retroactively. It must also be</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2032.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2045.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>emphasized that from the restoration of Latvia's independence, non-citizens, just like citizens, are paid for all employment periods equally. That is, when old age pensions are calculated</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2046.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2054.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>employment periods after 1 January 1991, both citizens and non-citizens enjoy the same rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2054.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2061.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the same approach cannot be applied to periods when Latvia was occupied by the USSR.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2062.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2080.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, Latvia, as a state that was illegally occupied as a result of the aggression, would not assume responsibility for individuals that entered its territory as a result of immigration policies exercised by the occupying power.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2080.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2106.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the light of these principles, and together with the fact that the applicants, like many other individuals, arrived to Latvia as a result of the immigration policies of the USSR, Latvia cannot be obliged to assume responsibility for other additional payments for persons who were neither the citizens of Latvia nor carried out their work in the territory of the USSR.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2106.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2124.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wish to recall that when the government adopted the citizenship law in 1994, applicants obtained the possibility to naturalize, to establish a bond with the state of Latvia, and their pensions would have been recalculated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2124.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2147.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In light of these arguments, and given the wide margin of appreciation afforded to states with respect to measures of economic and social policy, the government concludes that in the circumstances of the present case, the underlying distinction is linked to the fact that the applicants were not citizens of Latvia, but were citizens of the USSR.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2147.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2171.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the circumstances of the present case, the underlying distinction is linked to the fact that the applicants worked and lived outside the territory of Latvia for the disputed years, and the different treatment of the applicants, if compared to the citizens, was reasonable, necessary and proportionate. Therefore, the government considers that this application</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2171.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2182.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is inadmissible and requests the court to reject it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2184.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2187.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Mrs. Līce.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2187.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2192.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I confirm that both audio and video was sufficient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2192.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2194.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We heard you loud and clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2194.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2198.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the representative of the applicants, Ms. Nikuļceva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2198.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2198.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2200.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2208.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr President, honourable members of the court. In the present case,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2208.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2219.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>four remaining applicants are elderly so-called non-citizens of Latvia. Mr Nesterovs, Mr Podoliako,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2219.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2228.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs Sivitska and Mrs Vagapova. All the applicants are living in Latvia for a very long time already,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2228.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2241.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from 1979, 1968, 1951 and 1987 respectively. For all the applicants, certain periods of time</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2242.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2260.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of their service before 1991 were not taken into account in calculation of their retirement pensions. Those are years of work in Azerbaijan, Uzbekistan, Russia, Belarus, Turkmenistan,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2261.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2268.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tajikistan and also military service in the Soviet army. According to the Latvian law</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2268.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2290.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on state pensions, in principle, these periods up to 1991 shall be equivalent to periods of social insurance. However, the law provides for different treatment for citizens on one hand and, on the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2290.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2300.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>other hand, for foreigners, stateless persons and also for non-citizens. Had those periods been</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2300.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2308.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>included, the applicants would receive higher retirement pensions. We are speaking here about</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2308.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2312.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>retirement pensions and not only for supplements to those pensions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2314.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2322.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would now like to answer the questions of the Court and express our opinion. Firstly,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2322.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2338.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to address the issue of the exhaustion of domestic remedies and the six-month time limit. The applicants consider that all domestic remedies are exhausted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2340.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2370.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to well-established case law of the Latvian Supreme Court, if in respect of a person an unfavourable administrative act has been issued, that person may at any time apply again to that institution and request a favourable decision. Thus, after the court's judgment on 18 February</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2370.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2389.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>2009, in the case Andreeva v Latvia, all the applicants applied to the state social insurance agency, requesting recalculation of their pensions. Then, they went to an administrative court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2390.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2395.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which dismissed their claim. Then, the applicants applied to the constitutional court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2395.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2422.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Constitutional Court of Latvia can initiate proceedings on the basis of a constitutional complaint only if all options have been used to protect the rights with general remedies, or if such remedies do not exist. Thus, by initiating the proceedings, the Constitutional</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2422.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2431.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Court of Latvia at this point approved that all general remedies had been exhausted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2431.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2450.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of Grishankova v Latvia, I referred to the decision in the case of Grishankova v Grishankovs. If the applicant calls into question a provision of Latvian legislation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2450.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2466.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as such, in being contrary to the Convention and the Constitution of Latvia, proceedings should be brought before the Constitutional Court prior to the European Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2466.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2489.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the law on state pensions, paragraph 1 of the transitional provisions, directly regulates those periods that have to be taken into account in the calculation of retirement pensions. Thus, the applicants had to apply to the Constitutional Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2491.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2500.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Constitutional Court adopted a judgment on 17 February 2011. This judgment is final,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2500.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2514.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and not only the judgment itself but also the interpretation of legal provisions by the Constitutional Court is binding for all persons, also for Latvian courts. Thus, the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2514.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2520.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Latvian courts cannot decide on the contrary to the judgment of the Constitutional Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2520.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2535.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is why there are no effective domestic remedies following the Constitutional Court judgment. The applicants applied to the court within a six-month time limit from the date</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2535.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2538.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the judgment of the Constitutional Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2538.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2550.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I would like to address the relevance of the state continuity doctrine. The applicants</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2550.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2568.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>consider that the state continuity doctrine explained in the judgment of the Constitutional Court of 17 February 2011 is not relevant for the purposes of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2568.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2576.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government in the present case raises preliminary objections ratione personae. According</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2576.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2600.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the government, Latvia is not a successor of the former Soviet Union and did not undertake any obligation to provide any payments to individuals for work periods in the Soviet Union. And it corresponds with the explanation of the Constitutional Court judgment, which</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2600.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2624.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>also states that a state that has been occupied as a result of aggression carried out by another state does not have the duty to guarantee social security for persons who had arrived in its territory from the occupying state as a result of its immigration policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2624.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2634.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants disagree with this statement of the Constitutional Court. Although the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2634.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2654.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Republic of Latvia indeed avoided responsibility for the former Soviet Union actions, it does not set Latvia free from obligations. Firstly, to take into account the real situation, interruption</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2654.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2664.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of statehood for 50 years, lives and work of people during these times. And secondly,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2664.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2675.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to fulfill obligations Latvia itself has undertaken. The Republic of Latvia indeed was established</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2675.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2686.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in 1918 and the Euro retains its legal personality during the occupation by the Soviet Union.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2686.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2703.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the de facto interruption of statehood and the period of 50 years of de facto existence as a part of the Soviet Union shall be taken into account. In the period of time from 1940</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2703.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2719.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to 1990, when the restoration of Latvia's independence was declared, a large number of persons came to Latvia from other Soviet republics. After the dissolution of the Soviet</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2719.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2738.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Union and the restoration of independence in Latvia, Latvia took responsibility for these people. By 4 May 1990 independence declaration, not only it was proclaimed that following</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2738.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2780.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the restoration of independence the state created in 1918 had been preserved, but the Latvian state's commitment was declared to guarantee to those citizens of the Soviet Union who will express the desire to continue residing in the territory of Latvia without accepting its citizenship, their social, economic and cultural rights, as well as political freedoms. For these people, Latvia created a special status of non-citizens of Latvia,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2780.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2797.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>who are not stateless persons, and whose status has many similarities with that of citizens of Latvia. Inter alia, Latvia granted permanent residence in Latvia to almost non-citizens</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2797.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2806.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ex lega. Thus, on one hand, Latvia itself has undertaken obligation to provide to non-citizens</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2806.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2817.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>guarantees, including social guarantees, including retirement pensions. Latvia is the only state</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2817.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2827.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that has responsibility for these persons. On the other hand, Latvia itself has undertaken</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2827.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2844.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>obligation to provide pensions for work periods in the Soviet Union, both in Latvia and outside Latvia, and for military service in the Soviet army. The Republic of Latvia is not the legal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2844.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2860.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>successor not only of the former Soviet Union as a whole, but also of the Latvian Soviet Socialist Republic in particular. Thus, one should not make a distinction between work</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2860.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2869.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>periods in Soviet Latvia and in other Soviet republics. As to retirement pensions for work</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2869.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2889.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>periods in the Soviet Union before 1991, Latvian law on state pensions establishes that in principle these periods are taken into account in calculation of retirement pensions. Just</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2889.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2902.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a list of those particular periods differs for citizens and for non-citizens. Besides</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2902.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2924.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for non-citizens, also some periods, but not all, of work outside Latvia but in the Soviet Union are taken into account, for instance, higher education studies or the imprisonment of politically repressed persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2924.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2948.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of Andreeva v Latvia, the government also stated that insofar as the application concerned Article 40, taken in conjunction with Article 1 of Protocol 1, its subject matter fell outside Latvia's jurisdiction. In that case, the Court already came to the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2948.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2957.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>conclusion that the state continuity doctrine was irrelevant and Latvia has jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2957.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2972.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This reading is also supported by the following case law of the Court concerning discrimination on the grounds of nationality as regards pension rights. For example, in the judgments in the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2972.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2983.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>cases Rybač v Slovenia and Aleksič v Slovenia. Given that the applicants in the present case</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2983.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3002.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>are in almost identical position to the applicant in the case Andreeva v Latvia, the applicants asked the Court to reaffirm its position on the relevance of the state continuity doctrine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3002.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3025.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government in the present case also raised preliminary objection to the rationale materia, arguing that Article 1 of Protocol 1 of the Convention is not applicable in the present case. However, where a state, even voluntarily, creates a system of benefits, these should</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3025.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3032.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>not be allocated on the basis of criteria that are discriminatory. Latvia has created</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3032.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3052.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>such system and in calculation of retirement pensions, in principle, recognises work periods in the Soviet Union. Thus, this calculation should be made on the basis of equitable criteria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3052.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3085.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also in the judgment in the case Andreeva v Latvia, the Court already concluded where a state decides on its own accord to pay pensions to individuals in respect of periods of employment outside its territory, thereby creating a sufficiently clear legal basis in its domestic law. The presumed entitlement to such benefits falls within the scope of Article 1 of Protocol</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3085.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3094.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>1. The applicants claim inclusion in their retirement pensions only of those periods</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3094.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3102.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which are included in calculation of analogous pensions for citizens of Latvia. They do not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3102.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3110.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>claim any additional benefits. Thus, a pecuniary interest falling within the ambit of Article</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3110.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3117.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>1 of Protocol 1 exists and these rights shall be implemented without any discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3117.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3119.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3119.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3121.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I pass the floor to my colleague Mr Alexander Skuzmins.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3124.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3125.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3125.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3135.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next question of the court was on whether the applicants are in a similar relevant situation to that of Latvian citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3135.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3155.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the court noted in Andreeva, the status of a permanently resident non-citizen of Latvia means that Latvia is the only state of which they have any legal stable ties, and thus the only state which objectively can assume responsibility for them in terms of social security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3155.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3161.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is very close to the situation of Latvian citizens, and it is the status of all the applicants now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3161.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3176.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their close connection of all non-citizens, including the applicants, with Latvia is confirmed by domestic laws, by international expertise, so it is not necessary to consider the degree of connection with Latvia for each applicant separately.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3176.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3181.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The status of a non-citizen of Latvia is a quasi-citizenship of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3181.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3191.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In terms of English-speaking countries distinguishing nationality and citizenship, this status can be termed a kind of nationality as opposed to citizenship as a narrower group.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3191.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3196.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The evidence comes both from international organizations and from Latvia itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3196.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3203.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Internationally, the UN High Commissioner for Refugees, in his statistics, makes a note under non-citizens of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3203.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3214.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The note reads that non-citizens may currently be considered persons to whom the convention does not apply in accordance with Article 1, Paragraph 2, Subparagraph 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3214.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3215.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What does it mean?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3215.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3233.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That paragraph of the convention relating to the status of stateless persons refers to persons who are recognized by the competent authorities of the country in which they have taken residence as having the right and obligations which are attached to the possession of the nationality of that country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3233.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3242.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the international human rights community is quite critical of the status, and the essence of this criticism is that non-citizens do not have full rights of citizenship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3242.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3257.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the European Commission Against Racism and Indolence has noted that there is an urgent need to solve the problems linked to the status of non-citizens, which makes people concerned feel like second-class citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3257.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3267.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The recommendations of the international community also are telling in their requirement for Latvia to recognize for non-citizens the voting rights traditionally foreseen for citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3267.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3304.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those requirements are expressed in the calls of the bodies on the Council of Europe, like the same Commission Against Racism and Intolerance, like the advisory committee of the Framework Convention on National Minorities, in the OSCE Parliamentary Assembly, and the High Commissioner on National Minority Documents, and the UN Human Rights Committee, which also explains that non-citizens are treated by law as distinct category of persons with long-lasting and effective ties to Latvia in many respects comparable to citizens, but in other respects, without the rights that come with full citizenship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3304.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3315.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the UN Committees on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination and on Economic, Social, and Cultural Rights urge Latvia to phase out the status of non-citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3315.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3326.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As for Latvia itself, the Constitution provides that everyone having a Latvian passport shall be protected by the state when abroad and has the right to freely return to Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3326.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3330.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the non-citizens of Latvia do hold Latvia's passport.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3330.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3339.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In those passports, it is written that the holder of this passport is under the protection of the Republic of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3339.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3350.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Foreign Ministry itself, the Latvian one, non-citizens have the same social guarantees as Latvian citizens, and they enjoy majority of political rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3350.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3360.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, they have unconditional right to reside in Latvia without any residence permits or visas, to work in the country without any work permits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3360.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3366.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this has been the case since their status was codified in 1995.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3366.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3373.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are not foreigners under the immigration law, unlike stateless persons under the 1954 Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3373.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3385.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Latvia's Constitutional Court has recognized that the legal ties of non-citizens with Latvia are to a certain extent recognized, and mutual obligations and rights have been created on the basis of the above.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3385.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3405.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is very close to the definition of nationality provided by the International Court of Justice in Nottebohm case, quote, a legal bond having as its basis a social fact of attachment, a genuine connection of existence, interests, and sentiments, together with the existence of reciprocal rights and duties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3405.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3419.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, Latvia itself regularly recognizes, for the purposes of specific Council of Europe treaties, the non-citizens of Latvia to be Latvia's nationals, together with Latvian citizens, but in contrast to stateless persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3419.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3440.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the case with the criminal law convention on corruption, with convention on the transfer of sentenced persons, with the convention of extradition, with the convention on the transfer of proceedings in criminal matters, and with two agreements on social security schemes, those relating to old age, invalidity, and survivors, and to the rest of schemes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3440.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3450.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Currently, it needs to be noted that according to official statistics, as of 2020, 45% of the non-citizens have been born in Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3450.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3458.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next question begins from whether the applicants are discriminated based on national or social origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3458.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3484.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are discriminated based on their nationality, and the nationality falls under national or social origin under Article 14, as shown in many cases like Gajdusus, Guapuare, and also Andreeva, where the court indicated very, very key reasons would have to be put forward before it could regard a difference of treatment based exclusively on the ground of nationality as compatible to the conventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3484.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3490.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no such reasons, even more so in the present case than in Andreeva, as we explain later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3490.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3497.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question also included the issue on whether the decree of applicant's choice regarding their status is relevant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3497.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3505.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The one personal choice of the applicants which could have impacted the amount of their pensions was not applying for naturalization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3505.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3525.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This had been considered in Andreeva as well, and the court justly decided that the prohibition of discrimination enshrined in Article 14 is meaningful only if, in each particular case, the applicant's personal situation in relation to the criteria listed in that provision is taken into account exactly as it stands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3525.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3539.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To proceed otherwise in dismissing the victim's claims on the grounds that he or she could have avoided the discrimination, for example, by acquiring a nationality, would render Article 14 devoid of substance, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3539.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3544.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is to be noted that there is no subjective right to naturalize under a letter in law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3544.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3558.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So even had the applicants paid all the fees, passed all the language, history, and constitution exams, and taken the oath, getting the citizenship of Latvia wouldn't have been certain for them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3558.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3565.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government may refuse naturalization under vague security reasoning, and there is no judicial review available for such decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3565.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3573.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With a slightly different wording of the citizenship law, this was the case considered by the court in Petropavlovskis versus Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3573.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3577.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, naturalization takes place after the pension was granted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3577.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3583.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would not always put former non-citizens on equal footing with citizens with regard to their pensions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3583.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3589.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The main reason is the paragraph 33 of the transitional positions of the law on state pensions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3589.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3600.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The benefits provided there for people with a total insurance period over 30 years are only valid at the time when a pension is being granted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3600.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3604.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, we have to note the advanced age of all the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3604.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3615.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not a single of them was young in 1998 when applying for naturalization became possible for them as people born outside Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3615.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3621.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the process of naturalization would have been more difficult for them than for most non-citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3621.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3626.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fifth court questions was about how the case is different from Andreeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3626.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3633.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The one difference repeatedly highlighted by the government is that Mrs. Andreeva had worked in an enterprise located</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3633.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3634.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3634.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3641.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, this circumstance was not relevant for the court's conclusion that Andreeva's rights under the conventions had been violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3641.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3649.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quote, having regard to the conclusions set out below, the court does not consider it necessary to determine this issue separately, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3649.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3673.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The other issues, the other differences are either irrelevant for the scope of this case, like distinction between employment and mandatory military service periods because they are treated identically in law, like existence of agreements with Russia and Belarus, which did to some extent remedy the situation of some applicants after a certain point of their entry into force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3673.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3678.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the applicants have suffered the discrimination right from the beginning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3678.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3688.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the convention and the protocol number one became applicable for Latvia in 1997, long before the treaties with Russia and Belarus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3688.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3701.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The rest of the differences from Andreeva are showing that the situation here, the restrictions of applicants' rights, are even less proportioned than in Andreeva, as we explain later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3701.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3710.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The last question by the court begins from whether the difference in treatment between applicants and Latvian citizens will show a legitimate aim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3710.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3715.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, burden of proving any legitimate aim is existing is on the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3715.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3724.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the difficult time of an economic crisis when Andreeva was decided, the Grand Chamber has only identified one legitimate aim, the protection of the country's economic system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3724.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3726.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>12 years have passed since.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3726.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3742.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Latvian economy is now much stronger, as shown by its membership in the OECD since 2016, by our GDP per capita, per purchasing power parity, which has grown almost twice between 2009 and 2019 by the most recent World Bank data.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3742.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3747.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, the pension system in Latvia has grown as government itself points out in its memorial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3747.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3760.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the minimum pensions were recognized to be unacceptably low by the Constitutional Court in 2020, so the government's reference to existing basic pensions in the same memorial as sufficient is not convincing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3760.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3767.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No new legitimate aims have surfaced, so we invite the court to find that no legitimate aim is pushed by the differential treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3767.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3779.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should the court consider that the aim of protecting the economy still persists, we invite the court to find that it has become less stressing, so it cannot justify the same restrictions which were unjustifiable in 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3779.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3785.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The questions also includes whether the differential treatment between applicants and Latvian citizens meets the proportionality requirements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3785.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3789.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, the reasoning from Andreeva applies to the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3789.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3799.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was said that the applicant was a red law for the resident in Latvia on a permanent basis, and she received a permanent retirement pension in respect of her employment in Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3799.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3808.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The national authority's refusal to take into account her years of employment outside Latvia is based exclusively on the considerations that she does not have Latvian citizenship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3808.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3819.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not disputed in the instant case that a Latvian citizen in the same position as the applicant having worked in the same enterprise during the same period would have been granted the disputed portion of the retirement pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3819.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3821.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same applies here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3821.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3826.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As noted by the court, there are very, very few reasons needed to justify such distinction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3826.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3828.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Like in Andreeva, there are no such reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3828.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3838.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And again, to quote the criteria established in Andreeva test first, the applicant satisfies the other conditions entitling them to a pension in respect of all their years of employment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3838.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3843.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was an objectively similar situation to Latvian citizens with a similar career.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3843.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3849.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, there was no difference in the former USSR regarding the treatment between their nationals and the guard pensions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3849.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3855.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, Latvia is the only state which could objectively assume responsibility for them in terms of social security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3855.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3857.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same here as in Andreeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3857.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3861.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The few changes which are present are in favor of applicants of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3861.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3870.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In January 29, months before Andreeva was decided, there were 358,000 non-citizens living in Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3870.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3872.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their number have been falling ever since.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3872.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3876.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By early 2021, it has reached 209,000.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3876.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3885.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the benefits, the fees, for the budget from not paying full pensions to non-citizens are becoming smaller every year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3885.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3893.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the disputed restrictions on the pension rights of the applicants are as harsh now as they were in 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3893.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3906.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To conclude, we invite the court to declare that Article 14, in conjunction with Article 1 of the First Protocol, has been violated in respect of all four surviving applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3906.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3908.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Distinguished member of the court, Mr. President,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3908.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3909.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>this concludes our statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3911.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3913.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Kuzmins.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3913.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3919.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also thank Ms. Nikuļceva for the submissions of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3919.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3923.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I then finally turn to the third-party intervener, the Russian government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3923.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3923.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Galperin, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>ThirdParty</Role>
		<Name>TP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3926.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3931.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, dear Mr. President, honorable judges, Ms. Lidze, applicants' council.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3932.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3939.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will try to be short. My esteemed colleague tried to allege that this case about the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3939.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3946.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Latvian independence and so-called Soviet occupation, but it is not about that. It is</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3946.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3960.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a straightforward case about illegal social discrimination and going the opposite wrong way, which is proposed by the defended government. This court should examine and assess numerous</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3960.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3979.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>international and constitutional documents going back to 1939, 1940, 1990, and Latvian constitutions and laws during the years which Ms. Lidze called disputed. And it is clearly not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3979.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3986.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>within the competence of this court in the case. And if this court will go this wrong direction,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3986.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4020.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>then the conclusion will be reached that these applicants, including the third applicant, who was just three years old when he came to Latvia to live, that they are occupants, that these occupants and the international public are reliable for that, and this lifelong discrimination is the punishment for that occupation, which is absolutely wrong and goes not within the sphere of the European Convention of Human Rights. So the rights of non-citizens</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4020.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4040.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in Latvia, according to the national law of pension, significantly limited in comparison to citizens that are to the labor market, accrued both in the territory of Latvia and in other republics of the former USSR. And I would like to note that the USSR was a unified formation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4040.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4057.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Soviet citizens could travel all over the territory of the USSR, including not by the USSR, but as a result of a compulsory job placement by the state authorities and military service, as in the case of one of the applicants. And taking into account the long-term state</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4057.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4070.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of pension support, they had reasonable expectations that the labor record would be accounted on the whole territory of their country. Thus, the difference in the amount of pension payments</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4070.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4079.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of citizens and non-citizens is substantial, unfair, and discriminatory. The Latvian government</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4079.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4093.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>confirms these conclusions in their memorandum and justifies the doubtful policy on this matter by specifying objective grounds for the two categories. Especially astonishing, I would</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4093.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4105.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>like to say, is the statement that the labor activities of non-citizens outside the territory of Latvia make no contribution to the development of the state and the national economy. The</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4105.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4124.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>conclusions of the Latvian government that the existence of the majority of non-citizens was facilitated by the 50 years of occupation and the Soviet migration policy raised serious doubts, taking into account the fact that Latvia was a full-fledged part of the Soviet Union for 50 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4124.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4144.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is at least strange to use such controversial and non-legal categories as Soviet occupation, Sovietization, Russification, to justify clearly discriminatory provisions and continuation of their application 30 years after Latvia became independent again. Moreover, similar circumstances</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4144.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4157.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>were previously examined by the court and similar reasoning of the Latvian authorities received proper assessment. And as in the Andreeva case, which was also mentioned several times today,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4157.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4173.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Grand Chamber acknowledged a violation of the conventional rights of the applicant, who was also a resident non-citizen of Latvia. The court stated that differentiated approach</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4173.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4180.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to pension rights of citizens and non-citizens was discriminatory. The court pointed out that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4180.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4193.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>national authorities' refusal to take into account the years of applicants' employment outside Latvia was motivated exclusively by the fact that she was not a citizen of Latvia. A citizen of Latvia</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4193.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4205.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the same situation as the applicant who worked at the same enterprise for the same period of time would have received the retirement pension in the high amount. If the applicant became a naturalized</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4205.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4217.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>citizen of Latvia, she would automatically receive the pension based on her whole labor record, including all USSR republics. This court came to a conclusion that there are no reasonable grounds</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4217.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4224.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for limitation of the applicant's rights on the grounds of citizenship. The Grand Chamber</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4224.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4238.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>highlighted that Latvia is the only state with which the applicant has any stable legal relationship, thus the only state that can assume the responsibility to provide pension support to her.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4238.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4251.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court considered the submissions of the Latvian government insufficient to confirm compliance of the difference in treatment with the requirements of Article 14 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4251.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4263.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wish to point out that the situation of the applicants in the present case is similar to the situation in the case of Andreeva. In both cases, the applicants had stable legal relationship with</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4263.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4276.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Latvia and suffered from application of the same discriminatory provisions that remained unchanged from Andreeva case decision. The only change from the moment of the court's judgment in the case of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4276.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4286.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Andreeva is the Latvia signing of the bilateral agreements in the sphere of social support, as was mentioned by Ms. Lidze, including an agreement between the Russian Federation and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4286.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4293.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Latvian Republic that entered into effect in 2010-11. These agreements entitled people to apply</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4293.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4305.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for recalculation of the amount of their pension, taking into account their labor record, accrued during the Soviet period outside Latvia. However, such agreements are concluded by Latvia</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4305.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4319.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with only five out of 15 former Soviet republics and, correspondingly, only the service record accrued on the territory of these countries may be accounted for. The applicants in the present</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4319.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4329.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>case also worked in the territories of other republics of the USSR and Latvia has not signed any similar agreements with them. So it is not possible to account the additional labor record</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4329.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4342.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the applicants in this case, thus putting them into an unequal position as compared to the citizens of Latvia. Moreover, none of these agreements assumes its retrospective application</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4342.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4347.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and possibility of compensation of the amounts of pensions that have not been received before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4347.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4369.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, even in case of Latvia signing similar agreements with all the republics of the former USSR, and so we don't have any information that it will ever happen, the applicants will be able to receive only an increase in pension payments in the future, but not compensated for their losses due to the discriminatory approach of the Latvian government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4370.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4380.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It demonstrates the apparent difference in treatment of the applicants in comparison to the citizens of Latvia in the matter of determining their pension amounts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4381.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4398.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The existence of bilateral agreements in the sphere of social security does not guarantee the possibility of effective restoration of the violated rights, and it has also been pointed out by the court in Andreeva case. The attempt to solve the matter by implementation of the Andreeva</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4398.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4414.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>judgment and entering into the bilateral international agreements without any changes to national discriminatory legislation has been subjected to criticism by the bodies of the Council of Europe. For instance, the European Commission against Racism and Intolerance expressed its</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4414.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4420.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>concerns due to the insufficient actions taken by Latvia to implement the judgment of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4421.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4443.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The advisory committee on the Framework Convention for the Protection of National Minorities also expressed a deep concern that the court's judgment in the case of Andreeva had not resulted in a complete solution of the pension problem and the signed agreements were not applicable to all non-citizens. It was actually confirmed that national discriminatory norms were still</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4443.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4449.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in effect. Latvia shall cease its discriminatory policy in relation to resident non-citizens and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4449.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4459.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>bring its legislation in compliance with international standards and the court's Andreeva judgment. Therefore, the claims of the applicants in the present case are strongly supported.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4459.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4461.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4463.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4465.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Mr. Galperin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4465.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4472.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a slight interference for a very short period of time at the beginning, but I think it was insignificant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4472.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4477.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We heard all of your submissions adequately.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4477.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4485.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to judges of the Grand Chamber who want to pose questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4485.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4489.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Lemmens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4491.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4493.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4493.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4503.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question for the applicants and a question for the government, but both parties can answer both questions if they want.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4503.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4506.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question is to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4506.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4511.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's about the applicants' connection with Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4511.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4517.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We heard from you that there are objective legal ties with Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4517.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4520.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is more about the subjective ties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4520.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4528.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I apologize if this is a personal question and if you think that it is not relevant, you can of course tell me.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4528.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4536.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I would like to know whether the applicants consider themselves Latvians.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4536.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4542.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we heard about the difficulties to obtain naturalization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4542.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4550.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But is it possible to say that there is a choice of not acquiring Latvian citizenship?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4550.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4558.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, why did then the applicants prefer not to acquire that Latvian citizenship?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4558.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4562.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question is for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4562.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4570.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the applicants in this case worked for some time outside Latvia, and that's the reason why they didn't get that supplement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4570.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4586.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I would like to know whether the difference of treatment extinguishes with the passing away of the applicants, or whether there are further effects, for instance on their children, coming from that situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4586.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4586.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4588.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4590.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Hüseynov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Lәtif Hüseynov</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4593.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4594.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4594.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4599.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4599.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4613.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First question, I'd like to ask about the naturalization in Latvia, whether there were any new trends in this area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4613.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4631.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And more specifically, are there any differences as regards naturalization between permanently resident non-citizens on one side and foreigners and status persons on the other side?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4631.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4640.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my second question to the government, but of course the applicants, representatives may also intervene and answer this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4640.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4655.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are there any differences, or do you see any differences in the factual situations of the applicants in the present case that would justify a differentiated approach of our court vis-a-vis their complaints?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4655.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4655.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4656.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4658.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Mits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Mārtiņš Mits</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4660.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4661.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4661.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4663.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4663.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4667.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question goes to the Ms. Līce,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4667.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4669.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>representative of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4669.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4692.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the outset, the case was made as concerning the supplements of the pensions, whereas we heard from the representative of the applicants that this concerns these periods of employment concerns the pension itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4692.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4704.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would like to clarify and comment on the impact on the pension itself that the applicants receive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4704.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4712.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a question to the government representative, but of course also the applicant representatives may comment on it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4712.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4720.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question goes to applicant representative, and in particular to what Ms. Nikuļceva was saying.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4720.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4739.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to clarify what is the basis for an argument that Latvia must assume responsibility for paying pensions for the periods of employment of permanent resident non-citizens outside the territory of the Latvian Soviet Socialist Republic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4739.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4744.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it was mentioned, but I'm not sure I clearly understood it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4744.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4748.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, representative of the government may comment on this question as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4748.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4748.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4750.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4752.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Section President O'Leary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4754.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4757.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4757.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4774.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer this question to both parties, and it's based on a document published on the website of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Latvia entitled, Basic Facts About Citizenship and Language Policy of Latvia and Some Sensitive History-Related Issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4774.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4791.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in it, there is a paragraph which reads as follows, and I quote, Non-citizens enjoy equal protection under the law, both in Latvia and while living or traveling abroad, and are the only group of persons, in addition to citizens, who are granted permanent residence in Latvia ex legae.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4791.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4800.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Non-citizens have the same social guarantees as Latvian citizens, including, for example, with regard to pensions and unemployment benefits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4800.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4814.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to political rights, the only significant difference between Latvian citizens and non-citizens is the right to vote and to work in the civil service or occupy posts directly related to national security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4814.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4823.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would be interested in the observations of both parties in relation to that very broad statement on equal protection under the law in Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4823.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4823.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4825.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4826.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4826.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4832.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no further questions that will be posed by the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4832.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4834.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We will then break for 25 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4834.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4842.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would ask the parties to be present back at 11.45 sharp local time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4842.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4843.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4875.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4875.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4881.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4883.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4883.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4887.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Ms. Līce.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4890.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4892.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4892.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4896.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I will first respond to the questions posed by the judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4896.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4902.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then I will provide my final remarks considering various arguments raised today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4902.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4914.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I remain at the Court's disposal should the Court require further information in writing, including any specific statistics that I might not be able to provide at the moment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4914.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4924.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the questions, first, Judge Lemens asked about the ties of the applicants with Latvia and also about the naturalization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4924.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4935.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, I wish to underline that the present case is not about current ties of the applicants with Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4935.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4946.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case is about the alleged ties or not existing ties between the applicants and Latvia during the disputed years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4946.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4954.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, during the years when the applicants worked or served military service outside Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4954.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4966.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the case concerns the alleged discrimination in taking into account these periods of time when calculating the applicants' pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4966.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4977.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the government reiterates that during those disputed years, the applicants did not have ties with Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4977.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4987.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the naturalization and the possibilities to acquire Latvian citizenship, the naturalization process has repeatedly been simplified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4987.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4993.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are a number of exemptions, either from tests or from naturalization fee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4993.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5011.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would particularly emphasize that for any applicants aged 65 and above, there are a number of exceptions and naturalization for elderly is very, very easy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5011.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5024.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To answer the other question from Judge Lemens, whether there are any effects of this alleged difference treatments on other members of the applicants' families, no, the answer is clear, no.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5024.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5039.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This difference regards only the calculation of additional payments to the applicants and have no effect on other members of the family considering the very personal nature of the pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5039.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5055.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Coming to the question from Judge Huseino, also regarding naturalization, I would say briefly I responded that this process has been on a number of occasions facilitated and simplified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5055.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5071.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If one compares the possibilities of non-citizens and those of foreigners or stateless persons, it's much easier for non-citizens to naturalize considering that non-citizens much easier can comply with the residence requirements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5071.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5077.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I noted in my statement, non-citizens are considered permanent residents ex legge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5077.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5085.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They do not need to obtain separate residence permits to reside in the territory of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5085.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5113.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as to the factual differences between the applicants and, as I understood, the case of Andreeva versus Latvia, I can only reiterate that in the government's view there's significant difference in the fact that the disputed years, during those disputed years, the applicants in the present case were not in the territory of Latvia and did not form ties with Latvia during those disputed years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5113.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5130.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the question from Judge Mitz, whether the case is about the supplements or the pension, I wish to once again underline that there's a difference between the right to pension and the amount of pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5130.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5137.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Convention guarantees legitimate expectations and the right to receive all-day pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5137.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5142.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Convention does not guarantee a specific amount of pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5142.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5157.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the dispute is whether these years the applicants were not in the territory of Latvia should be taken into account in the calculation of the amount of pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5157.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5162.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does not concern the rights of the applicants to receive all-day pension as such.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5162.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5176.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I can only repeat that the applicants, all applicants do receive pension that Latvia pays to all citizens and non-citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5176.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5187.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the last question from Judge O'Leary, as I attempted to underline in my statements, there's a watershed in the history of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5187.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5209.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The occupation in 1940, when Latvia lost de facto control over its territory and over the body of its citizens, and then the restoration of Latvia's independence in 1990-1991.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5209.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5226.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For all the years since the restoration of independence, Latvia is able to assume full responsibility, and therefore it ensures all rights of non-citizens for those periods, as I underlined in my statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5226.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5235.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For all the years accrued for the pension purposes, non-citizens and citizens are paid equally.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5235.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5250.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also wish to underline that for the years non-citizens have worked in the territory of Latvia prior to the restoration of Latvia's independence, they are equally paid as citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5250.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5261.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope I have at least briefly responded to these questions, and I now wish to provide my final remarks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5260.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5268.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Līce, before you bring your final remarks, Judge Huseinov has asked to just to follow up on his question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5268.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5273.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would ask you, give him the floor and you would respond and then you conclude.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5273.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5273.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Hüseynov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Lәtif Hüseynov</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5275.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5279.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5279.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5285.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the government agent for answering my first question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5285.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5293.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I'm afraid my second question may have been wrongly interpreted or misunderstood.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5293.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5318.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question was whether you see any differences in the factual situation of the current applicants, of the applicants in the present case, among them, if there are any differences in the factual situation of the applicants that would justify, in your view, a differentiated approach of our court vis-a-vis their complaints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5318.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5318.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5320.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5321.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Līce, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5323.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5326.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. I apologise for misinterpreting the question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5327.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5341.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In my opening statement, we provided several arguments regarding the admissibility of the complaints regarding specific applicants. Yes, there are factual differences, depending on</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5343.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5358.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>whether the applicants have properly exhausted domestic remedies and whether the applicants have complied with a six-month time limit. This allows me to reiterate that the government does</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5358.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5379.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>not question that the applicants have wrongly submitted the complaint to the Constitutional Court or they have not exhausted domestic remedies by not complaining to the Constitutional Court. Instead, the government argues that these rounds of domestic proceedings should be disregarded</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5380.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5388.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as they constitute an extraordinary remedy. The applicants sought reopening of domestic</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5388.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5405.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>proceedings and there were no regular proceedings immediately after the national authorities for the first time rejected the applicants' request to recalculate their pensions. So, extraordinary</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5405.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5418.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>remedies according to this course practice are not taken into account while calculating the six-month time limit. But to summarise, yes, there are factual differences between the applicants,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5418.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5433.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>depending on when they arrived in Latvia and which periods of time are taken into consideration in calculating their pensions. However, when it comes to the disputed years, when neither of the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5433.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5440.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>applicants were in the territory of Latvia in that regard, the applicants are in identical situations. I hope that I have answered the question. Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5448.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5451.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So would you like to conclude then, Ms. Līce,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5451.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5451.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>your final remarks?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5452.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5453.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5455.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5462.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With your permission, I would like to highlight two, again, facts that are at the core of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5464.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5488.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the outset, and first of all, I again wish to reiterate that all additional supplements to the applicants, old age pensions that have been accrued after Latvia's restoration of independence, are calculated and indexed in the same way as supplements to old age pensions of Latvian citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5489.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5503.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, applicants, in the same way as citizens, can and do receive additional benefits for health, transportation, housing and other reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5503.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5529.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, it should be clear that there's no difference in treatment of the applicants if compared to the citizens of Latvia when it comes to the periods of pension accrued after the restoration of Latvia's independence, when Latvia was finally able to take full control over its territory and over the body of its citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5529.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5540.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For these years, the applicants are in identical situation with those citizens of Latvia that receive old age pensions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5540.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5556.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also wish to recall that for the years the applicants have worked in Latvian territory before the restoration of independence, they are also calculated their pensions in the same way as Latvian citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5556.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5585.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the only question in the present case is whether the Convention requires Latvia to pay the applicants additions and supplements to their pensions for the periods of work and military service outside Latvia's territory during Latvia's illegal occupation when the applicants neither resided nor worked in the territory of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5585.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5594.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second point is a recollection of the fundamental difference between the case of Andreeva versus Latvia and the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5594.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5608.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have on a number of occasions already underlined that in Andreeva case, the disputed years were those years when the applicants resided and worked in the territory of Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5608.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5617.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the applicants resided and worked outside the territory of Latvia during the disputed years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5617.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5624.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To conclude, Mr. President, this Court is required to interpret the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5624.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5639.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not the subject matter of the present case the nature of the status of non-citizen or the obligation of the states or the rights of the states to conclude international agreements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5639.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5646.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The subject matter of this case is interpretation of Article 1, Protocol 1 to the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5646.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5665.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Government submits that this Article cannot be interpreted in a way to oblige any contracting party to assume obligation for any work or service carried out outside its territory with no ties to this contracting state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5665.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5674.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That contracting state is not obliged to assume responsibility for payments of pensions in this regard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5674.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5675.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5676.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5677.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5677.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5681.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the applicants' representatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5681.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5683.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms Nikuļceva, Mr Kuzmins, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5685.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5692.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. Answering the first questions by Judge Lemons, the applicants do most certainly</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5692.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5699.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>consider themselves Latvians. There are also subjective ties for them with Latvia, like</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5699.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5712.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>their children go to Latvian schools, their friends are living here, they have worked here in Latvia. For some applicants, their spouses are Latvian as well. This goes beyond the objective</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5712.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5720.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>facts of living in Latvia and having the status of non-citizens. On why the applicants were not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5720.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5735.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>able to naturalise, the main common reasons for the applicants is that the requirements for naturalisation are rather high, specifically in regarding to the Latvian language. Not only</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5735.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5750.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is there a high level required just in Latvian language exams, but in addition, they would have to pass also the constitution and history exams also in the Latvian language. That's a difficulty,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5750.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5760.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in particular for them, because they were already elderly people when naturalisation became possible for them as people born outside Latvia in 1998.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5760.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5760.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for the next question, I will pass the floor to Dr. Nikulceva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5765.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5772.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. Thank you, Judge Hussainov, for your questions and I would like to answer to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5774.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5790.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding naturalization, I also would like to add that none of the applicants had the right to be naturalized just after the restoration of the independence of Latvia. Those rules at the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5790.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5821.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>very beginning were very strict and only from 1998 they had the right to pretend for naturalization because before only those non-citizens who were born in Latvia were entitled to apply for naturalization. From 1998 there were no principal changes in the rules of naturalization and those</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5821.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5834.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>rules are equal for non-citizens and for foreign persons, for stateless persons also. So, this</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5834.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5845.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>person should pass language examination and should know Latvian constitution and Latvian history.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5845.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5875.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only difference is that for foreign persons there is a requirement that they should permanently live five years in Latvia and this is not a requirement for non-citizens because non-citizens live in Latvia permanently. And those very difficult rules for elderly persons were</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5875.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5896.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>actually the reason why the applicants were not naturalized, why they were not able to become citizens of Latvia and this is also the reason for most other non-citizens of Latvia currently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5896.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5905.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. I would also like to thank Judge Mitz for your questions and I will try to</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5906.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5916.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>answer these questions. Firstly, I honestly do not understand the arguments that we are speaking</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5916.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5941.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>only about some supplement to the retirement pensions because in Latvia, according to our legislation, we have a retirement pension and we have some supplement for working years, those who worked for a very long time. And here, in this case, the applicants applied</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5942.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5949.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because of calculation of their retirement pensions. This calculation is provided according</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5949.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5957.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the formula of paragraph 13 of the transitional provisions of the law on state pensions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5958.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5985.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to this formula, the amount of pension, not of the supplement, but of the retirement pension essentially depends on the length of work periods accumulated prior to the adoption of this law. This is prior to 1995. And because of some periods of work in the Soviet times,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5985.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6000.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it was not taken into account for the applicants that the retirement pension is smaller than for the citizens. Of course, these concerns are also supplements, but we are not speaking</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6000.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6008.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in substance about supplements to pensions, but to retirement pension as such.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6008.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6032.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And thank you, Judge Mitz, also about for a second question concerning a fundament of Latvia's responsibility for work periods for non-citizens outside the Soviet Union.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6033.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6041.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And once more, I would like to explain that my arguments were twofold. There were two main</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6041.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6049.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>arguments. Firstly, that Latvia itself has undertaken responsibility for those citizens</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6049.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6057.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the former Soviet Union who stayed in Latvia without accepting citizenship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6057.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6062.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the independence declaration of 1990. This is the constitution of Latvia,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6063.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6070.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which guarantees social rights for those persons. And this is the law on state pensions,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6070.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6080.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which in principle guarantees non-citizens' retirement pensions. And the second argument</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6080.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6096.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is that Latvia never said that we are not responsible for the Soviet times, for work periods in the Soviet times. On the contrary, Latvia included those periods in the calculation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6096.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6104.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of retirement pensions. So, Latvia itself took this responsibility, but it took this</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6104.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6120.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>responsibility on different grounds, according to different criteria, to non-citizens and to citizens. And this is our main argument, that we think that this should be on an equal basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6120.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6128.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now pass the floor to Mr Kuzmin for answering the last question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6129.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6130.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6130.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6141.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you also to Judge O'Leary for her question about the equal protection and same social guarantees as declared by the foreign ministry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6141.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6165.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is exactly what we and the applicants are asking for this to materialize, to bring the practice in lettering laws in consistency with the equal protection as it was declared by the government and with the same social guarantees, including the specifically named age pensions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6165.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6166.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6166.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6166.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will return the floor for Dr. Nikulceva for the conclusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6171.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6182.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. I would like very briefly to address two issues regarding the government's opinion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6183.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6202.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, I really would like to stress out that in our understanding this is not the case about Latvia's responsibility for work periods outside the Soviet Union. This is an anti-discrimination</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6202.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6213.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>case. Applicants do not claim inclusion of some periods outside Latvia in those work periods</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6214.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6221.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which are used for calculation of their retirement pensions and such. They just claim equal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6221.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6231.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>attitude. They claim precisely the same benefits which are provided in Latvia for citizens of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6231.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6241.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Latvia. As I mentioned, for citizens of Latvia, those periods in the Soviet Union are taken into</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6241.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6253.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>account. We claim exactly the same. In addition to that, I would like briefly to address one more</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6254.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6264.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>argument of the government. That is that non-citizens did not contribute to the economy</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6264.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6273.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Latvia as Latvian citizens did. I would also like to provide two counter-arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6274.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6294.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first is that in Soviet times, it was a common, centralised, unified economy, a common state, and any particular unit of the Soviet Union lacked economic independence. So, we cannot</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6294.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6300.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>actually speak about contributions, particularly in the Latvian economy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6302.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6313.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, it concerns payment of taxes and payment of pensions from the budget. All of this was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6313.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6321.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>centralised in the Soviet times. Secondly, I would like to underline</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6325.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6333.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that non-citizens do not claim anything more than for citizens. Here, we speak about</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6333.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6343.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the work periods outside Latvia also for citizens. Those citizens of Latvia, when they worked outside</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6343.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6350.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Latvia, did not contribute to the economy of Latvia. But still, those periods are taken</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6350.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6354.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>into account. This is the difference between non-citizens and citizens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6354.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6359.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6360.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6364.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed to the applicants' representatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6364.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6370.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No particular questions were posed to the third party intervenors, so we have now come to an end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6370.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6375.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'd like to thank the parties for their submissions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6375.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6381.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits, and the judgment will be delivered at a later stage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6381.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6384.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6384.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6384.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
