<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>4987211_28082012</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>10.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>11.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>64.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>65.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>71.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>83.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case of Tymoshenko against Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>83.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>99.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case was lodged on the 10th of August, 2011, with the court under Article 34 of the Convention by a Ukrainian national, Miss Yuliya Volodymyrivna Tymoshenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>99.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>109.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the Fifth Section of the Court pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the Rules of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>109.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>118.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on the 14th of December, 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>118.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>125.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Mr. Kulchytskyy, assisted by Mr. Bem, Mr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>125.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>132.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bogush, Miss Moiseienko, Mr. Mykytenko,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>132.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>139.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Bairachnyi, and Mr. Motliakh advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>139.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>144.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mrs. Telychenko</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>144.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>148.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. Vlasenko, lawyers,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>148.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>152.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Mrs. Senyk, counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>152.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>158.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>158.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>167.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representatives of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>167.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>171.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Kulchytskyy for the government</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>171.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>179.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>will speak first, and then Miss Telychenko and Mr. Vlasenko for the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>179.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>182.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Kulchytskyy, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>186.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>188.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>188.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>195.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable Court, the government of Ukraine would like to present their comments as to additional questions put by the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>195.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>208.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the first two questions, the government would like to know that all necessary factual information with relevant documents was submitted by the government in the course of the previous stages of the proceedings before the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>208.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>213.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Summarizing those facts, we would like to note the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>213.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>230.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the period when the applicant was held in Kiev CISO, all her complaints about the identity of medical treatment were mainly connected with the alleged appearance of red spots on her skin and low back pain, which appeared for the first time on 5 October 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>230.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>241.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With reference to those complaints, we would like to reiterate that during the aforementioned period, the applicant was receiving medical treatment which was adequate to her state of health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>241.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>252.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, it should be emphasized that the success of treatment provided to the applicant was prejudiced by her permanent refusal from any examination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>252.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>265.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant and German doctors in their turn explained the aforementioned refusal by mistrust between applicant and state authorities, including doctors of state-run hospitals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>265.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>274.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant alleged that such a situation developed as a result of continuous ineffective treatment during the first months of her detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>274.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>284.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, we would like to draw the Court's attention to the fact that the applicant refused from any examination from the first day of her detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>284.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>296.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, it was not the treatment provided to the applicant that caused aforementioned mistrust, but the applicant's position from the very beginning of her detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>296.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>306.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, the applicant was permanently consulted by her person, nurse, and doctor, who could monitor the process of providing the applicant with medical treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>306.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>313.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We therefore consider that the aforementioned mistrust was artificial and groundless.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>313.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>321.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With reference to the applicant's refusal from medical treatment, the Government also would like to comment on each and every complaint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>321.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>330.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, on 16 August 2011, the applicant complained for the first time about appearance of red spots on her body.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>330.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>344.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, the Government noted that such hemorrhages clearly indicated that the possible disease was connected with blood and required conduction of biochemical blood analysis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>344.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>348.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such was the decision of doctors who examined the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>348.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>355.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to this, she was afforded to undergo such blood analysis, but she refused.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>355.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>361.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She refused from conducting this examination in an independent civil hospital as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>361.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>370.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead of this, she just allowed to determine the time of blood clotting on condition for further destruction of biological material.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>370.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>386.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, it should be emphasized that without a preliminary analysis, it was also impossible for a physician to put the right diagnosis or, if necessary, to forward the applicant to another specialist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>386.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>391.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same applies as to the applicant's initial complaints about low back pain.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>391.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>398.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those complaints appeared for the first time on 5 October 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>398.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>403.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the very beginning, the applicant was examined by a neurologist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>403.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>409.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Necessary medicine was prescribed, and until the end of October 2011, her state of health improved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>409.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>415.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Subsequently, the applicant refused from prescribed medicine and recommended examination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>415.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>427.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result, low back pain intensified, and the applicant was prescribed additional medicine and recommended to undergo necessary instrumental examination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>427.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>434.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant had been refusing from most of them until the second part of November, when she finally gave her consent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>434.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>442.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result, the diagnosis was specified, and several new drugs corresponding to her state of health were prescribed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>442.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>450.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would also like to remind that the diagnosis put to the applicant at that time was subsequently confirmed by German doctors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>450.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>459.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This fact was among other things mentioned in government's letter of 20 March 2012, and documents attached there, too.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>459.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>478.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we would like to emphasize one more time that in spite of the applicant's continuous refusal from some examination and prescribed medicine, she received medical treatment to which she gave consent, and which could be prescribed on account of conducted examination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>478.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>485.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, we would like to address course questions concerning condition of the applicant's detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>485.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>508.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, we consider that the applicant's complaints concerning electric light being permanently switched on in cell 242, as well as all applicant's complaints concerning material condition in cell 300, should not be considered by the court, as they were submitted out of six time limits prescribed by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>508.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>515.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those complaints clearly concerned applicant's detention before 29 November 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>515.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>522.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the date when the applicant was transferred to the cell number 260 in the medical unit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>522.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>526.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The condition of detention was totally different.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>526.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>538.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such transfer to the different type of detention regime, according to the court's well-established case law, put an end to alleged continuous violation of the above applicant's rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>538.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>546.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the applicant should have lodged the aforementioned complaint not later than on 29 May 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>546.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>552.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead of this, she laid down the aforementioned complaints in her letter of 31 May 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>552.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>558.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, we insist that those complaints are inadmissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>558.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>577.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to alleged lack of bedding, we would like to note that according to certificate submitted by the government, the remaining stock of new bedding in the CISO included several thousand items of bed lining above the number necessary to provide all detainees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>577.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>586.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead of this, applicant used just her own bedding, which included 278 items of bed lining.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>586.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>595.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For this reason, the government cannot be responsible for the quality of bed lining and regularity of its changes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>595.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>615.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to alleged impossibility to open the window in cell number 242, given its location, we would like to note that it was already indicated by the government in their observation of 20 March 2012 that the location of the window had in no way prevented the applicant from opening it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>615.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>628.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The above fact is supported by photos of the cell number 242 made after and before refurbishment and submitted by the government in their annex to observation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>628.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>638.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All those photos clearly indicate that the window was located in standard position right in front of upstanding person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>638.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>653.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to alleged lack of hot and cold water supply, as well as drinking water supply, we would like to note that according to certificate previously submitted by the government, the applicant was provided with all aforementioned issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>653.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>669.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, the water supply in cell 242 is a part of centralized city water supply system, and drinking water during the period under consideration, there were no interruption in its functioning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>669.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>678.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same applies to condition of the applicant's detention in cell number 300, which was also linked to the city water supply and heating system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>678.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>689.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also know that cold water from the city water supply system is a drinking water consumed to all habitants in Kiev city.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>689.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>699.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Additionally, it should be mentioned that during the period of detention in CISO, the applicant received 316 liters of drinking water.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>699.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>709.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, the applicant had approximately two liters of water for each day, which is, in our opinion, is completely sufficient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>709.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>728.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to refurbishment of the cell 242, we would like to note that according to certificate of inspection of the above cell, which was conducted when the applicant was held there, the walls and ceiling were in satisfactory condition, and every week the cell was cleaned with special washing means.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>728.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>745.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, the government, while upholding their position as to admissibility of the applicant's complaints concerning the electric light being permanently switched on, also would like to note that in cell 242, there were two regimes of electric lighting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>745.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>755.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first one, designed for normal lighting, was provided by two lamps, each including eight 40-watt electric bulbs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>755.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>762.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And second one, designed for nighttime, was provided by single 60-watt lamp.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>762.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>769.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, the government considered that one bulb for 16.4 square meters could</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>769.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>774.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>not create any inconvenience to the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>774.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>791.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the alleged violation of the applicant's rights set forth in Article V of the Convention, we would like to reiterate that in our opinion, detention of the applicant was conducted in accordance with Article V, Paragraph 1c of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>791.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>809.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, as reason for the detention and extension of term of detention, National Courts noted that the applicant might attempt to abscond from trial, avoid the execution of procedural decision, and obstruct the establishment of truth in criminal case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>809.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>814.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those reasons listed by the National Courts correspond to court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>814.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>826.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to relevancy and sufficiency of those reasons, we would like to note that they were supported by a set of facts and documents which were in detail addressed in government's observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>826.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>835.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also reiterate that those reasons were used by National Courts to justify the applicant's detention for a period of 67 days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>835.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>848.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the lawfulness of the applicant's detention within the abovementioned period was repeatedly reviewed by the court on the basis of the applicant's and her lawyer's request.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>848.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>856.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Every time aforementioned request and arguments given therein were scrutinized by the court in separate procedural decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>856.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>864.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In those decisions, the court continuously reached the conclusion that the reason for the applicant's detention persisted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>864.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>879.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, the fact that the court scrutinized the lawfulness of the applicant's detention upon her request attests that the applicant had at her disposal a factual procedure by which she could challenge the lawfulness of her detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>879.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>896.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also upheld the position according to which, in case National Court found violation of one of the applicant's rights set forth in Article V of the Convention, she could have lodged a civil claim with the court to receive a compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>896.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>903.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, there was no violation of her rights stipulated by Article V, Paragraph V of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>903.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>926.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to applicant's complaints under Article XVIII of the Convention, we would like to reiterate that the applicant alleged that the interference with her rights prescribed by Article V of the Convention bore political character and was determined by the purpose of the exclusion her from political life of Ukraine and from participation in forthcoming parliamentary election.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>926.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>950.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to these complaints, we would like to remind that according to the court's case law, an applicant alleging that his rights and freedoms were limited for improper reason most conveniently shows that the real aim of the State authority was not the same as proclaimed, or, as can be reasonably inferred from the context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>950.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>972.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, the government note that analysis of the court's case law upon this issue attests that only separate concrete facts which unambiguously indicate bias towards the person may support the fact that there has been a restriction of her rights for the purposes not established by the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>972.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>984.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such position was taken by the court in its previous judgments in cases Khodorkovsky and Gusinsky v. Russia and also Tsibutari v. Moldova.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>984.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1001.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the instant case, the applicant, in corroboration of her allegation under Article XVIII of Convention, gives description of her political activities, political situation in Ukraine, and also refers to statement of different political institutions and politicians.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1001.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1017.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government considers those evidences to be of a very general nature and political character, which substantially decreases the evidential value as it was established in the case of Khodorkovsky.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1017.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1037.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, in her comments of 31 May 2012, applicant refers to certain statements of higher-ranking State official concerning different proceedings against her and several procedural violations which were allegedly committed by national authority in the course of those proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1037.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1043.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those facts, in the applicant's opinion, corroborate that those proceedings were politically motivated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1043.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1060.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, we would like to uphold the government's position mentioned in Letter of 11 July 2012 and insist that all these facts took place after the applicant had been detained and cannot be anyhow connected with her detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1060.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1081.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would also like to note that the aforementioned arguments concern the alleged unfairness of criminal proceedings instituted against the applicant, while in the instant case, the applicant's allegations under Article 18 of the Convention are considered by the Court in conjunction with Article 5 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1081.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1101.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we consider that the applicant has not submitted any evidences which would support the allegation that her liberty was restricted for the purposes of the exclusion her from political life of Ukraine and from participation in forthcoming parliamentary elections.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1101.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1109.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, we would like to turn to the question about condition of the applicant's detention and medical care in Kachanivskaya Colony.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1109.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1117.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this part, we completely uphold the government's position laid down in the observation of 20 March 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1117.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1144.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the medical care provided to the applicant in Kachanivskaya Colony, we would like to reiterate that Kachanivskaya Colony was provided with all necessary medical equipment, medical specialists, medical treatments was provided by the applicant by medical specialists who concluded her when she was held in CISO, as well as a few new local specialists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1144.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1152.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In case of medical necessity, the applicant could undergo some of the prescribed examination in civil hospitals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1152.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1159.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to this, applicant could have received a full-scale medical treatment in Kachanivskaya Colony.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1159.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1168.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the applicant refused from being treated in the colony and demanded inpatient treatment in one of civil hospitals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1168.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1175.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, it should be mentioned that there were no reason for transfer of the applicant from the colony.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1175.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1187.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In spite of this, after her state of health could have worsened due to her own behavior, the government gave consent to her transfer which was performed in May.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1187.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1203.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, we continue to emphasize that such a measure bore extraordinary character and was not preconcerned by lack of resources in the colony or urgent medical necessity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1203.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1211.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence we consider that all delays in providing the applicant with medical treatment rest completely with the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1211.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1228.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also would like to reiterate that according to court's case law, the standard of medical treatment for a person who is in jail could be lower than in civil hospitals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1228.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1237.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the incident case, medical treatment was provided to the applicant by leading experts from the best Ukrainian institution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1237.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1261.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, in case the court finds violation of this part of the applicant's complaints, it will attest that any detainee or convicted person may demand treatment under conditions and in a manner he or she considers necessary, and every member state will have a corresponding obligation to comply with those demands.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1261.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1273.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the next question of the court, we would like to indicate that we uphold the government's position set forth in the observation of 22 June 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1273.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1277.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In part of the applicant's complaint under Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1277.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1301.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, we would like to draw attention to the fact that upon the result of the inquiry into the applicant's complaint, the domestic investigative bodies established for sure that the applicant's allegation about inflicting bodily injuries to her on 20 April 2012 do not correspond to the facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1301.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1306.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The aforementioned is confirmed by all evidences in case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1306.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1331.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, it was supported by testimonies of other detainees, ambulance team, patient penitentiary officers, medical commission members, Ukrzaliznitsa staff, and other persons who had contact with the applicant from 20 till 23 April 2012, as well as by the report of forensic medical experts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1331.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1348.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now it should be stressed that the purpose of the prosecutor's office inquiry was not only to refute the applicant's version of events, but also to establish when and under what circumstances the applicant's injuries could have appeared.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1348.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1357.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under the result of the inquiry into the applicant's complaints, two possible versions of origin of her bodily injuries were forwarded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1357.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1366.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the first one, localization of the applicant's bodily injuries indicate that they could be self-inflicted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1366.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1381.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the second version, bruises found on the applicant's body could have been nothing less than hypodermic hematomas, which had been appearing from time to time on the applicant's body earlier.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1381.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1395.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to confirm one of the above versions, it was necessary to conduct direct examination of the applicant by forensic expert and to conduct biochemical blood analysis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1395.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1407.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consenting to the aforementioned proceedings, the applicant would have shown interest in establishing of circumstances under which she sustained her injuries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1407.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1424.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead of this, she continuously insisted on her version as to how the injuries appeared on her body, and flatly refused from her direct examination by a forensic expert, as well as from blood analysis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1424.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1436.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such position of the applicant deprived, in our opinion, the investigative bodies from opportunity to establish additional information which could subsequently narrow the scope of investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1436.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1450.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we consider that under the circumstances of the present case, the domestic bodies took all possible measures to establish reason of appearance of the applicant's bodily injuries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1450.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1456.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, these attempts were neutralized by the applicant's behavior.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1456.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1471.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, as to the last question of the applicant, we would like to uphold the government's position set forth in the observation of 22 June 2012 in part of the applicant's complaint under Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1471.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1478.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here we reiterate that according to the court's judgment in the case Golder v. United Kingdom,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1478.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1492.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the ordinary and reasonable requirements of imprisonment may justify a wider measure of interference in case of any prisoner that is in that of person at liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1492.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1507.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to such court's practice, the government admits that in the present case, the surveillance upon the applicant at the hospital ward continues interference in her private life in context of Article 8 of Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1507.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1511.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, we contend that such interference was not excessive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1511.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1519.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, in our observation, we noted that three cameras of video surveillance are placed in the applicant's ward.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1519.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1523.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Video surveillance is not being carried out in toilet room.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1523.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1530.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, while the applicant was examined by the doctor in the ward, video surveillance was not carried out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1530.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1539.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The video cameras at that time were contained by black stiff material.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1539.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1553.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, mention is confirmed not only by the explanation taken from the medical personnel who examined the applicant and convicted person treated in the same ward, but also by the report of doctor from Hospital Charita.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1553.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1572.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the treatment of the applicant in Ukrzaliznytskyi Hospital from 21 to 22 May 2012, in particular, he noted that during the medical examination of the applicant in the ward, the video cameras were contained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1572.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1580.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Every time a person forgot to do it, he drew attention to this, and cameras were contained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1580.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1594.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, video surveillance in the applicant's ward has been carried out exclusively within the framework of necessary surveillance required by the regime and was proportional in meaning of Article 8 of Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1594.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1606.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, we insist that in present case, there was no violation of the applicant's rights guaranteed by Article 8 of Convention on account of permanent surveillance in her ward.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1606.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1606.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1613.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1618.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr Kulchytskyy. I call now Ms Telychenko please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1619.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1621.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1621.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1623.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dear Mr. President, honorable judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1623.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1632.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I represent the applicant, the leader of the United Opposition of Ukraine, the former prime minister of Ukraine, Ms. Yulia Tymoshenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1632.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1635.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was detained on August 5, 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1635.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1643.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since November, the applicant has experienced acute pain in her back and practically stopped moving on her own.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1643.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1649.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite her numerous requests for medical assistance, the applicant has not received any treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1649.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1653.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She trusted neither prison nor civilian doctors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1653.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1674.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since both of them made numerous official statements that the applicant had no serious health problem and did not need any hospitalization or medical treatment, the applicant could not invite doctors per her choosing to examine her, though this right is guaranteed by the national law of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1674.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1680.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>CISO has a medical unit which provides emergency care but does not provide any primary care.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1680.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1686.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>CISO has no neurologist in its staff but only therapist general practicing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1686.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1695.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite the applicant's health condition, she was forced by penitentiary authorities to participate in court hearings and to read her case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1695.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1705.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court hearing on the applicant's detention in the United Energy System case took place when the applicant was in the medical unit in December, 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1705.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1712.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the hearing on detention, the applicant had to undergo emergency treatment with painkillers three times.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1712.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1721.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the court's decisions, the state must ensure that the health and well-being of detainees are adequately secured by.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1721.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1749.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the applicant's case, however, the constant manipulation with the information on the applicant's state of health, providing her with painkillers on conditions of her cooperation with law enforcement bodies while knowing that she is seriously ill, manifest the lack of complaints of the government with the obligations under the European Convention on Human Rights to provide appropriate medical assistance to people in prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1749.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1760.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regards to the material and sanitary conditions of the applicant's detention, she was placed in cell 242 on the Kiev CISO on August 5.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1760.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1764.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The size of the cell was approximately 16 square meters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1764.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1768.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there were two other detainees in that cell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1768.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1772.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cell was without hot water and sometimes without even cold water.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1772.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1777.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cell had no shower and had a strong smell of mildew.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1777.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1785.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The light in the cell could not have been switched off as government confirmed and had been kept on 24 hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1785.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1793.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only window in the cell was located too high to be reached by the inmates and therefore had never been opened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1793.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1797.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ventilation was provided through the cracked glass in the window.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1797.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1804.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The toilet was in the cell, only separated from the rest of the room by one-meter-high partition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1804.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1809.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was allowed to shower only twice per week.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1809.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1817.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant felt humiliated to ask for the permission to take an additional shower or to get hot water.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1817.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1821.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no supply of drinking water provided to the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1821.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1826.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant received no bedding and requested it from her relatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1826.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1829.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She also asked her relatives for food.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1829.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1833.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The quality of food served in Kiev CISO is unacceptably poor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1833.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1841.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is a common practice for inmates to receive food in person from their relatives and friends.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1841.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1850.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Government did not provide pictures from the cell number 242 that were made before the renovation in that cell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1850.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1858.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On November 24, 2011, the applicant was transferred to another cell, cell 300.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1858.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1861.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cell 300 had no heating.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1861.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1869.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicant was forced to stay in that cell fully dressed, including her overcoat and gloves, even when she went to sleep.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1869.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1874.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a toilet in the cell and no hot water, as in previous.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1874.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1888.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On November 28, just prior to the CPT ad hoc mission visit to Kiev CISO, late at night, the applicant was transferred to cell 260 in the medical unit of the Kiev CISO.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1888.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1899.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This cell fully corresponded to the description provided by the government in its observation dated March 20, 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1899.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1907.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While being detained in Kiev CISO, the applicant was not given a chance to use her rugs because of her almost daily court sessions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1907.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1915.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the first 30 days of the detention, she spent 25 days in court at the court sessions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1915.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1917.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Each court session lasted until late evening.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1917.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1928.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the days when the applicant had to go to court, she was woken up at around 5 o'clock in the morning to be transported to the court around 8 AM.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1928.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1934.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then she spent sometimes 14 hours at the court session.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1934.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1940.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nina Karpachyova, the ombudsman of Ukraine, confirmed these facts by her document.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1940.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1948.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, despite existence of daily walks in the detainee's routine schedule, the applicant was deprived of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1948.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1956.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The detention authorities failed to provide the applicant with the food or water supply during the court sessions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1956.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1962.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the national legislation, no parcel of deliveries can be made to detainees in court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1962.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1970.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Water or food can be delivered to detainees by anybody except the penitentiary service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1970.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1980.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the applicant did not receive anything from her relatives during the court session days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1980.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1982.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Question three.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1982.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1993.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that the decision to deprive the applicant of liberty had been made by a court did not guarantee the complaints of the decision with the national law or international obligations of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1993.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2007.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Shevchenko District Court violated the national legislation by conducting hearings on the applicant's detention in the medical unit of Kiev CISO, since no secured court is allowed by the national legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2007.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2019.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the applicant and her lawyer were neither properly informed about the time of the hearing, nor given enough time to prepare to that hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2019.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2030.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were informed an hour before the beginning of the hearing, which indicates the arbitrariness of the whole process of the applicant's detention by the Shevchenko District Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2030.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2050.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Taken into consideration that the applicant is a public figure in Ukraine, and that there is a huge public interest in her case, the decision of having closed hearing on her detention violates the principle of non-arbitrary deprivation of the liberty, and violates Article 5, Paragraph 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2050.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2061.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the court hearing in the medical unit of the Kiev CISO, a significant group of journalists were waiting at the entrance to the CISO, since they were not allowed to get in.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2061.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2069.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Article 20 of the Criminal Code of Ukraine also provides that all court hearings shall be public in Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2069.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2079.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The protocol of the Shevchenko District Court on the applicant's detention stated that the hearing had been public, while it had taken place in Kiev CISO.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2079.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2088.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The access to Kiev CISO is regulated by strict rules, and nobody without a special permit can enter it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2088.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2094.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite high public interest to the court hearing, no journalists were allowed to attend it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2094.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2107.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the court hearing on the applicant's detention was not public, what constitute a violation of the national legislation of Ukraine, and the principle of the Article 5, Paragraph 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2107.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2118.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Pechersky Court justified the applicant's detention by her being suspected in committing a serious crime, and that she could have absconded the due course of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2118.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2125.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the trial court failed to provide any evidences on the attempt abscond of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2125.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2131.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Additionally, the applicant had never committed any violent crime, and had no criminal record.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2131.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2143.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She made no attempt to avoid inquiry during the pretrial investigation, or a trial that lasted more than a year before the applicant's detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2143.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2155.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant could not have continuing activities she was charged with, because she had not been Prime Minister for more than a year by the time when she was detained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2155.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2173.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a defendant, she complied with all procedural decisions, and came to all investigation questions and court sessions on time, with the exception of the court session on August 5, 2011, when she arrived with a seven-minute delay.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2173.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2179.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we believe that the court decision to detain the applicant was not proportional.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2179.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2188.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Shevchenko District Court, in its decision, explained the applicant's detention by her possibility of absconding the influence upon witnesses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2188.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2209.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Shevchenko District Court ignored the fact that the applicant could not have had any influence on anybody from Kiev's season, where she was already detained and held the weight in the appeal hearing in the gas agreement case, and she could not escape justice in that situation as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2209.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2213.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were two court decisions on detention of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2213.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2221.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One is made by the Pechersky Court on August 5, and another is by Shevchenko Court on December 8, 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2221.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2232.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both decisions were to detain the applicant for unlimited period of time, and this is in breach of the Article 5, Paragraph 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2232.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2249.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even though the order of the Pechersky Court was in accordance with the national law on detention during trials, it contradicted the court's interpretation of Article 5, Paragraph 1, per the court's decisions, in particular, Kharchenko against Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2249.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2260.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Shevchenko Court also held the decision to detain the applicant in the United Energy System of Ukraine case for unspecified time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2260.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2268.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The national legislation of Ukraine limits the detention during any pretrial investigation to two months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2268.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2277.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, Judge Trubnikov ignored the national legislation and held decision to deprive the applicant of liberty for unlimited period of time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2277.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2290.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant believed that there is a violation of impartiality of the Pechersky District Court since it failed to provide confirmation of the computerized random appointment of Judge Kireev.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2290.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2302.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the explanatory part of the court decision on the applicant's detention from August 5, Kireev referred to the following evidences of the applicant's noncompliance with the lawful order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2302.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2307.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's absence in court on August 5, seven minutes delay, in fact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2307.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2319.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Disrespect for him personally by not getting up when addressing the judge, and the applicant's refusal to answer a question on her permanent and current address.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2319.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2324.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was present at all court sessions and arrived on time each time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2324.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2337.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Her current and permanent address were written in her case file and on a relevant page of a copy of her passport, which she submitted to court in accordance with the national law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2337.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2350.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, it was not clear why Judge Kireev stated, as one of the reasons of the applicant's misconduct in court, her refusal to answer the question regarding her current address during the public hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2350.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2362.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Beside, the Constitutional Court of Ukraine recognized information about the place of residence of any person as confidential, and therefore allowed not make it public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2362.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2380.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regard to disrespect for Judge Kireev, the applicant made a statement in court that she considered the appointment of an unexperienced young judge who had not been confirmed by Parliament for permanent acting in breach of the national legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2380.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2386.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, she did not recognize the court as independent and impartial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2386.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2394.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant declared that therefore, she would not address Judge Kireev as your owner, but Mr. Kireev,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2394.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2398.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and would not arise from her seat to address him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2398.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2409.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant referred to Article 39 of the Constitution of Ukraine, which allowed to express individual protest in any form which is not dangerous for public order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2409.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2414.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The national legislation of Ukraine does not foresee detention for violating discipline in court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2414.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2430.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it was mentioned in answer to the question three, the Shevchenko District Court in its decision on the applicant's detention made in December 2011 explained the applicant's detention by her possible abscond and influence upon witnesses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2430.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2444.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court ignored the fact that the applicant could not have had any influence on anybody from CISO where she was held awaiting the appeal hearing in the gas agreement case, and she could not escape justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2444.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2456.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the national legislation, decisions on detention held on the basis of Article 274 of the Criminal Procedural Code of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2456.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2462.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decisions in the detention during the trial cannot be a subject of judicial review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2462.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2472.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the lack of the legal procedure to challenge the decision of detention for unlimited period of time, which is the violation of Article 5, paragraph 4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2472.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2482.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decision of the Shevchenko District Court to detain the applicant for unlimited period of time was appealed in the Kiev City Court Appeal and upheld by it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2482.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2502.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regards to the applicant's effective and enforceable right to compensation for her detention, I would like to mention that according to the national law Article 1176 of the Civil Code of Ukraine, anticipates compensation for damage in case of unlawful usage of the preventive measure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2502.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2512.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no legal procedure for applicants' detention to be recognized as illegal if the decision to detain has been held by a court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2512.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2521.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there is no appellation procedure to challenge the decision on detention by the Pechersk District Court, as has been shown above.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2521.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2531.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Shevchenko District Court has been shown above the Shevchenko District Court decision was appealed, but the Kiev City Court of Appeal upheld it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2531.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2543.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the applicant cannot use Article 1176 of the Civil Code of Ukraine, as government indicated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2543.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2553.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was transferred to Kachanivka colony on December 31, 2011, straight from the medical unit of the Kiev CISO.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2553.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2560.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And was placed in the ordinary cell despite her immobilized condition and permanent acute pain in her back.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2560.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2577.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite applicants' numerous requests to allow her to use rockets to assist her moving in that cell, Kachanivka colony authorities rejected her request, and she was condemned to staying in bed and was not able to enjoy daily walks outdoors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2577.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2591.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After three months of the applicant's loss of mobility in February 2011, she was examined by the group of German and Canadian doctors who confirmed her serious illness and requested her immediate hospitalization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2591.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2600.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 15 March 2011, the court indicated to the government of Ukraine under Rule 39 to ensure that Ms. Temushenko receives</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2600.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2607.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>treatment appropriate to her complaints in an appropriate institutionalized setting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2607.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2623.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government of Ukraine consistently tried to avoid transferring the applicant outside of Kachanivka colony, though it was ever aware of her critical state of health and her urgent need to be treated in the specialized medical institution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2623.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2633.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On March 16, 2011, the government bought medical equipment from nearby hospitals to Kachanivka prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2633.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2650.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the same day, the applicant was offered to undergo a procedure known as a lumbar puncture in the Kachanivka prison medical ward, which had no proper conditions or sterility and lacked appropriate medical equipment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2650.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2657.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant refused to accept the lumbar puncture procedure in the general medical ward in the Kachanivka colony.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2657.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2672.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 15, 22, 24, 25 March 2011, the applicant submitted a written request for medical treatment and complained about the lack of such to the administration of the Kachanivka colony.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2672.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2678.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On April 4, 2011, the applicant was offered a transfer to the Ugrzaliznitsa hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2678.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2690.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>German doctors did a research on conditions at this hospital, and they indicated a number of problems with the applicant undergoing treatment in the Ugrzaliznitsa hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2690.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2696.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And consequently, the applicant refused to go to the Ugrzaliznitsa hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2696.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2709.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On Friday, April 20, 2011, after 11 PM, the applicant was transferred by force to Ugrzaliznitsa hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2709.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2717.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result, on the prison ward's applying physical force to the applicant, her hands and stomach were abrasive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2717.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2733.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 106 of the Penitentiary Law of Ukraine allows the use of force against the prisoner if it was made strictly necessary by the conduct of the prisoner herself and if the degree of force used was at the minimum possible level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2733.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2740.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the applicant's case, there was no treat to life or health to any prison ward or other person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2740.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2749.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there could not have been any violence or aggression in the applicant's behavior since she has been immobilized for the last several months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2749.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2752.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the use of force was unjustified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2752.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2760.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In protest of physical abuse and humiliation, the applicant went to hunger strike on April 20 this year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2760.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2770.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was humiliated and threatened by the time she was transported to the Ugrzaliznitsa hospital late at night on Friday.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2770.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2772.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And she asked to see her lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2772.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2780.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's lawyer arrived in Kharkiv on Monday, April 23 and was allowed to see her only after 6 PM.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2780.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2787.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for whole day, he had to wait for the meeting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2787.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2801.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe the government of Ukraine failed to conduct an effective fact-finding and refused to initiate a criminal investigation on physical abuse of the applicant in breach of its duty under Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2801.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2815.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 27 April 2011, the ombudsman Nina Karpacheva announced to the national media about the applicant's physical abuse by the prison guards on April 20 during the transportation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2815.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2821.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ombudsman's office was searched by the KU prosecutor office soon after that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2821.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2833.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And some of the members of the ombudsman's secretary staff were called to be questioned by the KU prosecutor office, though no criminal investigation was opened against the ombudsman.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2833.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2842.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thereafter, the government declared that Nina Karpacheva forced her staff to make a failed statement about the process on Mr. Moshenko's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2842.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2848.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>body without mentioning any names or sources of that statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2848.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2857.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The prosecutor general of Ukraine declared this process a result of self-harm by the former prime minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2857.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2871.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regards to the applicant's right under Article 8, the applicant was under surveillance in the KFC zone by secret cameras while in the Kachanukha colony and Uxaleznitsya hospital, she could at least see some of the installed cameras.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2871.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2891.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the breach of Article 103, Part 2 of the Penitentiary Code of Ukraine, the applicant was not informed about the surveillance in the KFC zone and has never signed any documents informing her about the around-the-clock surveillance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2891.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2902.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant refused to undergo the medical procedure which required her getting undressed or discuss any intimate issues on the cameras.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2902.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2913.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant finds it humiliating to be under around-the-clock surveillance by three video cameras in her ward, in particular when she is undergoing medical treatment in the hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2913.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2934.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite numerous requests of the applicant and her treating doctors to respect the applicant's privacy and to cover the cameras during medical procedure and consultations with her treating doctors, the representatives of the surveillance and security unit of the Kachanukha prison often forget or refuse to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2934.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2958.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government insisted that the applicant was under 24-hour surveillance according to the national law, Article 103 of the Penitentiary Code of Ukraine, which allowed the around-the-clock surveillance for preventive escapes and other crimes, violations, or the order of serving sentence, the obtaining necessary information about the convicted prison's behavior.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2958.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2965.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government never specified particular reasons for Kachanukha administration to use 24-hour surveillance of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2965.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2976.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government does not mention any suspicious with regard to the applicant's preparation of escape or other crime or violations of the established by the legislation order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2976.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2986.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we assume that the only reason for the government to authorize around-the-clock surveillance over the applicant was to obtain information about the applicant's behavior.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2986.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2998.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the government failed to set out in a form accessible for the public any indication of the procedure to be followed for examining, sharing, storing, and destroying the recorded materials.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2998.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3000.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also did not make any specific recommendations for the use of 24-hour surveillance</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2999.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3006.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Litschenko, if I may interrupt you, I just want to draw your attention to the fact that you have already exhausted your allocated time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3006.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3013.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since you indicated that Ms. Flasenko will also take the floor, I would ask you to conclude your submissions, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3014.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3015.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President. Last paragraph.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3015.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3017.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3017.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3030.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the applicant's detention, she has been refused the right to use a pay phone to call her family except for May 24, when she was allowed to call to her mother-in-law with regard to the death of her father-in-law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3030.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3041.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Penitentiary Service of Ukraine made a statement that the applicant's rights to call her family after the death of her father-in-law was a luxury except for the applicant due to her political status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3041.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3047.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a person with special needs due to her immobilization, the applicant could not walk to the pay phone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3047.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3058.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Kachanivka prison administration was under a positive obligation to ensure that the applicant could have enjoyed her right to family life by talking to her relatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3058.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3069.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Article 110 of the Penitentiary Code of Ukraine, the applicant, as a convict, has a right to unlimited phone calls from a pay phone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3069.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3080.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, a fellow of the Kachanivka colony administration to ensure this right to the applicant is in breach of the national law, as well as Ukraine's obligation under Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3080.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3080.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3086.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3088.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Telychenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3088.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3091.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call now Mr. Vlasenko, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3091.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3091.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3100.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3104.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President, honorable judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3104.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3107.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, I want to say that Mrs. Tymoshenko believes</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3107.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3127.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the purpose of her detention was absolutely contrary to the Article 18 of the European Convention, and that actually serves her exclusion from political life in Ukraine and from participation in the upcoming parliamentary elections, which will be held on the 28th of October this year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3127.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3132.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm sure that in some two years, that case of Mrs. Tymoshenko will be studied</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3132.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3137.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by the law students in Ukraine, in Europe, and in the United States of America.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3137.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3153.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also think that that unprecedented legal and human cynicism, which is used by the Ukrainian nowadays government towards the leader of Ukrainian opposition, should be evaluated by that court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3153.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3164.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will also ask that very high court to evaluate that juridical ingenuity of Ukrainian authorities towards Mrs. Tymoshenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3164.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3176.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Ukrainian authorities, the Ukrainian government, think that they find out the mechanism, the possibility how to in jail Mrs. Tymoshenko for life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3176.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3193.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For that purpose, they are uprising the new and new absolutely absurd accusations against her, renewing the cases which were closed seven years ago by the Supreme Courts, because they understand that now in Ukraine, they could do it every five minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3193.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3197.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And only after that, Mrs. Tymoshenko would be obliged</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3197.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3214.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to fight against the old state machine, which includes the judiciary system, the prosecutor office, the state doctors, the penitentiary system, which coordinate their activity every day against Mrs. Tymoshenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3214.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3228.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because the main purpose of that is to take off the main political opponent of the nowadays president from the political life of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3228.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3237.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should say that there is no judiciary, there is no fair judiciary in Ukraine at all, and there is no fair judiciary for Mrs. Tymoshenko specifically.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3237.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3239.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's not my personal position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3239.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3242.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is not also the position of Mrs. Tymoshenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3242.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3255.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the position of a very high-rank European institution, such as European Parliament, Parliamentary Assembly of Council of Europe, OSCE, NATO General Assembly, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3255.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3275.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe, in its resolution 1862, dated January 26th of this year, reiterated its condemnation of the numerous shortcomings noted in the trial against the former government officials and the lack of a fair trial in Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3275.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3292.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Parliamentary Assembly of Council of Europe criticized Articles 364 and 365 of the Criminal Code as overly broad in application and such that effectively allowed ex post facto criminalization of normal political decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3292.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3302.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Parliamentary Assembly of Council of Europe recognized that practice as counter of the principle of rule of law and called that absolutely unacceptable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3302.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3307.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's also not the position of the governmental institution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3307.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3315.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such an independent experts, like Amnesty International, also stated their position on that issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3315.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3325.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, Amnesty International, in its statement dated October 11th of 2011, it was the day of the verdict of Mrs. Tymoshenko case,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3325.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3327.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>stated the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3327.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3332.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The prosecution against Yulia Tymoshenko is politically motivated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3332.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3337.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The charges against her are not internationally recognizable offenses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3337.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3343.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are attempts to criminalize decision that she made in the course of her work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3343.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3353.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Her conviction and her detention on these charges is illegitimate and she should be immediately released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3353.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3371.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But at that moment, the Ukrainian government hopes that the European Court of Human Rights will revise all that files for years and years and years and years and all that long time, Mrs. Tymoshenko will be in jail for nothing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3371.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3375.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I saw Mrs. Tymoshenko yesterday as her defense lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3375.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3379.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She still couldn't work without the working aids.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3379.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3381.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She couldn't sit for a long time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3381.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3383.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She is lying in bed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3383.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3390.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She couldn't use all her powers and all her rights, even as an imprisoned person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3390.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3395.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She couldn't use her rights that have any imprisoned person in Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3395.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3402.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She is absolutely isolated from any communication with her relatives and with the press.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3402.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3408.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I'm addressing you in the name of Mrs. Tymoshenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3408.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3425.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She asked me to address you asking help because, as I've said, there is no fair judiciary in Ukraine and the only help of Mrs. Tymoshenko is you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3425.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3433.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only the decision of the European Court could help the former prime minister, the leader of Ukrainian opposition in that situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3433.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3439.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sorry for such a long introduction, but Mrs. Tymoshenko asked me to tell you so, and I did.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3439.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3457.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>About the violations of the Article 18 of the Convention, I could specifically mention that, first of all, the absence of legal grounds or evidence for detaining the applicant in decision of the Pechersk and Shevchenkovsky District Courts prove the political purpose of that decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3457.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3462.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These decisions are not typical for Ukrainian judiciary practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3462.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3476.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also could say that there were no case in Ukraine's independent history which was held in the cell of the jail, specifically or in particularly when the person was immobilized and seriously ill.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3476.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3481.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was the first case in Ukrainian independent history.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3481.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3488.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All that violation of law during the court hearings and during the detention of Mrs. Tymoshenko</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3488.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3494.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>were supervised by the independent observers who were directly present in the courtroom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3494.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3505.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have in the case files the research done by the Danish Helsinki Committee, which absolutely and strictly says that the detention of Mrs. Tymoshenko was not legal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3505.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3507.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was politically motivated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3507.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3510.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were no criminal prosecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3510.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3517.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a political prosecution of the main political opponent of the nowadays Ukrainian regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3517.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3527.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also should mention that every day in the court were present the independent legal experts from the embassies of the countries of the European Union on the everyday basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3527.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3539.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And all that countries made their statements that that case was a politically motivated case and that had nothing to do with a fair trial, with a fair detention, with a fair judiciary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3539.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3545.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, I should mention that the detention of Mrs. Tymoshenko</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3545.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3568.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>restricted her ability to communicate with Ukrainian and foreign politicians, journalists, and voters, though she nominally remained the head of the political party, Batkivshchina, the main oppositional political party, but she was not able to perform her duties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3568.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3574.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Kiev, Sezov, 13, she was able only to communicate with her lawyers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3574.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3592.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should also say that the high-ranking officials in Ukraine, like President, Prime Minister, Prosecutor General, all his deputies, the Minister of Health, the Ministry of Justice, all vice prime ministers, among others, made numerous statements about the detention of Mrs. Tymoshenko,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3592.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3599.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that it was legal, that it was OK, and that it was absolutely criminally prosecuted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3599.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3608.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, I should mention such a brilliant quote, which was made by the member of the parliament, Mr. Chechetov, who is the head of the party,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3608.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3611.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the fraction of the party of region in the Ukrainian parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3611.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3614.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He said, if she would be silent, she would be free.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3614.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3618.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that's the consequences of what is going on in the case of Tymoshenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3618.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3622.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If she would be silent, she would be free.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3622.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3632.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, I should say that the political sense of her detention was shown in the verdict, in the verdict of Pechersky District Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3632.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3646.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In that verdict, the only motive for so-called criminal activity was mentioned by the judge as the creation of the personal political image as of prime minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3646.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3648.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So what's that?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3648.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3654.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's a direct violation of Article 18 of the European Convention of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3654.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3661.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also should say that...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3661.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3662.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>..the government high-ranking officials,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3662.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3667.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for example, such a Minister of Justice, Mr. Alexander Lavrinovich,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3667.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3672.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>stated to press that if Mrs. Tymoshenko had admitted her crimes</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3672.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3676.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and had asked to be pardoned, she would have been released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3676.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3682.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we know from the case of the former Minister of Defence, Mr. Ivashchenko, who actually declared himself guilty,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3682.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3686.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and he was immediately released in the courtroom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3686.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3691.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in this way, the government just managed the courts in Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3691.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3702.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also should mention that during the hearings in the High Specialized Court of Civil and Criminal Cases in Kiev, the representative of the prosecutor office, Mrs. Drogobetskaya,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3702.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3705.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>she said that Mrs. Tymoshenko was arrested</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3705.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3711.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because she don't want to stand up in the courtroom, and she was saying the political slogans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3711.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3718.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that are the real things what for Mrs. Tymoshenko was detained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3718.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3728.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should end my speech and I should just say once more that your court is the only hope of Mrs. Tymoshenko in Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3728.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3728.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3732.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3734.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Vlasenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3734.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3740.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the judges if there are questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3740.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3741.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Nuberger, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nuberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3745.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3748.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, please, I have some questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3748.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3753.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first set of questions concerns the reasons for the applicant's detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3753.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3773.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the reasons given for the applicant's detention on 5th August 2011 were that she might attempt to abscond, and I quote now, to abscond from trial, evade the execution of procedural decisions, abstract the establishment of the truth in the criminal case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3773.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3784.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was further argued that she failed to show respect for the court and participants of the trial and breached the order of consideration of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3784.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3794.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, she had failed to comply with instructions of the court and obstructed the process of interrogation of witnesses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3794.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3797.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So my questions are the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3797.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3806.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are there other cases in Ukraine in which courts have ordered pretrial detention for contempt of court?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3806.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3809.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is this a legal practice in Ukraine?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3809.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3817.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And second, what is meant by the reproach she obstructed the process of interrogation of witnesses?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3817.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3827.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If she just asked questions or contradicted witnesses, isn't that her procedural right on the basis of the Code of Criminal Procedure?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3827.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3837.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second set of questions concerns the transport to the hospital and thus the incident on 20th of April 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3838.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3841.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So my question first go to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3841.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3855.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was the video surveillance of the applicant's cell never recording or was it only not properly functioning the day when the applicant was brought to the hospital?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3855.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3866.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Next question, why was the prison inmate who shared the applicant's cell brought to another cell immediately before the applicant was removed?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3866.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3874.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third question, why has she been transferred to the hospital during the night after she had already gone to bed?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3874.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3878.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it was at 9.30, I think they arrived,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3878.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3882.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and she was brought to the hospital at 10.40 in the night.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3882.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3900.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And fourth question, in which way was the evidence obtained by the Ombudsman used by the general prosecutor when deciding about opening or not opening a criminal investigation into the incident?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3900.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3910.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then I want to know, the state authorities have given two possibilities, possible reasons for the hematomes found on the applicant's body.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3910.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3920.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, that they were self-inflicted, and second, that there were symptoms of the illness the applicant had had before already in August 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3920.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3945.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I just want to know concerning self-infliction, how could the applicant have self-inflicted the hematoma in prison as she was surveyed 24 hours by the video surveillance and it was never claimed that anybody has seen herself applying blunt objects against her body?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3945.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3959.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the question concerning this incident to the applicant, why has the applicant not complained about the use of force immediately when she arrived in the hospital Friday night?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3959.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3968.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And why did she show the hematoma only on 24th of April, that is four days afterwards and not before?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3968.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3973.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And why did she not accept a blood test to be taken after that?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3973.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3985.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And just one further question concerning the lack or the denial of provision of painkillers during the court hearings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3985.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3994.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to know, the applicant said that the painkillers were only given to her when she cooperated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3994.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4004.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I want to know which sort of cooperation was demanded and for how long was she denied the medicine she thought she needed?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4004.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4004.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4009.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4011.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Nuberger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4011.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4012.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Villiger, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Mark Villiger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4015.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4018.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4018.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4023.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a group of questions to begin with on the conditions of detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4023.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4037.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And here I would begin with questions to the applicant's representatives, in particular concerning the applicant's allegations as to inhuman treatment in Kiev Detention Center Number 13.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4037.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4060.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I note that the description of the detention conditions given by the applicant in the original complaint dated 5 October 2011 differs from the description given by the applicant later on received by the registry on 8th, 25th June and 6th July 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4060.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4075.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The descriptions differ in important aspects, for example, as the size of the cell, 16, 14 square meters, the amount of showers allowed, one shower per week, two showers per week, the necessity to ask for permission for an extra shower.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4075.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4085.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to ask the applicant's representatives why do these descriptions differ?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4085.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4093.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then still on the conditions of detention, I have questions both to the applicant's representatives and to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4093.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4108.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would wish to know was the applicant granted privileges which other detainees were not granted, for example, concerning food parcels, parcels with bed linen, parcels with fresh drinking water and so on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4108.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4110.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Were all prisoners provided?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4110.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4117.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, could all prisoners be provided with food, bed linen and drinking water in a sufficient quality?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4117.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4124.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if the applicant received special treatment, why was this necessary?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4124.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4135.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next group of questions concerns the applicant's medical treatment, and here I would begin with questions to the applicant's representatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4135.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4143.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What was the reason for the applicant not to trust the medical treatment and examination offered by the authorities?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4143.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4154.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, why did she at times accept to take the medicaments prescribed and to undergo examinations?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4154.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4160.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why did she refuse to be examined when Dr. P and her nurse were present, even though</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4160.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4169.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>previously she had wished that this happened, for example, 3rd September and 15th September 2011?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4169.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4175.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the government, I have a final question as to the medical treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4175.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4188.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I note that a different assessment of the health status of the applicant was made by the prison doctors on the one hand and by the foreign doctors on the other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4188.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4195.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How can such a different assessment be explained, particularly as regards the evaluation of the seriousness of the applicant's condition?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4195.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4196.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4196.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4197.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question was, how can this assessment be explained, particularly as regards the evaluation of the seriousness of the applicant's condition?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4197.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4197.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4200.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4204.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Judge Villiger, Judge Yudkivska please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ganna Yudkivska</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4207.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4212.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. I have a question to the government concerning the applicant's complaint under</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4212.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4217.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 8 of the Convention. You have stated in your submission that video surveillance</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4217.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4223.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the applicant in the hospital had a legal basis and pursued legitimate aim. I would</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4223.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4230.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>like to ask you to comment on proportionality and necessity of this measure. Also, had the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4230.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4241.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>applicant complained to the administrative court as the government suggested she had to do? Would the administrative court examine not only legality but proportionality of the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4241.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4247.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>impugned measure according to relevant legislation and domestic case law? And was this remedy</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4247.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4253.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>effective in the applicant's situation? And on this latter point, I would like to ask</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4253.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4255.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applicant to comment as well. Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4258.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4260.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. Are there any other questions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4260.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4263.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This doesn't seem to be the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4263.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4269.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there will be a break now for 20 minutes, and we will resume the hearing in 20 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4269.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4269.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4330.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4331.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4368.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4371.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4371.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4375.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Kulchytskyy, please. You have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4379.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4408.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the first question, I would like to know that, as it was mentioned before, the reason for the applicant's detention was clearly mentioned in the national court's decision, and it was mentioned that the applicant may attempt to abscond from trial, await execution of the procedural decision, and obstruct establishment of truth in criminal case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4408.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4418.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With respect of the applicant to the court, cannot be reason for her pretrial detention, and it never was in this case also.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4418.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4427.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was just mentioned by the court as one of characterized issues of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4427.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4431.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it never was a reason for her conviction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4431.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4452.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course, we cannot submit any examples of any decisions in which a person was jailed for disrespect to the courts, since it cannot be reason for held person in custody.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4452.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4468.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to video surveillance, in day when applicant was transferred to the clinic, there was never videotaping, as there was video surveillance in real-time regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4468.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4485.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And persons who were responsible for video surveillance also were interrogated, and their testimonies were included into conclusion of general prosecutor's office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4485.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4502.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to her cellmate, it's necessary to tell that she felt worse, and after this, she was transferred to medical unit of Kachanivskaya colony.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4502.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4548.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's also necessary to note that applicant's consent for transfer to Okruzhelyaznitsya hospital just in 5 o'clock in the evening, and she gives this consent to members of medical commission, and it took some time to organize her transfer from Kachanivskaya colony to Okruzhelyaznitsya hospital, and it was just time which was needed to organize everything, and it was done to avoid worsening of the applicant's health of state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4548.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4569.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's also necessary to point out that according to national legislation, testimonies of other person or photos which wasn't done by medical expert cannot serve as basic for conclusion in forensic examination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4569.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4595.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, although statement of ombudsman couldn't be taken as evidence of existing of some bruises on the applicant's body, and also it wasn't possible to understand character of this alleged bruises.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4595.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4624.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As concerning widow surveillance and self-injury, it's necessary to point out that widow surveillance is absent in bathroom which was in the applicant's cell, and according to expert conclusion, they were located in areas in which a person could make self-injuries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4624.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4637.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pain relief, it's also necessary to point out that applicant was, she never had pain relief medicines.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4637.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4649.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the time she was prescribed medicines against anti-inflammatory medicines.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4649.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4662.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were prescribed to the applicant, and she was provided with all necessary medicaments according to her sickness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4662.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4671.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So all the statements are not true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4671.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4688.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to privileges allegedly submitted to the applicant, according to national legislation, any person who is in custody can receive parcels from his relative or friends, and the number of such parcels are not limited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4688.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4702.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if someone's relatives or friends can make those parcels, person can receive this, and it's not some privileges to the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4702.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4711.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's also necessary to point out that there was no difference in conclusion of German and Ukrainian doctors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4711.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4724.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were just some misunderstandings in terms, since German doctors use term rupture, while Ukrainian doctors use protrusions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4724.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4749.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both these terms mean almost the same, and the fact that they were on the same opinion as to applicant's state of health is confirmed by the fact that medical treatment was appointed almost the same by German doctors and by Ukrainian doctors, and it's not possible if they were different opinion as to her state of health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4749.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4758.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if I'm right, the last question is concerning video surveillance and her possibility to claim this video surveillance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4758.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4770.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Code of Administrative Jurisdiction, any person can lodge claim on any action or inactivity of state authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4770.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4793.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for this reason, applicant can challenge video surveillance, and any state authority should act in manner prescribed in law and can take just action or decision which are necessary for its functioning and to execute its obligation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4793.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4807.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if applicant would be able to prove that it was not necessary, it couldn't be taken as argument, and such activity could be found illegal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4807.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4808.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4814.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4818.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mr Kulchytskyy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4818.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4821.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call now Ms Telychenko, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4821.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4823.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Oh, Mr Vlasenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4823.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4824.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yeah, thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4824.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4824.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You want to respond to the question?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4822.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4823.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yeah, thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4823.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4828.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You you you want to respond to the question? I will start to respond to some questions and Mrs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4828.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4830.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sulejanka will add a little bit to another questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4831.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4833.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. So, Mr. Vlasenko, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4834.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4835.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4835.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4848.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, I should say thank you to the representative of the state who said absolutely directly and strictly that according to Ukrainian law, disrespect to the court is not the basis for the person to be detained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4848.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4849.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4849.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4859.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there is no case in Ukrainian history that the person was detained because of disrespect to the court, because that is illegal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4859.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4862.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is not according to the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4862.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4870.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, I should tell the court about the situation which had happened on the April 20th, because I was the participant of that event.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4870.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4876.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I personally saw the bruises on Mrs. Timoshenko's body.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4876.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4879.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I am her defense lawyer in several criminal cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4879.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4887.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should just correct a little bit the court, because Mrs. Timoshenko just firstly said about that bruises</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4887.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4893.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>not on the 24th of April, but on the 23rd of April.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4893.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4898.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was Monday, as far as I remember, because the 20th, that was Friday.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4898.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4900.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I saw Mrs. Timoshenko in her jail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4900.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4903.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have the meeting with her as her defense lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4903.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4909.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I was with her in the meeting room until 3 PM, because there was announcement in the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4909.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4911.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I leave to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4911.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4915.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we never discussed at that moment with Mrs. Timoshenko</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4915.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4919.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>any her transference to any hospitals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4919.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4927.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So on Friday at 3 PM, she was not informed that she would be transferred to any hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4927.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4939.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet we expect at that moment the conclusion of the German doctors whether the Kharkiv Railway Clinic will be satisfactory for the treatment of Mrs. Timoshenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4939.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4954.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And when I leave the Kachanovskaya colony, I received a copy of that report in which it was strictly said that Kharkiv Railway Clinic will not provide an effective treatment to Mrs. Timoshenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4954.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4963.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's why when I have heard on TV on Saturday that Mrs. Timoshenko was transferred to the colony,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4963.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4966.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I was shocked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4966.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4969.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because I saw my client just half a day ago.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4969.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4971.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She's telling me nothing about any transference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4971.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4978.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I saw the report of the German doctors which said that that clinic is not satisfactory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4978.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4982.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I've heard that Mrs. Timoshenko was transferred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4982.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4986.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On Monday morning, I tried to reach my client.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4986.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4989.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wasn't allowed to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4989.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4993.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I asked the administration with the penitentiary system why.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4993.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4998.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They said, we have the cleaning day in the jail, the sanitary day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4998.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5000.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were cleaning the jail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5000.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5004.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's why they didn't allow me, as the defense lawyer of Mrs. Timoshenko,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5004.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5006.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to visit my client.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5006.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5010.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same situation occurred on the next day, on the 24th.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5010.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5023.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only because I am the member of the parliament and the parliamentary fraction of the bloc of Yulia Timoshenko made a political demarche in the Ukrainian parliament, I was allowed to visit Mrs. Timoshenko on the second part of the day,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5023.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5027.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the 24th of April, Tuesday.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5027.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5030.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When I reached Mrs. Timoshenko, I saw her lying</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5030.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5042.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the special bed, because our meeting room with the defense lawyers is equipped with a special medical bed in which Mrs. Timoshenko is lying every time</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5042.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5043.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>when I am meeting her.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5043.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5047.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And she showed me that bruises.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5047.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5055.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of the honorable judges asked about the version of the prosecutor's office that they were caused by herself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5055.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5059.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't know how I could cause that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5059.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5062.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That couldn't be done.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5062.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5063.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That couldn't be done.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5063.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5068.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were three video cameras on the way from the cell of Mrs. Timoshenko to the way</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5068.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5071.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>where the ambulance car stood.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5071.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5073.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We received no tapes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5073.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5076.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No tapes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5076.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5079.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They said, yeah, this is a video surveillance, but we are not recording.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5079.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5081.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are just supervising.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5081.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5082.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What for?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5082.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5084.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't know.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5084.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5086.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't know.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5086.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5094.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The honorable judge asked the question why she didn't say at the moment that she was injured.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5094.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5108.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, imagine the lady, which was the prime minister, which was severely beaten by two big guys in the night, crying all over the colony, help me, help me.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5108.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5109.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And no one helped.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5109.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5114.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And her neighbor lady was transferred from the cell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5114.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5118.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just not to hear what, not to see what is going on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5118.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5123.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With the only purpose, not to see what will be going on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5123.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5125.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was really shocked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5125.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5131.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first thing that she did, she asked to see her defense lawyers, any one of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5131.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5134.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was not provided.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5134.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5139.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was tried to show that bruises to the medical personnel of the Kharkiv Railway Clinic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5139.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5142.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They say, we don't want to deal with that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5142.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5144.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't want to deal with that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5144.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5146.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that was the answer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5146.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5150.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Timoshenko was transferred back</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5150.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5159.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because one of the ladies present here, the first vice deputy minister of health, said that the hospital, that's not the hotel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5159.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5167.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we'll throw you back to the prison, even giving you no treatment at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5167.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5168.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We'll throw you back.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5168.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5177.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After that, in the midday of Sunday, Mrs. Timoshenko was transferred back.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5177.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5184.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in the beginning of Monday, she wrote the request in written to the prosecutor's office of Kharkiv region.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5184.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5193.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same moment, she showed her bruises because she understood, she was informed that her defense lawyers will not be allowed to visit her.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5193.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5199.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that same moment, she wrote the request, as I've told you, to the Kharkiv Oblast prosecutor's office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5199.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5202.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also, she informed the medical personnel of the jail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5202.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5208.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they fixed all that bruises at the same moment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5208.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5212.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You ask why there was no blood test.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5212.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5228.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She made several requests for the blood test done by the independent doctor, not by that lady who said that the hospital is not the hotel, but by the independent doctor whom she trusts, whom Mrs. Timoshenko trusts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5231.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5236.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was also the question of trust, why there was no trust by Mrs. Timoshenko</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5236.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5237.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the state doctors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5237.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5248.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All these state doctors, since the beginning of the trial, since the beginning of the detention, were giving the public statement that Mrs. Timoshenko is healthy,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5248.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5250.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Timoshenko is simulating, Mrs. Timoshenko</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5250.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5253.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is manipulating with her health conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5253.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5257.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When Mrs. Timoshenko had the severe problems</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5257.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5268.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with her back, which was detected by the German doctors and reflected in the report of the German doctors, Mrs. Timoshenko asked the state doctors to help.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5268.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5271.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They say, no, we will not do that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5271.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5272.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We'll give you the painkillers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5272.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5273.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please eat that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5273.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5274.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5274.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5276.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She asked for the walking aids.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5276.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5282.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that lady who is sitting here, the first vice deputy minister of health, Mrs. Mysenko, she said,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5282.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5284.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>no, you don't need the walking aids.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5284.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5289.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You need to make much more physical trainings, and that will be your treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5289.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5291.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She did it in written.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5291.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5294.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was not oral.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5294.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5301.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But every day, these state doctors were giving the official statement that Mrs. Timoshenko is healthy enough</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5301.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5306.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to participate in the interrogation and investigation activity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5306.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5313.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on the day-to-day basis, the investigators of SBU were questioning Mrs. Timoshenko,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5313.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5330.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>were just giving her the files to revise, or they were making another investigation activity all day long for three, four, and five hours, with Mrs. Timoshenko lying in the bed, in the cell,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5330.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5335.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>even not in the special room for the investigation activity, in the cell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5335.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5347.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, there was also the question whether there were some extras for Mrs. Timoshenko, extra rides</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5347.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5348.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>like additional parcels.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5348.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5357.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also am very thankful to the representative of the state who said that according to the law, any imprisoned person have the unlimited right to receive the parcels.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5357.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5359.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Mrs. Timoshenko used that right</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5359.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5370.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because she never used the food and the meal from the CISO or from Kachanovska Colony because she is really afraid for her life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5370.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5379.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And because of the issue of security, she never used water and meals from that institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5379.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5383.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was also a question why Mrs. Timoshenko</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5383.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5389.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>didn't accept the participation of the doctor she trusts in her examination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5389.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5391.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should explain it to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5391.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5392.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was a very similar situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5392.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5396.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Timoshenko wrote the request</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5396.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5399.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for the independent doctor to visit her and to examine her.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5399.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5401.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was not allowed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5401.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5404.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That doctor was included in so-called commission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5404.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5410.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in that commission, there were some, maybe five or maybe seven, another state doctors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5410.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5412.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that doctor, whom Mrs. Timoshenko trusts,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5412.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5415.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>he was one of the members of that commission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5415.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5417.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And when Mrs. Timoshenko said, please,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5417.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5425.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I want that doctor to examine me, the commission said, no, only the whole commission will examine you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5425.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5427.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that's why Mrs. Timoshenko said, sorry,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5427.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5429.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>but that's violation of my rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5429.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5436.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Ukrainian law, as any citizen, even in prison, I have the right to choose my doctor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5436.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5438.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm choosing that guy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5438.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5440.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But he was not allowed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5440.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5446.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, I should stress that during the hearings in Pechersk District Court, the defense of Mrs. Timoshenko</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5446.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5460.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>presented to the judge Kireev more than 30 motions for the independent blood test and for independent medical examination of Mrs. Timoshenko.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5460.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5464.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of them were rejected with no grounds, all of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5473.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5475.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as I remember, that's all questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5475.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5477.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think Mrs. Timoshenko will add something.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5477.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5493.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would add only about the fact that applicants turned to the administrative court in Ukraine with her claim against the surveillance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5493.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5516.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But because we believe that there is a political will and political pressure under any court in Ukraine in a case where Timoshenko or anyone else from the oppositional government or Timoshenko government members involved, then there is no justice available in Ukraine from that point of view.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5516.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5529.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that's probably the reason why the administrative court of Ukraine did not scrutinize the case properly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5529.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5530.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for the attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5530.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5531.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'd like to thank you all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5534.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5545.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. We have now come to the end of the hearing. I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5545.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5554.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits. The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5554.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5562.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery. I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
