<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>5167110_04092012</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>12.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>13.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>64.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>86.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and the merits in the cases of Ewaida versus the United Kingdom, Chaplin versus the United Kingdom, Ladele versus the United Kingdom, and McFarlane versus the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>86.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>95.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cases were lodged with the court under Article 34 of the Convention by Ms. Ewaida</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>95.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>100.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on 10th of August, 2010, Ms. Chaplin on 29th September,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>100.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>105.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>2010, Ms. Ladele on 3rd September, 2010,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>105.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>110.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. McFarlane on 24th June, 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>110.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>114.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are all British nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>114.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>123.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were allocated to the fourth section of the court pursuant to Rule 52.1 of the Rules of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>123.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>130.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All applications were communicated to the government on 12th April, 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>130.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>138.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The governments are represented by their agent, Ms. Sornarajah,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>138.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>144.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Mr. Eadie, counsel, and Mr. Squires, counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>144.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>150.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and by Ms. Lehrer, Mr. Leslie, and Mr. Ford, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>150.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>155.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Eweida is represented by Mr. James Dingemans, counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>155.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>161.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Mr. Ellis, counsel, and Ms. Moore, counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>161.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>165.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and by Mr. Gregor Puppinck, advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>165.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>170.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Ladele is represented by Ms. Rose, counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>170.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>176.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Mr. Jaffey, counsel, and Mr. McCrudden, counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>176.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>180.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and by Mr. Jones and Mr. Webster, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>180.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>183.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Chaplin and Mr. McFarlane are represented</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>183.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>188.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by Mr. Diamond, counsel, assisted by Mr. Coleman,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>188.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>195.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>counsel, Mr. Hmelik, counsel, and Ms. Andrea Williams,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>195.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>204.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. Pasha and Mr. Marsh, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>204.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>208.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants, Ms. Chaplin, Ms. Ewaida, and Mr. McFarlane</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>208.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>211.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>are also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>211.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>216.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>216.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>227.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representatives of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>227.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>231.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Eadie for the government will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>231.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>236.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mr. Dingemans, Ms. Rose, and Mr. Diamond</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>236.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>239.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>will speak for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>239.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>256.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both parties will have 45 minutes, which means that the representatives of the applicants will have 15 minutes each to this first presentation before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>256.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>258.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Eadie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>260.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>279.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr President, members of the court, in a free and democratic society, everyone has the right to express and to manifest their beliefs, including to display religious symbols or to live out their beliefs on family values motivated by the teachings of faith.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>279.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>284.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But these are not absolute rights, or rights without limits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>284.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>293.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Convention is, as ever, sensitive to the rights and interests of others, including the general interests of the community.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>293.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>306.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And where those interests are in play, as in these cases, balances need to be struck so as to ensure that proper respect is accorded to the variety of interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>306.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>317.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Precisely where and how those balances are struck are for each contracting party to assess, according to its particular local history, culture and conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>317.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>321.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A wide margin is accordingly to be afforded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>321.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>330.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Government submits that a fair and compatible balance is struck by domestic law, and was struck in these cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>330.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>347.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These four linked cases, at their core, raise questions about the rights and the limits to the rights of employees to force their employers to alter employment conditions so as to accommodate the employees' religious practices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>347.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>352.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My submission will be that the Court's jurisprudence is clear and consistent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>352.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>354.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is to this effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>354.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>360.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Convention protects individuals' rights to manifest their religion outside their professional sphere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>360.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>369.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, that does not mean that in the context of his or her employment, an individual can insist on being able to manifest their beliefs in any way they choose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>369.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>373.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Other rights, other interests are in play and are to be respected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>373.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>382.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This notion is reflected in the case law, first at the level of determining whether there has been an interference with Article 9 rights at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>382.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>394.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also reflected, even if there has been an interference, in the requirement that any such interference, as a result of employment conditions, must have a reasonable and objective justification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>394.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>408.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, in cases involving the rights and obligations of private employers and employees, domestic law must, and I will submit plainly does, enable that issue to be considered with care by the domestic courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>408.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>416.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In each of the four applications before you, the domestic courts determined that the conduct of the employers was justifiable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>416.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>420.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will examine in a moment the key facts that led them to that conclusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>420.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>436.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My submission to this Court is that there is no basis for interfering with that conclusion, particularly given the subsidiary role of the Court in an area in which local needs and conditions are likely to be critical and a wide margin of appreciation appropriate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>436.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>443.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With that introduction, I start with the issue of whether or not Article 9 was engaged or interfered with.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>443.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>447.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This has two aspects in the present context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>447.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>453.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, Article 9 primarily protects personal beliefs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>453.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>459.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Protection is also accorded to religious practice, as enumerated in that article.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>459.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>465.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it is not every act or form of behaviour that falls within the protective sphere of Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>465.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>475.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Acts are protected only if they are indeed a practice, and moreover if the practice is generally recognised as such by the religion concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>475.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>489.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The description from the Court's constant jurisprudence refers to acts of worship or devotion which are aspects of the practice of a religion or belief in a generally recognised form.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>489.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>502.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's a quote from the commission case in Cey and the UK, which has been consistently repeated by the Court in Pichon, in Kalach, in Kuznetskov and Russia, to name but a few.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>502.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>507.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This limit on the scope of the protection of Article 9 has a consequence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>507.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>528.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was put in this way in Kalach at paragraph 27, that because Article 9 does not protect every act motivated or inspired by a religion or belief, in exercising his freedom to manifest his religion, an individual may need to take his specific situation into account.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>528.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>536.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That wording is also repeated by the Grand Chamber in Sahin and Turkey at paragraph 105.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>536.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>540.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These principles shaped the Court's judgement in Pichon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>540.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>542.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were pharmacists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>542.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>549.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had a sincere religious belief that precluded them from dispensing contraceptives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>549.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>557.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court held that their prosecution for refusing to sell contraceptives did not breach Article 9, and stated as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>557.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>582.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As long as the sale of contraceptives is legal and occurs on medical prescription, nowhere other than in a pharmacy, the applicants cannot give precedence to their religious belief and impose them on others as justification for their refusal to sell such a product, since they can manifest those beliefs in many ways outside the professional sphere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>582.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>586.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How, then, does this first set of principles apply in these cases?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>586.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>592.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms Liddell's and Mr Macfarlane's cases have very close parallels with Pichon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>592.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>597.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the reasoning in the passage just quoted applies equally to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>597.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>615.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the context of an employer-employee relationship, the principles articulated in Pichon mean that employers cannot be forced to accommodate the religious beliefs of employees who do not wish to provide services to the public or a section of the public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>615.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>624.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So far as Ms Liddell is concerned, it is only possible to enter civil partnerships through a civil partnership registrar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>624.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>638.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms Liddell cannot, to apply the logic and reasoning in Pichon, cannot give precedence to her religious views in her professional sphere as a justification for her refusal to register same-sex partnerships.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>638.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>658.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr Macfarlane, too, could manifest his religious beliefs as he chose outside the professional sphere and was not entitled to give precedence to his religious views and, in effect, force his employer to give precedence to those views in deciding to whom he would provide couples' counselling.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>658.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>666.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms O'Wader and Mrs Chaplin's cases concern the wearing of a visible cross or crucifix at work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>666.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>683.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should make it quite clear that the government does not doubt that the applicant's motivation to wear a visible cross or crucifix at work was a genuine personal expression of their faith, nor is there any question of the importance of the cross as a Christian symbol.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>683.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>692.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, as the constant jurisprudence of the Court makes clear, those are not the determinative questions under Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>692.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>696.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That jurisprudence draws an important distinction between types of act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>696.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>704.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not, as I indicated, every act motivated or inspired by a religion or a belief that falls within Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>704.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>714.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to do so, the act must be, and I quote, an aspect of the practice of a religion or belief in a generally recognised form.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>714.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>715.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is that so here?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>715.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>718.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the evidence, it is not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>718.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>733.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Employment Tribunal recorded that it was common ground that Ms O'Wader wished to wear the cross visibly, and I quote, as a matter of personal expression of faith, and not in response to a scriptural command.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>733.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>750.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court of Appeal noted that Ms O'Wader had, and I quote, an entirely personal objection to British Airways' uniform policy, neither arising from any doctrine of her faith, nor interfering with her observance of it, and never raised by any other employee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>750.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>761.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's paragraph 34 of their judgment, and we also refer the Court to paragraph 37 of that judgment, which is to similar effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>761.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>768.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Similarly, Mrs Chaplin regarded the crucifix she wore as, quote, a personal statement of faith.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>768.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>783.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the evidence was that they chose to wear the cross visibly as an expression of personal commitment, inspired by their religion, and not because they were following a scriptural command or teaching.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>783.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>790.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is a second aspect to the engagement or interference issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>790.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>813.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the House of Lords in the Begum case, at paragraph 23, Lord Bingham set out this court's jurisprudence, applicable where individuals voluntarily accept an employment or role that they then find does not accommodate their religious practices, but where there are other means open to them to observe their religion without undue hardship or inconvenience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>813.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>821.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That jurisprudence establishes that in such circumstances, there is no interference with Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>821.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>828.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lord Bingham described the jurisprudence as a coherent and remarkably consistent body of authority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>828.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>833.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Paragraph 24, it is submitted that he was right on both counts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>833.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>840.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A clear dividing line separating interference cases from no interference cases emerges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>840.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>852.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has consistently held that if an employer requires or prohibits conduct while at work, that individual employees consider inconsistent with their religious beliefs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>852.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>860.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no interference with Article 9 where they can obtain alternative employment in which they can practice their religion as they wish.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>860.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>872.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That approach reflects the respect that is to be accorded to, but also the need to strike fair balances between, the range of interests in play in this area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>872.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>884.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In no case has the court held that employees who have the option of resigning and obtaining alternative employment can require their religious practices to be accommodated by their employer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>884.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>893.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the same applies to individuals who access services, in particular education, provided by a public institution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>893.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>906.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, as long as someone is not substantially excluded from working or accessing services because of their religious belief or practice, there is no interference with Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>906.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>922.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cases in which an interference with Article 9 has been assumed or established are those in which the applicants had no alternative by which they could access public services, or in some cases avoid arrest, if they wish to continue to practice their religion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>922.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>934.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In those cases, the applicants had no choice of attending a different institution or obtaining work with a different employer in order to avoid a conflict with their religious beliefs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>934.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>943.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See the Kokkinakis case, Sahin and Turkey, Ahmet, Aslan and Turkey, Dogru and France, and Bayatayan and Armenia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>943.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>946.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This jurisprudence has been applied in the UK.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>946.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>958.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Begum, for example, the House of Lords considered an Article 9 claim brought by a girl not permitted to attend school wearing a jilbab, a long coat-like garment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>958.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>964.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court accepted that wearing a jilbab was a manifestation of the claimant's strict Muslim faith.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>964.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>978.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Faithfully following the court's jurisprudence, however, the House of Lords held that as there were alternative schools which the claimant could attend, at which she would be able to wear the jilbab, there was no interference with her Article 9 rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>978.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>985.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The core principle, it is submitted accurately, was summarised by Lord Scott at paragraph 87.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>985.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1011.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court's jurisprudence, he said, and I quote, demonstrates the principle that a rule of a particular public institution that requires or prohibits certain behaviour on the part of those who avail themselves of its services does not constitute an infringement of the right of an individual to manifest his or her religion, merely because the ruling question does not conform to the religious beliefs of that individual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1011.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1028.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in particular, this is so where the individual has a choice whether or not to avail himself or herself of the services of that institution, and where other public institutions offering similar services and whose rules do not include the objectionable ruling question are available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1028.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1032.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I said that Lord Bingham was correct on both counts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1032.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1040.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government submits that the court's jurisprudence is not merely consistent, but also coherent and correct in principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1040.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1043.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It strikes the right balance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1043.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1051.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In a pluralist society, individuals share a wide range of religions and beliefs, entitled to equal respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1051.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1057.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Individuals should be free to manifest their religion or belief unless a restriction can be justified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1057.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1074.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That does not mean, however, that states should require employers to recognise an enforceable right of employees to practise their religion or beliefs at work, irrespective of whether that clashes with the dress or other requirements of the employer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1074.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1083.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is both appropriate and necessary in assessing interference to have regard to the fact that employees themselves may have other options.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1083.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1093.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Convention does not allow employees simply to insist on their terms of employment being changed to accommodate their religion or belief.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1093.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1097.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How does this second set of principles apply in these cases?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1097.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1114.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As with the pharmacists in Pichon, the clergymen in Aix, the employees in Ahmed and Stedman, and the schoolgirl in Bagan, all the applicants were able to, quote, Pichon, to manifest their religious beliefs in many ways outside the professional sphere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1114.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1124.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court's jurisprudence makes clear that employees are free to resign if they consider that the requirements of their employment are incompatible with their religious beliefs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1124.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1130.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That, as the Commission held in Aix and Continent, guarantees freedom of religion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1130.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1141.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, in Mr Wader and Mrs Chapton's cases, the employees went further and were concerned to try to find ways to accommodate their beliefs even within the employment structure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1141.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1153.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs Wader and Mrs Chapton were not, as were the applicants in Ahmed, Continent and Stedman, faced with the choice of either acting contrary to their religion or being dismissed from their employment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1153.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1169.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both were told that they could wear the cross or crucifix, provided it was covered, when dealing with customers or patients, as indeed Mr Wader had in fact done from 1999 until 2006 without demur.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1169.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1180.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs Chapton was even offered the option of wearing the crucifix visibly by securing it to her identity badge, except when undertaking close clinical duties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1180.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1189.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But both were offered alternative employment by their employers on the same pay where they would be able to wear a visible cross in the manner they wish.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1189.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1201.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For all these reasons, my primary submission is that there has been no interference in any of these cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1201.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1206.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither Mrs Wader nor Mr Macfarlane were employed by public bodies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1206.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1222.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They must therefore show that Article 9, taken alone or in conjunction with Article 14, imposed positive obligations on the United Kingdom to ensure that their employers accommodated their religious practices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1222.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1231.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The possibility of positive obligations being imposed by Article 9, stroke 14, has been countenanced only in a very few cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1231.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1235.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their hallmark is extremity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1235.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1239.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Gildani Congregation of Jehovah's Witnesses in Georgia is an example.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1239.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1244.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were Jehovah's Witnesses attacked during a meeting of their congregation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1244.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1264.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were then, to quote from the judgment, court's judgment at 133, confronted with total indifference and a failure to act on the part of the authorities who, on account of the applicant's adherence to a religious community perceived as a threat to Christian orthodoxy, took no action in respect of their complaints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1264.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1272.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court found, unsurprisingly perhaps, that there had been a breach of Article 9 through their inactivity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1272.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1292.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The relevant authorities failed in their duty to take the necessary measures to ensure that the group of orthodox extremists tolerated the existence of the applicant's religious community and enabled them to exercise freely their rights to freedom of religion, said the court at paragraph 134.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1292.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1296.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The present cases are nothing like Gildani.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1296.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1299.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A relates termination of Mr. McFarland's employment</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1299.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1317.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and British Airways' refusal to permit Miss Iwida to wear a visible cross at work for a period of a few months did not prevent either of them from exercising their freedom to hold religious beliefs or practicing their religion in any way they chose outside their employment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1317.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1329.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has never recognized positive obligations on the state pursuant to Article 9 to intervene in such circumstances and we submit should not do so in the present cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1329.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1338.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, it is plain that the UK has satisfied any positive obligation that might arise under Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1338.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1345.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The domestic law we submit is more than sufficient to comply with any such positive obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1345.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1370.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the material time, the UK had in place the Employment Equality Brackets Religion or Belief Regulations 2003, which were implemented to comply with the UK's obligations regarding religion or belief pursuant to Council Directive 2078 EC of November 2000, establishing a general framework for equal treatment in employment and occupation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1370.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1379.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The 2003 regulations have now been replaced with substantially similar provisions by the Equality Act 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1379.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1386.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The 2003 regulations rendered it unlawful to discriminate in employment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1386.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1415.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regulation 3 defined discrimination to include direct religious discrimination, that is treating an employee less favorably on grounds of his or her religion or belief, and indirect religious discrimination, that is applying a provision, criterion or practice that places a person or persons of the same religion as the employee at a particular disadvantage and which the employer cannot show was a proportionate means of achieving a legitimate aim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1415.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1425.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both Mr Wader and Mr McFarlane brought proceedings in the Employment Tribunal for breach of those 2003 regulations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1425.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1440.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The remainder of my submissions on Article 9 are going to focus on the necessity and proportionality issues, assuming for that purpose, contrary to the primary case we advance, an interference in each case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1440.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1453.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I will indicate shortly, these submissions apply equally to necessity and proportionality when considered in conjunction with Article 14 or pursuant to Article 9 alone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1453.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1457.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The approach in principle at this stage is well established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1457.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1474.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I simply emphasize that the Court has specifically recognized the difficulty of the balance to be struck in democratic societies between individuals' rights to manifest their religious beliefs and the rights of others who are affected by that manifestation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1474.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1501.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Sahin, for example, the Grand Chamber recognized at paragraph 106 that, and I quote, in democratic societies in which several religions coexist within one and the same population, it may be necessary to place restrictions on freedom to manifest one's religion or belief in order to reconcile the interests of the various groups and ensure that everyone's beliefs are respected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1501.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1514.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both permitting and restricting manifestations of religious belief, of course, communicate important values for a society and have a significant symbolic as well as practical impact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1514.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1533.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How that impact is assessed and how the competing values are weighed against one another are matters on which, as I said at the outset, national authorities can legitimately and do legitimately take different positions and on which local concerns are likely to be critical.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1533.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1543.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But for that reason, as the Grand Chamber noted at paragraph 109 in Sahin, a particularly wide margin is therefore to be afforded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1543.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1546.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I deal first with Miss O'Wader.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1546.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1550.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Her employer, British Airways, was a private entity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1550.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1556.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, even if the state's positive obligations were engaged, they were satisfied for the reasons I've just set out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1556.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1564.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it's submitted if necessary that any interference with her rights would be justified on the facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1564.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1570.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Her claim pursuant to the 2003 regulations was dismissed by the Employment Tribunal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1570.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1575.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Her appeals to the Employment Appeal Tribunal and the Court of Appeal were unsuccessful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1575.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1596.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court of Appeal concluded that even if BA's uniform policy had placed Christians at a particular disadvantage, which it didn't find, the policy would nonetheless have been a proportionate means of achieving a legitimate aim, see paragraphs 30 to 39 of the Court of Appeal's judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1596.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1601.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chronology and the Court of Appeal's analysis were in summary as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1601.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1607.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An airline having a uniform code for its check-in staff was legitimate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1607.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1626.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>BA was entitled to conclude that a uniform played an important role in maintaining a professional image and strengthening recognition of the company brand, and it had a contractual right to insist on its employees who dealt with members of the public to insist that they wore a uniform.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1626.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1634.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was a matter for BA that its choice of women's uniform was a blouse worn with a cravat and without visible necklaces.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1634.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1647.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The rule that as part of the uniform visible items around the neck were not permitted had caused no known problem for Christians, including for two years for Miss Iweda herself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1647.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1653.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The uniform was worn by approximately 30,000 staff who had contact with the public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1653.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1670.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As already noted, Miss Iweda accepted in terms that her objection to BA's dress code was, quote, entirely personal and did not arise, as it was put by the Court of Appeal, from any doctrine of her faith, nor interfering with her observance of it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1670.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1684.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Miss Iweda raised an objection to the uniform code in 2006, as the Court of Appeal found in paragraph 34, not, as I said, by seeking a revision of the code, but by reporting to work twice in breach of it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1685.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1689.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She then lodged a formal grievance in June 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1689.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1696.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Without waiting for the grievance to be resolved, she again breached the code and on this occasion was sent home.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1696.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1715.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On previous occasions, when other employees had raised concerns about BA's uniform code on religious grounds, BA had viewed the matter, and again to quote from the Court of Appeal, paragraph 35, through the perspective of diversity and sought to accommodate staff diversity where appropriate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1715.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1728.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Other than Miss Iweda, every other individual who had requested accommodation of their religious circumstances had observed the existing policy until a change was authorised.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1728.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1731.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>BA considered Miss Iweda's objection to the uniform.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1731.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1740.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While the matter was being resolved, BA offered Miss Iweda work on the same pay, but involving no public contact at which she could wear a visible cross.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1740.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1746.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She refused and chose instead to stay at home and claim her pay as compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1746.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1756.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2006 November, BA announced a review of its policy on the wearing of religious symbols and consulted staff members and union representatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1756.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1762.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then in January 2007, BA, having considered the matter carefully, announced a new uniform policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1762.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1769.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With effect from February 2007, it permitted the visible wearing of religious and charity symbols.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1769.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1775.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Certain symbols such as the cross and the Star of David were given immediate authorisation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1775.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1788.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Court of Appeal observed, it is difficult to see how a previously unobjectionable uniform policy could become disproportionate as soon as Miss Iweda raised a complaint about it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1788.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1795.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once she raised the issue, it was then conscientiously addressed by her employer and the policy was changed within a matter of months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1795.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1812.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court of Appeal concluded that both during the years that the policy operated without objection and while it was being reconsidered following Miss Iweda's complaint, that the uniform policy constituted a proportionate means of achieving a legitimate aim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1812.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1824.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was a conclusion we submit that the Court of Appeal was entitled to reach and in her application to this court, Miss Iweda does not identify any error in its reasoning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1824.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1828.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court of Appeal carefully considered whether BA had acted proportionately.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1828.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1832.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It did so in relation to the 2003 regulations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1832.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1836.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, its conclusion applies equally to Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1836.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1839.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pursuant to Article 9.2, as the Court well knows,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1839.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1844.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the right to freedom of religion may be limited to protect the rights of others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1844.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1851.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That includes the contractual right of an employer to require employees to wear a prescribed uniform.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1851.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1865.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Where a complaint is made on religious grounds about a uniform policy previously found to be unobjectionable, the employer is entitled to consider carefully the employee's objection before making alterations to that policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1865.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1890.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When, as with BA in this case, the employer does so conscientiously and in a reasonable time and then agrees to change the uniform to accommodate the employee's request, and especially where the employer offers the affected employee alternative work in the interim, the employer has acted, we submit, entirely appropriately, and there was no breach of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1890.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1905.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Mrs Chaplin's case, to turn to that, the uniform policy to which she objected was the prohibition on all wearing of necklaces by medical staff dealing with patients, in her case, aged patients.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1905.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1915.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason for the policy was, as the Employment Tribunal decision at paragraph 12 found, to reduce the risk of injury when handling patients.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1915.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1928.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The concern of her employer, the Royal Devon and Exeter NHS Foundation Trust, was that a visible and hence accessible necklace might be seized and pulled by a disturbed patient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1928.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1939.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All nurses who were engaged in direct patient care, either of a clinical or personal nature, were thus prohibited from wearing a visible necklace as well as other jewellery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1939.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1956.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if the Trust's uniform policy had placed Christians at a particular disadvantage, again, which it did not find, the Tribunal accepted that the uniform policy would nonetheless have been a proportionate means of achieving a legitimate aim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1956.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1970.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Tribunal accepted that the aim of the uniform policy in protecting the health and safety of staff and patients was a legitimate aim, and that it pursued that aim in a proportionate manner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1970.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1991.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Tribunal also noted that the Trust offered to redeploy Mrs Chaplin to non-clinical duties on the same pay, paragraph 22 of their decision, and that it made other suggestions designed to enable her to wear the crucifix, such as attaching it to her identity badge or wearing a necklace under her clothes, in a way that could not be grabbed by patients.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1991.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2004.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs Chaplin, in her application to this Court, does not suggest that the Trust's aims of reducing risks to health and safety were not legitimate, nor does she state that its policy was disproportionate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2004.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2012.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under those circumstances, it is, we respectfully submit, hard to see on what basis she contends that Article 9 was breached.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2012.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2035.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs Chaplin does assert that, quote, if Sikh or Muslim medical personnel were permitted to breach infection control for religious reasons, wearing of the hijab, Sikh kara bracelet, or Islamic modesty rules, there is a requirement of weighty reasons for banning Mrs Chaplin from wearing, as she put it, a small crucifix.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2035.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2039.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That submission is wrong on the facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2039.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2048.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sikh nurses were not permitted by the Trust to wear the kara bracelet or the kirpan, that's Employment Tribunal, paragraphs 15 and 26.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2048.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2055.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Trust did not permit Muslim staff to wear clothing that it regarded as a risk to health and safety.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2055.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2072.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the contrary, it prevented the wearing of a flowing hijab, paragraph 16 of their reasoning, and permitted only the wearing of, as it was put in the Employment Tribunal's judgment, close-fitting sports hijab akin to a balaclava helmet with no loose ends.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2072.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2083.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Trust was plainly entitled to prohibit all staff from wearing clothing or jewellery considered to be a risk to the health and safety of patients and staff.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2083.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2087.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It applied the policy consistently to all religious groups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2087.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2100.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Trust's policy was therefore rightly found to be proportionate and to pursue the legitimate aim of protecting staff and patient safety by the Employment Tribunal, whose decision was not appealed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2100.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2107.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is again no basis, we submit, for impugning that decision before this Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2107.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2116.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Liddeli McFarlane cases, or the Liddell McFarlane cases, are concerned with striking a fair balance between the rights and freedoms of different groups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2116.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2130.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the one hand are the rights of those who believe, whether or not motivated by religion, that homosexual acts are morally wrong, or that same-sex relationships should not be promoted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2130.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2144.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand are the rights of homosexuals to equal treatment, and the principle that those who provide services to the public should not be permitted to discriminate on grounds of sexual orientation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2144.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2162.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How that balance is to be struck, and the circumstances in which private beliefs should be required to give way to wider public concerns, is a matter on which different opinions may be held, attracting therefore a particularly wide margin of appreciation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2162.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2180.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms Liddell sincerely believes, as the Court put it at paragraph 7, that's the Court of Appeals judgment, she sincerely believes that, enabling same-sex unions to be formed was, contrary to God's instructions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2180.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2190.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr McFarlane sincerely believes that homosexual activity is sinful, and that he should do nothing which directly endorses it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2190.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2213.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their employers, respectively the London Borough of Islington, a public authority and, relate, a private body, were however committed to the provision of services on a non-discriminatory basis, and to ensuring that members of the public, regardless of their sexual orientation, are treated with dignity and have equal access to services.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2213.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2229.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There can, we submit, be little doubt that promoting equality and tackling discrimination on grounds of sexual orientation is a legitimate, indeed a weighty, aim for a public authority or a private employer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2229.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2238.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Discrimination affects individuals' sense of self-worth and the public perception of their value as members of the community.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2238.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2252.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court has now held on many occasions that particularly convincing and weighty reasons are necessary to justify subjecting individuals to differences in treatment on the grounds of their sexual orientation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2252.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2265.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is submitted by Ms Liddell that any interference with her Article 9 and 14 rights was not proportionate, as there were, as she put it, less severe and intrusive means available to Islington.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2265.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2276.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Islington could, it is said, have arranged its services so that other registrars, without Ms Liddell's beliefs, would officiate in civil partnerships.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2276.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2286.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also noted by her that other local authorities did not designate marriage registrars as civil partnership registrars if they had religious objections.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2286.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2293.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those submissions, with respect, do not deal with the aim that Islington was pursuing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2293.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2304.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In requiring Ms Liddell to register civil partnerships, Islington was not simply ensuring that it had sufficient registrars available to cover the borough.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2304.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2324.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It may well be that by rearranging its services, Islington could in practice have assigned same-sex couples to other registrars, or it could have decided, again on the same pragmatic basis, not to designate Ms Liddell as a civil partnership registrar because of her views on same-sex unions and required others to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2324.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2332.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Similarly, Mr Macfarlane could perhaps have been assigned only heterosexual couples to council.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2332.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2341.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But providing an efficient registrar and counselling service was not the legitimate aim that was and is at issue in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2341.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2360.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Islington and Relate's aim, as found by the Court of Appeal and the Employment Appeal Tribunal respectively, was to provide equal access to services irrespective of sexual orientation and thereby to communicate a clear commitment to non-discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2360.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2364.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is in itself a legitimate aim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2364.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2383.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Islington and Relate were entitled each to conclude that it would undermine its pursuit of that aim to make exceptions for employees as to the work they were required to perform because those employees did not wish to provide services to same-sex couples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2383.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2394.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Islington and Relate's approach also reflects the decision of the UK legislature as to how competing interests in this area are to be balanced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2394.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2406.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That legislation in effect, and subject to narrow exceptions, outlawed discrimination on grounds of sexual orientation, save in very limited circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2406.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2409.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The following legislation applied at the material time in Great Britain.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2409.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2415.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's now been replaced by the Equality Act 2010, but with essentially the same provisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2415.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2422.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The 2003 regulations prohibited discrimination on grounds of religion and belief in employment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2422.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2443.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Insofar as the applicants complained that Islington or Relate should have altered their policies to accommodate their religious beliefs and not required them, as it required all other employees, to offer services to members of the public irrespective of their sexual orientation, they were able to bring proceedings for indirect discrimination pursuant to Regulation 3.1b.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2443.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2454.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if the applicants were disadvantaged by those policies, however, it would not be unlawful to apply the policies if they constituted a proportionate means of achieving a legitimate aim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2454.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2458.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's Regulation 3.b. Roman III.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2458.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2463.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was thus a factual inquiry for the domestic courts to undertake.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2463.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2476.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Legislation was also put in place to prohibit discrimination on grounds of sexual orientation, in particular in the provision of services and the exercise of public functions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2476.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2488.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See for that purpose the Equality Act brackets sexual orientation regulations of 2007, referred to and analysed in particular in the Court of Appeals judgment in the Liddell case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2488.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2491.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pursuant to Regulation 4.1 of those regulations,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2491.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2502.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it was unlawful to discriminate on grounds of sexual orientation by refusing to provide goods, facilities or services that were otherwise made available to the public.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2502.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2506.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pursuant to Regulation 3.1, a person discriminates against another</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2506.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2514.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by treating them on grounds of their sexual orientation less favourably than others are or would be treated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2514.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2522.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were only limited exceptions which applied to organisations, the purpose of which is the practice or advancement of religion or belief.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2522.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2544.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such organisations were permitted to discriminate on grounds of sexual orientation, in restrictions on membership or in the provision of goods, facilities and services, provided that the restrictions were necessary to comply with the organisation's doctrine or to avoid conflict with strongly held religious convictions of a significant number of the religion's followers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2544.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2556.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Treating people less favourably on grounds of sexual orientation is thus prohibited unless some clear exception, such as that recognised by Regulation 14, applies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2556.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2581.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, it is submitted that the Court of Appeal at paragraph 73 in the Liddell case was correct to conclude that the legislature has decided that the requirements of a modern liberal democracy, such as the United Kingdom, include outlawing discrimination in the provision of goods, facilities and services on grounds of sexual orientation, subject only to very limited exceptions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2581.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2589.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is a balance that we submit a democratic society is entitled to take.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2589.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2592.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can deal with Article 14 much more shortly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2592.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2600.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My submission is that Article 14 adds nothing to the Article 9 analysis in context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2600.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2617.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is to be noted that the applicants in the present cases do not suggest that they were less favourably treated than other employees because they were Christians or that members of other faiths were treated more favourably, or insofar as such claims are made, they aren't sustainable on the facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2617.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2637.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not suggested that Ms O'Wader and Mrs Chaplin were not permitted to wear a visible cross because their employers had some particular animus towards Christians, or that explains, relates or is linked in the treatment of Mr Liddell and Mr Macfarlane.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2637.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2654.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's contention is that they should have been treated differently to other employees in that their employer's uniform policy or requirement that they provide services to all, regardless of sexual orientation, should have been waived or disapplied to accommodate their religious beliefs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2654.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2661.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is thus evident that that raises essentially the same issues as arise under Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2661.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2671.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this kind of case, the court has frequently in the past recognised that the reasoning under Article 9 will be equally applicable when that article is read with Article 14.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2671.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2687.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, for example, in Sahin, the Grand Chamber concluded that the applicant's rights protected by Article 9 had not been breached because the ban on wearing the headscarf in the educational institutions in Turkey pursued a legitimate aim and were proportionate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2687.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2703.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It noted at Para 165 that the reasons which led the court to conclude that there had been no violation of Article 9 incontestably also apply to the complaint under Article 14 taken individually or together with the aforementioned provision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2703.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2711.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Precisely the same approach was taken by the Grand Chamber in Jewish Liturgical Association, see Para 86.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2711.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2732.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If a decision to ban Islamic headscarves is a justified and proportionate interference with the rights of Muslim women to manifest their religious beliefs pursuant to Article 9, it cannot, we submit, constitute unjustified, disproportionate discrimination against Muslims pursuant to Article 14 read with Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2732.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2735.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That applies equally to the present cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2735.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2744.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The justification for the interference, if any, with Article 9 rights will apply equally to preclude a finding of unjustified discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2744.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2768.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, for example, if, for the reasons set out above, requiring Ms Liddell to conduct civil partnerships notwithstanding her Christian beliefs is justified and proportionate pursuant to Article 9, it will not constitute an unjustified failure to treat her as a Christian differently to others who do not share her beliefs so as to breach Article 14.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2768.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2776.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For all these reasons, we invite the court to find that there has been no violation of either Article 9 or Article 9 read with Article 14 in any of these cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2785.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2787.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2787.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2793.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I call Mr. James Dingemans for the first of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2794.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2801.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President and members of the court, in the case of Miss Oueda, we respectfully ask</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2801.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2807.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the court to do the following four things. First, to affirm the fundamental importance</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2807.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2814.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of religious rights, notably absent from the United Kingdom government's submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2814.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2829.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, to repudiate judicial doctrines which have been employed to undermine religious rights and which are not founded on the wording of the Convention. Thirdly, to find violations</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2829.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2837.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Article 9 on its own and Article 9 when read with Article 14. And finally, to award</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2837.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2843.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>just satisfaction. My learned friend has taken you to some facts. May I highlight some of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2843.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2851.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>them. Miss Oueda was a committed, practising, Anglo-Egyptian Christian who wished to wear</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2851.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2864.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>visibly a small cross on a chain around her neck at her place of work at British Airways as a personal expression of faith. Miss Oueda regarded wearing and displaying the cross</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2864.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2870.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as integral to her identity and being. And she's hardly the first Christian who has wanted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2870.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2877.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to wear the cross as a distinguishing feature of her faith. She was working alongside colleagues</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2877.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2892.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>who were able to wear religious symbols and attire, including the Sikh turban, the Sikh bracelet, the Muslim hijab, and the Jewish shawl cap. It was indisputable that wearing</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2892.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2900.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the cross visibly did not have any detrimental effect on Miss Oueda's ability to do her job.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2900.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2908.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>British Airways prevented Miss Oueda from wearing her cross. She was told it was jewellery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2908.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2926.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>British Airways said that an employee who wished to wear a religious item outside his or her uniform was only permitted to do so if British Airways accepted that it was a mandatory scriptural requirement. British Airways considered that that condition was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2926.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2941.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>fulfilled in the case of items such as the hijab, the turban, but not fulfilled in the case of the cross. Miss Oueda has never sought to contend that wearing a cross is a mandatory</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2941.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2947.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>scriptural requirement, but it was of great importance to her to be able to wear it visibly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2947.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2959.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And she found the requirement to conceal it, next to colleagues wearing their own religious symbols and attire, a great insult to her. We submit that it is not for British Airways</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2959.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2971.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>or the courts, then deciding on her claim for discrimination, to judge whether the religious symbol is mandatory or not. It's notorious that Islamic scholars disagree on whether</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2971.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2979.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>wearing a hijab is mandatory or not. Internal discussions and memoranda did not alter the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2979.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2985.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>situation. My learned friend has almost lost a year in submissions. It was May 2006 that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2985.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3005.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the issue first arised, and it was until the 3rd of February 2007 that British Airways changed their policy and Miss Oueda was permitted to come back to work and to start to be paid again. British Airways refused to compensate Miss Oueda for her loss of salary, pension</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3005.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3011.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and benefits during the period she was off work. And Miss Oueda says that they've continued</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3011.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3016.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to harass her since. She's never received any payment for the period of time that she</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3016.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3040.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was off work, and unless she succeeds in these proceedings, there will be nothing in the laws of the United Kingdom to stop British Airways from going back to its pre-existing uniform policy, permitting others to wear religious attire and symbols, and preventing Miss Oueda from wearing her cross. The importance of religious rights. Religious freedoms and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3040.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3046.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>rights guaranteed by Article 9 are some of the most important rights in the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3046.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3071.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That does not mean that they can trump or outrank other rights, but it does mean that they should not be relegated below other rights or undermined by judicial doctrines such as the doctrine of non-interference, especially in circumstances where such doctrines are not derived from the wording of the Convention. There is nothing in the wording of Article</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3071.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3083.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>9 which justifies the Government's approach that Article 9 stops the moment you cross the threshold of work. If 80% of our lives is spent working, what value is a right that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3083.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3093.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ceases the moment you cross the threshold of work? Did sexual orientation rights stop</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3093.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3098.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the moment that persons crossed the threshold of working for the armed forces? No. Was there</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3098.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3110.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>any difference in wording between the words of Article 8 and 9 which justifies drawing a distinction for work? No. Unless this Court declares and affirms and shows the value of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3110.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3117.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>religious rights, the worth of religious rights will continue to be diminished. Where is the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3117.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3125.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>pluralism indissociable from a modern democratic society in that? In our written cases we have</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3125.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3131.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>set out a number of authorities affirming the importance of religious rights. For reasons</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3131.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3136.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of time I won't go through them, but we do respectfully commend them to the Court. Those</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3136.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3150.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>are propositions that have to be confronted and in our submission are not confronted by the Government's approach. As Lord Nicholls said in Williamson and Secretary of State,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3150.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3163.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>without the right to express and practise one's belief, freedom of religion would be emasculated. And we submit that the following principles of general application under Article</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3163.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3170.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>9 can be discerned. First, that they have a primordial place in a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3170.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3182.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, that the pluralism indissociable from a democratic society depends on protecting these freedoms. And thirdly, that without the right to express and practise one's beliefs,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3182.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3190.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>freedom of religion would be an emasculated right. We also submit that Article 9 contains</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3190.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3197.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>within it a positive obligation. That's not new jurisprudence. In Otto Preminger and Austria</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3197.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3209.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Court said, the manner in which religious beliefs and doctrines are opposed or denied is a matter which may engage the responsibility of the State. In Jzef Kossuth and Poland</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3209.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3232.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Court said that whether the case is analysed in terms of a positive duty on the State to take reasonable and appropriate measures to secure the applicant's rights, or in terms of an interference by a public authority to be justified, the applicable principles are broadly similar. And there's nothing in Gildani and Georgia to justify the narrow approach</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3232.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3240.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>contended for by my learned friend. We therefore ask you to repudiate the doctrine of non-interference</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3240.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3246.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which has been analysed by the courts in the United Kingdom. In Williamson in the Court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3246.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3257.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Appeal, Lady Justice Arden suggested that the doctrine could be expressed in the following manner. A person who can take steps which will avoid any conflict between his beliefs</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3257.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3274.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and those acts which he claims interferes with those beliefs, or voluntarily accepts a regime which leads to such a conflict, cannot complain of an interference with his freedom to manifest his beliefs. That doctrine was described as harsh, it was described as unlikely</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3274.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3281.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to be right, and we do respectfully submit that it is plainly wrong. It is inconsistent</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3281.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3299.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with the proper approach to religious rights, it is impossible to reconcile the doctrine with the general points of principle made by the Court about the importance of religious rights. There is no other fundamental right or freedom which is subjected to this doctrine,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3299.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3312.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and there are no material differences between Article 9 and the text of other articles which suggest that this is justified. It is, we submit, worse than the austerity of tabulated</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3312.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3318.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>legalism. It isn't even founded on the wording of the Convention. It is a judicial attempt</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3318.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3326.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to rationalise authorities which, in our submission, has come up with the wrong answer. Was there</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3326.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3332.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>an interference with the right to manifest in this case? This is question 1 of the Court's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3332.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3356.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>questions to us, and we submit that the answer was plainly yes, because this was a situation where Miss Aweda wanted to wear her religious symbol next to persons who were wearing their religious symbols. A sincere desire to display universally recognised symbols of faith, whether</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3356.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3368.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>or not it is a scriptural requirement, and however many other people wish to do so, is plainly an expression of religion that falls within the scope of Article 9 protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3368.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3387.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The act of wearing the cross had no purpose other than to declare and make outwardly manifest her Christian faith, which has worldwide recognition as a symbol that is intrinsic to the faith and was recognised by this Court in Lauzzi and Italy. Then the question is whether it</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3387.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3401.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was infringed, and BA stopped her from wearing the cross, and we say it is no answer to say that she was permitted to wear it hidden. That required her to conceal her own identity</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3401.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3407.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>next to employees who were entitled to express it. The treatment by the courts in the United</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3407.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3415.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kingdom was inadequate. At paragraph 22 of the Court of Appeal's judgement, it was said</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3415.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3425.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the jurisprudence of Article 9 adds nothing to Miss Aweda's case. Well, if that is right,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3425.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3438.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>we respectfully submit that the Court of Appeal have failed to grasp the fundamental importance of Article 9 in these cases. There was a clear infringement of Miss Aweda's right to manifest</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3438.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3445.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>her religious belief, which required justification. Can it then be justified? The Employment Tribunal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3445.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3452.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>found not. The Employment Appeal Tribunal found not. It was only the majority of the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3452.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3457.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Court of Appeal who said it could be justified. But how could it be proportionate when she</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3457.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3464.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was working next to other colleagues who were entitled to express their religious freedoms?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3464.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3470.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the short time remaining, I will deal with Article 9 and 14. We submit that the United</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3470.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3482.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kingdom Government and courts are in breach of obligations under Article 9, read with Article 14. My friend Miss Rose, on behalf of Miss Liddell, will develop the law and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3482.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3487.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>submissions in respect of that, and we respectfully adopt it. But we do say this. There was nothing</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3487.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3504.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that my learned friend said, or could be said, to justify the difference in treatment between Miss Aweda and those of her colleagues who were entitled to display their own religious beliefs. What? Because she is a member of a tolerant religion where you are entitled</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3504.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3510.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to choose, you have less rights? That, we respectfully submit, would be a very unfortunate</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3510.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3516.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>conclusion. Can I just conclude by saying this? Miss Aweda has suffered a real loss</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3516.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3525.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of earnings, interest on the loss of earnings, real loss of pension, and union dues. The</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3525.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3530.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>process described in paragraph 23.4 of the Employment Tribunal's judgment, by which</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3530.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3543.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>her dress was physically rearranged, with a hand around her neck, tucking it into the front of her blouse, caused her shame, upset, embarrassment and humiliation. It was a violation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3543.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3550.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of her, an unconsented touching, and bullying and victimisation. The fact that she has never</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3550.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3557.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>obtained her address is a burning sore to her that continues to this day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3559.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3563.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. I call now Ms Rose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3568.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3574.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr President and members of the court, my submissions concern the case of Ms Liddell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3574.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3587.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lillian Liddell was a registrar whose duties included registering and conducting civil marriage ceremonies. She'd been employed in that capacity by the London Borough of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3587.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3599.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Islington, a local government authority, since 2002. Some years later, in 2005, new legislation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3599.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3620.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>came into force in the United Kingdom, under which couples of the same sex were entitled to seek to register civil partnerships, which are for all practical and legal purposes indistinguishable from marriage. Ms Liddell is a Christian. She has a sincere religious belief that marriage</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3620.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3626.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is only properly a relationship which can be concluded between a man and a woman. For</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3626.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3632.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that reason, she has a conscientious objection to conducting or registering civil partnerships.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3632.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3647.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And she thus asked Islington, before the new law came into force, not to designate her as a civil partnerships registrar under the new law. Islington refused and insisted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3647.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3658.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that Ms Liddell, together with all of its other registrars, should change the terms of her employment and should be designated as a civil partnerships registrar. She was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3658.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3673.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>disciplined for gross misconduct and ultimately forced to resign because of her refusal in these circumstances to act as a registrar of civil partnerships. The issue before this</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3673.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3694.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>court is whether, in treating her in that way, Islington subjected Ms Liddell to unjustified discrimination on grounds of her religious belief, contrary to Article 14 of the Convention, read together with Article 9. And we stress that this is not a claim brought under Article</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3694.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3702.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>9 alone, it is a claim brought under Article 14, a claim of discrimination. The particular</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3702.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3718.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>facts of this case and the history of the national legal proceedings are, we submit, of crucial importance. And we stress the following points. First, as I have said, Ms Liddell</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3718.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3732.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>had already been employed as a marriage registrar for a number of years before the enactment or coming into force of the Civil Partnerships Act. In that capacity, there was no question</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3732.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3739.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of her being required to register same-sex unions. She did not volunteer for a career</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3739.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3747.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which involved the registering of civil partnerships. Mr Eadie, in his submission, suggested that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3747.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3755.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>these were cases of employees seeking to force their employer to alter their terms and conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3755.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3762.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not so. This was a case of Ms Liddell's employer seeking to force her to accept an</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3762.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3776.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>alteration in her terms and conditions and disciplining her for gross misconduct when she refused to accept it. Secondly, the new national legislation itself permitted Islington</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3776.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3789.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to take a decision not to designate all of its marriage registrars as civil partnerships registrars. Islington was only required to have sufficient civil partnership registrars</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3789.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3796.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to provide the service. A conscientious objection such as that of Ms Liddell could have been</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3796.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3803.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>accommodated under national law. This is thus not a case in which the national legislature</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3803.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3812.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>had decided that all marriage registrars should conduct civil partnerships. Third, the national</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3812.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3826.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>courts found as a fact that accommodating Ms Liddell's conscientious objection would not have caused any detriment to the service received by same-sex couples in Islington.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3826.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3840.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no question in this case of the acts of the local authority being necessary to prevent discrimination against same-sex couples. The right to equal treatment of same-sex couples</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3840.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3855.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>seeking a civil partnership could have been accommodated alongside the right of a long-standing marriage registrar like Ms Liddell during this transitional period of rapid social change.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3855.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3862.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourth, Ms Liddell's religious belief is a mainstream traditional Christian belief. It is derived</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3862.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3869.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from scripture. It is shared by most major Christian European denominations, including</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3869.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3877.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Roman Catholic Church, the Orthodox Churches and many Protestant churches. Although many</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3877.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3889.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>people take a different view from Ms Liddell, her belief is plainly a belief that must be considered worthy of respect in a democratic society. This is an important point because</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3889.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3902.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>some of the interveners have sought to compare Ms Liddell's belief with the belief of a person who refuses to conduct a mixed-race marriage. But such a belief would not be worthy of respect</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3902.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3914.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in a democratic society, unlike the traditional Christian belief of Ms Liddell that marriage is a union between a man and a woman. Fifthly, the effect of Islington's treatment on Ms</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3914.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3929.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Liddell has been to deprive her of her livelihood and to cause her serious distress and financial loss. Sixthly, no proper analysis of Islington's purported justification for its treatment</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3929.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3936.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Ms Liddell has ever been conducted by the national courts. The aims pursued have been</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3936.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3942.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>repeatedly reformulated and were put in a different way again by Mr Eadie today. No</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3942.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3949.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>proportionality analysis has been conducted. There has been no attempt to balance Ms Liddell's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3949.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3968.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>rights, including her right to equal treatment in the manifestation of her religious beliefs against Islington's aims, or to consider what alternatives were open to Islington to avoid the severe adverse consequences suffered by Ms Liddell. No weight at all has been given</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3968.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3974.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by the Court of Appeal to Ms Liddell's fundamental right undoubtedly engaged by this treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3974.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3987.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On a proper analysis, any of the aims now put forward by the United Kingdom could have been met without requiring Ms Liddell to be designated as a civil partnerships registrar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3987.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4019.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the achievement of the local authority's asserted aim of demonstrating its commitment to equality of opportunity is in fact defeated by its treatment of Ms Liddell, because what the local authority has done by its doctrinaire approach is to discriminate against Ms Liddell and subject her to a detriment because of her religious belief, contrary to the values of diversity and equality which Islington purported to be upholding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4019.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4026.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these circumstances, the following questions arise under Article 14. First, does Ms Liddell's</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4026.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4034.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>claim fall within the ambit of Article 9 so that Article 14 is engaged? Secondly, was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4034.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4052.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>she treated to her detriment in the same way as those who did not have a religious conscientious objection to the performance of civil partnerships, even though her circumstances were materially different from those of such employees? And thirdly, has her treatment been shown to be</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4052.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4058.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>justified as a proportionate means of meeting a legitimate aim?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4058.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4071.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that there is no doubt that Ms Liddell's case engages Article 9 and falls within its ambit. Although she does not need to go so far because this is an Article 14 case, on</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4071.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4092.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the facts of this case, her refusal to conduct or register civil partnerships was indeed the manifestation of a religious belief, just as this Court has held that a refusal to undertake military service on the part of a Jehovah's Witness is the manifestation of a religious belief.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4092.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4102.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Contrary to the submissions of the United Kingdom, there is no need for Ms Liddell to show a prima facie breach of Article 9 in order for Article 14 to be engaged. The United</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4102.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4113.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kingdom's submissions on this point are contrary to the established case law of this Court, going back at least 30 years to the case of Abdul Aziz and the United Kingdom. We note</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4113.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4120.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that Mr Eady has not sought today to grapple at all with this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4120.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4136.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is also no doubt that Ms Liddell was treated by Islington in the same way as other employees who had no conscientious objection, and that she suffered a disadvantage arising from being treated in that way. As this Court has recognised in the case of Thliminos and</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4136.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4153.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Greece, treating a person in the same way as another whose circumstances are materially different is a form of discrimination which will be contrary to Article 14 unless objectively justified. To put the matter in a different way, the apparently neutral requirement applied</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4153.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4172.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by Islington that all of its registrars should be civil partnerships registrars placed Ms Liddell as a committed Christian under a particular disadvantage, and such treatment is discriminatory unless justified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4172.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4177.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, no justification for Ms Liddell's treatment has been demonstrated. No clear</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4177.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4185.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>or coherent legitimate aim has been identified. It has not been shown that the treatment of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4185.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4208.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms Liddell was proportionate, and in the absence of any proper proportionality analysis conducted by national courts, it is not appropriate for a broad margin of appreciation to be afforded to the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4208.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4222.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The aims pursued by Islington have been differently expressed by both Islington and the United Kingdom at different stages in the proceedings. In the tribunal, Islington stated that its</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4222.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4230.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>aim was to provide an effective civil partnership arrangement service. This aim was accepted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4230.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4248.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by the tribunal as legitimate, but the means for achieving it were clearly found to be disproportionate because the aim could have been achieved without designating Ms Liddell as a civil partnerships registrar. Since then, the government has sought to reformulate that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4248.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4256.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>aim. The government initially argued in this court that the local authority's aim was</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4256.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4268.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to provide equal access to services, irrespective of sexual orientation, and thereby communicate a clear commitment to non-discrimination. This formulation could not justify the discrimination</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4268.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4274.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in this case, since on the fact it could have been met without designating Ms Liddell. The</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4274.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4294.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>government now restates its legitimate aim as being that its employees should not treat less favourably or withhold services from members of the public on grounds of sexual orientation. But this aim also could have been met without designating Ms Liddell. Had</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4294.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4305.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>she not been designated as a civil partnerships registrar, there would have been no question of her withholding services from members of the public. She would not have been employed</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4305.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4313.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to perform such services, as indeed she was not when first employed by the council.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4313.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4319.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So all the aims identified could have been met without designating Ms Liddell. Moreover,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4319.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4336.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the national courts have failed to give any weight to the adverse effects of Islington's conduct on Ms Liddell's rights, or to seek to balance those effects against the importance of the aims pursued. The Court of Appeal gave no consideration to the fact that the means</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4336.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4354.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>adopted by Islington were contrary to its own policy, its equal opportunities policy, which expressly included a prohibition on religious discrimination and afforded it equal weight with discrimination on grounds of sexual orientation. That policy stated Islington</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4354.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4365.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>would actively remove discriminatory barriers that can prevent people from obtaining employment opportunities for which they are entitled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4365.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4370.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is not a case in which a broad margin of appreciation should be afforded. The appropriate</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4370.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4380.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>role for a margin of appreciation would be in the context of assessing the results of a properly conducted proportionality exercise. Where no such exercise has been conducted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4380.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4387.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by the national court, it is not appropriate to give the Member State such a margin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4387.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4398.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, we adopt the submission of Mr Dingerman's that religious rights are a fundamental part of the Convention. This is a suspect category of discrimination, expressly prohibited under</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4398.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4407.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 14, closely related to ethnicity, and cannot be justified in the absence of very weighty reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4407.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4418.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The national authorities have failed to appreciate there were two rights to equal treatment engaged in this case, which required balanced consideration. Instead, they have focused only on the rights</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4418.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4423.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of same-sex couples, which on the particular facts of this case were not in fact in jeopardy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4423.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4441.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that the celebration, toleration and accommodation of diversity to which importance is rightly attached as being central to the achievement of equality of opportunity has wrongly been disregarded by the local authority, the Court of Appeal and the United Kingdom in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4441.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4453.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before I end my presentation, there is one important point on which I would like to update the Court. At paragraph 104 of our written observations of January 2012, we noted that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4453.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4468.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Government of the Netherlands had asked the Council of State to give advice on the very same issue that arises in this application, the question of marriage registrars with a conscientious objection to performing same-sex marriages. The Council of State has now issued</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4468.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4473.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>its advisory opinion. We obtained a translation yesterday and we have copies available for</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4473.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4476.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>members of the Court, if you would like them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4476.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4489.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In summary, the Dutch Council of State has adopted precisely the same analysis that we have adopted in our application. It has found that dismissing an existing marriage registrar</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4489.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4508.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with a conscientious objection constitutes unjustified, indirect discrimination on grounds of religious belief and would be contrary to Article 14, read with Article 9 of the Convention because it falls within the ambit of Article 9, even though it would not be a breach of Article 9 read alone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4508.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4534.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Council of State has rejected precisely the justification advanced by the United Kingdom in this case and has said that the objections of conscience of registrars who take the traditional view of marriage deserves respect in a tolerant democratic society and must be accommodated where this is reasonably possible without a detrimental effect on the provision of the service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4534.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4549.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The importance of this principle of reasonable accommodation, which has now been endorsed by the Dutch Council of State, reflects the observation of Justice Sachs in the South African Constitutional Court in the case of Foury. He said,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4549.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4565.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The State should, wherever reasonably possible, seek to avoid putting believers through extremely painful and intensely burdensome choices of either being true to their faith or else respectful of the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4565.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4577.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For all of these reasons, we invite the Court to find that there has been a violation of Ms Liddell's right to equal treatment under Article 14 of the Convention and to award her the just satisfaction which she seeks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4579.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4581.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4581.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4583.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I call Mr. Diamond.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4603.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4607.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4607.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4619.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the cases of Shirley Chaplin and Gary McFarland are not complex, but they raise very serious issues for the United Kingdom and for members of the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4619.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4625.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issues before this esteemed court today are to be summarized in three main points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4625.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4638.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, this court must determine to what extent freedom of thought, conscience, and religion must be protected and guaranteed, not just for applicants here today, but for Europeans as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4638.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4648.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The effect of the respondent's position in this case is essentially to limit Article 9 to mere freedom to worship in private or in a church setting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4648.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4669.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That leads to the second issue before this court, which is to find a workable, bright-line test by which to determine in the workplace context to what extent freedom of thought, conscience, and religion may be limited by the scope of this test necessary in a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4669.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4683.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our submissions, the doctrine of reasonable accommodation has shown itself to be the most workable standard to protect both the interests of the employer and employee within Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4683.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4693.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, in my respectful submission, this court is called upon to determine the extent to which conscience is to be protected under Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4693.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4697.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Freedom of thought, conscience, and religion are inextricably linked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4697.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4711.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as this court decided in Britannia and Armenia, that the protection of conscience can be extended merely beyond the right to be exempt from military service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4711.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4728.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regrettably, the courts of the United Kingdom have not adopted a simple, straightforward, principled approach to Article 9 so as to enable the religious adherent to live his life with the least violation and infringement on his religious beliefs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4728.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4736.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regrettably, the courts instead appear to have created insurmountable hurdles to ensuring this freedom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4736.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4749.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>National courts have ruled on whether the religious manifestation is a mandatory requirement, whether religious apparel is a scriptural requirement, whether the claimant is part of a group as a sole adherent is not protected under indirect discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4749.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4754.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The exact meaning and context and size of this group remains unknown.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4754.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4757.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let's begin with Shirley Chaplin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4757.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4762.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Chaplin has worn a cross on a chain around her neck</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4762.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4772.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>since her confirmation in 1971 and considers it to be a manifestation of her faith on her understanding of the scriptures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4772.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4781.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She's worked as a nurse for approximately 30 years with a faultless employment record and has never stopped wearing the cross.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4781.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4788.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In those 30 years of wearing the cross, the cross has never injured a single patient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4788.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4802.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hospital, ignoring their own policy to permit religious and cultural apparel, argued health and safety issues that the cross and chain might cause injury if an elderly patient pulled on it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4802.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4805.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To alleviate such concerns, Mrs. Chaplin</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4805.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4814.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>suggested that a magnetic clasp could be fitted to the chain, which would allow it to break when pulled, thus solving the problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4814.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4821.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the hospital rejected this as a solution and suggested that the cross could scratch a patient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4821.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4832.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no nature of any form of compromise that took place with other faiths to adapt their religious apparel to suit the hospital requirements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4832.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4844.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cross was considered a piece of jewelry that could be hanged around the lanyards or worn as an earring, but no respect or recognition was given of the religious significance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4844.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4850.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No evidence has been submitted to support the claim that the cross ever posed a health and safety risk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4850.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4870.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is equally clear is the refusal, in our submission, to make an allowance for her to wear the cross, even after any legitimate safety issue had been alleviated, breached the standard and the necessity standard used by this court in analyzing where a violation of Article 9 has occurred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4870.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4877.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Freedom of thought, conscience, and religion is a fundamental right, both under European and British law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4877.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4885.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Christians enjoy the same rights to adorn themselves with religious symbols and clothing of their choosing as does other religions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4885.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4888.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no issue here for Muslim dress.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4888.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4889.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4889.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4891.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For Christians.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4891.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4902.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The failure to provide even the most simple of accommodations for the right of a patient to wear a cross, particularly where other religions have been accommodated, in our submission, is a clear breach of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4902.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4910.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, any difference in treatment on the basis of religion will require very weighty reasons to be justified under Article 14.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4910.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4912.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These reasons do not exist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4912.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4914.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that doesn't end there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4914.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4928.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, a week after the judgment in this case, the Department of Health announced a modification of the health and safety rules in relation to coverings below the elbow to accommodate nurses of the Islamic and Sikh faith.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4928.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4937.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is inconceivable that the hospital was not aware of this development to modify health and safety rules to accommodate religious practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4937.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4943.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Soon after the media interest in this case ended, Mrs. Chaplin lost her clerical employment</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4943.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4946.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as the position came to an end.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4946.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4949.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now Shirley has no employment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4949.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4952.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Chaplin is suffering economically,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4952.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4954.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>feels humiliated, and disrespected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4954.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4959.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the National Health Service has lost a good nurse willing to work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4959.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4965.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no legitimate reason to discriminate in this way against her and against Christians in general.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4965.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4968.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Chaplin, who sits in the court today behind me,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4968.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4971.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>wanted to just say this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4971.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4973.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The tribunal left me shattered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4973.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4976.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My world was turned upside down.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4976.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4979.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My pay band immediately dropped.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4979.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4986.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The knowledge of the role I had enjoyed for the majority of my adult life was no longer open to me.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4986.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4992.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They also implied that I was a danger to patients because of my failure to remove my cross.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4992.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4996.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can't put into words how that made me feel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4996.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5001.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My whole nursing career was based on this one moment, not over 30 years of caring and devotion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5001.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5006.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My finances are now limited, and I do not have the lifestyle I anticipated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5006.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5011.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Real people, real lives, real damage and suffering.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5011.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5014.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let's look at the case of Mr. McFarland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5014.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5019.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since 2003, Gary McFarland worked as a counselor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5019.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5036.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He now is finding employment very difficult because he's unable to register with any reputable professional body, because he was dismissed for gross misconduct on grounds of sexual orientation, something which sadly labels him as a homophobe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5036.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5039.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nothing could be further from the truth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5039.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5041.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. McFarland's hurt is all the more greater</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5041.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5045.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because he'd always acted professionally.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5045.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5050.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He had, and note this, never refused to counsel a same-sex couple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5050.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5057.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He'd counseled two such couples in the past and believes that Christianity and non-discrimination principles are fully compatible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5057.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5060.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His trouble arose on a training course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5060.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5068.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He decided not to watch a film called Broadback Mountain, a film about a homosexual relationship, because he was tired.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5068.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5072.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Suspicion arose among his co-workers because he was a Christian.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5072.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5079.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was required to state his position in the counseling of same-sex couples in psychosexual therapy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5079.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5084.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He had expressed in confidence to his supervisor some private anxieties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5084.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5091.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His supervising therapist breached all professional rules with impunity to reveal these private anxieties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5094.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5097.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. McFarland did not know himself</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5097.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5101.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>what he would do if required to give directed sexual therapy to a same-sex couple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5101.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5112.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He'd had a similar problem with couple counseling and relations to same-sex relationships, but this had been resolved to the satisfaction of all parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5112.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5118.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say Her Majesty's government's submission on the beliefs of Mr. McFarland are extraordinary</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5118.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5121.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because he himself did not express what his own beliefs were.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5121.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5132.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All we know in this case is that a private citizen had private religious views that an employer and the state did not deem worthy of respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5132.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5148.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was required to state his position on giving same-sex therapy to same-sex couples without having worked through what he himself believed and prospectively deny his own beliefs as a condition of employment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5148.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5153.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's important to know, as I said before, there was no refusal to see a client.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5153.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5156.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, there was no client.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5156.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5165.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And he was prevented from returning to couple counseling, which he'd successfully worked in, and which there'd been no discrimination issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5165.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5170.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His inner forum, we submit, within the first sentence of Article 9 was violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5170.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5176.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This line of inquiry is wholly intrusive and was disapproved in Smith and Grady in the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5176.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5181.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moral integrity is a component part of both Articles 8 and 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5181.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5184.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. McFarland worked for a private employer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5184.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5189.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He did not provide any statutory service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5189.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5196.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His employer simply introduced a non-discrimination policy and became judge and jury in its own application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5196.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5204.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no name where this will end as society moves in a more secular direction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5204.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5207.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The implications in these two cases go far beyond these two individuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5207.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5219.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the United Kingdom, religious people who have followed their conviction in the workplace in the face of overtly vague non-discrimination laws have been sacked, demoted, or disciplined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5219.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5226.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Among them have been lawyers, have been doctors, magistrate, teachers, foster parents, therapists, and many others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5226.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5234.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In my respectful submission, the situation of religious liberty in the United Kingdom is now critical.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5234.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5240.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In all four cases, the sincerely held beliefs of the applicants could have been accommodated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5243.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5251.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the applicants wanted to do was follow their faith quietly, and they neither imposed their views or faith on any third party.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5251.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5258.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 8 rights and Article 10 rights have been applied in the employment context, and so should Article 9 rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5258.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5264.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 9 rights need to be fully recognized and protected with or without an Article 14 analysis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5264.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5271.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's wholly unrealistic to say someone is free to resign and face unemployment and suffering.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5271.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5280.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You can't want contract out of one's convention rights in a situation of inequality of bargaining power between an employer and an employee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5280.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5286.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can every employee make it a condition of employment that you contract out of your convention rights?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5286.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5290.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And would any other vulnerable group be so treated in such a dismissive manner?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5293.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5298.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The real issue is where Article 9 is engaged.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5298.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5310.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the employment context, the national courts must correctly balance the clash of rights between an employer and employee in accordance with the fundamental rights and guarantees of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5310.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5317.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This should be a strict form of scrutiny, and the concept of reasonable accommodation is a practical working model.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5317.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5325.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this process can take place under Article 9, Article 14 in conjunction with Article 9, or even under Article 6 of access to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5325.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5334.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The state is under a positive obligation to protect these Article 9 rights, and the United Kingdom has done this by means of anti-discrimination legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5334.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5346.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit the United Kingdom under a positive obligation to give effective protection to these rights, and this extends to an obligation to exercise domestic legislation in conformity with the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5346.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5352.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no lack of consensus of the member states or the Council of Europe on the importance of Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5353.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5359.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The problem is perceived animus to the Christian faith by the courts of the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5359.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5364.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Religious faith should never be so treated, described, or disparaged by a state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5364.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5369.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Christian faith is worthy of respect in a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5371.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5384.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In my respectful submission, this court is the conscience of Europe, and it has now had the opportunity to effectively recognise and accommodate religious freedom in Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5384.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5384.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5388.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5390.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5390.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5403.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now we can start the second phase of this part of the hearing, namely the questions put by judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5403.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5409.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Who would like to ask a question? Judge Bratza.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5414.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5418.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a number of questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5418.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5424.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first of all, three questions I would like to put to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5424.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5450.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, is it the government's argument that before an act can be regarded as a manifestation of a religious belief, as opposed to being motivated or inspired by that belief, it must be mandated by the religion in question, or at least form part of the practice of the religion or belief in a generally recognized form?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5450.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5463.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If so, how is this court to determine this question in cases where an applicant asserts and the respondent denies that it is so mandated?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5463.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5482.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is this rather narrow approach consistent with that adopted by the Grand Chamber in the Leyla ahin case, where the court did not examine whether the wearing of an Islamic scarf was mandated by the Muslim religion?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5482.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5500.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, do the government argue that there can be no interference at all with the manifestation of religious belief in the context of employment if the applicant can reconcile that conflict by resigning and seeking employment elsewhere?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5500.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5510.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If so, must the employer do more than merely assert this by showing the genuine possibility of alternative employment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5510.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5519.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If this is not the government's argument, in what circumstances would the government accept that there could be an interference?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5519.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5525.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And thirdly, in the case of Mrs. Ladele, does it, in the view of the government, make a</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5525.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5541.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>difference that at the time of her original employment, civil partnerships did not exist and that new requirements were effectively imposed on her when she was asked to perform civil partnership ceremonies?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5541.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5548.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I have one question to the counsel for Mrs. Eweida and Mr. McFarlane.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5548.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5563.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do you argue that the same approach should be adopted to the claims under Article 9 and under Article 14, whether the employer is a state authority or a private law company or association?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5563.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5574.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If not, how is it suggested that the court's approach should differ when dealing with the positive obligations of the state, as in the two cases in question?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5574.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5597.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I note that reliance is placed, strong reliance is placed in the written observations on this section's judgment in Jakbski, but that, of course, was a case which clearly involved direct state intervention in the sense it concerned the prison authorities in Poland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5597.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5599.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then I have two factual questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5599.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5607.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first addressed to Mrs. Eweida, is it correct that prior to May 2006, Mrs. Eweida wore a</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5607.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5613.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>cross, but that the cross was not visible over her uniform?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5613.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5619.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then one in respect of Mr. McFarlane, was it the applicant's own choice to apply</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5619.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5629.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for the psychosexual therapy diploma, or was this a requirement of his being able to be employed by Relate?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5629.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5640.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the former, did he know that this would require him to give PST counseling to same-sex couples at the time he applied for the diploma?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5640.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5640.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5642.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5644.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. Judge Hirvel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Pivi Hirvel</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5647.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5648.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5648.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5652.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question concerns the Eweida case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5652.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5666.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we heard and read also from the documents that the British Airways adopted in 2007 a new uniform code which allowed carrying visible religious symbols at work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5666.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5674.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my question is whether the parties know what was the reason for the change of this policy?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5674.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5675.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was it the Eweida case?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5675.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5678.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was it the policy of other companies?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5678.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5684.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or was there something in the national non-discrimination legislation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5684.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5694.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then we also know that 30 other staff members, they were happy with the code, or at least they followed it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5694.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5707.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my question is whether the parties know, has the change of this code had any other larger impact other than that Mrs. Eweida could return to her work?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5707.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5707.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5709.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5710.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5710.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5712.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge, Judge de Gaetano.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Vincent A. De Gaetano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5714.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5732.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, I would like to ask a factual question in the context of what has been proposed, that employers cannot be forced to accommodate the beliefs of the religious convictions of their employees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5732.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5765.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question, and I ask this sincerely out of sheer ignorance of what the position is in England, but is there any law in the United Kingdom which, in the context of hospital services, allows hospital employees, particularly nurses but possibly even doctors, to opt out of certain interventions, operations, whatever, on the grounds of conscientious objection?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5765.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5770.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't know what the position is. If it was mentioned in one of the papers submitted,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5770.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5778.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I apologise for putting that question again. It may have slipped, I may have not noticed it. Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5779.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5781.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. Judge Vuini.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Neboja Vuini</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5784.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5786.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5786.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5802.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is related to the previous questions of Judge Hirvel concerning change in British Airways dress code policy, symbol policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5802.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5805.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What did it mean?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5805.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5808.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This question is for both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5808.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5818.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Did it mean that British Airways indirectly and tacitly recognized the violation of the applicant's rights?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5818.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5818.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5822.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5825.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5825.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5835.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is similar to that of Sir Nicolas and is directed mostly to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5835.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5860.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, it transpires from the facts and it was not disputed at this hearing that the British Airways allowed some types of religious dress like turbans or headscarves, at the same time prohibiting other types.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5860.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5872.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it was stated by the counsel for the applicant, this was based on a so-called mandatory scripture requirement test.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5872.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5883.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is, was it really so that this was such a test that was decisive for differentiations?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5883.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5893.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, what is the conventional basis for applying and enforcing such tests?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5893.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5906.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as there are no other questions, I suppose both parties need some time to reflect on the answers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5906.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5912.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So let's have a 15-minute break and we start at 5 to 11.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5952.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5953.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5994.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5995.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6000.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6032.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, taking into account that there are several questions put by judges, I will assign 10 minutes for the government to answer and to comment on any other problems they wish, and 5 minutes for each of the three councils. I call Mr. Eadie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6034.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6037.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, may I start with the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6037.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6056.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Bratt, first of all, asked whether it was the government's case that before there could be any manifestation for the purposes of Article 9, the matter in question or the action in question must be more than merely motivated by and must be mandated or a generally recognized form.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6056.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6061.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, how does the court go about assessing the answer to that question, if that is the question?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6061.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6068.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My submission is that the position is as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6068.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6078.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does not need to be established that the action in question is a formal requirement in the sense of mandated in its strict sense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6078.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6090.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But what does have to be shown, because it isn't every act that is covered by Article 9, is that in the words of the court, the action in question is a generally recognized form of the religion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6090.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6093.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That has been the consistent and constant case law of the courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6093.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6096.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we do make that submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6096.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6100.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The domestic courts have put that test in a variety of different ways.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6100.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6103.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I say the court's case law is generally a recognized form.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6103.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6112.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The domestic courts have on occasion used words such as intimately linked to the core values of the religion in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6112.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6115.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How does the court go about assessing that?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6115.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6126.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My submission in relation to that is that it does so by, if necessary, in the case of a dispute, receiving evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6126.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6130.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, of course, a matter for the domestic courts if there is a dispute about that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6130.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6150.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there's nothing invidious about that, because what one would be looking for in investigating is not the subjective belief of the individual in question, but the objective question, which is whether or not the action that is before the court is indeed a generally recognized form of the religion in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6150.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6156.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we respectfully submit that there's nothing invidious about the approach that asks the objective question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6156.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6160.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, it has the benefit of being an objective question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6160.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6168.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I emphasize finally in answer to that question that in these cases, particularly in the case, for example, of Mese Wada, there was no dispute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6168.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6182.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The domestic court specifically considered that issue, and it was common ground and accepted that she was wearing the cross, not as it were as a generally recognized form of practice of the religion, but as a matter of pure personal preference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6182.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6194.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So to put the point rather more simply, a great many Christians do not insist on wearing crosses either at all or still less visibly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6194.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6203.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We respectfully submit that our answer to that question is not in any shape or form undermined by the Sahin case, which Judge Bartser refers to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6203.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6212.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's evident, if I recall that case correctly, that when they dealt with the interference aspect of the matter, they dealt with it very shortly, and I think a single paragraph, before moving on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6212.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6222.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it's evident from the report of that case, I think, that there was no challenge in that particular case to the interference issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6222.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6238.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we do submit that Sahin doesn't stand, as it were, as authority against the previous clear and consistent jurisprudence of the court, which is, as I've said, clearly to the effect that what is required is a generally recognized form of the religion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6238.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6256.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And indeed, it might be thought that it's unsurprising there was no dispute on the facts of Sahin, because the wearing of a headscarf is, I think one could take it as common ground, is a well-recognized form of practice or manifestation for Muslim women.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6256.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6268.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we respectfully submit that Sahin does not stand in opposition to the test that we propose, which is the right test recognized by the court and acceptable in principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6268.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6280.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Garlicchi then asked a similar question, which related to the BA policy in the Uweda case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6280.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6295.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think, again, from memory, someone will correct me if I'm wrong, but I think that the position is that the BA policy was indeed that there should be no jewelry unless mandatorily required by a religion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6295.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6308.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact of the matter is, however, that in relation to BA, first of all, they did reconsider the policy as soon as it was raised in the case of Miss Uweda, and then changed the policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6308.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6318.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That isn't, we submit, a recognition that the previous policy was not in a compliant state with the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6318.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6337.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would be a question in every case, and on the individual facts of every case, to assess whether or not operating a policy to preclude a particular form of jewelry or a particular form of item of clothing did or did not interfere with Article 9 rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6337.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6354.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that a private employer's policy, previously and before it was reconsidered, was in that form, does not, we submit, and cannot be taken to being some form of implicit acknowledgment that prior to the change, the policy was non-compliant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6354.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6375.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, you'll recall the Court of Appeals judgment, which was clearly an expressive to the effect, that before the policy was changed, it, as a policy, leaving aside how it was actually applied on individual cases, as a policy was not non-compliant, and didn't suddenly become non-compliant when the complaint was raised.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6375.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6385.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as I say, BA conscientiously looked at the policy when it was raised and decided to change it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6385.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6393.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On that point, and to interpose a short point by way of reply to Mr. Dingaman's submissions, he made a bit of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6393.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6397.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a point about how long it took BA, on his case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6397.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6404.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think it was a matter of months rather than anything else, but on his case, he made a bit of a point about how long it had taken BA to change that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6404.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6418.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, you will recall again that in the Court of Appeal domestically, they specifically considered that complaint, and they rejected any suggestion that there had been any form of unreasonable delay by BA in changing that policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6418.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6421.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once the complaint was received, they conscientiously considered it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6421.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6426.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They followed their past practice of doing so through the lenses of diversity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6426.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6449.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And at least one of the reasons, as appears from the Court of Appeal's judgment at paragraph 36, why the thing took so long to change was, in the words of the Court of Appeal quoting the Employment Tribunal, because the claimant's insistence on introducing wide policy considerations, forcing a broader range of issues onto the agenda.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6449.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6452.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is, with respect to Ms. Iwida, all of a piece with</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6452.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6476.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>paragraph three of the Court of Appeal's judgment, in which they record another express finding of the Employment Tribunal, namely that she exhibited serious insensitivity towards her colleagues, lack of empathy for those without a religious focus of their lives, incomprehension of the conflicting demands which professional management seeks to address and resolve on a near daily basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6476.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6484.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we don't accept that BA delayed unduly in changing the policy that they did.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6484.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6502.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second of Judge Bratz's questions to return to those was whether or not the government's case was that there could be no interference with Article 9 rights if the applicant's religious beliefs can be reconciled by resigning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6502.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6505.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't put it quite as starkly as that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6505.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6521.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You'll recall that in the domestic courts, particularly in Lord Bingham's speech in Begham, cast the position rather differently by reference to whether or not there were steps that the employee could take without undue difficulty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6521.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6529.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we submit that that is the right way of approaching the matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6529.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6542.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is, in terms of the proof of that position, for the employee to assert, under domestic law, we believe, it is for the employee to assert that there would be such undue difficulty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6542.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6550.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if there was a dispute about that, the domestic courts would then resolve the factual question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6550.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6558.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But there was no issue on that front, as we understand it, from the domestic court's judgments in any of those or any of these cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6558.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6562.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The option remained available to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6562.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6567.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we remind the court that there are perhaps two aspects to this part of the interference argument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6567.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6570.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, there is the resigning and moving to another job.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6570.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6585.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But secondly, there is the clear and consistent jurisprudence of the court that acknowledges that the person who asserts religious rights may, on occasion, have to take account of their position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6585.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6601.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And by that, as we understand it, the court has consistently acknowledged that there is a difference between the professional sphere, where your religious freedoms necessarily are bought onto and confront other interests, and the private sphere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6601.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6617.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is highly relevant in assessing interference to note that the employee concerned could indeed pursue all the manifestations, the well-recognized, generally recognized manifestations of their religion, outside the work sphere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6617.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6624.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we do say that the without undue difficulty test is the one, and we adopt Lord Bingham in relation to that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6624.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6633.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the way in which that is proved and tested is by the domestic courts on evidence, if necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6633.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6649.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third of Judge Box's questions related to the Liddell case, and it was whether or not it made a difference that the law changed, in effect, after Miss Liddell had taken up her employment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6649.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6655.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our answer to that is no, it doesn't make any difference to the Article 9 analysis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6655.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6661.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The conditions in many spheres of employment can change.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6661.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6672.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to turn to the, there's nothing wrong with employers insisting if they have a contractual right to do so, and there's no dispute that in this case they did have a contractual right to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6672.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6681.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Conditions can change, and employers can insist on employees conforming their duties to new circumstances as they arise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6681.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6706.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, and more specifically in relation to Miss Liddell's case, it was, we respectfully submit, not, as it were, in any shape or form, unpredictable or deeply surprising, that the law should move in the direction that it ultimately did, with civil partnerships becoming essentially part of what would be regarded as the normal and core functions of people performing the sort of employment that she was performing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6706.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6712.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we respectfully submit the answer to that question is it doesn't make a difference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6712.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6728.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Hervella's question related again to Miss Weider, and it asked the factual question, which was whether or not any of us know what it was that prompted the BA change of policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6731.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6733.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I imagine there will be common ground around this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6733.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6737.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we understand it, the trigger for the change was Miss Weider's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6737.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6748.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There had in the past been a series of different requests by different employees to add particular items of clothing or jewelry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6748.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6753.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And those had always been conscientiously considered, as the domestic courts found.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6753.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6757.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So her request was indeed the trigger for the change.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6757.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6766.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It wasn't, as I emphasized before, it wasn't any form of implicit recognition, I think, by them that the previous policy had been unacceptable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6766.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6773.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You'll remember that the uniform itself had changed, so that there were open-necked shirts and so on for a period of time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6773.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6781.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You are quite close to the time limit of frankly speaking, even over the time limit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6781.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6784.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So please do it in a concise way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6785.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6787.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I've got a couple more questions to go.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6787.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6798.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Judge De Getano's question, which is whether or not there is any law in the context of hospital services which allows a conscientious objection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6798.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6803.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We haven't, I'm afraid, in the time available been able to get a complete list, but there are some.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6803.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6810.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think abortion is one where you can say, I object to abortion and I do not want to participate in that form of it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6810.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6816.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There may well be others, but if there are, we can no doubt inform the court, but there is at least that one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6819.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6827.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I've addressed sufficiently Judge Vucinich's question, which was about changing the dress code and whether or not BA were implicitly recognizing, we say.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6827.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6834.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There wasn't any implicit recognition, so far as that is concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6834.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6846.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can I finally respond very, very briefly to at least one set of points by my own friend Miss Rose?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6846.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6847.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two points, perhaps.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6847.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6860.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, in relation to the Dutch document that she referred to, we haven't had a chance fully to consider it, but we do at least put down a question mark about the status of that document.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6860.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6866.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it actually a formal government position, or is it advice that the government in Holland is now going to consider?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6866.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6875.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, and more substantively, what it does indicate is that different countries can take different positions, and these are difficult balances that need to be struck.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6875.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6891.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We note from the document, for example, the Equal Treatment Commission in Holland, as is recorded in that document, originally took the position that you shouldn't refuse to permit objection on the sort of grounds indicated, and then in 2008 changed their position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6891.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6895.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it simply indicates that there are difficult balances to be struck.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6895.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6912.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, we do respectfully reject the underpinning logic of Miss Liddell's case, which effectively runs, I sincerely believe, she says, that gay relationships are sinful, contrary to God's law, however one wants to put it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6912.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6920.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I won't do anything that I might consider endorses or promotes them, and I must be allowed to refuse to provide services.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6920.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6932.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We respectfully submit that that isn't the logic, and nor is it the logic of Article 9 or 14 to say that the mere existence of some other alternative is enough to establish disproportionality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6932.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6938.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The logic of Article 9 requires the striking of balances with the broad margins involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6938.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6945.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It may have been lawful under domestic law for the council to set up its employment furniture, as it were, differently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6945.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6958.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But there was nothing disproportionate as a matter of policy about it adopting a policy which gave full reign to the promotion of non-discrimination on grounds of same-sex orientation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6958.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6959.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6959.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6960.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm sorry to have gone over the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6960.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6960.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those are my submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6963.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6967.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. I call Mr. Dingemans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6970.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6974.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question I was asked to address was from Judge Bratzer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6974.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6984.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And how should the court approach and deal with the positive obligations, if there are any, in Article 9, having regards to the Jakobsky case?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6984.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6988.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I entirely accept the Jakobsky case was a case that involved state authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6988.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6994.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the reasoning of the court was not limited to the fact that it involved a state authority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6994.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6999.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If one looks carefully through it, one can see the language of a positive obligation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6999.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7004.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is consistent with the court's own jurisprudence in Otto Preminger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7004.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7015.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it would be wrong not to find a positive obligation in Article 9 when there is a positive obligation in, for example, Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7015.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7021.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, you will lead to a system where the courts impermissibly rank rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7021.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7030.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you get to all the problems that have been caused by these cases, because people stop treating religious rights seriously.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7030.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7036.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question I was asked was about what Ms. Oueda had done by way of dress.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7036.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7041.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can I just read very briefly paragraphs 9.5 and 9.6</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7041.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7043.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the Employment Tribunal's judgment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7043.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7044.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just commend them to you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7044.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7049.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What happened was, well, in fact, because of time, I'll have to paraphrase.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7049.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7053.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2004, the uniform changed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7053.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7057.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before, she had worn a blouse and therefore covered her neck.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7057.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7059.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, the cross wasn't visible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7059.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7063.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After 2004, a new uniform was rolled out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7063.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7065.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was called the McDonald uniform.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7065.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7071.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And you could wear either the cravat done up to the neck or with a toggle outside the neck.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7071.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7074.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms. Oueda started wearing the toggle outside the neck,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7074.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7075.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>showing her cross.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7075.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7079.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is where the problems started.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7079.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7085.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the first formal memo where the problem is documented is the 20th of May, 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7085.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7090.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think that has been submitted to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7090.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7096.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, 9.12.2 of the judgment deals</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7096.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7099.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with the mandatory religious items.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7099.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7110.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It said, an employee who wished to wear a religious item visibly outside the uniform was permitted to do so if the item was mandatory and could not be concealed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7110.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7115.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Obvious examples were any form of headgear, such as the hijab, the turban, or the skullcap.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7115.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7120.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's all set out there in the relevant findings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7120.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7128.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next question I was asked was from Judge Borgvitsen in relation to the reason for the change of the BA policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7128.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7133.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is paragraph 3.3 of the Employment Tribunal's judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7133.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7147.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A storm of media attention, much of it hostile to the respondent, which was British Airways, led the respondent to reconsider its uniform policy and to introduce an amended policy on the 1st of February, 2007.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7147.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7158.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think we have also submitted the internal petition that was raised in support of Missy Weeder's position, many from other faith groups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7158.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7167.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relation to Judge de Gaetano's question, my friend, Miss Rose, is going to deal with that in some detail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7167.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7178.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And can I deal with Judge Bucinich's question to me, which is, what is the effect of the change, and does it mean it was not proportionate?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7178.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7194.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we do respectfully submit that it shows that there was never a legitimate aim proportionately pursued in this case that the courts could accept, because incorporated into UK domestic law are the European Convention rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7194.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7197.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the Court of Appeal took the impermissibly narrow route.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7197.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7204.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This comes back to the answer to Judge Bratz's question to me about the obligations incorporated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7204.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7211.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court of Appeal we respectfully submit had misdirected themselves in relation to those matters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7211.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7217.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, the president's question related again to the wearing of religious symbols and types.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7217.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7231.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my instructions are that Miss Weeder is aware that many people now wear a cross, but she couldn't possibly give you any accurate estimation as to numbers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7231.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7233.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those are the answers to the questions, I hope.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7236.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7237.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7237.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7238.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ms Rose, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7241.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7251.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can I deal first with the question that was asked by Judge D'Catano about provisions in national law in the United Kingdom for conscientious objection?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7251.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7266.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We addressed this in our original application to the court at paragraph 54, where we identified a number of places in the United Kingdom law where provision is made for conscientious objection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7266.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7300.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These include the right of medical staff to conscientiously object to involvement in abortion, the right of any person to conscientiously object to participation in work involving treatment and development of human embryos outside the body, right of medical staff not to advise on or provide contraception, the exclusion of jurors from jury service on the grounds of conscientious objection, and other miscellaneous rights, including the right of Sikhs not to wear motorcycle crash helmets, which are obligatory for anyone else riding a motorcycle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7300.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7305.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So those are some examples of where conscientious objection is provided for in United Kingdom law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7305.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7334.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, our submission is that the Civil Partnerships Act itself, the legislation at issue in this case, permitted conscientious objection because it did not oblige the local authorities to designate all marriage registrars as civil partnership registrars, but simply required them to ensure that they had sufficient civil partnership registrars in their area for the service of civil partnership to be provided.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7334.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7345.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, a question asked by Judge Bratsa, is there an interference with Article 9 if the employee is free to seek employment elsewhere?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7345.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7366.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whether or not that is the appropriate test where the allegation is of a breach of Article 9, and we would say it is not, we submit it most certainly cannot be the appropriate test where the complaint is of discrimination under Article 14, and the question is merely whether the treatment is within the ambit of Article 9.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7366.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7376.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is because Article 14 prohibits any detrimental treatment on prohibited grounds which is not justified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7376.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7384.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The nature of the detriment cannot be limited to total exclusion from all forms of employment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7384.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7391.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is obvious that an employee who loses their job has suffered a very serious detriment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7391.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7411.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The logical implication, indeed, of the government's position is the rather startling one, that a state employer could have a policy of refusing to employ practicing Jews, and say that that was not a violation of Article 9 or Article 14 because other employers were prepared to employ them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7411.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7430.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also make the point, of course, that, and this has been raised by counsel for the other applicants in this case, that in the gays and the armed forces case, the issue under Article 8 plus 14 was not resolved by the fact that those individuals could have had other careers apart from careers in the armed forces.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7430.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7445.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we do ask the Court to note the very close links between Articles 8 and 9, because a person's religious beliefs are an integral part of their personal identity, which Article 8 protects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7445.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7456.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Bratza also asked the question whether it made a difference that Ms Liddell was already in her post, and Mr Eadie remarkably responds that it makes no difference at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7456.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7460.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that it does indeed make a very significant difference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7460.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7488.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It makes a difference to the question of the extent to which the local authority was under an obligation to seek to accommodate her, and to the assessment of the proportionality of the treatment to which she was subjected, because the severity of the adverse consequences of that treatment are significantly greater for an employee who has been employed for a number of years and then finds that suddenly conditions change.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7488.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7504.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that an employer is contractually entitled to change an employee's terms and conditions of employment has no bearing on the question whether that treatment by the employer constitutes unlawful discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7504.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7508.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Contrast the case of Sbbenhaar in Germany.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7508.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7525.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That case decided in February of last year was a case in which this Court rejected a complaint of a violation of Article 9 on the basis that the employee knew when they applied for the job that their religious practices were incompatible with the job.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7525.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7528.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That, we say, cuts both ways. This employee did not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7528.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7544.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the suggestion that she should, as a simple employee, have been expected to anticipate controversial and novel developments in the law that took place years after her employment is, with respect to Mr Eadie, a startling one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7544.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7557.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, we make the point that it is not disputed that the service to same-sex couples could have been provided in Islington without any detriment had Ms Liddell not been designated a civil partnerships registrar.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7557.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7568.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The United Kingdom's position is that Islington was entitled to sacrifice Ms Liddell in order to send a message about its commitment to equal opportunities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7568.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7571.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are two fundamental objections to that position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7571.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7585.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first is, of course, that it defeats a commitment to equal opportunities for the local authority to dismiss the employee who has a sincere religious conviction when it was unnecessary to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7585.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7592.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What they have actually done is to show that they place no weight at all upon the right to equal treatment of Ms Liddell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7592.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7606.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, and independently of that, the submission of the United Kingdom entails the permitting Islington to treat Ms Liddell as an instrument for the propagation of its public message.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7606.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7619.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we submit that to treat a person, an individual, as a means and not an aim in themselves is fundamentally incompatible with individual human dignity and incompatible with Convention rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7619.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7619.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7622.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7623.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7623.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7625.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Diamond, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7637.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7643.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If I may just commence by addressing the questions of Judge Bratzer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7643.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7651.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question was addressed to, I pose to answers about Mr McFarland and his position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7651.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7664.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His position was he did not particularly think or address the issue of what the nature of psychosexual therapy would involve. He planned to specialise in sexual therapy, ultimately</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7664.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7671.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in private practice. His own views of his position on this were uncertain as we have</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7671.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7677.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>discussed. They had been previously resolved and he believed they would be previously resolved</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7677.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7683.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>again. If they were unable to be resolved, he hoped that civilised people would have</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7683.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7688.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>reached a sensible accommodation. There are a few points I just want to mention on this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7688.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7701.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first thing is that Mr McFarland has been banned now from a number of reputable therapeutical bodies because of what took place to him. He is unable to join a mainstream organisation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7701.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7708.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and this is having a far-reaching prohibition on his professional practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7708.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7722.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of SID, Abros and Lithuania 2004, the Lithuanian government introduced a wide-ranging employment ban on former KGB officers. That was held to be disproportionate because of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7722.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7727.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>its wide-reaching effects under Article 8, not Article 9. I will come on to that in a</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7727.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7734.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>minute, the same as my learned friend Mr Dinglemans has addressed. It affects his Article 8 rights</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7734.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7738.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to have a career, have professional colleagues and provide for his family. These are similar</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7738.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7745.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>considerations of the widespread right. Not only do we have a religious bar to office,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7746.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7759.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>but additionally to that we have a denial of choice of autonomous individuals who may have wished to see Mr McFarland. He may well have specialised in a particular type of therapy,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7759.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7772.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>particularly those from a religious community, and they may have wished to have obtained his professional references. Finally, the question of referral, the question of therapists</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7772.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7777.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>saying, I am too busy to see this person, is very normal. Therapists refer all the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7777.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7782.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are not experienced enough, they are not specialised in that field. They themselves</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7782.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7787.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>have an issue of abuse or alcoholism, which is a patient. They go on holiday, they move</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7787.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7794.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>home. Referral is normal and should be extended to religious grounds. On the issue of public</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7794.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7800.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and private employment, I endorse the grounds again raised by my learned friend. We feel</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7800.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7813.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that if additional grounds are given to the state, that will privilege public employees under the Convention over private employees. We say that is wrong in principle and will</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7813.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7819.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>result in a partition of Convention rights in a highly regulated field. There is significant</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7819.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7837.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>amount of legislation in the United Kingdom on employment law which tends to treat public and private employers similarly, and the United Kingdom has introduced legislation in this field in equality to prevent discrimination likewise on grounds of religion. Article 1</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7837.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7845.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>requires the state to secure the rights under the Convention to all persons. That will not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7845.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7851.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>be achieved if a whole sector of the economy is excluded. If we take the case of Arts for</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7851.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7862.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then, Lieben, I digress perhaps, you have a right to demonstrate, but other groups can appear and prevent you demonstrating. The state is under a positive obligation to enable</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7862.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7868.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>you to demonstrate or manifest your religious practice. The Convention has been applied</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7868.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7875.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in many circumstances to employment. We have Article 10 applies. There were sashes in Spain</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7875.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7880.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>where the Spanish trade union degraded their employer. They were dismissed, but Article</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7880.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7887.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>10 implied. There have been other cases involving whistleblowers. The question is, we have cases</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7887.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7896.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on Article 8, and I have mentioned Siberbos and Lithuania. We have also had Sus and Germany</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7896.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7907.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>where the court had to do an Article 8 analysis where a church dismissed an individual for having a second family. All these cases involved a Convention right in the employment nexus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7907.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7920.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is so special about a national authority saying, you have this right, we will do a proportionality analysis and judge where it is going? The only petitioning in my submission</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7920.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7931.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that should exist in the labour market is not between public and private employees, but between ideological employees and normal employees. Mr McFarland's employer is an</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7931.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7938.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>employer. He has no ideology. Perhaps a church, as in Sus's and Germany's case. Perhaps</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7938.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7942.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a political party, you have to be committed to socialist or conservative ideology. Perhaps</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7942.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7946.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Friends of the Earth, you should be committed to Friends of the Earth ideology.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7946.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7952.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The final point is conscience clauses. My learned friend Mrs Rose has read the list.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7952.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7957.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We stand by that. But we just draw one point. The exemption clauses were quite widely</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7957.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7964.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>covered, a wide range of areas including Sikh helmets, jurors and medical staff. The court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7964.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7976.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in Batanian in Armenia founded the objection to military service on an Article 9 approach There is no reason to limit that case simply to military service. What is so special about</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7976.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7981.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>military service? Many people have deeply held conscientious views on very sensitive</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7981.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7982.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>issues and none is more sensitive than the field of religion. Thank you so much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7991.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7994.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7996.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8000.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any other things to say?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8000.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8002.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yeah, Miss Eadie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8002.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8002.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8002.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8030.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just before this hearing closes, and it relates not at all to the facts or issues arising in this case, but word has reached us that this is Judge Broxer's last live UK hearing, however much his modesty may wish it, that cannot be allowed to pass without something being said on behalf of us all. I emphasise that this isn't simply me saying it, this is on behalf of all of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8030.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8037.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>us. Judge Broxer has, as the court will well know, been at the forefront of human rights development</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8040.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8053.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from its early backwater days to where it is now, at the heart of European decision making, infusing almost every decision taken by almost every public authority across Europe and beyond.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8053.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8064.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before he became a Commissioner of Human Rights, Judge Broxer had appeared in over 100 cases before the court and the Commission. He then became the European Commissioner for the United Kingdom,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8064.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8076.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was then elected to the court when the court was set up, and now fittingly, just before his retirement, is its President. All of his work on this court, certainly from the perspective of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8076.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8099.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>those who have appeared before it, has been done with intellectual rigour, with humanity, with a characteristic generosity of spirit, and the twinkle that over the years has forgiven at least my very worst points. It has also come to our attention that Judge Garlicky is to leave the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8099.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8109.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>court as well, and everything that I've said in relation to Judge Broxer of course applies equally to Judge Garlicky. We wish you both very well in whatever you choose to do hereafter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8112.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8116.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, thank you very much for these nice words.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8116.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8134.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, it's always a pleasure when such words of proper recognition arrive from our native countries, and this was a very nice accent to terminate this hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8134.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8139.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Anyway, we now come to the end of this hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8139.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8146.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8146.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8152.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on both the admissibility and merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8152.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8158.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment or, as appropriate, decision will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8158.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8163.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8163.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>8163.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
