<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>529414_18122019</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>8.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>9.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>80.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>87.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Albert and others versus Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>87.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>103.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on 10 January 2014 under Article 34 of the Convention by Mrs. Józsefné Albert and 240 other Hungarian nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>103.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>113.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the fourth section of the court pursuant to Article 52 paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>113.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>120.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on 12 September 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>120.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>135.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 4 April 2017, a chamber of the fourth section declared the case admissible and on 29 January 2019, it delivered its judgment in the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>135.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>154.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 29 April 2019, the applicants requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on 24 June 2019.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>154.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>160.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent government are represented by their agent, Mr. Zoltán Tallódi, assisted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>160.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>170.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by their co-agent, Mrs. Mónika Weller, and Mr. Tamás Kende and Mr. Pál Sonnevend, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>170.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>177.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mr. Péter Gárdos, counsel, and by Mr. Richard Mosonyi,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>177.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>183.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Dániel Karsai, and Mrs. Orsolya Csaba, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>183.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>187.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>187.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>198.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome judges of the Supreme Court of Latvia and of the Supreme Court of Justice of the Republic of Moldova who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>198.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>207.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>207.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>214.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Gárdos for the applicants will speak first and then Mr. Tallódi for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>214.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>215.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Gárdos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>222.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>225.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>225.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>232.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it is our privilege to submit our pleadings today on behalf of the 234 applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>232.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>235.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were shareholders of Kineji Bank and Mohachi Bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>235.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>238.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will refer to them as the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>238.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>252.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The legal predecessors of the banks were established 60 years ago as savings cooperatives by the local community, primarily to provide basic financial services to residents and later to finance local businesses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>252.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>264.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The assets of the savings cooperatives consisted typically of relatively small investments of members, such as the applicants in this case, who had a direct say in the operation of the savings cooperatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>264.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>272.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were not simply investors in the predecessors of the banks, but they actively took part in the operation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>272.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>282.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following the transformation of the country into a market economy in 1990, they began accumulating capital in order to transform their cooperatives into banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>282.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>287.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The transformation took place in 2006 and 2008.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>287.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>302.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In July 2013, the Hungarian Parliament passed a bill in an extraordinary two-day procedure on the forced integration of the savings cooperatives without any prior consultation of those affected by the legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>302.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>310.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Integration Act severely restricted the rights of the shareholders and deprived the banks and the savings cooperatives of their independence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>310.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>316.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They became nothing more than branches of the savings bank, the central bank of the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>316.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>325.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By the time the Integration Act entered into force, as a direct consequence of their transformation, the banks no longer belonged to the savings cooperative sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>325.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>352.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They no longer fell under the rules specific to the savings cooperatives, but under the rules pertaining to banks, the only tie they had with the savings cooperative sector was that they remain members in the voluntary institution protection scheme of the savings cooperatives, because the scheme asked them to remain members for the sole reason that the funds contributed by the predecessors of the banks would have been missing from the scheme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>352.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>363.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants always felt some responsibility for the savings cooperative sector, and as a result, they undertook to contribute financial resources to the operation of the scheme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>363.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>380.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They never imagined that this act of pure generosity would later be the reason why their banks will fall under a forced integration regime, which severely limited their rights as shareholders, and which ultimately forced them to sell their lifelong investments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>380.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>385.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We explained in our previous submissions how the Integration Act affected the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>385.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>393.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To avoid repetition, I would only highlight the following facts concerning the restrictions introduced by the Integration Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>393.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>400.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the Integration Act forced the applicant to approve new uniform articles of association.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>400.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>405.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The articles of association determines the competence of the bodies of a company.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>405.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>413.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As this document is adopted by the general meeting, the shareholders have the power to take control over any issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>413.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>417.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Integration Act eliminates this power of the general meeting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>417.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>425.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the Integration Act required the approval of the integration organization and the savings bank for every decision of the general meeting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>425.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>433.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the sake of simplicity, I will refer to the integration institution and the savings bank as the integration institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>433.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>441.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decisions requiring approval include the approval of the annual account, the election of the management, and the decision on the payment of dividend.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>441.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>450.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, the Integration Act entitled the integration institutions simply to suspend in certain circumstances the applicant's voting right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>450.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>454.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Integration Act introduced further rules that were very onerous to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>454.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>456.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will name three examples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>456.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>465.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, contrary to the government's arguments, the conditions based on which the integration institutions were allowed to exercise their rights were not defined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>465.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>475.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By way of example, the Integration Act contained no conditions regarding the content of the article of association or the approval of the annual reports of the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>475.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>482.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whereas in other cases, the conditions were to be set out in rules defined by the integration institutions themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>482.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>495.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the Integration Act provided that the sanction of noncompliance is the exclusion from the integration, which practically would have meant the withdrawal of the bank's licenses and the liquidation of the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>495.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>499.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Liquidation inevitably leads to a significant loss for the shareholders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>499.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>512.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The figures relating to Kineji Bank, referred to by the government in its observations, support this as it shows that in case of liquidation of Kineji Bank, the value of the bank would have been minus 1.5 billion forints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>512.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>522.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third, the government argues that if the applicants believed that remaining in the integration was not beneficial to them, they could have simply left the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>522.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>533.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the government fails to mention that the condition for leaving the integration was that the shareholders pay an additional 3 to 4 billion forint as capital to the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>533.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>542.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the sake of comparison, this amount exceeds the funds the predecessors of the banks accumulated over 50 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>542.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>546.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This condition, therefore, in practice, made an exit impossible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>546.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>549.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What was the effect of these rules?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>549.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>560.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Investors typically invest in companies because they believe that the company is managed properly, therefore they believe that the company will pay dividend to its shareholders and the value of their shares will be maintained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>560.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>572.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They know, furthermore, that if the company is not managed properly, the management will be hosted and replaced by better managers and that they can easily exit their investments by selling their shares.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>572.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>576.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Integration Act effectively extinguished these rights in relation to the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>576.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>584.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a consequence of the legislation, the shareholders no longer had the unrestricted right to pay dividend to elect the management of the bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>584.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>591.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was clear to any potential investor that even the remaining limited shareholder rights can further be restricted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>591.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>598.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, that the integration will lead to the termination of the banks and the creation of a new commercial bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>598.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>608.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is easy to understand, therefore, that under such circumstances, no investor decided to enter the market, nobody wished to acquire the applicant's shares.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>608.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>623.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, when it became clear that the applicants will not approve the final merger of the savings cooperatives that finally took place on 31 October 2019, an exit possibility was finally provided to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>623.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>635.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the applicants' rights were severely infringed and they otherwise would not have been able to leave the forced integration, the applicants had no other option but to accept the offer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>635.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>644.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As this Court stated several times, not only specific measures, but a law itself may also violate the Convention, irrespective of its application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>644.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>651.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The subject matter of this procedure is, therefore, not one or more individual acts of the integration institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>651.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>657.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants claim that the Integration Act itself infringed the rights of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>657.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>661.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We claim, let me now turn to the question of victim status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>661.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>670.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We claim that the Integration Act infringed the rights of the applicants as it restricted their voting rights, thereby fatally distorting the market in the shares.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>670.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>674.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as a consequence, the applicants' right to sell was also infringed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>674.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>688.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To better understand how the restrictions of the Integration Act infringed the rights of the shareholders, it is useful to start by explaining that the general meeting of the company has a dual role, and therefore, its character is also twofold.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>688.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>707.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the one hand, this is the supreme organ of the company responsible for making decisions, whereas on the other hand, it is also the forum of the shareholders where they discuss and decide on issues of common interest where they cast their vote, through which they exert their influence on the operation of the company.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>707.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>709.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me now turn to the right to vote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>709.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>720.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The right to vote means that the shareholders can participate in the meeting and freely decide whether to support a proposal or not, knowing that their vote shall have an effect on the company.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>720.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>734.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government's argument seems to suggest that forcing the shareholder to support a proposal by threatening with sanctions or overwriting the decisions of the shareholders does not affect the individual right of the shareholder.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>734.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>743.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that this is an extremely formalistic understanding of the shareholder's voting right, which is an essential element of the shareholder rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>743.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>759.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By way of analogy, it is useful to recall that a citizen's right to vote at a national election is violated not only if the citizen is not allowed to cast a vote, but also if the vote cost is not taken into account, or if the citizen is forced to vote in a particular way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>759.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>767.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In such a case, although the citizen could still go into the polling booth and cast her vote, the citizen's right is still restricted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>767.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>784.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As this court formulated it in the Risa and others versus Bulgaria case, the vote of each elector must have the possibility of affecting the composition of the legislator, otherwise the right to vote, and ultimately the democratic order itself would be devoid of substance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>784.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>788.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I argue that the above circumstances are analogous to the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>788.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>800.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the field of business entities, if the general meeting of the company becomes in many respects important, the shareholder's right to participate and vote in the general meetings becomes a mere formality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>800.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>810.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such a situation therefore infringes the property rights of the shareholders, irrespective of the fact whether or not the particular shareholder was a controlling shareholder.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>812.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>818.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The infringement of the applicant's right to vote, as I explained, led to the result that the shares lost their value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>818.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>821.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the shareholder's right to sell was also infringed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>821.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>825.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such loss is not the consequence of unsuccessful operation of the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>825.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>835.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rather, these losses were foreseeable, inevitable, and might also add intended consequences of the restrictions introduced by the Integration Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>835.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>841.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe therefore that the Integration Act violated the rights of the applicants as shareholders of the bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>841.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>853.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In case the court would find that the rules of the Integration Act that I referred to previously only infringed the rights of the banks, but not the applicants, we submit that in this case, the court should lift the corporate wheel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>853.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>864.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although we are aware that a company's legal personality could be disregarded only in exceptional cases, we argue that in the present case, there are grave facts which justify the lifting of the corporate wheel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>864.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>870.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the applicants own almost 100% of the shares of the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>870.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>878.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court has already acknowledged that 90% shareholding may have a relevance relating to the piercing of the corporate wheel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>878.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>889.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question in this case is therefore whether this court finds a difference between one shareholder holding 90% or several applicants having the same 90% relevant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>889.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>892.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We argue that this difference is irrelevant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>892.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>900.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants who together hold a very significant stake in the company whose rights are infringed should also be provided with the right to turn to this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>900.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>911.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second exceptional circumstance is that, although theoretically the banks would have been able to apply to the court, it is easy to understand why this could not reasonably have been expected from the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>911.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>915.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The integration institutions drew the management of the banks under strict control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>915.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>928.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The management of the banks was criticized by the integration institutions for resisting and obstructing the procedure established by the Integration Act, in particular for seeking remedy at the Hungarian Constitutional Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>928.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>933.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The integration institutions could easily have forced the management to withdraw their application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>933.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>956.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, I recall the case of Credit and Industrial Bank versus the Czech Republic, in which the court applied a strict test of impossibility established in the Agrotechs in case in a more practical way, emphasizing the need to interpret Article 34 of the Convention in a more practical and effective way, as opposed to purely theoretical and illusory guarantee of the rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>956.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>966.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the court under the present circumstances required that the complaint is filed by the banks and not the applicants, the shareholders would be left without effective legal protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>966.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>974.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I shall briefly turn to the government's argument regarding the question by the applicants have not lost their victim status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>974.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>989.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the established practice of the court, an applicant is deprived of the victim status only if the national authorities have acknowledged, either expressly or in substance, the breach of the Convention, and then afforded redress for the breach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>989.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>997.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, it is undisputed that neither of these conditions is met, which in itself shows that the applicant's victim status is not lost.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>997.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1003.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the sake of completeness, I would also respond in some detail to the allegations of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1003.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1010.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first argument of the government is that the victim status was lost as the Integration Act is no longer applicable to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1010.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1030.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This argument fails to recognize, however, that before the applicants were provided with an exit right, they had to endure the violation of their rights for several years, and furthermore, they also had to accept that they ceased to be owners of the banks that they themselves or their ancestors established, and for which they have made sacrifices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1030.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1037.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second argument of the government is that the consideration that the applicants received provided adequate redress for them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1037.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1045.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants certainly accept that the amounts received should be taken into account when deciding about the amount of the just satisfaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1045.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1055.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These amounts, however, do not have any effect in relation to their victim status or the legality of the impugned legislation for the following reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1055.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1065.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government notes that the fact that the bank's valuation for 2013 exceeded zero shows that the applicants falsely argue that their shares lost their value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1065.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1070.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government's argument is clearly wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1070.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1076.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The valuation was prepared by the applicants for the purposes of the present procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1076.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1081.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The valuation, therefore, does not take into account the effects of the Integration Act itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1081.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1089.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the fact that the valuation showed that the bank's head value does not in any way support the government's arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1089.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1091.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government further argues that the 2.1 billion</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1091.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1099.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>foreign dividend in case of Mohajibank and the 300 million foreign dividend in case of Kinijibank should also be taken into account.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1099.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1101.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This argument is also wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1101.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1111.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As these dividends related to earnings accumulated before the entry into force of the Integration Act, the source of the dividend was not included in our valuation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1111.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1115.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would, therefore, be wrong to deduct this dividend once again from the valuation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1115.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1120.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Summarizing these arguments, we submit that the applicants have standing in this procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1120.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1125.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I will turn to the question of unjustified interference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1125.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1130.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not disputed between the parties that there was an interference with the applicant's right to property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1130.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1137.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we have explained in our submissions, the interference qualifies as deprivation of property or at least control of use.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1137.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1146.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whichever is the correct characterization of the state's interference with the applicant's rights, the requirements laid down in Article 1 of Protocol Number 1 apply.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1146.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1158.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the impugned legislation violates the convention unless it serves the public interest, it complies with the requirements of the rule of law, and it is proportionate and provides adequate compensations for the victims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1158.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1163.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our position is that the Integration Act fails to meet any of these requirements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1163.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1173.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Concerning the question of public interest, the government argues that the Integration Act was necessary to protect the depositors and investors and to ensure profitable operation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1173.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1182.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, I will explain that these reasons, even if they were valid in relation to the savings cooperative sector, do not apply to the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1182.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1188.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then I will also show that the alleged reasons are also wrong in relation to the savings cooperative sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1188.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1196.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When the Integration Act was introduced, as I explained, the applicants were shareholders of the banks and not of savings cooperatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1196.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1207.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government never contested that the banks operated profitably, complying with the statutory capital requirements, maintaining at all times their solvency and liquidity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1207.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1216.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government argues that the banks fell under the scope of the Integration Act because it was unavoidable to extend the scope of the legislation to the banks for two reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1216.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1225.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, because the banks were members of voluntary institution protection scheme, and second, because they had other strong ties to the sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1225.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1227.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me now turn to the first argument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1227.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1237.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The starting point is that the predecessors of the banks and the banks themselves were free to leave the voluntary institution protection scheme before the introduction of the Integration Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1237.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1246.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was absolutely no legal necessity to extend the scope of the Integration Act to the banks, which is clearly supported by the following facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1246.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1254.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the joint and several liability among the members of the integration was only introduced about a year after the new rules entered into force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1254.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1261.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The joint and several liability would not cover institutions who exited the integration in this period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1261.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1270.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, not all institutions who were previously members of the voluntary institution protection scheme became members of the new integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1270.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1274.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the Integration Act was not applicable to six savings cooperatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1274.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1280.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, Széchenyi Bank was also exempted, even though it was also a member of the voluntary institution protection scheme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1280.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1293.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And furthermore, the integration institutions themselves excluded from the integration four savings cooperatives that were in difficult financial position before the joint and several liability entered into force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1293.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1302.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These examples show that contrary to the government's allegations, it would have been possible both legally and technically to exclude the banks from the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1302.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1312.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, these special treatments not only prove the lack of public interest, but they also show that the personal scope of the Integration Act was defined arbitrarily.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1312.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1315.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the Integration Act was discriminatory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1315.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1324.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second argument of the government, according to which the banks were included in the integration as they had strong ties to the sector, is also not convincing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1324.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1336.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The banks, based on their free choice, considering the reasonable price offered, used some services of the saving bank and other service providers who also provided services to the savings cooperatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1336.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1350.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is difficult to see, however, how the fact that, for example, the banks use the same provider of IT or cash transportation services as some other savings cooperatives would make it inevitable to force them into the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1350.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1362.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The banks were not in a position that would have required any kind of state intervention, and the government failed to give any convincing argument why it was unavoidable to include the banks in the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1362.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1367.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, in respect of the banks, the Integration Act served no public interest at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1367.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1375.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me now summarize why the government's arguments supporting public interest in relation to the savings cooperatives are also without merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1375.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1378.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let us focus first on the profitability argument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1378.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1381.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our position is that this argument is wrong for two reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1381.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1387.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the government failed to prove that the savings cooperative sector was not operating profitably.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1387.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1398.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we have proved in our submissions in 2011 and 2012, the last two years before the integration, the losses of the commercial bank exceeded 400 billion forint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1398.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1402.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the same years, the savings cooperative sector operated profitably.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1402.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1412.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, we deny the government's claim that the more effective and profitable operation of the private entities in itself qualifies as public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1412.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1415.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This justifies state interference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1415.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1430.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is in particular the case in the savings cooperative sector where although efficiency is an important requirement, the main objective is to serve the residents even if they are not wealthy and educated enough to use the more sophisticated banking services.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1430.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1436.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second argument of the government is that the depositors of the savings cooperatives were in danger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1436.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1447.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before showing that this argument is unfounded, it is important to highlight that the problems referred to by the government have only been identified after the Integration Act entered into force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1447.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1455.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, potential problems not yet even identified logically could not have served as the basis for the legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1455.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1467.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government supports its position primarily by referring to the fact that out of 117 savings cooperatives, four did not meet the capital requirements in 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1467.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1471.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, these cases actually contradict the government's argument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1471.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1476.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the losses of these savings cooperatives arose out of grave misconducts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1476.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1484.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is clearly supported by the fact that several criminal procedures were launched in relation to the activities of some of these institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1484.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1488.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such reckless behavior has never been typical at the savings cooperatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1488.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1493.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, it is groundless to make any general conclusion with respect to the sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1493.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1504.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To provide perspective for comparison, within the 20 years of the operation of the Voluntary Institution Protection Scheme, no savings cooperative belonging to the scheme became insolvent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1504.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1514.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, it is particularly striking that the four savings cooperatives which served as the raison d'etre of the integration were excluded from it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1514.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1520.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These cases, therefore, cannot support that the impugned legislation served the public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1520.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1527.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government further tries to support the necessity of the impugned measures by the results of the audits completed following the adoption of the Integration Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1527.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1537.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government reports that as a result of the audit, almost two-thirds of the savings cooperatives were obliged to increase their reserves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1537.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1557.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government, however, fails to mention that these institutions complied with the instructions received from the integration institutions and provided the missing capital from their own funds, and it was necessary to provide additional funds only in respect of three savings cooperatives in the total amount of 1.7 billion forint,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1557.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1563.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>less than 1% of the solvency capital of the savings cooperatives falling under the scope of the Integration Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1563.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1577.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This example clearly shows that in general, these institutions were sufficiently capitalized, and what was needed is not the reorganizations of the saving cooperative sector, but rather the strengthening of the state supervision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1577.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1581.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In summary, we argued that the interference was not based on public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1581.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1587.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One might, therefore, ask what the real reason for the brutal interference was.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1587.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1590.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This brings us to the third argument of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1590.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1596.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also argues that one of the purposes of the integration was the protection of investors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1596.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1604.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, this argument is nothing more than a severe insult on the applicants and all other ex-members of the savings cooperatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1604.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1617.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result of first acquiring majority state ownership in the savings bank and control of the integration institutions, and then reprivatization, the shareholders of the savings cooperatives have been swept out of the sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1617.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1632.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Integration Act was used as a tool to ensure that the savings cooperatives and some banks carefully cherished by the state and the integration institutions are merged into a single commercial bank controlled by a handful of selected new owners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1632.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1649.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government's goal has already been announced in July 2013 in a speech of the Prime Minister when he said that the purpose of the government with the restructuring of the savings cooperative sector is to create a market participant that can be measured to OTP, the largest Hungarian bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1649.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1669.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not surprisingly, with the mergers on the 31st of October 2019, the savings bank became the fifth largest bank in Hungary and the CEO of the bank announced earlier that with further mergers, the goal is to create the second largest Hungarian bank without whether creating a competitor to another bank could qualify as public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1669.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1687.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More importantly, as Professor Kish judged the Hungarian Constitutional Court in his dissenting opinion stated, the Integration Act makes it clear that the confiscation was executed not with a view to public interest, but for the benefit and in the interest of private individuals through the state as intermediary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1687.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1699.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before the Integration Act entered into force, the savings cooperative sector had 150,000 owners and the savings cooperatives had majority stake in the savings bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1699.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1703.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under the new regime, there are no savings cooperatives anymore.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1703.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1707.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The previous owners of the absorbed institutions have lost any control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1707.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1718.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to newspaper articles and company documents, the savings bank has three dominant owners and all assets of the extinguished savings cooperatives are owned in majority by the savings bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1718.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1729.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is common knowledge that the three owners are all government-friendly investors who have an established status in the new economic elite established after the 2010 re-election of Mr. Orbán,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1729.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1731.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Hungarian Prime Minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1731.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1738.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should the court find that the interference still served public interest, I will now argue that it was not proportionate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1738.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1746.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court stated in several cases that it is not for the court to say whether a legislation represents the best solution for dealing with a problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1746.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1752.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the court always said that this does not give an absolute exemption from the scrutiny of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1752.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1760.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court may find that the interference was disproportionate if the legislator did not remain within the bounds of its margin of appreciation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1760.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1765.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We respectfully submit that the government in this case failed to remain within these bounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1765.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1769.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We ask this court to find that the interference was disproportionate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1769.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1771.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will give three reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1771.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1776.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the government failed to prove that it carried out any kind of balancing test.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1776.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1780.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the government could have applied less intrusive measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1780.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1791.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the years preceding the Integration Act, the Voluntary Institution Protection Scheme, with the support of the Banking Supervisory Authority, effectively assisted the consolidation of the sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1791.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1801.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this process, in every region, the biggest and most efficient institutions absorbed those, the efficient operation of which on the longer term did not seem assured.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1801.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1804.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Similar methods were used in other European countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1804.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1819.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are not aware of any European country where the original owners lost their rights as a consequence of direct state intervention, where even the technical details are included in acts so that no legal remedy would remain available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1819.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1834.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The safety and effectiveness of the sector could have been significantly improved by measures such as further increasing the competence and resources of the Voluntary Institution Protection Scheme and strengthening the supervision of the institutions in the savings cooperative sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1834.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1848.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These measures would have resulted in the strengthening of the protection of depositors and also in the increasing of the efficiency of the sector without interfering with the property rights of the members or the shareholders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1848.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1858.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our third reason concerning the lack of proportionality is that contrary to the government's allegations, neither the applicants nor the bank benefited from the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1858.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1860.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just to give two examples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1860.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1871.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first example is that the 136 billion foreign state funds to which the government referred only ensured that the state acquired 99.75% share</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1871.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1877.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in the integration organization, but never provided any benefits to the banks or the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1877.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1884.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second example shows that contrary to the government's arguments, all benefits of the integration were allocated to the savings bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1884.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1889.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is clear if we compare the average earnings before and after the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1889.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1904.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Comparing the years 2010, 2012 to the years 2014 and 2018, the earnings of Kineji Bank decreased by almost 90% and the earnings of Mohachi Bank decreased by 64%.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1904.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1909.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the earnings of the savings bank increased by 1000%.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1909.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1914.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If we compare 2012 to 2018, the increase is 4000%.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1915.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1922.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that all benefits of the integration was allocated to a well-chosen small circle of shareholders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1922.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1927.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To conclude, the question this court needs to answer is a very simple one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1927.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1940.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the absence of legitimate public interest, does the fact that the applicants' voting rights were severely restricted, and as a consequence, the share lost their value, qualify as an infringement of Article 1 of Protocol No. 1</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1940.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1941.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the Convention?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1941.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1944.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We respectfully submit that it does.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1944.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1950.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we ask the court to establish that the Integration Act violated the rights of the applicants and to afford just satisfaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1950.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1950.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1958.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1959.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1959.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1961.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call now Mr. Tallódi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1961.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1961.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1972.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1973.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1973.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1976.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable members of the Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1976.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1987.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ladies and gentlemen, it's a privilege and an honor to appear before the Court and set out the position of the Government of Hungary in this seemingly complicated but ultimately rather clear case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1987.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2000.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case concerns a legislative reform affecting the financial sector of Hungary in the aftermath of 2009 global financial crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2000.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2023.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This reform, initiating a process of integration of cooperative credit institutions, had the purpose to ensure the stable and profitable operation of a financial sector comprised of 121 cooperative credit institutions, following well-known models of integration of savings cooperatives and in accordance with the relevant European Union law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2023.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2046.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>EU legislation were decisive in shaping the reform as they require for an integration of financial institutions the power of instruction by the central body vis-à-vis the affiliated institutions, the joint and several liability of the members, and the joint monitoring of the solvency and liquidity of the central body, and of all the affiliated institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2046.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2057.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reform was considered essential to enhance financing for enterprises and consumers in smaller towns and villages where cooperative credit institutions mostly operate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2057.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2080.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the following, I shall first address the scope of the case and then argue that the applicants lack victim status or in any event they have lost their locus tandi on behalf of the affected companies as a result of voluntarily selling their shares in Moacibank or by the selling of a part of the portfolio of Kinezibank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2080.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2094.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the alternative, I shall argue that even if the applicants could be considered as victims, the integration act did not constitute deprivation of property as alleged by the applicants, but a measure of control of use of property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2094.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2109.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, this interference was justified by important public interests and was proportionate in view of the significant financial contribution of the state to the integration of cooperative credit institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2109.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2126.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the scope of the case, the measures complained of are certain provisions of act, number 135 of 2013, on the integration of cooperative credit institutions, the so-called integration act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2126.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2131.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The complaint is not about their application, but about their very existence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2131.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2145.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants did not complain of any specific measures taken on the basis of the integration act, but claimed that they had been deprived of their property by virtue of the entry into force of the integration act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2145.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2151.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They alluded that the measures complained of amounted to confiscation of their possessions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2151.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2173.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it must be borne in mind that the possessions they had allegedly been deprived of in 2013 consisted of shares in their banks operating in the cooperative credit sector, which yielded them about 3.5 billion forints in dividends between 2014</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2173.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2186.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and 2016, and which they later sold for 4 billion forints altogether, while still retaining a company with a value of 2.9 billion forints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2186.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2202.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a quite significant profit from a property the applicants have allegedly no longer had since 2013, or it is a clear indication that the applicants' allegations of interference with their right to property are manifestly untrue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2202.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2205.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2205.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2223.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the integration act affected cooperative credit institutions, that is, corporate entities, yet the applications the court is dealing with today were submitted by a group of shareholders of two such financial institutions, Mohachi Bank and Kinezhi Bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2223.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2231.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government of Hungary agrees with the findings of the judgment of the chamber that the applicants lack victim status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2231.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2240.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are basically two main reasons why the applicants could not be regarded as victims of the alleged violations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2240.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2250.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the applicants complain of certain provisions of the integration act in the abstract, and not the application of these provisions to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2250.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2259.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the present application is in essence an actio popularis, which is not admissible under article 34 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2259.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2265.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants complain that the ownership structure in the cooperative credit sector was altered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2265.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2270.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, these changes did not affect their ownership in their banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2270.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2277.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They complain that shareholders of the savings bank were obliged to sell certain type of shares.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2277.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2285.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the applicants were not shareholders of the savings bank and did not own that particular type of shares.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2285.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2297.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They complain that the shares obtained by the state, not from the applicants, were later sold to a rival private company and not to the applicants' banks and their partners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2297.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2302.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the convention doesn't grant the right to obtain property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2302.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2306.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It only requires that existing possessions be respected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2306.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2313.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The transaction complained of did not affect the applicants' possessions as shareholders of their banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2313.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2318.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They might as well claim to have been affected by such transaction as taxpayers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2318.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2328.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the state budget is not covered by the notion of possessions within the meaning of article 1 of protocol number 1 to the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2328.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2343.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The above are examples of allegations about effects of the integration act, which are essentially true, but did not directly affect the applicants' possessions and therefore cannot serve as a ground for recognizing their victim status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2343.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2348.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, the applicants also made some allegations which are untrue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2348.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2364.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Contrary to the applicants' allegations, none of the impugned provisions provided for the loss of any competence of the general meeting of their banks, nor can we talk about total control of their activities, as the applicants suggest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2364.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2381.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead of a direct interference, as the applicants suggest, the respective provisions of the integration act provided for the possibility of interference by the integration organization or the savings bank with certain decisions of the general meetings of the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2381.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2392.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In accordance with EU legislation, the central body of the integration has the power of supervision and instruction vis-a-vis the affiliated institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2392.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2399.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Like, as the constitutional court's decision also referred to its powers, a quasi-administrative authority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2399.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2418.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The designation of the savings bank as the central bank of the integration and not the base bank, as the applicants have chosen to translate it, clearly shows that the savings bank had tasks and powers in respect of the members of the integration, similar than the central bank of Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2418.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2424.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Hungarian National Bank has, in respect of financial institutions outside the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2424.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2436.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With the difference that unlike the applicants' banks at the general meeting of the savings bank, normally banks have no say at all in the functioning of the central bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2436.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2461.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It seems to be the right place here to note that the integration act provided for exactly those enhanced supervisory powers in respect of the applicants' banks, notably the decisions of the general meeting of the shareholders, which the applicants claim in their observations to should have sufficed as less intrusive measures to ensure the future stability of the sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2461.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2473.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows that as far as the measures affecting the powers of the general meeting of the shareholders are concerned, the applicants accepted their necessity and proportionality in their observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2473.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2499.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in spite of the fact that the provisions governing the powers of the integration institutions indeed had relevance for the operation of the general meetings of the applicants' banks, the applicants still cannot claim to be victims of an interference with the right to property as shareholders of their banks simply on account of the entry into force of the integration act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2499.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2517.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is so because besides the reasons connected with the issue of corporate veil, which I shall elaborate upon later, the provisions of the integration act had no direct effect on the functioning of the general meetings, but further measures were needed to put them into effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2517.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2523.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These measures were specifically excluded by the applicants from the scope of the application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2523.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2534.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Had it not been so, their case probably would have failed to meet the requirement of exhaustion of domestic remedies in addition to their lack of victim status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2534.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2557.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The abundance or confusion of possible grounds for inadmissibility at this juncture proves exactly the point raised by the court's judgment in the case of Agrotexim, cited in the government's written observations about the practical difficulties ensuing from the piercing of the corporate veil as regards the requirement of exhaustion of domestic remedies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2557.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2573.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the decisions of the integration organization and the savings bank taken pursuant to the integration act may be challenged through different remedies before the Hungarian courts as it is required in the case of the decisions of administrative authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2573.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2589.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only after the organs of the integration have taken certain decisions and the banks have exhausted the available remedies could it be assessed whether there was an interference with the rights of the banks and eventually of the shareholders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2589.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2603.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To be more specific, most powers of the integration organization and the savings bank, the applicants complain of has not even been exercised at all in relation to Mohachi Bank or Kennedy Bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2603.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2615.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither the integration organization nor the savings bank denied the issuing of bonds, any merger or demerger of the respective banks or the purchase of all shares.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2615.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2624.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nor did they suspend or terminate the office of chief officers or suspend the voting rights of the shareholders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2624.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2629.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, the application seems to be of the nature of an actio popularis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2629.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2649.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relation to the power of the integration organization and the savings bank to adopt a model statute or articles of association, it needs to be noted that cooperative credit institutions did have the right to comment on the model statute and to propose changes to the articles of association as they were adopted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2649.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2658.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This, in fact, happened in the case of Mohachi Bank, where Mohachi Bank proposed several changes that were accepted by the savings bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2658.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2666.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result, Mohachi Bank adopted new articles of association on the 17th of December, 2015, in agreement with the savings bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2666.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2686.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, if shareholders of Mohachi Bank suffered any infringement of the rights protected by the convention, such infringement only occurred with the adoption of the new articles of association, which could have been subject to remedies by the shareholders under Hungarian law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2686.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2692.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kinezsi Bank has never adopted new articles of association in accordance with the Integration Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2692.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2721.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this context, it must also be noted that the provisions of the model articles of association complained of by the applicants in their observations before the ground chamber, which were later elevated to the level of binding legal provisions, contained rules aimed at ensuring access by the central bank of the integration to the information necessary for the effective exercise of the supervisory powers conferred upon it by the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2721.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2731.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such provisions don't exceed the scope of ordinary regulation powers of the state and cannot be challenged in abstracto before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2731.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2741.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants also argue in their submission to the ground chamber that the integration institution refused the payment of the dividends by the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2741.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2768.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although these allegations fall outside the scope of the case, since such refusal would be a specific measure excluded by the applicants from the scope of their application and did not happen by virtue of the entry into force of the Integration Act, the government informed the court that in reality, the dividends had been paid to the shareholders of both Moaci Bank and Kinezhi Bank, irrespective of the disapproval of the savings bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2768.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2797.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it is shown by the document submitted by the government, the savings bank refused to approve the annual report of Kinezhi Bank in 2015, and for the same reasons in 2016, because Kinezhi Bank did not make it possible to carry out an audit by the audit firm responsible for carrying out a consolidated audit for the whole integration, and it decided to pay dividends, even though this could have potentially jeopardized the solvency of the bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2797.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2816.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the savings bank disapproved of the payment of dividends by Kinezhi Bank, since the legal conditions for such payments set out in the law applicable to the entire financial sector, not specific to the cooperative credit sector, had not been met.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2816.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2824.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the savings bank's disapproval didn't have any effect on the payment of dividends, which had already taken place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2824.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2833.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was then for the savings bank to institute court proceedings challenging the resolutions of the general meeting of Kinezhi Bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2833.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2839.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These proceedings were discontinued after transformation of the Kinezhi Bank into an investment company.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2839.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2852.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The aggregate amount of dividends paid by Moaci Bank between 2014 and 2016 amounted to 2.77 billion Hungarian forints,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2852.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2864.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>whereas shareholders of Kinezhi Bank received dividends as much as 769 million Hungarian forints between 2014 and 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2864.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2882.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second reason for the lack of victim status follows from the fact that the measures taken pursuant to the impugn provisions of the Integration Act could have affected the margin of maneuvering of the general meeting of the banks and not the shareholders' rights vis-a-vis their company.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2882.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2889.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the rights of the bank and not those of the shareholders would have been affected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2889.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2902.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The shareholders, either a majority of shareholders or all of them, cannot identify with the company which has a legal personality distinct from its owners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2902.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2920.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The actions of the shareholders taken through the general meeting are, for all intents and purposes, attributable to the company, and it is the company that bears civil law liability for the decisions of the general meeting and not the individual shareholders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2920.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2940.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the corporate entities directly or potentially affected by the impugn legislation were functioning with full legal capacity at the time of the filing of the present application, there are no exceptional circumstances in the present case justifying the disregarding of the legal personality of Mohatchi and Kenezi banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2940.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2946.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no exceptional circumstances justifying the piercing of the corporate way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2946.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2961.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government recalled the well-established case law of the court, concordant with the jurisprudence of the International Court of Justice, that the concept of the public company is founded on a firm distinction between the rights of the company and those of its shareholders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2961.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2967.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only the company, endowed with the legal personality, can take action in respect of corporate matters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2967.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2978.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A wrong done to the company can indirectly cause prejudice to its shareholders, but this does not imply that both are entitled to claim compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2978.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2987.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whenever a shareholder's interests are armed by a measure directed at the company, it is up to the latter to take appropriate actions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2987.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2996.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An act infringing only the company's rights does not involve responsibility towards the shareholders, even if their interests are affected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2996.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3008.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such responsibility arises only if the act complained of is aimed at the rights of the shareholders as such, or if the company has been wound up.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3008.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3018.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants in this case have not put forward any reasonable explanation as to why their banks had failed to submit the present application themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3018.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3028.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither could they prove, for it was not so, that the banks had been in any way hindered by the law or by the authorities' actions to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3028.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3050.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To paraphrase the court's findings in Agripexim, there is no evidence to suggest that at the material time, it would have been impossible as a matter of fact or a flaw for the organs set up under the Articles of Association of the Applicants' Companies to seek protection of their rights before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3050.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3057.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the relevant period, both banks did take part in domestic legal proceedings with full legal capacity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3057.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3070.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There may be two equally possible reasons for the individual shareholders being the applicants in this case, instead of the banks on whose behalf they complain of the introduction of the Integration Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3070.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3072.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It might have been an error.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3072.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3078.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, it is not for the court to rectify this error by departing from its well-established case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3078.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3092.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The principle of effective legal protection cannot be interpreted as proposed by the applicants to the effect of disregarding any and all of the admissibility criteria set forth in the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3092.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3106.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, the choice of putting the shareholders in the position of applicants instead of the banks themselves might as well have been a deliberately calculated move to obscure the facts of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3106.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3125.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For if the applicants had been the banks themselves, the focus on the case would have quickly shifted to the banks' gains from the integration, and the numbers would have spoken loudly for themselves, far from having suffered any loss of the value of their shares in the savings bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3125.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3133.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants' banks benefited from a significant increase of the dividends paid for their shares in the savings bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3133.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3148.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While in 2013 and 2014, the dividends paid to the shareholders of the savings bank amounted to 3.55% and 7.45%, respectively,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3148.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3168.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of the normal value of the shares in 2015 and 2016 after the raise of the savings bank's capital by the contested measures, the dividends paid amounted to 48% and 65% of the nominal value of the shares.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3168.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3181.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The dividends obtained in the three years following the entry into force of the contested measures altogether were 10 times higher than in the prior three years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3181.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3202.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This significant increase in profits in itself proves that the contested measures successfully fulfilled their purpose of increasing the profitability of the cooperative credit sector and provided sufficient compensation for any actual or perceived loss of influence over the management of this sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3202.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3222.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That being said, even if the applicants could have claimed low custody before the court to complain of the prejudice allegedly suffered by their banks on account of the entry into force of the Integration Act, they lost their low custody as a result of voluntary transactions they entered into following the filing of their application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3222.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3241.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All shareholders of Mohatchi Bank, including the applicants, sold their shares to the savings bank and Kinezhi Bank with consent by the general meeting of the shareholders, transferred its contract portfolio to B3 Takareg Sovetkazet, and now operates as an investment company.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3241.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3248.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a result, the applicants hold no shares in any bank that would be subject to the provisions of the Integration Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3248.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3258.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the applicants can no longer claim to represent the banks formerly affected on account of having an economic interest in them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3258.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3274.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, the fact that the applicants have made a considerable income from these transactions prove that the complaints concerning the alleged deprivation of property, whoever the victim of the impugned measures was, were manifestly ill-founded from the outset.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3274.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3278.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3278.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3283.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the efforts that make it abundantly clear that the applications are inadmissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3283.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3313.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, should the court piercing the corporate veil without exceptional reasons, leaving out of consideration the line between the individual applications and actio popularis and the requirement of exhaustion of domestic remedies, grant locus tendi to the applicants, and find that there was an interference with the right to property, the government argued that such interference pursued an important public interest and was proportionate to this public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3313.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3326.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The interference was affected in the general interest to ensure a more effective, secure, and profitable operation of the banking sector, with special emphasis on providing proper financial services in rural areas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3326.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3351.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition to the fact that the low capitalization of saving cooperatives led them to limit their lending activity and to substantially invest in state bonds and other low-risk forms of investments, thereby not providing services much needed for the development of rural areas, small size and low capitalization of savings cooperatives presented a twofold risk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3351.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3366.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the relatively small saving cooperatives did not always have proper risk assessment mechanisms to assess the actual risk of a transaction, and thus capital adequacy ratios were often calculated on the basis of the unsound estimates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3366.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3373.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These were the estimates the applicants relied on in contesting the necessity of the interference by the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3373.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3386.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In reality, an audit carried out by the independent audit firms showed that equity of the whole sector were more than 55 billion Hungarian forints, less than indicated in the balance sheets.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3386.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3397.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, already a limited number of larger scale loan defaults could pose a significant risk in view of the low capitalization of saving cooperatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3397.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3405.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These risks were demonstrated by the bankruptcy of two saving cooperatives in 2011 and in 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3405.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3411.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More bankruptcies could have followed had it not been for the measures introduced by the Integration Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3411.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3430.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Integration Act attempted to address the deficiencies of the highly important cooperative credit institutions to ensure the sustainability and profitability of these financial institutions, and through this to assist economic recovery by enhanced lending activity in small towns and the countryside.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3430.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3438.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These economic goals are sufficient to justify the state interference with the operation of the financial market.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3438.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3447.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>States enjoy a wide margin of appreciation in the field of regulation of the use of property in accordance with their economic policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3447.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3476.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Contrary to the applicant's allegations, the general interest referred to in Article 1 of Protocol Number 1 to the Convention does not have to confirm to a pressing social need as required under Article 8 to 11 of the Convention, and no deprivation of property took place either, which would have arguably had to be justified by a stronger public interest than the realization of an economic policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3476.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3496.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the complex aims of the Integration Act did include the protection of the rights of others in response to a pressing social need, while some measures simply pursued social and economic goals which governments are free to set in the general interest in the framework of their economic policies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3496.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3500.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not for this Court to review these policies in the abstract.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3500.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3506.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It can only assess the effects of specific measures on the applicant's rights in concreto.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3506.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3511.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the applicants don't contest the effects of specific measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3511.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3516.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such measures were specifically excluded from the scope of their application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3516.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3530.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the applicant's arguments contesting the general interest behind the adoption of the Integration Act, the government noted that the exclusion of certain financial institutions from the integration is no proof of the applicant's allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3530.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3543.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reasons for exclusion of some banks from the scope of the Integration Act by the legislator had been examined and upheld by the Constitutional Court in its decision number 20 of 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3543.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3556.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Later decisions by the integration authorities were based on an individual assessment of the situation of each institution concerned as well as of the possible effects of their failures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3556.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3598.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As an example shown by the document submitted to the Court, Széchenyi Credit Cooperative was excluded after having found that, one, it had acted rather irresponsible in the past despite any warnings by the supervisory authorities, and two, it provided services only to its members or owners, three, whose claims as depositors were covered by the General Insurance Fund, and thus, four, its failure would have no serious effect, five, whereas the integration's aim was not to protect the imprudent owners of cooperative credit institutions but the depositors and the prudent investors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3598.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3619.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The exclusion of such institutions from the integration also served the applicant's interests directly and indirectly, since thereby the losses of these institutions did not diminish the profits of the cooperative credit sector, more specifically the savings bank, which thus could pay higher dividends to the applicant's banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3619.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3624.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, these measures served the applicant's interests as much as the general interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3624.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3642.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not only was the reform pursuing the public interest in relation to stabilizing and intensifying the activity of cooperative credit institutions, it also contained a significant element of compensation, which ultimately rendered any interference proportionate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3642.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3660.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The compensation manifestly itself by the financial contribution of the state to the integration organization amounting to 136 billion Hungarian forints, which resulted in a significant increase of dividends paid by the savings bank to the applicant's banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3660.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3668.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The indirectly affected applicants also were indirectly compensated by the increase of profitability of their enterprises.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3668.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3686.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But most of all, the fact that the applicants realized quite a significant income from their shares, which had allegedly been expropriated by the state as a result of the integration act, proves that they were not forced to bear an individual and excessive burden, if any at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3686.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3688.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, this concludes what</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3688.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3690.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wish to say at this stage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3690.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3692.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I thank you, Mr. President and members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3692.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3696.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for listening to me so patiently and that intently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3696.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3696.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3698.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3699.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3699.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3700.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3700.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3707.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now invite the judges of the Grand Chamber wishing to do so to put their questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3707.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3707.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Wennerström.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Erik Wennerström</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3718.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3719.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3719.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3720.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3720.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3736.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me first ask whether acting through the companies was ever considered seriously by the shareholders, and if so, why it was discarded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3736.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3737.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That would be my first question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3737.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3745.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question concerns the imperatives for the legislative reform that took place that has been described.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3745.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3758.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, we have been informed of events taking place in Hungary and a national interest in the reform, but we have also had references to EU legislation making requirements on the legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3758.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3762.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Could you please elaborate upon the proportions of these two imperatives?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3762.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3765.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To what extent was this defending a national interest?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3765.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3767.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To what extent was it EU compliance?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3767.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3767.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3770.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3772.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Chanturia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Lado Chanturia</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3774.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3776.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3776.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3780.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions, one for the applicant and second for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3780.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3803.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question for applicant, in your application, you complained about the violation of your rights under Article 1, Protocol Number 1, as shareholders of “Kinizsi” Bank and “Mohácsi” Bank, but not as representatives of your banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3803.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3805.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it correct?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3805.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3817.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm asking it because formally, the decision to remain in the new scheme was the decision was made by the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3817.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3827.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is necessary to make distinction between the bank as a legal entity and shareholders of this bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3827.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3847.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second question to the government, you mentioned in your communication that the cooperative credit institutions had a choice to remain in the new scheme, new system, or to leave it, to exit the system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3847.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3852.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant contested it because the exit was not realistic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3852.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3858.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my question is, how realistic was the option of exit?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3858.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3868.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And do you have information about the banks who did apply this right to exit from the new scheme?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3868.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3868.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3869.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3871.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. Judge Dedov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Dmitry Dedov</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3876.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3878.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3878.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3887.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, I would like to ask the applicants to clarify their victim status, because they did not raise this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3888.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3892.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question is to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3893.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3895.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question is very simple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3895.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3906.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whether the government apply the Basel principles of the prudential supervision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3906.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3915.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if yes, and I think that the government surely apply this principle, because they're very recognized and known principles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3920.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3927.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do these principles include the corporate control over the financial institutions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3928.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3943.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if not, why the government choose to go further and to have this control in addition to these principles and requirements for the capital of the financial institutions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3943.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3944.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3948.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3950.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Pavli.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Darian Pavli</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3953.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3955.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3955.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3961.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question for the applicant, but the government, of course, may feel welcome to comment as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3961.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3994.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question relates to one of your submissions with respect to when you discovered the possibility of the banks themselves as corporate entities bringing this case, you argued that they were under various forms of pressure and specifically that there was pressure exerted on them after their filing a petition with the Constitutional Court of Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3994.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4005.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so I'd be grateful if you could elaborate a little bit on that, on the specifics of what happened after the filing of the petition with the Constitutional Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4005.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4005.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4008.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4011.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4011.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4020.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like also to put a question to the applicants, but perhaps the government may wish to react also.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4020.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4034.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Could you please clearly resume the ways by which the applicants have been directly and personally affected in their capacity as shareholders in this particular case?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4034.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4045.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And second question also, the government says that dividends have in fact been paid during the years 2014 to 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4045.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4049.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can the applicants confirm this or not?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4049.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4050.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4050.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4067.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So with this, I think that we can withdraw for 30 minutes, following which the parties will be able to submit their brief observations in reply to each other's submissions and to reply to the questions of the judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4067.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4070.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the hearing is suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4182.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4183.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4225.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4226.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4238.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4242.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4242.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4243.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Gárdos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4248.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4254.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. President, members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4254.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4260.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would answer the questions of Mr. Wennerstrom, Mr. Giantulli and Mr. Pavli in one because</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4260.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4263.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>they relate to the very same question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4263.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4270.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do not deny that the integration act could have also infringed the banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4270.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4280.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, contrary to the government's arguments, we submit that it was not an error that we are here on behalf of the shareholders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4280.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4288.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The banks and the shareholders deliberated who should come to this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4288.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4326.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also understand that coming on behalf of the shareholders inevitably means that the scope of this action is more limited than if we were representing the banks, simply because of the fact that the rights restricted on behalf of the shareholders are much more limited, these are simply the rights to vote and the right to sell the shares, than the rights of the banks, which are much more lengthy as the act introduced several infringements relating to the banks, which are, as we are representing now, the applicants, not the subject matter of this procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4326.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4351.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason that we are here on behalf of the shareholders is the fact that the banks and the shareholders decided that due to the pressure from the integration institutions, the risk that an application from the banks will later need to be withdrawn or will be withdrawn by someone is much less if we represent the shareholders and not the banks, simply because of the numbers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4351.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4370.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In case of the banks, withdrawal would have simply meant a declaration from one single manager of the bank, whereas in case of the applicants, it would require convincing or pressuring over 200 individual applicants to withdraw their application to this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4370.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4389.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that there had been pressure from the integration institution is clearly supported by the fact that when we came here originally, there were more applicants in this case who finally decided to withdraw their applications after lengthy discussions with the integration institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4389.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4422.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We understand that these support the argument that it was not, it would not have been reasonable to come on behalf of the banks because there would have been an actual and real threat that these applications would later be withdrawn, and then this court would not be in a position to show that such an infringement of shareholder rights and such a brutal intervention in the life of private entities is not allowed under the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4422.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4427.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now in relation to Mr. Chantoury's second question, this question was raised to the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4427.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4432.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>government, but still I would take the opportunity to try to answer it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4432.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4440.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question was, if you understood it correctly, whether it was possible in practice to leave the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4440.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4447.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that there was one bank, to our understanding there was only one bank who finally managed to exit the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4447.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4456.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the bank that was referred to by the government as D-Bank, and the government argues that the exit was a reasonable alternative with this example.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4456.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4470.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now before responding to this argument, let me reiterate that in order to exit, the applicants would have had to pay an additional almost 4 billion forint, which was simply impossible taking into account the shareholders of the bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4470.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4478.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This basically would have meant that simply from a financial point of view, that a new bank needs to be established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4478.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4500.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now answering the specific question relating to D-Bank, it is important to understand that D-Bank was a member of a corporate group, the central entity of which, as it subsequently was found in 2015, committed severe crimes, leading to client's losses exceeding 100 billion forints, as the client funds disappeared.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4500.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4509.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under such circumstances, it is maybe less surprising that their shareholders were able to provide the necessary funds, the necessary capital for the exit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4509.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4527.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in case of companies operating in line with the laws, fulfilling this condition was simply not feasible, especially for private individual owners who collected the funds necessary for transformation into banks over 50 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4527.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4534.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now answering the question raised by Mr. President and also answering the question of Mr. Dedov,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4534.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4543.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it may be useful to repeat how the rights of the shareholders were infringed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4543.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4551.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that the General Meetings is the supreme body of the company where the shareholders exercise their collective rights to control the company.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4551.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4563.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, as I explained previously, the General Meeting is also the place where the individual shareholders meet, where they exercise their individual rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4563.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4582.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court previously reiterated in its judgment in the present case that a share is a complex object certifying that the holder possesses a share in the company together with corresponding rights including, and I quote, especially voting rights and the right to influence the company's conduct and policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4582.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4585.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These are the rights, the infringement of which we argue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4585.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4594.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The right to influence the conduct of the company is not equal to the individual right of a majority shareholder to control the company.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4594.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4599.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The individual right to control is related to the amount of influence a shareholder has.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4599.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4610.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By contrast, the right to influence the conduct of a company refers to the substance of voting right of each and every shareholder regardless of the number of votes they can cast.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4610.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4623.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The right to vote ensures that the shareholder has the potential to influence the operation of the company and we argue that the Integration Act violated these rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4623.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4628.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relation to Mr. President's second question, we confirm that the dividends indeed were</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4628.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4629.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>paid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4629.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4633.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, we also argue that this is not the issue here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4633.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4660.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government wrongly argues that the measures are the subject matter of the present case and we also argue that the judgment of the chamber was also misleading in this respect when it argues that only the measures actually suspending the voting rights of the shareholders or blocking the payment of dividends to the shareholders might violate the rights of the shareholders and these measures could have been taken only in exceptional cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4660.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4668.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment argued that the applicants should have demonstrated that they were in fact likely to run the risk of being affected of such measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4668.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4685.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our claim is based on the fact that before the Integration Act entered into force, the shareholders had the right to freely decide issues reserved to the general meetings of the banks and the Integration Act restricted this right by subjecting the decisions of the shareholders to the integration institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4685.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4694.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For assessing this claim, it is irrelevant whether the integration institutions actually exercise their right to veto or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4694.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4704.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We argue that we are not potential victims but actual victims of the legislation and we also argue that this case is not an actio popularis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4704.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4718.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To support this, I refer to the established case law of this Court which argues that it is open to a person to contend that a law violates his or her rights in the absence of an individual measure or of implementation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4718.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4740.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We argue that the Integration Act itself created a result where the right to vote was left without any meaningful content which inevitably led to the fact that the right to sell was also infringed simply due to the fact that the shares no longer had any value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4740.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4764.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relation to the government's argument, I think it is also important to mention that the government in its observation and also partly in its speech now argued that the Integration Act was not used as a tool to replace the original owners of the integration and we are only complaining here because we did not receive shares in the savings bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4764.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4769.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a complete misunderstanding or misinterpretation of our arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4769.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4801.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We argue that due to the fact that the government acquired majority ownership in the savings bank and then reprivatised it later in a way that in effect led to the result that only three owners have dominant position in the sector simply meant that everyone else who previously had ownership in this sector and who were able to control the savings cooperatives and the complete sector no longer had such a right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4801.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4812.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is clear from corporate documents, regulatory decisions and newspaper articles that the three investors who have dominant shareholdings now in the sector is Mr. Mészáros, Mr. Vida</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4812.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4817.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. Gál, although I assume that these names may not reveal much to the court, it</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4817.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4820.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>may be useful to provide some background.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4820.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4828.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When we discuss economic matters in Hungary, one needs to take into account the new economic structure introduced by the Prime Minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4828.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4843.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As an analysis published by the Central European University Press, Central European University itself being a victim of this new era formulated it, the new economic system involves using state power to capture oligarchs and markets.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4843.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4849.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Mészáros, who according to Forbes accumulated $1 billion from state-related investments,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4849.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4854.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is the most prominent figure mentioned when analysing this new economic political system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4854.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4859.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Gál is closely linked to Mr. Mészáros, just to give one example he is the CEO of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4859.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4863.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the largest company of Mr. Mészáros and Mr. Vida sits in the management of companies</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4863.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4868.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of Mr. Mészáros and owns one of the Hungarian commercial televisions under state influence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4868.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4876.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We argue that this easily can explain the real reason behind the change of ownership structure in the sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4876.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4884.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now there is one final point that I would like to mention and I see that my time is basically over.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4884.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4892.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government keeps repeating to the fact that what happened here is simply a regulatory exercise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4892.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4901.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Governments always have the power to regulate financial institutions, especially in light of the 2008-2009 financial crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4901.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4916.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also mentioned in its pleadings now that what the powers provided to the integration institutions is basically nothing more than the powers each and every financial regulator has throughout Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4916.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4940.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now just to give one example to show that this argument is a complete misinterpretation of the situation, let me refer to the fact that at a certain stage in the integration procedure all the members of the integration were forced or obliged to submit all their data relating to all their clients to the integration institutions into a newly set up database.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4940.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4973.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was not simply, first of all, this never happens in case of a normal financial regulator, but more importantly this database was also shared with each and every members of the integration, meaning that when our bank would have been obliged to upload all of its data to this database, each and every competitors of this bank and each and every other shareholders through their banks would have had the opportunity to see all their data relating to their clients.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4973.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5004.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now there was also a reference in the government's argument relating to the regulatory regime in relation to the, I assume it must have been the CRR regulation, which provides that national authorities may waive the application of capital requirements and it also answered the question of Mr Dedov, this is indeed based on the Basel Accords, but this is not the Basel rules themselves, but this is the European implementation of these rules.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5004.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5013.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it provides Article 10 of this regulation that national authorities may waive the application of the capital requirements set forth by the regulation if certain conditions are met.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5013.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5020.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do not dispute that the savings cooperative sector in its current form falls under Article 10 of the CRR.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5020.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5027.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We argue however that this does not have any relevance regarding the rights of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5027.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5029.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason for this is fairly straightforward.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5029.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5034.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The CRR does not empower the government to infringe the rights of the shareholders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5034.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5047.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just to give a few examples, it does not provide that the shareholders' right to vote shall or could be suspended or that the shareholder decision may require approval or consent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5047.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5058.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government's agent also referred to the fact that instruction rights, similar to the instruction right provided to the integration institutions, also exist under the CRR.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5058.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5059.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is correct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5059.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5074.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the government's agent fails to mention that this right relates to the institutions themselves, so the authority has the right to provide instructions to the institutions falling under its scope.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5074.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5089.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the CRR does not allow the regulatory authority to provide instructions that infringe or, anyhow, affect the rights of the specific shareholders of the organs or the organs of the company.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5089.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5095.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The CRR, to put it very simply, does not give the right to the state to intervene in shareholder rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5095.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5103.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was also a very brief reference previously to the so-called BRRD rules by the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5103.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5108.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These are the recovery and resolution rules introduced by a European directive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5108.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5130.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I do not really want to take your time discussing this in detail because we believe that this argument is completely groundless, as this directive provides state power in case of an unsound and failing institution, even if we were to accept, which we strongly deny, the fact that the savings cooperative needed help from the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5130.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5145.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has never been proven and it has never been even argued by the government that this sector and each and every of its members was an unsound and failing sector and unsound and failing institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5145.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5151.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To summarize my answers, let there be no mistake.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5151.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5156.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is not a case about defining the powers of a government in case of economic crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5156.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5162.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no economic crisis at all in Hungary at the time of the legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5162.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5166.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The savings cooperative sector in particular was not in a crisis situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5166.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5175.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We argue that this is a case of whether a government is allowed to establish a new economic elite under the guise of an economic crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5181.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5182.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5182.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5183.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call now Mr. Tallódi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5188.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5194.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5194.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5206.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, I would like to react to the question of Judge Wennerstrom concerning how much national and how much EU law refers to the topic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5206.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5212.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The choice of carrying out a reform was certainly a decision of the Hungarian Government of Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5212.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5222.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This decision was made not only to enhance the profitability of the cooperative credit institutions, but also to ensure their safe and prudent operations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5222.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5245.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, the legislative reform had the purpose of enhancing the lending activities of these banks in the rural areas where these banks mostly operated and where financing was especially needed for small and medium-sized enterprises in the face of the recovery from the 2009 financial crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5245.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5251.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, the Basel Accords actually raised capital adequacy ratio requirements for all banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5251.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5261.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the fact that saving cooperatives were relatively undercapitalized, the integration was also a means to ensure compliance with the Basel Accords.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5261.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5309.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once the government and the parliament made this choice to integrate this sector, several aspects of the specific form of the integration followed from EU law, most importantly, regulation 575, 2013, article 10 of regulation 575 specifically provides inter alia that in case of a similar integration, the management of the central body must be empowered to issue instructions to the management of the affiliated institutions that there must be joint and several liability between the members and that solvency and liquidity of the central body and of all affiliated institutions are monitored as a whole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5309.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5320.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the power of instructions by the central body, as well as sharing the risks between the members through joint and several liability were a comment of EU law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5320.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5327.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This, again, necessitated specific measures that ensure that all members of the integration operate prudently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5327.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5332.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The measures complained of by the applicants are exactly such measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5332.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5339.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>EU law was also relevant as regards the amount of the contribution of the state to the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5339.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5347.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not contested by the applicants that the Hungarian state paid as much as 136 billion forints to the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5347.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5358.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the integration act, this amount was to be calculated on the basis of the value of the rights the state acquired through the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5358.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5380.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was not only necessary to avoid any eventual concerns as regards the interference with the rights of cooperative credit institutions, it was also a requirement of the European Union state aid law that the state is not contributing more to the integration than the value of the rights it acquired.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5380.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5387.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the question how realistic was it to leave from the structure, the answer is the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5387.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5398.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The provisions to restrict leaving the integration were put in place in order to protect the rights of depositors and the rights of those banks and investors who remained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5398.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5404.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, several banks have decided to leave the integration and have, in fact, left the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5404.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5412.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>IRB Bank, DRB Bank, DDD Bank, and TTT Bank have left the integration before the end of 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5412.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5430.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The joint and several liability scheme in the integration required by regulation 575, 2013, has entered into force gradually following audits by big four auditors, PWC, KPMG, and BDO.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5430.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5435.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The audits of the 121 banks took almost one year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5435.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5448.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before the banks acceded to the joint and several liability scheme, it was possible to exit the integration without depositing a significant amount of deposit, the amount equal to the regulatory capital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5448.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5464.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If a bank was to exit the system following access to the system of joint and several liability, it was required in salary to set aside an amount equal to its regulatory capital for a period of two years following the exit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5464.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5481.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This deposit was meant as an insurance as depositors and financial parties could make a claim on all other banks remaining in the integration for the obligations undertaken by the exiting entity for two more years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5481.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5495.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because of loopholes in the legislation, any participants were able to exit the integration if they decided to pursue their activities not as deposit-taking banks but other forms of financial institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5495.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5513.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in summary, four banks exited before joining the joint and several liability scheme, and among others, Kinezio Bank itself exited the integration in 2018 also without the need to deposit the amount of the regulatory capital for two years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5513.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5516.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has deposited nothing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5516.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5529.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the question of Judge Dadov, I would like to answer that, as stated before, the Basel Accords in Terraria raised the required capital adequacy ratios for all banks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5529.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5533.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This could have posed a problem for a number of cooperative credit institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5533.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5553.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, the purpose of the legislation was not only to ensure solvency but also to ensure a prudent operation and to contribute to the development of rural areas through enhanced lending activities in the countryside by the very banks that had the mission to the banks of the countryside.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5553.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5564.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me briefly react also some of the applicants' arguments concerning the legislative process and the methods of regulation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5564.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5573.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Integration Act provided for a process of integration with various measures taking effect at different stages.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5573.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5591.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A gradual entry into force, therefore the period of adaptation allowed by the law cannot be counted as simply the time elapsing between its adoption and the entry into force, but it is much more complicated and it was different in respect of different elements of the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5591.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5601.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, such elements of the regulation had to take effect very quickly in order to prevent the actors in the financial sector to undermine the purposes of the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5601.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5608.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the financial sector, one hasty transaction can potentially jeopardize the solvency of the bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5608.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5621.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any management could decide to exploit irresponsibly the protection accorded by the joint liability introduced under the new regulation or take any action undermining the purposes of the Integration Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5621.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5635.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As an example, in the period between the adoption of the law and the entry into force, three cooperative credit institutions opted to transform into banks in order to escape from under the supervision introduced by the Integration Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5635.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5643.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Subsequently, these banks went bankrupt and several criminal proceedings followed, including for fraud and money laundering.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5643.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5659.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the applicant's perspective, it was a gain because it was not the integration which had to bear the costs of these bankruptcies, but at the same time it was a loss for the depositors and eventually the state budget.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5659.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5671.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the law had to ensure, including by the choice of the date of its entry into force, that its purposes cannot be undermined by the actors of the financial sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5671.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5683.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Contrary to the applicant's allegations, consultations had taken place between the government and the representatives of the financial sector concerned before the adoption of the Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5683.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5698.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2013, the government appointed a government commissioner who conducted an extensive consultation with saving cooperatives and also contracted audit firms to review the financial position of the saving cooperatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5698.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5705.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The audit firms found that the sector was not sufficiently capitalized and the risks were not properly assessed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5705.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5722.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These documents contain sensitive business secrets, thus the audit firms would only consent to the publication of these audits if all parties agreed to sign a so-called reliance letter undertaking not to sue the firms for the finding of the audit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5722.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5744.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the applicant's comments on the purposes of the integration, the government note that the statements of the new management on the business policy of the bank, which had emerged from the integration, cannot be taken as a proof of the original intentions of the Integration Act, neither can later modifications of the integration process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5744.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5755.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Integration was necessary both to improve banking services in the rural areas and to ensure a more effective supervision in the financial sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5755.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5762.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The necessity of a more effective supervision has also been acknowledged by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5762.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5770.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prior to the Integration Act, the great number of saving cooperatives made it impossible for the Hungarian National Bank to carry out effective supervision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5770.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5778.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following the entry into force of the Integration Act, this supervisory functions were delegated to the organs of the integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5778.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5788.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was exactly the same cause for concern of the President of the Republic, who first sent the law back to the Parliament for consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5788.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5795.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These concerns were eliminated by the amendment of the Act on the National Bank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5795.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5802.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants also claim that prior to the Integration Act of 2013, the integration proceeded voluntarily.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5802.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5810.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the integration organizations created in 1993 were only formally voluntarily.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5810.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5830.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Constitutional Court noted in its decision 20 from 2014, in 1993, saving cooperatives received significant financial support from the state, and this support was made conditional upon membership in an integration organization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5830.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5839.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the Integration Act was organic development of the formerly applied integration methods.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5839.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5861.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the capacity of the applicants' banks to file an application before this Court, the government note also in response to the question of Judge Pavli that the integration institutions could not and did not force the applicants' banks to withdraw their application from this Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5861.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5867.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For one reason, it would have been a violation of Article 34 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5867.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5876.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the applicants' banks did conduct several proceedings against the integration institutions in Hungarian courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5876.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5884.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, a withdrawal would not have bound the Court if there were any pressure by the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5884.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5912.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Insofar as their allegations about the prospective appointment of an integration commissioner decided in 2018, after years of unlawful operation of Kinyarbank can be interpreted as an attempt to prove that the organs established in accordance with the Articles of Association of the banks were not free to act in this field in accordance with the decisions of the shareholders' meeting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5912.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5929.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government point out that the decision of 2018, irrespective of the assessment of its content, is irrelevant for the bank's legal capacity in 2014 when the application was filed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5929.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5938.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, I wish to react to the applicants' reference to a sum of 1.5 million forints quoted from the final audit report</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5938.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5942.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>prepared before the selling of their portfolio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5942.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5962.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I may refer to this sum as the loss of the value of the company's shares, whereas it was a hypothetical calculation as to the losses of the integration in case of an eventual liquidation of Kinyarbank.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5962.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5962.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5968.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5969.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5969.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5975.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now invite the judges who have put questions to ask for further clarification if they so wish.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5978.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5981.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Apparently this is not the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5981.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5984.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5984.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5989.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their submissions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5989.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5992.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5992.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5995.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5995.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5999.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5999.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6001.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
