<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>5308013_16122015</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>39.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>40.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>44.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>51.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Béláné Nagy versus Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>53.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>64.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on 12 August 2013 on the Article 34 of the Convention by a Hungarian national, Mrs. Béláné Nagy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>64.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>75.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the second section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph one of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>75.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>80.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on 21 January 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>82.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>91.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 10 February 2015, a chamber of the second section delivered its judgment in the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>91.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>98.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It held that there had been a violation of Article One Protocol Number One to the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>98.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>111.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 24 April 2015, the government requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>111.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>116.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on 1st June 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>116.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>136.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 4 September 2015, the European Trade Union Confederation was granted leave under Article 36, paragraph two of the Convention and Rule 44, paragraph three of the rules of the court to make written submission to the court as third party.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>136.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>151.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Mr. Zoltán Tallódi,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>136.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>151.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>agent of the government,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>136.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>151.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Mrs. Marianna Lévai, advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>151.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>161.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mr. András Cech, counsel, assisted by Mr. Erik Látrányi and Mr. Balázs Várhalmy, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>163.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>168.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>168.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>178.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant, we have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>178.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>180.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Cech for the applicant will speak first</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>180.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>183.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mr. Tallódi for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>183.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>184.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I call Mr. Cech, please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>188.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>192.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>192.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>203.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>if you were to go back in time 40 years to Nyiregyháza, Hungary, you would meet a young girl, Katalin, full of ambition who has just started to work at the labor court as a clerk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>203.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>208.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You would hear the old typewriter clicking under her fingers, which are black from the carbon paper.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>208.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>212.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You would smell the coffee she's making for her boss.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>212.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>219.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She's so talented that the president of the court employed her even before she passed her final exams at the vocational school.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>219.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>227.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She's just embarking on her adult life, starting to work, and thus becoming a contributor to the social security scheme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>227.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>236.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A few years later, this young woman, the applicant, moves to another place and gets a new job at the local forestry company, again as a clerk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>236.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>238.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Her life is a struggle, but she's happy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>238.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>239.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She loves her job.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>239.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>244.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She's her boss's right hand, and she gives birth to three children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>244.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>248.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But years later, things take a turn for the worse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>248.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>254.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the mid-'90s, her leg starts swelling, and she has to see the doctor regularly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>254.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>255.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And when it rains, it pours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>255.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>261.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A few years later, the forestry company is wound up, and she loses her job.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>261.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>270.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She does her best to find another job, but to no avail, because at that time, this is almost impossible in the underdeveloped eastern regions of the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>270.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>277.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, she's facing more and more serious health problems and undergoing numerous surgical interventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>277.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>289.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She becomes less able to work, and the state of her health gets so poor that in 2001, she's finally assessed to have suffered a loss of her capacity to work and is granted disability pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>289.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>297.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For more than a decade, she has been suffering from agonizing gout, which even hinders her housekeeping.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>297.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>303.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She would be sitting here with us were she able to endure the pain caused by traveling.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>303.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>317.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Still, in spite of everything, the government is still trying to sell you the idea that the applicant's health status improved in 2009 to such an extent that she was no longer eligible for the disability pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>317.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>320.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this is clearly not the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>320.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>330.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They argue in paragraph 21 in their memorandum that an expert opinion and domestic court decisions assert the improvement in my client's health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>330.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>334.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this statement is far from the truth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>334.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>346.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has never submitted or relied on expert report or court judgment other than those already adjudicated by the chamber, which are at your disposal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>346.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>355.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, we observe that none of these documents encompass directly or even indirectly a single word which would support the alleged improvement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>355.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>375.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the contrary, in the course of the first domestic lawsuit in 2011, the forensic medical expert clearly stipulated that no substantial improvement had indeed occurred in the applicant's state of health since 2007, when the last medical checkup maintaining the applicant's disability had taken place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>375.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>380.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government's assertion is therefore simply not true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>380.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>383.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Former Vice President of the United States Hubert H.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>383.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>400.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Humphrey said that, quote, the moral test of government is how it treats those who are in the dawn of life, the children, those who are in the twilight of life, the elderly, and those who are in the shadow of life, the sick, the needy, and the disabled, end quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>400.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>407.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the Hungarian government is treating the disabled applicant by trying to confuse the blatant facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>407.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>413.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nonetheless, this only emerged after the delivery of the chamber judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>413.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>429.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, the court, when communicating the application to the government, established in the statement of facts that the change in the applicant's level of disability in 2009 was due to a modification of the applicable methodology and not to any change in her health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>429.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>437.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In their subsequent observations, the government did not opine this fact, as is clear from Appendix 1 to their memorandum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>437.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>451.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, whatever the respondent government may say, the facts and evidence prove that regarding my client's health, there is neither any improper assertion nor any false assumption in the chamber's judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>451.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>460.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a crucial issue, since the hard core of the present case is the fact that the applicant's state of health has not improved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>460.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>471.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Notwithstanding the attitude of the government towards disabled persons, and especially towards the applicant, the court must embark on the issue of the possession within the meaning of Article 1 of Protocol Number 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>471.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>478.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government and the applicant dispute whether the applicant has had a possession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>478.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>482.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do assert that she has.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>482.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>488.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to this court's case law, possessions may be either existing possessions or valuable assets.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>488.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>501.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The latter comprises pecuniary assets, such as debts, by virtue of which the applicant can claim to have at least a legitimate expectation of obtaining effective enjoyment of a particular pecuniary asset.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>501.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>512.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows that in terms of legitimate expectations, there are, on one hand, already existing pecuniary assets, like a regular disability pension benefit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>512.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>525.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on the other hand, there are pecuniary assets that do not currently exist, but which are expected to be obtained in the future, such as a potential pension benefit to be paid in the future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>525.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>532.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is therefore clear that both kinds of pecuniary assets qualify as a possession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>532.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>542.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no doubt that the applicant had a possession in the form of an existing valuable asset by receiving her disability pension from 2001 to 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>542.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>557.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, what the court has to decide in the present case is whether my client, as of the withdrawal of her disability pension in 2009, has had a legitimate expectation of obtaining the disability benefit again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>557.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>582.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, before exploring the issue of legitimate expectations, including the core question of the existence of an acceptable right on the side of the applicant, I would like to address a few words to the remarkable proposal of the third party intervener, namely the European Trade Union Confederation, ETUC, which was made as to the interpretation of Article 1 of Protocol Number 1, which regards social security rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>582.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>590.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ETUC's approach represents an absolutely new understanding of this issue, which I believe is worth mentioning and even deliberating on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>590.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>592.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What does the ETUC suggest?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>592.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>615.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Its starting point is the Demir and Baikara judgment, which concludes that, I'm quoting here, the court, in defining the meaning of terms and notions in the text of the convention, can and must take into account elements of international law other than the convention, the interpretation of such elements by competent organs, and the practice of European states reflecting their common values.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>615.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>631.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Based on this, the ETUC examined its submission to pertinent international law and practice, including that of the UN, the ILO, the Council of Europe, and the EU, and outlined the relevant practice of the European states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>631.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>643.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not going into details here, it found that the overwhelming majority, if not the totality, of Council of Europe member states have accepted the protection against the risk of invalidity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>643.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>649.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is obvious that the European consensus has emerged in this matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>649.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>665.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the strength on this finding, their final conclusion is not less than, quote again, the material scope of Article 1 of Protocol Number 1 should include the right to social security in general and the right to invalid benefits in particular, end quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>665.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>672.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ETUC admits that against this conclusion, several arguments might be advanced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>672.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>679.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it is quick to add that these arguments are not convincing, and we tend to agree with that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>679.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>697.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, Hungary's international ratification status concerning, in particular, Part 9 of ILO Convention Number 102 may not be brought into play because the interpretation of the convention does not rely on the status of ratification of an individual country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>697.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>713.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Additionally, we have to underline again what we have already asserted in our memorandum, namely that Act 100 of 1999 promulgated the European Social Charter in Hungary, which is this way, became part of the domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>713.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>728.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, when setting forth the minimum standards of the social security system, paragraph 2 of Article 12 of this charter refers to the ILO Convention, thereby even, if indirectly, rendering it part of Hungarian domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>728.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>734.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to top it all, Hungary is bound by a direct international obligation as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>734.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>745.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, it has ratified the UN International Covenant on Economic, Social, and Cultural Rights, Article 9 of which expressly guarantees the right to social security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>745.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>759.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, it might be advanced against the ETUC's conclusion that on the state side, the right of protection of a property is considered as mainly a negative obligation, whereas it does not contain positive obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>759.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>771.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, although the court has elaborated ample jurisprudence as to those kinds of obligations, it must be also recognized that there is no clear-cut division between negative and positive obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>771.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>802.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, we also tend to agree with the ETUC's standpoint, according to which it is of the view that since the court has already acknowledged that social security rights qualify as proprietary rights as long as they are guaranteed at national level, from this starting point, it is only a matter of future interpretation to arrive at the conclusion that Article 1 of Protocol Number 1 should be regarded as containing the fundamental social right to social security in general and invalid benefits in particular.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>806.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>826.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we interpret the ETUC's above position, this does not mean that states would not have the possibility to set up and maintain well-differentiated social security schemes, where the granting of full benefit amounts beyond a certain level of health impairment is subject to the meeting of additional statutory requirements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>826.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>848.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would, however, mean that no one with a partial or full disability should find themselves in a situation in which not even a minimum supply requisite to basic subsistence is granted to them by the state, even though the amounts could be considerably lower than those granted to persons satisfying additional statutory requirements as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>848.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>853.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This would undoubtedly place an additional financial burden on member states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>853.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>859.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, on the one hand, so do other institutions of modern democratic states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>859.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>871.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on the other hand, this financial burden cannot be compared to the individual burden of those who, owing to their misfortune, lose their working capacity and along with it, their income.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>871.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>885.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards our interpretation of the ETUC's standpoint, both German and Hungarian constitutional courts seem to have arrived at similar conclusions, which are deduced from the fundamental right to human dignity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>885.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>900.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The German Constitutional Court, in its decision number 1 BVL 1 slash 09, brought on 9 February 2010, ensured the right to social care requisite to basic subsistence for those in need.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>900.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>914.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is more, this social care, according to the judgment, shall secure not only the conditions for basic existence, but at least to a certain degree, the possibility to take part in economic, cultural, and political life as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>914.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>933.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the same vein, the Hungarian Constitutional Court, in its decision number 37 slash 2011, held that the state must interfere if the individual is not able to ensure for him or herself a life of dignity in a material sense and lives under the poverty line.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>933.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>940.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, human dignity has a function which supports a claim for social benefits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>940.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>956.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable members of the court, however striking and revolutionary the ETUC's conclusion may sound at first hearing, it reflects nothing else than the ever-evolving nature of the convention and its interpretation, which is frequently accelerated by this court as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>956.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>969.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And indeed, if we take a broader view into the historical evolution of human and civil rights concerning both their mere list and the content thereof, we can see an ever-evolving tendency.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>969.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>984.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this progress, there necessarily has to be a point at which each individual right changes from a mere potential into a substantive and recognized right with all the associated criteria, including judicial assertability.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>984.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>997.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is, of course, for the honorable court to decide whether in the European Human Rights Protection System under the convention, this point in time has arrived for the right to social security and within this to disability benefits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>997.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1004.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is, however, in our view incontestable that this question may not be swept under the rug.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1004.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1019.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if it is, it will from time to time be raised again and again because the tendencies outlined in the ETUC's submission are sensibly pointing to the full recognition of social security rights and individual benefits as human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1019.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1025.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only question is whether it is happening right now, perhaps in these very proceedings, or only in the future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1025.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1036.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, this court cannot ignore the aforementioned reasons advanced by the third party intervener and must make a thorough examination of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1036.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1055.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should the court, as a result of that examination, come to a conclusion that Article 1 of Protocol Number 1 includes the right to invalidate the benefits, at least in an amount required for basic subsistence, we invite you to hold at the same time that the applicant, having been disabled for 15 years, has had a possession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1055.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1066.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, if the court refrains from drawing such a conclusion, the existence of a possession on the applicant's side may still be established on other grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1066.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1073.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our firm stance is that she had and still has a legitimate expectation to obtain disability benefits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1073.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1085.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning now, therefore, to the concept of legitimate expectations, it must be observed that it concerns the question whether an addressee of the norm could, and to what extent, rely on an existing norm.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1085.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1091.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It implies that authorities must respect the expectations which they created by their representations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1091.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1103.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government raised a genuine question, notably, whether legitimate expectations prohibit a change in the law with special regard to the long-lasting and continuous nature of social security relationships.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1103.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1108.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In such relationship, according to the government's schema, there are two entry points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1108.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1114.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first is the starting date of the social security relationship coupled with the payment of contributions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1114.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1119.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second is the starting date of becoming eligible for receiving the benefit at issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1119.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1123.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We agree with this schema.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1123.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1132.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They further submit that during the time between these two entry points, which is usually many years, the law may be subject to changes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1132.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1135.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We tend to accept this too.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1135.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1151.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we also concur with the government's point, according to which requests for social security benefits are usually not adjudicated on the basis of the law applicable at the time of the first entry point, but rather on the basis of the law enforced at the time of the second entry point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1151.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1164.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent government, with the view of rejecting the applicant's legitimate expectations, places great reliance on the findings in the Richardson versus United Kingdom decision, which is a prominent reflection of the foregoing theorems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1164.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1167.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In that case, the court ruled that Mrs. Richardson</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1167.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1174.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>had no possession because she had not reached the pensionable age, so she was not eligible for the pension benefit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1174.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1182.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the government's aforementioned schema, she simply did not reach the second entry point of the social security relationship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1182.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1188.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this argument hardly seems to be persuasive in the case at hand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1188.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1196.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is because at the time the law changed to her detriment in 2008, my client, in contrast to Mrs. Richardson, had already</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1196.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1200.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>reached the second entry point by having become eligible for disability pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1200.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1204.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And she was in receipt of this benefit, of course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1204.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1220.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that the applicant reached the second entry point in 2001 entails that all her subsequent requests for disability allowance, as well as all subsequent straight measures, must be adjudicated on the basis of the law enforced in 2001.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1220.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1226.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is what follows from the aforementioned governmental standpoint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1226.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1236.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the issue of the applicable domestic law in respect of the existence of an assertable right on the applicant's side, I will go on to make a few references to our memorandum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1236.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1250.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, we invite the court to bear in mind that well-established case law of the Hungarian Constitutional Court, based on the constitution enforced at the material time, clearly asserted a right to welfare benefits on the part of the individual in need.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1250.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1261.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this context, regard must be paid to the case law of the court, which recognizes the relevance of the domestic law in the determination of possession, despite its autonomous concept.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1261.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1275.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, international conventions enshrining the rights of persons with disability are also of great importance in respect of the question of possession, since many of them became part of the domestic law, as to mention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1275.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1290.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, we reiterate that the applicant became eligible for disability benefits by virtue of the law enforced, without any act by the authorities, just because she met the requirements set forth in the applicable legal rules.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1290.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1299.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The authorities, therefore, merely asserted her right to benefit, but in no way conferred this right on her.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1299.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1302.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, they were not in a position to revoke this right either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1302.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1308.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For this reason, when the disability pension was withdrawn, her substantial right did not cease to exist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1308.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1316.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the applicant's right to disability benefit has remained assertable under the applicable terms of 2001.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1316.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1330.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is noteworthy that, in line with the foregoing, the government, in paragraph 17 of their memorandum, does not contest the existence of the applicant's legitimate expectations that were generated by the domestic law enforced in 2001.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1330.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1345.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, they acknowledged if the law had changed to the detriment of the applicant at the time when she was still eligible for the benefit, thereby processing legitimate expectations, she would definitely have an arguable case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1345.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1348.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1348.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1351.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>this is exactly what happened in our case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1351.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1356.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because, I repeat, the applicant's health has not improved, not even temporarily.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1356.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1361.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So she was still eligible for the benefit when the law changed to her detriment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1361.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1373.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, neither the following withdrawal of the benefit due to the change in the rules, nor the new law applicable as of 2012, made her legitimate expectation groundless.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1373.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1400.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The conclusion may be drawn with special regard to the principle of the rule of law that granting of disability pension in 2001 created for the applicant a reasonable and legitimate expectation according to which she could expect to receive disability benefit as long as she satisfied the criteria applied in 2001, and, of course, if there was no reason for the withdrawal under the rules which were enforced at that time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1400.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1407.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The existence of that continued and recognized legitimate expectation is also well demonstrated by the ensuing periodic reviews.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1407.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1427.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, on the one hand, we have just set forth that the applicant has had a possession in form of a continuous legitimate expectation for disability benefit, which is based on her unimproved food, physical condition, and the fulfillment of the additional statutory requirements applicable to her case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1427.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1438.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nor is it disputed, on the other hand, that her disability pension disbursed beforehand also constitutes a potential benefit beforehand also constitutes a possession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1438.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1456.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No doubt, especially in the light of the Kelton Asponson versus Eisen judgment, that the respondent state interfered with the applicant's right to possession when the payment of this possession was terminated exclusively on account of the change in the law, but without any change in her circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1456.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1465.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This interference, however, did not entail the disappearance of her possession, which continued to exist as a legitimate expectation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1465.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1472.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Based on that legitimate expectation, the applicant requested a new disability benefit in 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1472.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1480.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The denial to grant the benefit, despite the outstanding eligibility, constitutes an interference with the right to possession as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1480.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1496.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court, in the Poste and Rakho versus Finland judgment, stated that the concept of a continuing situation refers to a state of affairs which operates via continuous activities by or on the part of the state to render the applicant victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1496.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1515.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After the withdrawal of her disability pension, which is an obvious interference with her right to peaceful enjoyment of possession, the applicant, as a person who had been satisfying the requirements of contributions, was subject to ensuing periodic reviews.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1515.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1528.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, she has been constantly denied disability care, although she has fulfilled all statutory conditions which entitled her to such a benefit in 2001 at the time of the second entry point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1528.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1538.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to the withdrawal and the subsequent denials of disability care, she is therefore subject to a continuing restriction in her substantive convention rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1538.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1545.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, there has been a continuing interference with the applicant's peaceful enjoyment of possessions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1545.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1557.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also part of the well-established Strasbourg case law, to which we made several references in our memorandum, that as long as a continuing situation exists, the six-month period does not commence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1557.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1567.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the applicant's understanding, this means no less than all state activities implemented throughout the continuing situation may be subject to examination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1567.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1582.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We therefore invite the court to conduct a thorough inquiry into the lawfulness of the determination of the applicant's disability pension in 2009, and to hold that it constitutes an interference with the right to possessions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1582.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1603.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To proceed, this court hardly needs to be reminded that essential conditions for interference to be deemed compatible with Article 1 of Protocol Number 1 are that it should be lawful, must serve a legitimate public or general interest, and must strike a fair balance between the aim that is so to be realized and the personal interest of an individual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1603.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1612.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable court, the government will not address these issues because in its view, the applicant had no possession when the impugned state actions were undertaken.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1612.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1618.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, we have just given a concise outline of why such a stance is untenable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1618.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1625.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we do assert that there have been interferences with the applicant's right to possession during a continuing situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1625.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1630.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These interferences, first of all, were not lawful in terms of the rule of law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1630.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1638.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me remind you that in our memorandum, we clearly demonstrated that the new assessment methodology rules can hardly be seen as law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1638.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1644.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And what is more, their application contravenes the principle of prohibition of retroactivity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1644.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1657.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, though the government did not put forward any argument as to the public interest, the applicant admits that states enjoy a certain margin of appreciation in determining their social security systems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1657.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1662.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, this liberty of state cannot go as far as impeding vested rights to prevail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1662.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1677.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I reiterate that changes of eligibility rules of social security benefits might only be applied insofar as the person concerned has not yet reached the second entry point, that is, has not yet become eligible for that benefit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1677.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1683.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, the applicant affirms that she had to bear an excessive individual burden due to the interferences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1683.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1692.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite her continuous illness, her disability benefit was unduly withdrawn, and her subsequent requests were also unduly denied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1692.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1696.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It appears in the well-settled case law of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1696.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1705.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The obligation to endure a reasonable and commensurate reduction might be compatible with the convention because it constitutes no essential infringement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1705.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1715.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By contrast, a total deprivation of a pension benefit by definition breaches the essence of one's pension right, imposing an excessive burden on the individual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1715.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1728.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to the drastic and unjust series of measures resulting in the total divestiture of the applicant's only mean of subsistence, her day-to-day survival is indeed at risk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1728.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1730.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1730.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1736.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>attacking people with disabilities is the lowest display of power I can think of.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1736.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1742.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These words might not sound like a legal argument because they do not come from a legal expert.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1742.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1745.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I was quoting the famous American actor Morgan Freeman.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1745.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1753.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, these words pretty well reflect the way that ordinary people in democratic societies think about the care of disabled people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1753.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1765.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the same vein, we do believe that no state measures can be justified if they deny even the least support from a person in need, a person who has been a respected member of the community, thus leaving her in a hopeless situation forever.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1769.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1772.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mr. Cech.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1772.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1775.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I call Mr. Tallódi, you have the floor please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1781.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1783.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1783.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1786.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>honorable members of the court, ladies and gentlemen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1786.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1794.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a privilege and a pleasure to have the opportunity to appear before the court to present the oral submissions on behalf of the government of Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1794.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1803.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the written procedure before the court, both parties, as well as the intervening third party, have been given the opportunity to put forward their position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1803.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1819.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now the government has the aim to develop the main arguments in support of its standpoint and simultaneously to react on the content of the memorials submitted by the applicant and the third party, where applicable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1819.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1843.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, let me reaffirm that the government considered that pension rights, including the right to allowances on account of disability, are fundamental human rights to be guaranteed in a democratic society based on the rule of law and had been and are clearly enshrined both in the Constitution and in the fundamental law of Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1843.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1855.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The present case, however, is not about whether the Convention can afford protection to fundamental social rights, as this question had already been decided in the affirmative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1855.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1881.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question is rather whether such protection can be afforded independently from the will of member states when such entitlement had already been withdrawn, thereby elevating the protection mechanism of the Convention to the level of a social charter and creating an independent European social law on an undefined basis without the normal checks and balances that only state legislation can guarantee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1881.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1893.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the government wished to express its critique as to the Chamber judgment and reiterate that the position of the majority, according to which Article 1 of Protocol No. 1</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1893.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1912.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the Convention shall be applicable in the present case, which is flatly incompatible with the Convention, inconsistent with the case law of the Court, and entails serious repercussions with regard to the social security and welfare system not only of Hungary, but all member states of the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1912.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1927.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to substantiate these assertions, the government emphasized that the crux of the whole case is the issue whether before dealing with the question of proportionality there was a property right to start with.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1927.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1930.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer in the majority's view had been affirmative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1930.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1942.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the government is of the view that the judgment follows a flawed chain of logic, which never should have substantiated the applicability of Article 1, Protocol No. 1,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1942.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1952.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and therefore the complaint shall be deemed inadmissible and being rationa materie, incompatible with the Convention and rejected accordingly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1952.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1963.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before revealing the government's position, while the Chamber erred in establishing the applicability of the impugned article, the government wished to make two clarifications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1963.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1980.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the judgment rightly points out, there had been a change of law in 2008 that introduced the institution of rehabilitation allowances and therefore necessitated the compliance of the old rules on the disability pension system therewith.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1980.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1997.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Simultaneously, a new scheme had been introduced to assess the condition of the person concerned, which, instead of establishing the degree of loss of working capacity, as previously applied, assesses the degree of health impairment in general.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1997.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2023.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the degrees under the two systems suit one another in compliance with the general principles binding on professionals, the 67% loss of working capacity, as assessed for the applicant in 2001 under the old system, corresponded to 50 to 79% health deterioration under the new scheme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2023.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2043.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, had the applicant's level of health impaired remained the same, her health status should have never scored between 50 and 79% instead of 40%, and thus she should have remained eligible for the pension also under the new scheme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2043.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2064.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As concerns the impugn degree of health deterioration itself, the government point out that it is exclusively a matter of medical expertise, the assessment criteria, all which correspond to the recommendation of the World Health Organization, and which, for these reasons, may not be questioned by any judicial forum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2064.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2074.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government further note that there had been two separate proceedings in front of the Hungarian authorities on which the applicant's claim is founded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2074.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2083.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of these proceedings concerned the original withdrawal of the applicant's disability pension back in 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2083.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2109.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the law applicable during the time of withdrawal had been amended in 2008, it is of great importance that there is no causal relationship between the amendment of the law and the withdrawal, since the latter, irrespective of the new methodology for assessment, is a direct consequence of the actual improvement detected in the applicant's health as explained before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2109.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2134.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this juncture, the government warned that the Honorable Court established the lack of jurisdiction to review this part of the applicant's complaint, for instance, the 2010 withdrawal, due to the applicant's failure to file her complaint with the court in a timely fashion, that is, within six months following the final decision of the competent domestic authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2134.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2148.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The other proceedings goes back to 2012, when the impugned law entered into force, reforming the whole system of disability benefits and replaced the scheme of pensions with allowances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2148.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2170.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although at the time of the entry into force of the new legislation, the applicant had already not been eligible for any disability pension, due to the 2010 withdrawal, she, of course, had the right to file a new request for disability allowance under the new scheme if her health condition so necessitated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2170.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2180.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The claim constituting the basis for the impugned judgment of the chamber arises from the rejection of this new request by the Hungarian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2180.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2195.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This time, the applicant didn't have a sufficient period of social cover as required by the new rules, although due to the amelioration of her health, she did have again the requisite degree of disability.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2195.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2212.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having made these clarifications, now the government wished to turn back to the erroneous reasoning of the chamber judgment, on which the majority established the continuity of legitimate expectations and shed light on the points why the majority failed in this respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2212.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2214.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2214.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2244.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the first element of the flawed logic the government wished to deal with is the question whether legitimate expectation is and property interests indeed could have been generated by the legislation of Hungary in force when the applicant first became eligible to the benefits in 2001, and whether such legitimate expectations could continue existing despite the withdrawal of entitlements in 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2244.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2264.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, the government find it extremely important that the court acknowledged as much that the applicant had no assertable right under domestic law to the disability allowance when she requested it in 2012, and when the interference in subject occurred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2264.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2305.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not having disputed the court's longstanding position according to which a claim of an unjustified interference with a right in the field of welfare rights will not be considered to fall under Article 1 of Protocol Number 1, if the applicant cannot demonstrate as an absolute threshold issue that he or she had at the time of the interference an assertable right under domestic law, the ultimate question remains how the majority could still substantiate the applicability of the article in subject, thereby allowing itself to rule on the merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2305.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2330.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Chamber's analysis, the rationale seems to be that legitimate expectations could not be considered extinguished by the fact that in a new methodology of assessment, the applicant's disability was scored down to 40% in December 2009, apparently without material change in her condition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2330.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2349.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, the court finds the legitimate expectations to be continuous because it argues that the entitlement of the applicant ceased to exist unlawfully, solely due to the change of the law when it was originally withdrawn back in 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2349.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2383.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government finds this argument one or mostly problematic because the court takes the issue of lawfulness, unlawfulness of the 2010 withdrawal as decided despite the fact that the government contested the applicant's assertions in this regard and claimed in a consistent way that the 2010 withdrawal is a direct result of the factual improvement of the applicant's health and has nothing to do with the altered method of assessment introduced in 2008.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2383.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2405.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides the lawfulness, unlawfulness of the 2010 withdrawal is exactly the issue of the first proceedings also complained about by the applicant, which, however, had been declared inadmissible by the Honorable Court since the applicant failed to submit its application in compliance with the six-month rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2405.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2437.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, if the Honorable Court followed the Chamber's majority decision and handled the unlawfulness of the 2010 withdrawal as if it was decided, it will build the applicability of the 2012 claim through establishing legitimate expectations on this basis on an alleged but unproven unlawfulness violation stemming from the 2010 withdrawal concerning which the court itself said that it doesn't have the right to examine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2437.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2473.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, legally, the right decision for the Grand Chamber would be not to take position in this regard and to reject the applicant's complaint since the legitimate expectation she once had seized to exist due to the 2010 withdrawal, and there is no such circumstance, for instance, the unlawfulness of this withdrawal, or at least the court is precluded from considering it, which would rectify this problem and lend continuity to the legitimate expectation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2473.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2482.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government warned that the Grand Chamber is not entitled to reverse the inadmissibility decision of the Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2482.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2504.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this juncture, the government would like to briefly react on the arguments of the applicant's memorial presented in this regard and submit that saying that the applicant's property claims did have a solid domestic law basis because social rights were enshrined in the then-effective Constitution is an extremely weak argument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2504.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2515.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is so because our former Constitution and fundamental law in force today only lays down the basic principles of certain institutions, freedoms of rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2515.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2520.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the details are to be elaborated in other sources of law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2520.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2546.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If we accepted this argument, it would mean that anyone who considers himself, herself disabled could claim state subsidies right away in contrast to the law containing the detailed rules and without taking into account what additional terms are prescribed for as regards the degree of health impairment, number of covered days by insurance, age, and et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2546.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2558.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As this logic is obviously flawed, the government remains to contend that the applicant's claim had no basis in domestic law when the alleged interference occurred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2558.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2565.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the government wished to refer to the Asmundsson v. Iceland case,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2565.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2577.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>also invoked in the applicant's memorial, and submit that the present situation may not be comparable to the invoked judgment where the court found a violation on reasonable grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2577.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2587.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, in that case, the applicant's expectation did definitely have a legal source at the domestic level at the time of the interference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2587.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2598.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Plus, the applicant had lost his disability pension, obviously not because of a change in his health, but because of a legislative change.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2598.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2604.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As these circumstances differ in the present case, no analogy can be used.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2604.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2612.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government respectfully note that the Asmundsson case would only be relevant if the applicant, Mrs. Bélané Nagy,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2612.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2634.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>had filed her application in due time regarding the withdrawal of her allowances in 2010, because in that scenario, she also had a valid legal basis at the domestic level for legitimate expectations, which would have allowed the court to examine the lawfulness or unlawfulness of the withdrawal as it did in the cited case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2634.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2649.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, due to the divergent circumstances of the present case, this issue cannot be subject to scrutiny anymore, and therefore, nor can it substantiate the continuity of legitimate expectations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2649.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2674.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the second element of the flawed judgment of the government, note that it might also be possible that the Honorable Chamber, to avoid the above-mentioned mistake, had not taken into account the presumed unlawfulness of the 2010 withdrawal, but established the continuous existence of legitimate expectation solely on the ground of the applicant's former eligibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2674.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2678.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any way, this approach shall also be deemed mistaken.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2678.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2694.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the government wished to point out that it is quite clear that had the applicant been a new entrant in the pension system, meaning that had she never been eligible before, the court would not have afforded protection for her claim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2694.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2702.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This emanates directly from the case law, namely, among others, the Richardson v. United Kingdom case,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2702.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2719.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in which the applicant, who was born in October 1955, had not been afforded protection by the court against the retroactively altered law elevating the age for retirement from 60 to 65 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2719.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2741.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the applicant of the present case differs in that she at least once had legitimate expectations on the basis of the domestic law to acquire property rights, still, to provide protection solely on this ground, independently from the will of the Member States, would entail undesired consequences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2741.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2760.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of these consequences would be that establishing the continuous nature of legitimate expectations of social benefits merely on the ground that the applicants once, but no longer, had been eligible for the entitlement is discriminative to those who have never been granted social state aid before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2760.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2781.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is so because these two groups are in a comparable situation, whose difference in treatment cannot be justified in any way, not even by saying, as the court referred to this, that those people once being eligible deserve protection because otherwise they were exposed to ex post facto legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2781.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2813.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ex post facto kind legislation is typical of the social security system, by definition due to the lengthy, continuous nature of social security relationships between the insured person and the state, and due to the fact that there are two entry points in the social security system, the starting date of the social security insurance relationship coupled with the payment of contributions, and the starting date of becoming eligible for receiving benefits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2813.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2822.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, in the most favorable scenario, the relevant law should remain unchanged between these points to ensure foreseeability.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2822.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2836.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, due to the average length of these periods in a lifetime and to the changes of circumstances during such a long period of time, this is something that cannot be expected from the lawmaker.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2836.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2851.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We further submit that such position would place an excessive financial burden on the member states who would be forbidden to change their social benefits policies to the detriment of people who once, but not anymore, had been entitled to benefits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2851.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2866.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government further claim that should the court depart from its previous interpretation as to the applicability of Article 1 of Protocol Number 1, such move can easily have a chilling effect on the laws and proceedings of member states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2866.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2869.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2869.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2880.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the third questionable issue to be considered is the majorities interpretation as concerns the relevance of contributory pension scheme as to the issue of applicability.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2880.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2904.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finding relevant whether the applicant contributed to the pension scheme during the time when she was employed in a contradiction with the case law, as explained in Stets and others, which made it clear for the purposes of Article 1 of Protocol Number 1 that making a distinction between contributory and non-contributory pension schemes would be increasingly artificial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2904.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2912.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the convention provides for protection in any event, irrespective of contributions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2912.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2926.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any way, the government first and foremost argue that the issue of contributory or non-contributory pension system may only be examined for the purposes of applicability as a collateral precondition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2926.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2946.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This issue can only be reached after it had been established that the applicant's legitimate expectation to acquire property rights has a basis under domestic legislation, which term cannot be ignored on the ground of the finance scheme's contributory nature.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2946.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2960.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fourth problematic issue of the court's reasoning to be referred to is whether legitimate expectations to receive disability care entails the right not to have the eligibility criteria changed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2960.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2981.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As already referred to this above, the ex post facto kind legislation is typical of the social security system by definition due to the lengthy, continuous nature of social security, legal relationships, and to the fact that there are two entry points in the social security system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2981.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2998.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the altering of legislation in the field of social security entitlements may impose individual burden on anyone irrespective of the circumstance whether he or she has formerly been eligible or not as it happened in the Richardson case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2998.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3008.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Still, retroactive legislation in this sense may not be attributable to the state and thus cannot serve as a reason for ignoring the lack of domestic legal basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3008.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3027.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, such amendment of law, legally speaking, may not be referred to as an ex post facto law as it had not been applied retroactively with an ex tunc effect but with an ex nunc effect for the future also with regard to the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3027.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3051.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, in the interpretation of the Hungarian Constitutional Court, which the Honorable Court also agreed with, the right to disability pension is a mixed social security and social welfare allowance aimed at temporarily replacing the lost income of active-aged persons as long as their health impairment so necessitates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3051.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3072.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, even if someone was eligible for allowances for a period of time in contrast to age pensions, conditions may change by time unless he or she belongs to the protected circle of those who are in receipt of the allowances at the time of the interference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3072.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3094.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to substantiate the obligation not to change the eligibility criteria to the detriment of the applicant applied at the time when she was originally granted the benefits, the court relied on the ILO Social Security Convention and the WHO International Classification of Functioning, Disability, and Health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3094.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3099.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Making references to other international instruments is not unknown before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3099.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3107.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are, however, a number of issues about their application in this case which are of some concern.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3107.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3115.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the government presented these in its memorial in details, I would refrain from repeating them here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3115.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3131.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As concern the citation of international documents such as the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, ICCPR, and so on, both by the third party and the applicant, the government respectfully submit that we couldn't agree more with them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3131.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3141.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is absolutely necessary for the convention's protection system to guarantee certain social rights under Article 1 of Protocol Number 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3141.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3147.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So what the third party decide to achieve in this regard is already guaranteed by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3147.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3154.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On this basis, found honorable court a violation, for instance, in the Rasmunsen case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3154.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3172.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, everyone should recognize that the present case has different circumstances as a result of which under the old boundaries of protection, the applicant's claim cannot be deemed to be covered by the scope of Article 1 of Protocol Number 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3172.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3188.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To do so would require the court to sever the social rights protection mechanism from the regulation of member states and to broaden its jurisdiction contrary to the principle of subsidiary and state sovereignty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3188.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3215.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As one of the closing remarks, the government wished to emphasize that when a similar case arises where there is an ex-eligibility element, but the applicant's property claim for benefits doesn't have a domestic law basis anymore, taking into consideration the issue of lawfulness, unlawfulness as concerns the continuity of legitimate expectation in itself is not a flawed idea from the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3215.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3230.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The problem in this particular case is, however, that the issue of lawfulness, unlawfulness of the 2010 withdrawal had and could not been decided by the court due to the failure of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3230.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3250.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, in this particular case, it cannot be taken into account, whereas in other cases with different circumstances, it might be a valid factor to consider for the court for the purposes of establishing legitimate expectations and the applicability of Article 1 of Protocol Number 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3250.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3273.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government further repeat that to follow the other way, meaning that not to consider the withdrawals relevant and to find ex-eligibility under domestic law to be the sole condition, regardless if there had been any withdrawals, would also entail serious side effects besides the ones already mentioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3273.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3289.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The broadening of the notion of legitimate expectation on the basis could not be regulated in a consistent way and would lead to unclear expectations for member states to meet and to jeopardize legal certainty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3289.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3310.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As an example, the government shed light on the question whether the applicant retains legitimate expectations to receive allowance with the old term if her medical condition again so necessitates, even if her entitlement was withdrawn 10, 15, 20 years prior to her new claim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3310.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3322.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, what if the eligibility had originally been established for a definite period of time and the withdrawal occurs for this reason at the time when the definite period expires?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3322.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3338.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this scenario, does the eligibility for allowances for a definite period of time also entail lifelong legitimate expectations for allowances with the same old terms if the concerned person's health again so requires?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3338.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3345.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If so, the burden imposed on member states by this interpretation would be even much heavier.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3345.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3361.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To sum up, the government is of the view that even if supposing but not acknowledging that the alleged interference imposed an excessive individual burden on the applicant, the court cannot be allowed to conduct an examination on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3361.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3369.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber reached an affirmative conclusion when examining the applicability of Article 1 of Protocol Number 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3369.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3379.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, this analysis contains essential problems, errors leading to flawed conclusions which the court should have never arrived at.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3379.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3383.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, that concludes what I wish to say at this stage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3383.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3386.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I thank you, Mr. President and members of the court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3386.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3389.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for listening to me so patiently and attentively.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3389.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3389.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3390.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3393.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Tallódi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3393.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3397.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank both parties for their interventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3397.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3406.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I should like to invite my colleagues, judges of the Grand Chamber, to ask the questions they may have.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3406.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3410.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>President Sajó.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3413.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3415.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3415.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3423.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question is addressed to the government, but the applicants are free to react to this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3423.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3434.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Government refer to the continuous legal relationship inherent in this type of welfare or pension schemes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3434.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3441.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, I would like to ask two questions, factual questions related to this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3441.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3474.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, assuming that Act 191 of 2011 does not exist, did not enter into force, would the applicant be eligible on the basis of her medical condition as established in 2012, although she was not a recipient of benefits at that point of time?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3474.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3488.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So once again, the hypothetical is, without the new law under the old system, was would have been a possibility to provide her benefit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3488.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3493.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question is somewhat similar to this one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3493.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3511.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a change in 2014 regarding the years in service which are to be taken into consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3511.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3517.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those, to some extent, if I may call them, are more favorable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3517.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3523.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant, nevertheless, if I understand correctly, was still not eligible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3523.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3557.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, assume that someone in her situation, that is to say, denied of the benefit in 2012, but satisfying the new conditions of 2014, would that person be eligible to be a recipient of the benefit from 2014 onwards?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3557.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3557.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3559.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3560.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3560.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3561.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>President Nußberger please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3564.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3566.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3566.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3569.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would have first two questions to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3569.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3582.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first question is the withdrawal of the disability pension as of 1st February 2010 was brought to the labor court, which decided on 1st April 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3582.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3592.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as I understand, the case was not brought further to any other Hungarian court or the Hungarian Constitutional Court nor to the European Court of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3592.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3595.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would just like why.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3595.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3607.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my second question is on what financial means did the applicant live after the withdrawal as of 1st February 2010?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3607.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3618.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if she had no financial means as a basis for existence, why was the case not argued under Article 3?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3618.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3625.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My other three questions are of quite a technical nature and more addressed to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3625.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3643.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in as far as the applicant has contributed to the disability pension, is there a specific contribution to disability pension or covers it both disability and old age pension?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3643.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3645.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or is there a differentiation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3645.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3660.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the next question is, if the pension had not been withdrawn, would it be transferred, the disability pension, into an old age pension at a certain moment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3660.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3663.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if yes, when?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3663.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3675.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And last question, if she now, is she still eligible to get an old age pension or is she excluded from the possibility of having an old age pension as well?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3675.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3675.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3676.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3678.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. President López Guerra.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3680.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3681.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3681.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3697.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, as far as it could have any relevance for the assessment of the case by this court, could the applicant give us some information on the medical or clinical reasons for the disability of the applicant?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3697.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3708.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, I'm not asking for any details, but just some general information of the reason for the impairment of the applicant, which made him unable to work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3708.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3708.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3708.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3712.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. Judge Wojtyczek, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3714.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3715.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3715.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3721.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions, both to the government and to the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3721.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3724.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question is the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3724.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3739.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was the applicant, after the withdrawal of her disability pension, eligible to receive any types of benefits or allowances under the Hungarian law?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3739.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3745.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Did the applicant apply for such benefits or no?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3745.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3755.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question, I would like to know the exact amount of the disability pension which was granted, if I remember correctly, in 2001.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3755.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3765.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What was the amount at that time, and what was the amount of that disability pension at the time it was withdrawn?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3765.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3766.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3766.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3766.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3766.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3769.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. Judge Lemmens, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3771.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3773.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3773.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3779.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a bit of a question in line of what my colleague just asked, but a very precise question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3779.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3793.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When the pension allowance was withdrawn in 2010, did the applicant at that moment receive a rehabilitation allowance?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3793.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3795.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some uncertainty in the facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3795.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3816.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm asking that because if she had received a rehabilitation allowance, which I understand is of a lower amount than the pension allowance, than a disability pension, then she might benefit from a transitional rule in the act of 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3816.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3822.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So a very precise question about the disability allowance, whether she received it or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3824.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3826.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3826.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3832.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there are no more questions, the court will now rise for 20 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3832.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3844.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we'll resume at 25 to 11, following which the parties will return for the second round of short pleadings to respond to submissions in the first round and to the questions put by the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4234.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4235.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4273.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4280.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated. The hearing is now resumed, and I call Mr. Cech.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4286.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4290.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4290.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4305.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>first I would like to address the question put by Judge Nussberger regarding the domestic local remedies after the first jurisdiction in Hungary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4305.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4328.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As you pointed out in the proceedings, according to the judgment of 2011 of the Nenet Hazal Labor Court, the withdrawal of the applicant's disability pension is the result of the change in the governing eligibility rules while her health status has remained unchanged.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4328.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4333.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court held that the pension authorities had correctly applied the relevant law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4333.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4344.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows that the only prospect for redressing the unfavorable judgment would have been a new assessment, finding the applicant's loss of capacity to work to be 50% or less.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4344.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4356.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, there shall be neither record of evidences nor reconsideration of evidences in the procedure of review before the Supreme Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4356.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4377.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the final judgment of the Nenet Hazal Labor Court was in compliance with the relevant legal provisions and no other expert opinion could have made, the courier could have adopted no other decision than upholding the final judgment according to the section 275 of the Civil Procedure Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4377.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4389.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the second question, why we complain under Article 1, it is well-certain case law of this court that the master of the case is of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4389.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4398.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant submitted the fact and complained about the loss and the denial of her benefit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4398.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4411.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the court communicated the case and the complaint by raising the question whether there has been a violation of Article 1 of Protocol Number 1, we had to address this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4411.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4431.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the question of Judge Lemons regarding the medical status of the applicant, we know actually that the applicant is suffering from permanent joint goods as much as she is unable to do even the housekeeping.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4431.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4445.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She is in a bad condition that the 250 kilometers traveling from her home to my office caused serious difficulties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4445.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4455.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we assume that her physical condition is poor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4455.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4474.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the question of Judge Wojticek regarding the amount the applicant received, at the time of the withdrawal, her disability pension amounted to about 190 euros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4474.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4491.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We don't have proper data here, but we assume that the amount of the disability pension when it was granted has to be lower since there is a yearly increase on the basis of the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4494.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4517.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the second question, we will submit that after the withdrawal, she was not eligible for disability allowance because the competent authority in its discretion power did not find feasible her rehabilitation, therefore was not advised.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4517.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4521.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this way, she didn't get any allowance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4529.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4540.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, sorry, maybe I addressed the question of Judge Lemons, but I think it was clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4540.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4542.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My answer is improper.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4542.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4573.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the question of Judge Guerrero of any other allowance of the applicant, we put forward that the only allowance she got, it was a housekeeping allowance of an amount of 12 euros by month given on an equitable basis by the municipal authority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4573.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4574.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She does not have other income.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4580.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4586.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She has to rely on the support of her family, of course.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4586.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4604.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, I have to address the issue that the government raised concerning the status of the applicant's health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4604.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4618.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We haven't seen, and the government has never demonstrated a genuine medical report which would have clearly stated any fact of improvement in the applicant's health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4618.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4627.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They only rely on the comparative schemes put forward in the memorandum as regards the loss of capacity to work and health deterioration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4627.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4633.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But there is no legal base thereof in the domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4633.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4639.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, it cannot be assumed more than a speculation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4639.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4651.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By contrast, the forensic medical expert report produced in the course of the first domestic litigation is a prima facie evidence of the fact that the applicant's health has not improved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4651.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4660.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, it is the sole evidence purporting any statement of a medical expert on the state of health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4660.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4676.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the records of the medical checkups, only scores on the applicant's physical condition were made according to the DEN methodology, but no conclusion was drawn as to whether her health improved or worsened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4676.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4682.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here I emphasize again that there has been no improvement in her health since 2001.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4682.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4691.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, the real cause of the withdrawal of her disability benefit cannot be other than the change in the assessment methodology.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4691.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4704.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the legitimate expectation, the existence of the continued and recognized legitimate expectation is also well demonstrated by the ensuing periodic reviews.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4704.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4715.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Hungarian government debate this conclusion by relying on the information provided by the competent authority, though no evidence thereof has been advanced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4715.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4724.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they argue that the reviews took place upon the applicant's request and not as a result of the authorities or expert orders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4724.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4728.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the reality, this argument is not convincing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4728.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4742.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's requests for review were not made on her own initiatives, but were the fulfillment of her obligation imposed by the authorities, namely the competent social security authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4742.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4748.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Each time when the applicant's assessment took place, scheduled the next review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4748.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4754.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The labor court in the course of the first proceeding also alluded in its judgment to the time of the next assessment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4754.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4758.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These documents are in the case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4758.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4768.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To sum up, with regard to the applicant's unimproved health status, the government has interfered continuously with the rights to possession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4768.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4777.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For this reason, we invite the court to hold that there has been a violation of Article 1 of Protocol Number of Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4777.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4777.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4778.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4781.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Cech.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4781.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4784.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I call Mr. Tallódi, please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4785.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4787.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4787.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4793.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We tried to collect all the relevant information concerning the question of Mr. Schuyl,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4793.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4799.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>who is the vice president of the court, Mrs. Nussberger, Lopez Guerra,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4799.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4805.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vojticek, and Lemons judges, and I would like to ask my colleague to give you the information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4811.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4814.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for the floor, Mr. President,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4814.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4816.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>honorable member of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4816.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4821.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like first to answer the question of Mr. Judge Shio.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4821.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4840.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer for the first question is that, yes, she would have been eligible for the entitlement had the new law not entered into force in 2012 from the date when her health status deteriorated, that is from October 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4840.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4860.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To answer the other question, yes, the law had been modified in 2014 in a favorable way, so if someone had met the number of days covered by Social Security under the new, more lenient rule, yes, that person would have become definitely eligible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4860.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4864.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But Mrs. Béla Né-Nagy could not meet the new rules either,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4864.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4870.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>so she didn't, she hadn't become eligible under the new rules either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4870.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4892.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To answer the questions put by Judge Nussberger, I would say that from 2012, contributions for allowances of persons with changed working capacity are paid to health insurance funds, whereas other contributions are paid to the pension insurance fund.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4892.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4906.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, yes, there are two kind of funds now, and contributions for the age pension and the disability pension go into different funds now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4906.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4927.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To answer the second question, I would say that, yes, if she would have been in receipt of the disability pension, she would have continued receiving this kind of pension, so it wouldn't have been transformed into an old age pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4927.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4940.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to answer the third question, yes, now if she reaches the requisite age, Mrs. Béla Né-Nagy would be entitled to partial age pension</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4940.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4957.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because she hadn't been working since 1997, so she could not meet the requisite insurance period for the full age pension, but only the partial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4957.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4961.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But, yes, partly she would be entitled to that one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4961.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4974.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To answer the questions of Judge Wojciech, yes, she also applied for other kinds of allowances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4974.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4993.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She applied for a so-called regular social allowance, however it was denied because her health did not deteriorate when she was working, but after, and it was a precondition for this kind of allowance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4993.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4998.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now she is also in receipt of other kinds of allowances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4998.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5008.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as the government knows, she now is in receipt of a certain kind of subsidy related to house maintenance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5008.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5018.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to answer the third question, the sum of the pension was 60,000 forints when it was withdrawn in 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5018.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5027.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to answer the very last question put by Judge Lemons, the government say that Mrs. Béla Né-Nagy</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5027.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5043.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>was never in receipt of a rehabilitation allowance, but in receipt of a disability pension, so the guarantee rules under the new law could not have been applied in her case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5043.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5078.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in any way, the government wish to repeat that even supposing the unlawfulness of the withdrawal back in 2010, the court is not allowed to examine this issue for the purposes of establishing the applicability under Article 1, Protocol Number 1, as this is exactly the issue the court has prevented from examining, even according to the court itself, as it was phrased in the disability decision relating to the proceedings back in 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5078.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5080.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is all that I wish to say.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5080.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5082.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope we could answer all of your questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5082.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5082.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5084.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5086.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5086.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5089.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Tallódi, would you like to add something?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5089.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5092.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Anything?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5092.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5093.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5093.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5095.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5095.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5099.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5099.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5105.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5105.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5109.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5109.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5113.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5113.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5116.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5116.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5117.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
