<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>5550807_13022013</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>16.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>16.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>54.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>73.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sit, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>73.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>75.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Good morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>75.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>83.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Janowiec and others versus Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>83.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>101.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case originated in two applications lodged with the court under Article 34 of the Convention by 15 Polish nationals on 19 November 2007 and 24 May 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>101.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>106.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were allocated to the Fifth Section of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>106.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>118.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 5 July 2011, they were joined and declared admissible by a chamber constituted within that section.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>118.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>147.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 16 April 2012, the chamber delivered its judgment, in which it found that it was unable to take cognizance of the merits of the complaint under Article 2 of the Convention, that there had been a violation of Article 3 of the Convention in respect of 10 applicants and non-violation of that provision in respect of the other applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>147.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>156.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also found that the respondent government had failed to comply with their obligations under Article 38 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>156.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>170.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 24 September 2012, the panel of five judges of the Grand Chamber decided to accept the applicant's request that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>170.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>184.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Polish government expressed the wish to take part as third party in the written and oral proceedings before the Grand Chamber in conformity with Article 36, paragraph 1 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>184.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>198.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Subsequently, leave was granted to the following organizations to submit written comments as third parties under Article 36, paragraph 2 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>198.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>208.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Open Society Justice Initiative, Amnesty International, and Public International Law and Policy Group.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>208.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>225.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A group of three non-governmental organizations, Memorial, European Human Rights Advocacy Center, and Transitional Justice Network were also granted leave to make a joint written submission as third parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>225.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>231.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian government are represented by Mr. Matyushkin, the representative of the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>231.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>241.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Russian Federation before the Court, assisted by Mr. Mikhaylov and Mr. Smirnov, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>241.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>252.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the hearing, the applicants are represented by Mr. Kamiński, Sochański, Szewczyk, counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>252.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>263.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the applicants, Mrs. Wołk-Jezierska, Mrs. Krzyszkowiak, and members of their families</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>263.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>265.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>are also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>265.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>273.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Polish government are represented by Mr. Szpunar, Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>273.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>278.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Mężykowska, counsel, and Mr. Schabas, advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>278.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>283.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties in the name of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>283.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>298.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to welcome delegations from the High Council of Judges and Prosecutors of Turkey, from the Greek Legal Council of State, and from the German Constitutional Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>298.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>304.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the representatives of the parties, I have determined the order of address as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>304.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>312.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Szewczyk and his colleagues for the applicants will speak first, then Mr. Matyushkin for</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>312.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>319.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the Russian government, and finally Mrs. Mężykowska for the Polish government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>319.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>331.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in two official languages of the Court, English and French, interpreting from Polish has been authorized for the oral submissions of Mr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>331.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>333.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Szewczyk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>333.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>344.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, interpreting to Turkish has been authorized for the benefit of the delegation of Turkish judges and prosecutors attending this hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>344.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>355.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The later interpreting is not arranged by the Court, and non-transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>355.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>357.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Szewczyk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>360.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>362.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Szanowny Panie Przewodniczący.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>367.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>371.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Szanowne Panie i Szanowni Panowie Sędziowie Wielkiej Izby Trybunału.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>373.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>382.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ja reprezentuję Panów Jerzego Janowca, syna kapitana Andrzeja Janowca i Antoniego Trybowskiego, wnuka pułkownika Antoniego Nawratila.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>382.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>390.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Oficerowie ci zostali zamordowani wiosną 40 roku przez funkcjonariuszy NKWD w Charkowie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>391.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>424.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Na pytanie Wielkiej Izby odnoszące się do artykułu 38 konwencji odpowiadam jednoznacznie, iż rząd Federacji Rosyjskiej, odmawiając Wysokiemu Trybunałowi przekazania kopii postanowienia z 21 września 2004 roku o umorzeniu śledztwa Dio 159, naruszył w sposób bezsporny artykuł 38 konwencji w związku z artykułem 27 Wiedeńskiej Konwencji Prawa Traktatów z 1969 roku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>424.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>434.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Szeroko na ten temat wypowiedział się już Wysoki Trybunał w wyroku z 16 kwietnia ubiegłego roku w naszej sprawie w punktach 99 do 111.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>434.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>440.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do jego uzasadnienia odnoszę się z pełnym uznaniem i aprobatą.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>440.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>445.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ze względu na ograniczony czas mojego wystąpienia nie rozwijam szerzej tego tematu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>445.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>470.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Z ubolewaniem natomiast twierdzam, że strona rosyjska przyjęła od pewnego czasu strategię totalnej negacji oraz ukrywania ustalonych wcześniej w sposób bezspornych faktów i okoliczności dotyczących zbrodni katyńskiej, które cała społeczność międzynarodowa poznała w najdrobniejszych szczegółach, dokonując jednoznacznych ocen historycznych, politycznych, moralnych i prawnych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>470.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>505.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Utajnienie owego postanowienia z 2004 roku, z września i bardzo wielu dokumentów procesowych z nadaniem im klauzulu w zawierszenno-sekretności śletajne i to już po zakończeniu śledztwa było zabiegiem organu administracyjnego Rosji mającym na celu ukrycie przed światową opinią publiczną, przed rodzinami ofiar zbrodni, a w końcu także przed Wysokim Trybunałem danych i okoliczności tej zbrodni dokonanej przez NKWD w 1940 roku i sposobu jej wyjaśnienia przez dzisiejszą Rosję.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>505.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>516.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Przy czym nie jestem w stanie zrozumieć logiki tej decyzji. Przed 21 grudnia 2004 roku materiały śledztwa były jawne.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>516.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>528.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Studiowali je rosyjscy i zagraniczni historycy, prawnicy, dziennikarze. W oparciu o nie ukazywały się w wielotysięcznych nakładach i w wielu językach publikacje książkowe</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>528.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>538.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>odsłaniające wszystkie fakty i okoliczności tej zbrodni. Co więcej, w niektórych z nich zostało zamieszczone in extenso w postaci aneksu</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>538.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>549.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>orzeczenie Komisji Ekspertów złożonej z wybitnych rosyjskich uczonych pod przewodnictwem prof. Topornina, członka rzeczywistego Rosyjskiej Akademii Nauk</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>549.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>558.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>z dnia 2 sierpnia 1993 roku, opracowane w odpowiedzi na postanowienie Naczelnej Prokuratury Wojskowej Jabłokowa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>558.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>569.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W postanowieniu ten pułkownik Jabłoków powołał imiennie ten zespół, sprecyzował zagadnienia, na które otrzymał również precyzyjne odpowiedzi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>569.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>589.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ten jawny i powszechnie upubliczniony dokument procesowy, mający szczególny walor dowodowy, nie tylko ukazał państwu rosyjskiemu i całemu światu wszystkie okoliczności zbrodni i kłamstwa katyńskiego, lecz także wnioskował o podjęcie przez organ prokuratorski Rosji konkretnych kroków procesowych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>589.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>598.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cytuję, z aresztowaniem i ukaraniem zbrodniarzy w Rosji, nie czekając na wniesienie sprawy do Trybunału w Hadze.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>598.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>603.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nie pojmuję, co można było utajniać w tym stanie wiedzy na ten temat.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>603.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>614.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Przy tym nie sposób nie wspomnieć, że sama Federacja Rosyjska w art. 7 ustawy o tajemnicy państwowej wyklucza utajnianie jakichkolwiek informacji</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>614.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>618.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>o naruszeniach praw człowieka przez funkcjonariuszy państwowych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>618.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>634.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>O zakłamywaniu bezspornie ustalonych faktów świadczy także fragment świeżego, zupełnie świeżego, pisma pełnomocnika rządu rosyjskiego z dnia 30 listopada 2012 roku.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>634.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>644.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W punkcie 106 jego autor stwierdza, że w piśmie z 23 czerwca 2003 zawarte zostały błędne wnioski.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>644.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>654.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tak to jest sformułowane. Chodzi w tym przypadku o pismo generała Kondratowa z tej daty, będące odpowiedzią na moją prośbę</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>654.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>666.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>przedstawioną osobiście ówczesnemu Naczelnemu Prokuraturowi Wojskowemu, panu generałowi Pawienkowowi, kiedy w dniu 18 czerwca złożyłem wizytę u niego w Moskwie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>666.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>704.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otóż pan generał Kondratow powiadamia mnie tym pismem na polecenie swojego zwierzchnika, że Naczelna Prokuratura Wojskowa Federacji Rosyjskiej w toku prowadzonego śledztwa ustaliła, cytuję dosłownie, Nawratil Antoni syn Juliana rocznik 1883 i Janowiec Andrzej syn Jana rocznik 1890 zostali rozstrzelani w 1940 roku przez organ NKWD. W czasie ekshumacji przeprowadzonych w 1991 roku wydobyto około 200 zwłok obywateli polskich.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>704.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>714.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Niektórych z nich na podstawie znalezionych osobistych rzeczy i pośmiertnych żetonów, tak jest w tekście, udało się zidentyfikować.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>714.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>724.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W ich liczbie zostały zidentyfikowane zwłoki wymienionych przez wnioskodawcę, czyli przeze mnie, polskich oficerów.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>724.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>734.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nawratil i Janowiec zostali pochowani w rejonie Charkowa, a nadto ich nazwiska znajdują się w spisach starobielskiego obozu NKWD.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>734.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>742.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pan generał Kondratow był wówczas szefem Zarządu Nadzoru nad przestrzeganiem prawa w Naczelnej Prokuraturze Rosyjskiej.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>742.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>749.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dysponował najpełniejszą wiedzą o zbrodni katyńskiej i wynikach prowadzonego w tej sprawie śledztwa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>749.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>760.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Wiedział zatem doskonale co i o czym pisze. Napisał więc rzetelną prawdę wbrew temu, co usiłuje dzisiaj ukryć pan pełnomocnym rządu rosyjskiego.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>760.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>781.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Odnowiły się więc elementy skompromitowanego już dawno kłamstwa katyńskiego w orzeczeniach moskiewskich sądów, a w ślad za nimi w memorandach pełnomocnika rządu federacji powielane są twierdzenia, iż brak jest dowodów, że polscy oficerowie zginęli z rąk funkcjonariuszy NKWD.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>781.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>794.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Oczywistą zbrodnię wojenną nazwano wydarzeniami katyńskimi o nieustalonym przebiegu i nieznanym losie ponad 20 tysięcy polskich jeńców wojennych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>794.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>813.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To tak jakby ci oficerowie, proszę darować mi sarkazm, osadzeni w obozach NKWD o najsurowszym reżimie więziennym, udali się z im turystem na wycieczkę po Związku Radzieckim, odłączyli się od swoich klub, gdzieś się zajął i ruszili i ślad po nich zaginął.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>813.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>824.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Proszę o stwierdzenie wyrokiem Wysokiej Izby, że Federacja Rosyjska dopuściła się w naszej sprawie naruszenia artykułu 38 Konwencji.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>824.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>850.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Zresztą Wysoki Trybunał orzekł już bardzo trafnie w wyroku 5 Izby z 16 kwietnia ubiegłego roku, iż państwo rosyjskie naruszyło ten przepis Konwencji, co uniemożliwiło, tak jest w tekście, co uniemożliwiło Trybunałowi wszechstronną ocenę całości sprawy, w tym zwłaszcza przesłanek i podstaw prawnych umorzenia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>850.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>861.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ze swej strony dodaję, że w ten oto sposób państwo rosyjskie osiągnęło wyraźną korzyść ze wskazanego wyżej naruszenia przez siebie prawa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>861.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>872.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nastąpiło tu ewidentne złamanie starożymskiej zasady Nemo auditur propriam turpitudinem elegans, Przęga VII Kodeksu Justyniańskiego.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>872.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>878.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ma ona zastosowanie także w obecnym prawodawstwie ukształtowanym na fundamentalnych wartościach współczesnej demokracji.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>878.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>889.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moi mocodawcy, panowie Jerzy Janowiec i Antoni Trybowski zobowiązali mnie do przedstawienia na dzisiejszym wysłuchaniu kwestii rehabilitacji ich przodków.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>889.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>893.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Odnosi się to zresztą do wszystkich ofiar zbrodni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>893.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>898.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otóż w tej kwestii mamy do czynienia z wyraźną hipokryzją strony rosyjskiej.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>898.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>913.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jej stanowisko sprowadza się do tego, że gdyby polscy oficerowie, jeńcy wojenni zostali rozstrzelani po uprzednim ich osądzeniu i skazaniu na karę śmierci, to byłaby obecnie podstawa prawna do ich rehabilitacji.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>913.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>926.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Skoro zaś zostali zamordowani bez wyroku sądowego, bez zapewnienia im elementarnych praw do obrony, to już nie można ich rehabilitować, bowiem nie mieści się to w rosyjskim systemie prawnym.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>926.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>929.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jest to oczywista nieprawda.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>929.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>940.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W powołanym wyżej orzeczeniu ekspertów profesora Topornina z 1992 roku na stronie 59. jest jednoznaczne stwierdzenie, cytuję</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>940.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>957.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Polscy jeńcy wojenni podlegają rehabilitacji jako niewinne ofiary represji stalinowskich zgodnie z artykułem 2 i 3 ustawy Federacji Rosyjskiej o rehabilitacji ofiar represji politycznych.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>957.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>972.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>W tej kwestii wypowiedział się także już wysoki trybunał w punkcie 160 wyroku V Izby z 16 kwietnia ubiegłego roku, odrzucając argument rządu rosyjskiego, w cudzysłowie, że należy pominąć postępowanie rehabilitacyjne.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>972.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>986.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pozostaje jedynie problem wyegzekwowania od Federacji Rosyjskiej rehabilitacji wszystkich ofiar zbrodni, co jest w ramach obecnie obowiązującego rosyjskiego prawodawstwa możliwe, a moralnie absolutnie konieczne.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>986.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1003.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Konkludując, podtrzymuję przedstawione wcześniej Wysokiemu Trybunałowi swoje pisemne wnioski oraz popieram prośby Panów Janowca i Trybowskiego wniesione przez nich bezpośrednio do Trybunału o zasądzenie od strony rosyjskiej na ich rzecz stosownego zadośćuczynienia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1003.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1017.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Korzystając z okazji, pragnę wyrazić głęboką wdzięczność rządowi RP oraz Rosyjskiemu Stowarzyszeniu Memoriał, a także wszystkim organizacjom pozarządowym, które wspierają nasze działania w tłuczącym się postępowaniu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>pl</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1017.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1018.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dziękuję za uwagę.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1024.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1026.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Szewczyk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1026.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1027.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Kamiński.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1034.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1037.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the distinguished court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1037.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1041.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>today the court asked us several complex questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1041.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1050.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the short time allotted to us, we are able only to summarize our answers, concentrating on the focal points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1050.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1063.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Longer answers with numerous references to international law and case law constitute an elaborate written memorandum of more than 60 pages we've just deposited in the court's registry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1063.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1067.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article two, admissibility of the complaint.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1067.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1074.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian government questions the court's competence rationae temporis to deal with the procedural obligation under article two.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1074.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1085.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian government is relying only on several pre-Silich inadmissibility decisions and is ignoring altogether the coherent post-Silich law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1085.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1094.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today, the court has unanimously applied its position adopted in Silich in 21 subsequent judgments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1094.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1102.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian government wants to turn the Strasbourg clock back to the pre-Silich period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1102.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1108.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Katy massacre is an imprescriptible crime of international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1108.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1120.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When committed in 1940, it constituted a violation of universally binding customary rules of international law that prohibited killings of prisoners of war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1120.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1125.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That such a universal prohibition existed is evidenced by post-war trials.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1125.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1155.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Katy massacre may be qualified also as a genocide when seen in a broader perspective of four waves of deportations after the Soviet aggression in 1939 and the so-called Polish operation in 1937, 1938, in which more than 100,000 citizens of Polish nationality were executed in the Soviet Union because of their national origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1155.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1166.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Katyn massacre was called, I quote, a war crime having the features of genocide, for example, in a statement of the delegation of the European Union-Russia Parliamentary Cooperation Committee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1166.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1175.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a mass scale and imprescriptible crime of international law, the Katyn massacre is contrary to the underlying values of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1175.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1178.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber agreed on that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1178.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1186.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the last sentence of paragraph 163 of the Schillig judgment applies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1186.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1195.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the chamber's majority decided that additionally, there must be new sufficiently important material surfacing in the post-ratification period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1195.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1205.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We agree with the three dissenting judges that such a requirement limits the rational referring to the underlying values of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1205.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1221.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There exist violations of international law of such magnitude at scale, for example, the Holocaust and the Katyn massacre, for which the court should be competent under Article 2 in its procedural limb, of course, without referring to the new material test.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1221.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1234.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this context, we draw the attention of the court to the constructs of aggravated state responsibility and state crimes as applied in the case law of the Inter-American Court of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1234.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1245.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We share the view of the three dissenting judges that the death of almost 22,000 people committed by the state's order cries out for such consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1245.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1254.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Inter-American Court granted its razione temporis jurisdiction on the fact that the state had been involved in a given massacre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1254.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1263.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To translate it into the language of the European court, a genuine connection resided in the very character of the crime as a crime of international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1263.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1271.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No other elements were needed for the Inter-American Court to become temporarily competent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1271.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1278.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we consider that this court will be competent to hear this case even when the new element test is accepted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1279.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1291.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This test should not be limited to the new important evidence surfacing in the post-artification period, but should be understood more broadly as a new procedural fact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1291.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1308.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there is a sudden radical shift in the proceedings leading up to the adoption of conclusions that starkly contradict the findings in the previous stages of the investigation and even the historically established facts, this constitute a new element relevant for the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1308.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1315.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such cases can be called perversion cases and the cutting investigation in Russia is one of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1315.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1325.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian authorities turned dead people lying in several burial sites into disappeared people whose fate is allegedly unknown.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1326.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1336.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But also we allege that even the restrictive reading of the new element test as new evidence would lead the court to having jurisdiction in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1336.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1352.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As recently as on the 2nd August, 2004, the Russian prosecution made a ruling to include into the cutting case files voluminous materials received from Ukraine on this part of the cutting massacre which had been perpetrated in Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1352.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1361.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was expressly stated in this ruling that the Ukrainian materials related to the execution of the Polish citizen in 1940.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1361.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1382.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its recent letter to the court dated 17th of January this year, the Russian government attempts to dismiss these materials and containing a manifestly unsubstantiated conclusions about the fact those documents concern the execution of 3,435 Polish citizens in the spring of 1940.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1383.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1396.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is puzzling which national authority and on which legal grounds excludes or disqualifies the material in question from the file when the case is already closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1396.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1409.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian government submitted there is a difference in legal terms between situation in which a material act, killings, death occurred before and after the date on which the European convention came into legal force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1409.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1412.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do not agree for the following reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1412.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1418.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the obligation to investigate is of an autonomous and continuing character.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1418.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1421.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not a novelty created by the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1421.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1428.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The procedural obligation is implicit in the prohibition of killing of prisoners of war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1428.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1448.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If under international law, violations of such prohibition were deemed to lead already before the war to both state and individual responsibility, investigative obligations must be presumed as mandatory for the establishment of the relevant facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1448.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1454.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, we broadly refer to the case law of several international institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1454.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1467.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Inter-American Court on Human Rights found itself competent to adjudicate on the obligation to investigate when the killings occurred before the Inter-American Convention entered it into legal force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1467.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1470.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, the Gomez-Lund case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1470.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1479.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Highly relevant for this case is also the decision of the United Nations Human Rights Committee in Norma Urich versus Chile.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1479.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1487.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case concerned a killing that preceded the date on which the Convention on Political Rights entered into legal force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1487.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1498.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The committee found the communication inadmissible over a short time period, having regard to a declaration of the Chilean government made upon the ratification of the covenant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1498.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1509.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The declaration stipulated that the committee would be competent to consider communications in respect to acts, I quote, which began after the 11th of March, 1990.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1509.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1519.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are good reasons to hold that states are precluded from making these kinds of declarations in respect of human rights, international law treaties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1519.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1539.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as this room is not a lecture hall, I only say that taken at face value, this declaration of, and the committee's accepting reaction to it demonstrates that there exists a legal instrument for states wishing to limit in temporal terms the application of a given treaty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1539.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1547.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian Federation has not made such a declaration or reservation when ratifying the European Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1547.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1559.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, we wish to stress that unless otherwise stated in the treaty, its provisions apply to situations that do not cease to exist after the treaty's entry into legal force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1559.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1570.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That a state party wishing to exclude the application of the treaty to such situations must do so by means of an expressed reservation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1570.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1584.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This position is mirrored in the case law of the Permanent Court of International Justice and the International Court of Justice, Mavromatis Palestine's concession, Fosfax in Morocco, for example.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1584.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1602.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this context, we respectfully draw the attention of the court to the distinction made between the situations or facts of the treaty and the facts which constitute a source of the rights claimed by a party to the proceedings and a source of the dispute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1602.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1622.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Permanent Court of International Justice and the International Court of Justice confirmed that whereas the source of the dispute must relate to the situations or facts subsequent to the ratification, the rights of a party to the dispute may originate in the pre-ratification period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1622.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1638.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our government holds, moreover, that this court is not competent, ratione materie, to assess the Ketting massacre as it is a matter of international humanitarian law lying beyond the reach of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1638.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1639.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, we object.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1639.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1654.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, a number of international courts confirmed that international humanitarian law and international human rights law are not separated but constitute complementary sets of rules.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1654.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1665.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A ratione materie rejection of the kind submitted in this case by the Russian government was also raised by Salvador in the case of Serrano Cruz's sister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1665.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1668.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Inter-American Court rejected it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1668.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1680.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When humanitarian law is applicable, rules of this law are used to establish the scope and content of the rights and freedoms protected under human rights treaties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1680.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1685.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we conclude that the court is competent to hear this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1685.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1697.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And going to the merits of the complaint, we wish only to state that for the following reasons, the Ketting investigation in Russia cannot be considered effective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1697.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1703.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the applicant's right to participate effectively in the investigation was not secured.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1703.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1709.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants were denied victim status and access to the case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1709.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1714.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The classification of the most important parts of the case file appears arbitrary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1714.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1721.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application faced a prolonged denial of information about the fate of their relatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1721.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1728.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian authorities adopted the version of the disappearance of the applicant's relatives as the official one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1728.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1742.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian courts rejected all applications for rehabilitation, claiming that it was not possible to determine the specific legal provision forming the basis for the execution of the Polish prisoners of war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1742.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1766.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do not find it reasonable to entertain, and going to the decision on the classification of the Russian case file on the Ketting massacre, we wish to state that this decision does not apply to one single document, but to as many as 35 volumes of the case file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1766.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1776.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do not find it reasonable to entertain the security reasons interest that might have justified the decision of the Russian Federation to classify.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1776.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1780.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, we wish, again, to refer to international law standards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1780.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1793.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are many international law documents and case law emphasizing the need for revealing truth, a right to truth, as it is stated, in cases of gross human rights violations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1793.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1798.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This right to truth is both of individual and societal character.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1798.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1806.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Relatives must know what happened to their loved ones and where their bodies are buried.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1806.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1813.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And societists must discover what atrocities occurred under the authoritarian rules in cases of power abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1813.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1832.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We respectfully submit that this case offers the court a special opportunity to declare that under Article 2 of the Convention, read in conjunction with Article 1, there exists the right to truth when human rights have been grossly violated by state's agents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1832.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1832.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1834.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1837.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Kamiński.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1837.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1839.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Sochański.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1842.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1847.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished judges, if my watch is correct,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1848.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1853.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm a little bit behind the schedule, so I have five minutes left.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1854.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1860.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I shall concentrate on questions number three, four, and five of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1860.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1870.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course, shall uphold the standpoint produced for the court in our written observations in this respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1870.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1875.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I quoted the jurisprudence and appropriate judgments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1878.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1881.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, question number three.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1881.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1893.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is an established case law of this court under Article Three concerning the state obligations towards relatives of persons who are victims of enforced disappearances or killings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1893.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1917.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These obligations include obligation to investigate and to prosecute, if appropriate, obligation to give equal and effective access to justice, the obligation to redress damage, as well as the obligation to adopt a humanitarian approach, of course, obligation to provide information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1920.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1937.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as the quest for information is concerned, the victims' families have the right to know the fate of their missing relatives, including their whereabouts, or if dead, the circumstances and cause of their death, as well as the location of their burial site and access to their mortal remains.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1937.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1940.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My colleague has already presented this subject.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1940.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1947.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, this duty originates from the right to truth, which has both individual and collective components.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1947.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1958.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, we have to agree with the chamber judgment referring to obligation of a state to adopt a humanitarian approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1958.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1975.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It enjoys this humanitarian approach principle, requires the authorities to react to the plight in a human and sympathetic and compassionate way, even in cases of procedural obstacles hindering the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1975.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1993.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Shortly to question four, here we cannot agree with the chamber's decision to divide the applicants into two groups according only to proximity of family ties and the dates of birth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1993.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2000.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Chechen cases, considering minor applicants the chamber relied on, are irrelevant in the cases issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2001.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2019.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, children's emotions depend on their relations to parents, but as far as adults are concerned, their emotions do not depend so much on remembrances of their relatives, but rather on authorities' reactions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2019.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2024.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It becomes then irrelevant if they do or do not remember their fathers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2024.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2029.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Victim recognition assessment should depend on all circumstances of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2029.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2044.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as far as Article Three is concerned, it should strongly depend on the involvement of family member in the attempts to obtain information about the disappeared person and the manner in which the authorities responded to this inquires.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2044.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2067.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our case, the essence of alleged violation of the Russian Federation does not lie so much directly in the fact of disappearance or assassination of victims, Polish prisoners of war, but rather it concerns about the authorities' reactions and attitudes toward the applicants when searching for justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2067.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2082.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this point, I would like to refer to our written observation and show some books written and edited by those applicants who are not assessed by the chamber as victims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2086.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2098.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, it is clear and obvious that the Russian Federation manifested violent Article Three of the Convention by subjecting all applicants to degrading treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2098.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2102.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We entirely agree with the chamber judgment in this respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2102.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2117.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In points, in 10 points, 157 to 166, the court explains in detail the actions and omissions of Russian authorities that must be assessed as degrading treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2117.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2142.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The exclusion from the rights to study the materials, cart and uninformative replies, self-contradictory and ambiguous findings contrary to historical facts, lack of official information, consistent rejection of rehabilitation requests under pretext of disappeared files, and the suggestion that the Polish prisoners might have faced criminal charges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2142.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2154.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, the Russian authorities' denial of the killings of the Polish officers is contrary to underlying values of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2154.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2157.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, ladies and gentlemen, for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2157.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2158.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2159.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2161.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Sochański.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2161.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2163.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I give the floor to Mr. Matyushkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2175.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2198.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, I would like to start my submission by stressing that the Russian authorities have been repeatedly expressing their condemnation of the atrocities of the totalitarian regime, to which not only the Polish nationals, but also hundreds of thousands of Soviet people have fallen victims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2198.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2216.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the present case, the Russian authorities believe that while considering this case, it is necessary, first of all, to decide which particular basic rules of international law concerning the responsibility of states can be applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2216.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2231.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, some relevant guidance can be found in the report of the International Law Commission to the General Assembly on draft articles on the responsibility of states for internationally wrongful acts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2231.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2275.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The statement in their report, assuming that a question has arisen as to whether the state has complied with its obligation, a number of other issues of a general character arise, namely, determining in what circumstances conduct is to be attributed to the state as a subject of international law, specifying when and for what period of time there is or has been a breach of an international obligation by the state, determining any procedural or substantive preconditions to invoke the responsibility of the state in the circumstances in which the right to invoke responsibility may be lost.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2275.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2285.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The basic principle of international law is that each state is responsible for its own conduct in respect of its own international obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2285.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2294.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For this to happen, it is necessary that the conditions required to establish the existence of an internationally wrongful act of the state are met.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2294.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2296.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two elements are identified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2296.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2303.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the conduct in question must be attributable to the state under international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2303.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2312.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the conduct must constitute a breach of an international legal obligation in force for the state at that time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2312.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2322.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These two elements were specified, for example, by Permanent Court of International Justice in their Fasfazi in Morocco case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2322.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2328.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>International Court of Justice has also referred to the two elements on several occasions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2328.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2355.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Similarly, in the Dixon Carville Company case, the Mexico United States General Claims Commission noted that the condition required for a state to incur international responsibility is that an unlawful international act be imputed to it, that is, that there exists a violation of a duty imposed by an international judicial standard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2355.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2367.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that, as a normative operation, attribution of an act must be clearly distinguished from the characterization of conduct as internationally wrongful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2367.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2372.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None of the conditions above are met in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2372.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2381.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For a responsibility to exist, the breach must accue at a time when the state is bound by the obligation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2381.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2404.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As stated by Judge Huber, Permanent Court of Arbitration, in the Island of Palmas case, a judicial fact must be appreciated in the light of the law contemporary with it, and not of the law in force at the time when a dispute in regard to it arises or falls to be settled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2404.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2415.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same principle has been applied by the European Commission and this court, for example, in the X versus Germany case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2415.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2422.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There seems to be no reason for departing from the well-established case law in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2422.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2440.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the procedural obligation under Article 2, it is not simply beyond the court's jurisdiction, but it has not been triggered at all since it can arise only as a suppliment to the respondent state's obligation to protect someone's right to life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2440.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2449.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 1940, the applicant's relatives were not within the jurisdiction of Russia for the purposes of Article 1 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2449.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2461.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 1990, the Russian authorities were under no obligation to pursue the investigation into the cut-in events in accordance with either international or domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2461.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2474.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that they choose for whatever reasons to conduct an investigation does not have the effect of imposing Article 2 standards on their corresponding proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2474.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2490.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The procedural obligation binds the respondent states throughout the period in which the authorities can reasonably be expected to take measures with an aim to elucidate their circumstances of death and establish responsibility for it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2490.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2500.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, it was, however, impossible to reach those goals due to a number of objective insurmountable obstacles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2500.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2525.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian authorities also maintain that their compliance with the procedural obligation under Article 2 falls beyond the court's jurisdiction ratiotemporis, since when it is prevented ratiotemporis from examining the circumstance of death or killing, it cannot establish whether or not this fact gave rise to the procedural obligation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2525.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2539.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their specified position goes in line with Article 28 of the Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties, which defines the rule against retroactivity of treaties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2539.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2553.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the rule of temporal jurisdiction establishes that a court cannot exercise jurisdiction with respect to events occurred before such time when the court came into existence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2553.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2563.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in the case of the ICC statute, it states in Article 11.1 that the court has jurisdiction</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2563.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2570.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>only with respect to crimes committed after the entry into force of the statute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2570.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2577.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Paragraph 131 of the judgment, the chamber fully endorse the sealage approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2577.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2583.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian authorities find the implementation of this approach in practice to be at least problematic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2583.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2594.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No matter how separate, autonomous, or detachable their procedural obligation is, it is not disputed that it can be triggered only by a death or a killing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2594.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2605.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court cannot turn to the examination of the obligation without first establishing whether the circumstance of the death or the killing have brought this obligation into play.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2605.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2614.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the court shall be precluded from taking this step when the death or a killing occurs before the ratification of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2614.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2622.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, the subsequent initiation of the criminal proceedings cannot bring these events within the court jurisdiction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2622.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2645.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber, in Para 136 and 140 of its judgment, established the fact and the circumstance of the death of the applicant's relatives and even assessed their killing from the standpoint of international humanitarian law, contrary to the results of the completed domestic investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2645.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2652.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By doing so, the chamber obviously overstepped its jurisdiction ratio temporis and ratio materia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2652.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2660.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cutting events constitute a distant historical fact that can receive no legal assessment from the standpoint of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2660.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2676.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relying on the assiliate approach, one should not lose sight of restricting criteria to ensure legal certainty and prevent an unforeseeable extension of the court's jurisdiction and of the convention's outreach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2676.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2688.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, for the procedural obligation imposed by Article II to come into effect, there must exist a genuine connection between the death and the entry into force of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2688.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2701.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, as rightly stated in Para 135 of the chamber judgment, the lapse of time between the triggering event and the identification date must remain reasonably short.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2701.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2728.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it is to comply with the genuine connection standard, the chamber correctly noted that the period of 58 years between the events and the identification of the convention is not only many times longer than those which triggered the coming into effect of the procedural obligation under Article II in all previous cases, but also it is excessively long in absolute terms to establish any genuine connection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2728.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2738.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The major part of all the investigative actions and all the most significant actions in the criminal case were taken between 1990 and 1995.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2738.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2748.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No investigative actions of comparable significance or intensity were performed under 1995, as it is confirmed by the chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2748.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2765.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since then, most of the time the investigators were waiting for the Ukrainian and Belarusian authorities to finish the independent investigations, which later appeared to reveal no pieces of evidence, allowing the investigation to be pursued further.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2765.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2796.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the test formulated in the last subparagraph of Paragraph 163 in SILIC, it is necessary to emphasize that its application implies that the court is called upon to establish whether the triggering event which had happened before the ratification of the convention is of a larger dimension than an ordinary criminal offense and constitute a negation of the very foundation of the convention, such as, for instance, war crimes or crimes against humanity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2796.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2801.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Obviously, the court is prevented from performing such an assessment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2801.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2824.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regard the new material test in Para 140 of the judgment, the chamber confirmed that after 5th May 1998, no piece of evidence of a character or sentence which could revive a procedural obligation of investigation or rise new or wider issues have been produced or uncovered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2824.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2838.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the Polish authorities pointed out certain events which occurred between 5th May 1998 and 23rd September 2004 and, in their view, could warrant the court's temporal jurisdiction in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2838.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2845.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be noted, however, that none of these events were capable of undermining the conclusions of the earlier investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2845.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2848.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None of them required any fresh investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2848.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2855.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After 1995, the actions essentially amounted to the refinement of the information already obtained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2855.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2859.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No expert examinations were performed after 1998.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2859.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2872.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The documents in question are mere requests for clarification of certain circumstances forwarded to educational institutions, and the replies thereto were not joined to the criminal case file as evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2872.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2881.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The classification of certain documents cannot be viewed as new material for the purposes of triggering any investigative obligations under Article 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2881.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2897.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Requests received by the Chief Military Prosecutor Office since 1998 conserved rehabilitation information about the applicant's relatives, issues of victim status, and declassification of the case file, and didn't contain any new pieces of information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2897.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2928.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under the court's case law, a request for information, let alone a rehabilitation request, especially made many years after the killings, does not constitute a new plausible allegation, piece of evidence, or item of information relevant to the identification and eventual prosecution of or punishment of the perpetrators, such as to revive the authorities' procedural obligation to investigate the applicant's relatives' deaths and to bring their procedural obligation under Article 2 within the temporal jurisdiction of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2928.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2944.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regard the documents presented by the Ukrainian authorities in 2002, including the so-called Ukrainian cut-in list, they don't concern the execution of the Polish citizens in the spring of 1940, pursuant to the decision of 5 March 1940.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2944.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2950.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This statement is supported by the additional documents submitted by Russian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2950.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2956.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Polish authorities have failed to produce any additional documents to substantiate their allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2956.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2972.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it was ruled in Brecknell, the nature and extent of a belated or renewed investigation might be different from that to be expected immediately after a suspicious or violent deaths have occurred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2972.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2989.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The extent to which the requirements of effectiveness, independence, promptness, and expedition is simply to the family and sufficient public scrutiny apply is influenced inevitably and considerably by the passage of time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2989.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2994.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the effectiveness was undermined by objective reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2994.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3001.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regard the right of the applicants to participate effectively in the investigation, there were no grounds for securing it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3001.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3010.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the investigation was initiated in the absence of any obligations under either the domestic or international law as a goodwill gesture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3010.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3018.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the remains of the applicants' relatives have not been discovered and or identified during the exhumations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3018.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3033.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, there was no sufficient evidence for establishing a causal connection between the cut-in events and the deaths of the applicants' relatives up to the standard required for the purposes of criminal and rehabilitation proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3033.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3047.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Though the proceedings lasted 14 years and received a broad coverage in the mass media, it was not until after the discontinuation of the proceedings when two of the applicants claimed victim status for the first time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3047.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3063.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the Russian criminal procedural law does not allow granting victim status after the discontinuation of the criminal proceedings while the request of the applicants would not trigger the resumption of the criminal proceedings since the suspects were dead.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3063.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3078.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the classification of some volumes of the case file, it didn't run contrary to the public interest in uncovering the circumstance of the events and the applicants' private interest in finding out the fate of their relatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3078.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3096.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Most of the documents referred to by the applicants and the Polish authorities are located in volumes 3, 12, 14, 24, 31, and 120, which have never been classified or marked for internal use only.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3096.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3109.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These volumes are also among the 67 volumes studied by a delegation of the Polish National Remembrance Institute from 10 till 19 October 2005.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3109.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3122.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only the list of personal records of the prisoners from the Astashev camp are located in volumes 10 and 11 that used to be marked for internal use only until 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3122.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3135.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Copies of the specified volumes were officially handed over to the Polish authorities on 7th and 8th May and 23rd September 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3135.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3159.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In total, copies of 148 of 183 volumes were handed over in 2010 and 2011, including volumes 158 till 170 with the documents submitted by the Ukrainian authorities in 2002.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3159.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3181.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Copies of 20 volumes of the criminal case file and copies of the documents from the so-called case file number one, including the Politburo's decision of 5th March 1940 and the Chelyabinsk note of 3rd March 1959 were officially handed over to the Polish authorities already in 1992.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3181.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3195.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the early 90s, a lot of documents relating to the Katyn events, including those from the criminal case file, have been published freely and were available to the general public in their archives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3195.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3215.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, all the major documents relating to the Katyn events and all the few documents mentioning the applicants' relatives contained in the criminal case file have not been classified and must have been well known to the applicants and the Polish authorities long before their application to this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3215.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3220.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its third question, the court calls the applicants' relatives missing persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3220.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3222.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, they are not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3222.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3231.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the determination of the status of the applicants' relatives is crucial for establishing whether their separate issue arise under Article III.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3231.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3252.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under the court's case file, no matter whether the victim appears to be killed or missing by the end of the domestic investigation, there should be a period of time when the relatives of the victim remains in a status of uncertainty as to the fate of the victim and their suffering during the period are further aggravated by the action inaction of the authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3252.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3270.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While the exact circumstance of the death of the applicants' relatives in the present case have not been established up to the standard required for the purposes of criminal or rehabilitation proceedings, one could not have reasonably expected that they were still alive by 5th May, 1998.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3270.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3277.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it is confirmed in chamber judgment, at least after 5th May, 1998, the applicants' relatives should be presumed dead.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3277.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3285.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the applicants could have hardly remained in a state of uncertainty as to the fate of their relatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3285.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3301.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For Article III to come into play, there have to be special factors which give the suffering of the applicants a dimension and character distinct from the emotional distress which may be regarded as inevitably caused to relatives of a victim of serious violation of human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3301.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3305.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The proximity of the family ties is one of such factors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3305.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3322.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are five applicants who were born right before or after 1939 and therefore could not have known their relatives personally, and there could have been no strong family bonds established between them and their relatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3322.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3333.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the light of the court case law, the Russian authorities point out a number of circumstances that have significantly diminished the alleged aggravating impact of their actions or inactions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3333.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3340.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there has been any such impact in the present case at all, firstly, none of the applicants witnessed their events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3340.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3350.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, a period of 58 years separates the events and the date of ratification of the convention by the Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3350.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3359.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, any suffering experienced by the applicants until 1990 can be in no way attributable to the Russian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3359.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3372.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourthly, at least since 5th May 1998, the applicants' relatives cannot be considered missing persons, and the applicants cannot claim to have been in a state of uncertainty as to their fate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3372.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3384.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The replies of the chief military prosecutor's office to the request of the applicants contain all the available information about their relatives, which is based solely on the three lists of prisoners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3384.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3394.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case file contains no other documents enabling the establishment of the fate of the applicants' relatives or indicating their sites with their remains.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3394.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3404.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The list of prisoners were examined with the participation of their applicants' representatives during the domestic court proceedings and were handed over to the Polish authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3404.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3417.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The inconsistencies in their replies to the applicants' requests come to the sole question whether the circumstances of the death of their relatives have been established up to the required standard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3417.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3433.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The incorrect conclusions, which were based on a broad interpretation of the documents available in the criminal case file, were corrected by the domestic courts through the proper assessment of the documents mentioning the application relatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3433.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3441.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither the chief military prosecutor's office nor the domestic courts have ever denied the reality of the cut-in events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3441.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3452.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They merely pointed out the lack of sufficient evidence for establishing the circumstances of the death of each of the applicants' relatives up to the standard required.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3452.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3459.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reality of the cut-in events was acknowledged by the Russian authorities as early as in 1990.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3459.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3473.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had not intention to distorting or denying historical facts and subjecting the applicants to inhuman or degrading treatment by lawfully applying strict standard of proof in the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3473.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3505.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lastly, the court has on many occasions stated that in the absence of a finding of the respondent's state's responsibility for a disappearance or killing, it is not persuaded that the investigating authorities conduct, albeit negligent to the extent that it has breached Article 2 in its procedural aspect, could have in itself caused the applicants' mental distress in excess of the minimum level of severity which is necessary in order to consider treatment as falling within the scope of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3505.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3516.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regard the obligation under Article 38 of the convention, it cannot be said that Russian legislation prevents confidential information from being communicated to international organizations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3516.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3527.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It rather provides for a special procedure and requires certain arrangements to be implemented for the purposes of ensuring accountability for the possible disclosure of such information.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3527.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3537.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same provisions might very likely be foreseen in the domestic legislation or the other member states or the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3537.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3547.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Based on the Russian legislation, the competent domestic bodies have not come to a conclusion that the ruling of 21st September 2004 may be disclosed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3547.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3562.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not necessarily against the requirements of Article 38, which does not expressly oblige to disclose a state's secret information, and it does not explicitly prohibit withholding information that can impair their security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3562.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3576.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, it is not uncommon that international instruments contain express rules allowing the states to withhold information, the dissemination of which can impair their security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3576.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3586.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the courts have repeatedly accepted that the High Contracting Party enjoy a wide margin of appreciation in the sphere of national security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3586.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3596.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian authorities believe that their refusal to furnish a copy of a mentioned ruling is compatible with their obligation under Article 38.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3596.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3609.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To discharge their obligation, they provided sufficient information about this ruling, explained which agency classified it, and what their security concerns were, and indicated the grounds for the termination of the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3609.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3620.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They noted that the ruling didn't mention the applicants and contain no information about the fate of their relatives or about the location of their burial sites.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3620.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3626.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Beside that, the ruling of 21st September 2004 is an interim procedural document.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3626.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3633.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not a final judicial decision establishing the guilt of any state officials for having committed crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3633.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3642.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The validity of the classification of 36 volumes of the criminal case file was checked by the competent bodies and confirmed by the domestic courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3642.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3665.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, the Russian authorities recall that mindful of its subsidiary role and the wide margin of appreciation open to the states in matter of national security, the court usually attached significant weight to the judgment of the domestic authorities, and especially of the national courts that are better placed to assess their corresponding evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3665.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3683.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The ruling of 21st September 2004 was classified because it contains information in the sphere of intelligence, counterintelligence, and operational and search activity, which constitutes state secret under Article 5 para 4 of the law on state secrets of Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3683.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3695.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is compatible with Article 7 of this law, since the information about the violation of human rights by state officials contained therein have remained public and are assessable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3695.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3733.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>References being made to the documents stored in the archives, the documents from the so-called case file number one, which were handed over to the Polish authorities in 1992, and 20 volumes handed over to the Polish authorities in 1992, the 67 volumes, the access to which has never been restricted, and was given to the representative of the Polish authorities in 2005, as well as the 148 volumes, which were handed over to the Polish authorities in 2010 and 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3733.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3734.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3737.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3740.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. Matyushkin, for the Polish government, I call Mrs. Mężykowska.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>ThirdParty</Role>
		<Name>TP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3752.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May it please the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3764.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These oral submissions of the government of Poland are intended to complement the written submissions, bringing in mind the questions raised by the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3764.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3768.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland, of course, fully supports the claims of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3768.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3778.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also find the materials submitted by non-governmental organizations that have intervened in the proceedings to be helpful contributions to this important case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3778.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3783.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland is here today to present the matter in a broader framework.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3783.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3792.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Chamber decision notes, more than 20,000 people were murdered in what is known around the world as the Katyn massacre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3792.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3797.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The voice of the victims and of their descendants should also be heard today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3797.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3807.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Katyn crime holds a very important place in the recent history of our continent, and the judgment the Grand Chamber will deliver should reflect this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3807.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3817.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The terrible irony of these proceedings is that it was the Respondent State that initially insisted upon punishing the perpetrators of the Katyn crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3817.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3830.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At Russia's request, the Nazis were charged for the Katyn crime before the International Military Tribunal at Nuremberg with the war crimes of murder and ill-treatment of prisoners of war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3830.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3835.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the Soviet government put forward the report as an evidence of a Nazi guilt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3835.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3843.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Burden Commission report is referred to in paragraphs 18 and 19 of the Chamber decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3843.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3855.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ironically, the commission was supervised by Vsevolod Merkulov, the man behind the Katyn operation and head of the troika that signed off on the list of prisoners bound for execution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3855.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3864.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, no other single atrocity received so much attention during the Nuremberg trial as the Katyn crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3864.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3869.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nonetheless, the Katyn judgment remains silent on the subject of Katyn massacre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3869.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3880.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, paragraph 18 of the Chamber decision is not quite right when it says that the charge was dismissed by the US and British judges for lack of evidence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3880.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3885.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, the judgment did not provide any explanation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3885.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3894.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the Soviet Union's request, the indictment of the Nuremberg trial read that 11,000 Polish officers were killed in the Katyn forest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3894.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3899.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At its most recent submission, Russia suggests a number of less than 2,000.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3899.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3907.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Grand Jamba might note its contention at Nuremberg at about 11,000 and dim it a stop from making such cynical allegations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3907.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3922.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The real numbers were actually much higher, and it is now established that at least 21,857 Polish nationals were murdered at Katyn and the other atrocity sites.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3922.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3927.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Soviet lie in the Nuremberg indictment persisted for many decades.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3927.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3942.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although Russia finally admitted the crime in 1990, the dishonesty of the past continues to haunt the present litigation, as well as the continuing resistance of Russia to fully disclose the facts and documents in its possession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3942.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3948.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Russia still holds the key to the full truth behind the Katyn crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3948.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3959.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question of the Grand Jamba raises the issue of its jurisdiction and asks whether the mass murder of Polish prisoners can be characterized as war crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3959.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3971.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first significant mention of the notion of war crimes in international law appears in the report of the Commission on Responsibilities, which met during the 1919 Paris Peace Conference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3971.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3977.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Commission noted that its list was not intended to be complete and exhaustive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3977.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3993.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These discussions resulted in Article 228 of the Treaty of Versailles, which contemplated the persecution of what was called violation of the laws and customs of war, a term that is synonymous with war crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3993.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4003.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no doubt that the murder of over 20,000 prisoners is a war crime, as the term was already understood in 1919.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4003.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4014.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It appears that the Chamber accepted the conclusion that the killing, Katyn killings were a war crime, although it would have been preferable for it to say it outright.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4014.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4022.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have included in our delegation today a renote expert on the subject of war crimes and international criminal law, Professor William Schappas.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4022.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4030.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should the Court desire further clarification on this point, it might direct a question to him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4030.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4037.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Corridor of Death, the first question asked by the Grand Jamba, points to an issue that was not addressed with precision by the Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4037.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4052.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We fully understand the concern of the Grand Jamba with an interpretation of the procedural obligation in Article 2 that goes back in time long before the Convention was adopted or entered into force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4052.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4067.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Silly, the Grand Jamba spoke first of the need for a genuine connection between the death and the entry into force of the Convention for the Respondent State in order to establish the existence of a procedural obligation in such a case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4067.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4072.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Silly, the temporal proximity was quite close, a matter of about a year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4072.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4078.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, obviously, the temporal dimension is much more distant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4078.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4083.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet there can be other compelling indications of a genuine connection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4083.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4100.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Inevitably, the attempt by the Grand Jamba in Silly to identify the applicable parameters with respect to the objectival breach of the right to life was scolored by the facts in that case, which concerned a civil claim relating to medical negligence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4100.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4110.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is difficult to compare such circumstances with one of the most harrowing atrocities to take place on European soil in the past century.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4110.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4137.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We entirely endorse the remarks of the three dissenting judges in the Chamber, and now I quote, the gravity and magnitude of the war crimes perpetrated in 1940 in Katyn, Kharkov, and Tver, coupled with the attitude of the Russian authorities after the entry into force of the convention, warrant application of the special circumstances clause in the last sentence of paragraph 163.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4137.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4147.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the new material confirm that it is not some stale case, long forgotten and revived on the basis of old and well-known material.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4147.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4161.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Take, for example, the so-called Ukrainian Katyn list, which we referred to in our related pleadings, consisting of 3,435 files of victims of the 1940 massacres.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4161.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4173.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2004, the list was included, among other documents as material evidence by Russian investigators, into the case file 159.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4173.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4188.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The statement by Russia in the letter dated 17 January 2013, and today, the dimensioned list is not a list of persons who have been killed, is unfounded and contrary to the actual state of affairs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4188.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4195.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a list of murdered Polish citizens, the document is closely related to the subject matter of the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4195.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4205.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, there were absolute grounds to include it in the case, together with other documents received by way of legal assistance from Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4205.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4217.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today, some eight years ago, the decision by a competent state body of the Russian Federation in charge of the Katyn crime investigation cannot be questioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4217.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4231.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The inclusion of these 13 volumes of evidence should be seen as a breakthrough in the proceedings with respect to the murder of prisoners incarcerated in the so-called Western Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4231.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4237.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, these volumes are a source of particularly significant knowledge about the person's guilt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4237.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4243.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet, the Russian prosecutors have not carried out any analysis of the list.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4243.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4259.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regard the attempt to question its credibility, found in point 7 of the Russian memorandum, the arguments presented therein are also utterly false as evidence in our possession and not yet in the court file confirms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4259.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4273.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, attachments 2 to 6 to the Russian memorandum are not only connected to the Katyn crime, but indeed stand contrary to the Russian conclusions made under attachment number 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4273.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4289.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a general rule, the procedural obligation under article 2 will exist from the time of the interference with the right to life, although it may continue in time until the date when the convention enters into force and afterwards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4289.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4297.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A distinction must be made between the existence of the obligation and the court's jurisdiction to adjudicate a violation of the obligation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4297.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4300.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, when did the obligation begin?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4300.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4309.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as the respondent state Russia is concerned, it began in 1943 when the Burdenko Commission was sent to investigate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4309.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4316.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It certainly existed in 1945 when Russia insisted that the crime be prosecuted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4316.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4331.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason it continues to the present day is because of the decades of lies and concealment are true, followed by a period of only partial disclosure of the relevant evidence during the investigation number 159.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4331.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4341.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The nature of the interference in international atrocity crime provides another strong criterion to be weighed in the assessment of a genuine connection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4341.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4350.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The interference in Silic was not in such a category, and it seems reasonable, therefore, that a closer temporal connection be retained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4350.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4359.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Virtually all national legal systems impose statutory limitations with respect to negligence claims, some of them quite strict.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4359.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4363.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With the passage of time, they lose their salience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4363.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4368.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This cannot be the case with war crimes, crimes against humanity, and genocide.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4368.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4372.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>International law prohibits any form of statutory limitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4372.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4387.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One important reason for this is the fact that States often conceal the truth and prevent it being uncovered through amnesty and similar measures, or through sheer denial and dishonesty, as in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4387.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4401.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is unlikely that the Grand Chamber will ever get a better opportunity to explain the scope of the seemingly enigmatic words in the last sentence of paragraph 163 of the Sili v. Slovenia judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4401.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4406.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Necessarily, it is a test that depends upon the circumstances of each individual case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4406.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4409.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Wisely in Sili v. Slovenia, the Court</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4409.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4425.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>left itself a degree of flexibility and did not foreclose the possibility of addressing the procedural obligation under Article II with respect to any particular interference by setting a precise date that might result in a formulaic response.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4425.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4441.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The suggestion that 3rd September 153, the date of entry into force of the Convention, might fulfill a useful purpose here simply returns the Court to the straitjacket that was suggested by the Respondent State in Sili.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4441.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4448.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It replaces one inappropriate date, the entry into force for the Respondent State, with another.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4448.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4462.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Poland suggests that the Court adopt a functional approach to this problem, one that resists an essentially technical or procedural solution and that takes into account the nature of the substantive infringement of Article II.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4462.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4466.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is nothing uncertain about such a standard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4466.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4484.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, an emphasis on this factor will assist the Court in establishing legal certainty with respect to pre-ratification interferences with one of the basic values of democratic societies making up the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4484.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4496.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Answering the Court's question concerning the effectiveness of the Russian investigation, the Polish government regrets to reiterate that the Russian cut in investigation has not been conducted effectively.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4496.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4503.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our written observation on this, we already pointed out several instances of the lack of effectiveness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4503.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4517.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, we would like only to emphasize, as did one of the third parties, that there still are possibilities to investigate crimes committed in the distant past under previous regimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4517.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4536.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Answering in a most diligent way the Court's question concerning Article 38 of the Convention, it is important to underline that according to obtainable information, the classification of the decision to discontinue the domestic proceedings is itself incompatible with Russian law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4536.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4541.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, the decision constitutes a violation of substantive law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4541.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4559.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 7 of the Federal Act on State Secrets specifies that it is forbidden to classify as a State secret information on violations of human and civil rights and liberties, as well as information on any violation of law by public authorities and their officials.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4559.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4572.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the protection of personal data can also not be seen as a premise for classification of documents due to the lapse of the 30-year classification period that applies to such data.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4572.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4583.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such an interpretation of the Act of State Secret was reaffirmed in the latest ruling of the Constitutional Court of the Russian Federation, dated 15 January 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4583.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4591.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the ruling in question is unlawful under Russian law, as it constitutes a violation of formal law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4591.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4598.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be assumed that the materials were classified as secret only by marking them with a relevant classification level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4598.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4602.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is in violation of the established procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4602.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4616.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, it should be noted that the classification of the file materials concerns events that took place 71 years ago and which by no means have any bearing on the present security of the Russian State.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4616.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4634.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no justification under the Convention to place the alleged public interest to protect the circumstances and suspect of the cutting of the crime perpetrated by a totalitarian regime above the continuing interest of the applicants to learn the fate of their closest relatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4634.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4635.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The whole respectfully submits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4640.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4644.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mrs. Mężykowska.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4644.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4648.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's the end of the first round.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4648.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4653.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this first part, I told to my colleagues there is questions from the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4656.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4659.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No, it's not the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4659.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4667.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I will give the floor to the applicant representatives for your reactions for 10 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4667.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4670.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Who wish to take the floor?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4670.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4673.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, Mr. Kamiński.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4698.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4703.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. President, members of the distinguished court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4703.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4712.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Very briefly, to react to the arguments presented by the representative of the Russian Federation's government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4712.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4736.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We cannot agree that the cutting massacre, we call it massacre, we don't call it cutting events because it's offensive, was committed by another state, by the Soviet Union, from which the Russian Federation is completely separated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4736.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4750.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian Federation is the legal successor of the Soviet Union, so there is continuity between the Soviet Union and Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4750.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4782.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our memorandum, we also provided numerous references to international law, to international case law, precising that the definition of war crime consisting in killings of prisoners of war was clearly defined before the war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4782.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4809.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If we look, for example, at the Nuremberg tribunal proceedings, there were some hesitations about the definition of the crime against peace, about the crime of aggression, but no, I stress this, no problems arise as to the definition of the war crime of killings of prisoners of war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4809.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4820.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this crime was clearly defined, both its content and the scope of responsibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4820.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4855.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the Nuremberg tribunal, as well as other post-war trials, were very, very specific about this issue, stressing that the responsibility for war crimes, for killing innocent prisoners of war, was not limited only to state responsibility, but also individuals were responsible for such atrocities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4855.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4869.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also disagree that there is a retroactive application of the convention as suggested by Minister Matuszkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4869.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4907.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In my argumentation, and this part of argumentation is elaborated in the memorandum, we addressed these questions in details, identifying the case law of the Permanent Court of International Justice and the International Court of Justice, and the distinction I mentioned in my address between the origin of some rights and the origin of dispute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4907.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4941.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The root of a dispute must be located after the ratification period, but the origin of rights can be located in the pre-ratification period, if they are of continuous nature, of autonomous nature, of detachable nature, as it is with the investigative obligations in case of killings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4941.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4956.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also stress in our observations, in our memorandum, the significance of the case law of the Inter-American Court of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4956.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4996.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Inter-American Court was confronted with many massacres committed by state agents, and this case is relevant for the temporary questions or questions related to the competence ratione temporis of the judicial institutions, and the Inter-American Court did not require any, any new material, new element surfacing after the ratification period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4996.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5033.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also very respectfully draw the attention of the Court to the Gomez-Lund case of the Inter-American Court of Human Rights, in which the triggering act of a massacre of 70 people was located before the entrance of the Inter-American Convention into force, but was adjudicated in 2010, so 40 years after the killings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5033.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5046.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this case law is very, very relevant, with all respect deserved, also for the European Court of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5046.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5064.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the Ukrainian list, I will only stress that I'm not a historian, but looking at the materials in the attachment to the letter of the Russian Federation government of the 17th of January this year, I discovered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5278.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5282.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Kamiński.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5282.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5283.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Matyushkin, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5289.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5294.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, let me try two short remarks.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5294.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5322.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First one, let me object the evaluation of so-called Ukrainian cut-in list, which we heard now from a respectable representative of applicant because it was independent investigation of Ukrainian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5322.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5334.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ukraine is independent state, member of Council of Europe, and not the participant in this procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5334.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5353.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's why we don't think that evaluation of significance of this document should be done in frames of this procedure, historical or legal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5353.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5405.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, we welcome the fact that respectable representative of Polish government in her speech actually confirm and share our position that no investigative activity took place in 2002 on the basis of this Ukrainian list of person which Russian authorities got from Ukrainian authorities because we think that this point is very important from the point of view of evaluation of obstacles from criteria rata temporis in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5405.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5405.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5408.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5411.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5411.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5413.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5413.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5417.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5417.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5421.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5421.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5425.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5425.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5430.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of the delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5430.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5430.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
