<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>5746715_24062020</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>11.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>13.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Good morning, please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>16.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>29.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome all participants to this public hearing organized by the European Court of Human Rights with the use of video conferencing technology which has been made necessary due to the COVID-19 health crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>29.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>41.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wish to begin by thanking the applicant and the respondent government for their cooperation in preparing this hearing on the merits in the case of Savran versus Denmark, which I now declare open.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>41.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>50.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should note before proceeding that this hearing is being recorded in its entirety and will be webcast in order to ensure its public character.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>50.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>57.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It will be available to the public on the court's website tomorrow, Thursday, June 25.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>57.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>69.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The present application was lodged with the court on 16 November 2015 under Article 34 of the convention by a Turkish national, Mr. Arif Savran.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>69.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>81.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was allocated to the fourth section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the rules of court and was communicated to the government on 20 June 2017.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>81.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>88.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 1st October 2019, a chamber of the fourth section delivered its judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>88.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>104.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It declared the application admissible and held by four votes to three that the applicant's expulsion to Turkey would give rise to a violation of Article 3 of the convention and that it was not necessary to examine his complaint under Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>104.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>119.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 12 December 2019, the government requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the convention, and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on 27 January 2020.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>119.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>142.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Leave to intervene under Article 36, paragraph 2 of the convention and Rule 44, 3 of the rules of court was granted to the governments of France, Germany, the Netherlands, Norway, Russia, Switzerland, and the United Kingdom, and to Amnesty International and the Center of Research and Studies of Fundamental Rights of the Paris-Nanterre University.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>142.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>150.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government of Turkey did not avail themselves of their right to intervene under Article 36, paragraph 1 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>150.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>159.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this hearing, the respondent government are represented by their agent, Mr. Michael Braad, and their co-agent, Ms. Nina Holst-Christensen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>159.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>177.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are assisted by Ms. Lisbeth Kunnerup, Ms. Anna-Sophie Saugmann-Jensen, Ms. Øzlem Akar, Mr. Christian Wegener, Ms. Sara Sarah Larsen, Ms.  Cathrine Engsig Sørensen, Ms. Maria Korsgård  Thomsen, Ms. Sofie  Bach Andersen, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>177.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>183.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mr. Tyge Trier, counsel, and Mr. Anders Boelskifte, co-counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>183.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>188.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are assisted by Ms. Sabrine Hussain and Ms. Thea Husum, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>188.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>193.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>193.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>200.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representatives of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>200.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>203.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Trier for the applicant will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>203.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>206.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mr. Braad for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>206.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>211.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Trier, you have the floor, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>215.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>220.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President, distinguished judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>220.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>233.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'll start by mentioning a core element that the Supreme Court convicted our client to psychiatric treatment and ruled that Mr. Savran was mentally insane</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>233.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>235.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>at the time of the crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>235.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>252.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will also stress that he has been in closed hospital from 6 May 2008 until 23 June 2015, more than seven years and one month in a psychiatric hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>252.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>258.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the detailed description of the treatment of Mr. Savran as an inpatient at the St. John</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>258.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>265.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hospital, and I refer to the important role of his guardian.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>265.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>285.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also will mention that he has low intellectual level, is dependent on follow-up, and he has to ensure that he gets continuous treatment, and he gets regular visits with his family while he's in treatment in the hospital in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>287.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>302.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here in the beginning, I also state that the chief physicians said that an essential element of his treatment is monitoring and follow-up by qualified staff.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>302.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>311.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Severe mental suffering, as in this case, can be interpreted in the category exceptional cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>311.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>323.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This has to be done by the court on a case-by-case review, but it also has to take into account the potential consequences of a removal of a patient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>323.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>336.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This can constitute a real risk of being exposed to serious, rapid, and even irreversible decline in his state of health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>336.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>351.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 3 protects against the risk of significant deterioration or worsening of the threshold established in Papua New Guinea.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>351.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>358.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I argue today that the significant worsening for Mr. Saverin established a clear risk</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>358.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>362.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of inhuman, degrading treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>362.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>370.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding our client, I refer to the forensic psychiatric reports from St. John.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>370.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>380.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They describe the consequences of an abruption of his treatment and the consequences of his mental health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>380.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>386.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reports also state the different components of his treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>386.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>399.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Strong medication with prescriptions that require a close follow-up and attention to possible side effects in weekly or monthly blood samples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>399.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>408.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also involves family and social relations to support him and to hold the structure and the frames.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>408.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>421.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It includes a contact person to motivate that he follows treatment and takes his medication to keep him away from the environment and the drug abuse that can cause a relapse for him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>421.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>434.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also to pay attention to any side effects of the medication that he cannot see and he cannot react to on his own.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>434.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>438.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I stress today, Mr. President, that the treatment and care</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>438.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>441.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>at the St. John Hospital consisted</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>441.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>461.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of medical treatment, psychiatric nursing care, conversation therapy, environment therapy, physical training, occupational activities, including physical work that he did in the garden of the hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>461.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>472.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of this to secure to him that he had structure and frames and motivation which was necessary for treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>472.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>477.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I stress that St. John is a leading psychiatric hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>477.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>484.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is owned by the Danish government and it employs a staff of 600 persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>484.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>493.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the description in the annexes, especially our annex 8 to the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>493.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>504.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The complaint today is based on the de facto lack of the necessary and required treatment for his mental illness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>504.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>519.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To prevent a relapse, supervision by a regular contact person is essential, such as the existence of a family and social network, as we see in the statement from the chief physicians.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>522.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>529.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The appropriate care should be available in practice and not merely in general.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>529.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>541.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I know today that Savran has not had any access to a psychiatrist since his arrival in Turkey five years ago.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>541.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>555.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The few times he has seen a doctor, it has been a somatic treating doctor, and sometimes no doctor, only a nurse or a secretary in the hospital in Konya.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>555.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>571.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although psychiatric treatment is available in general in Turkey, a follow up and control scheme by means of a regular contact person is essential for his treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>571.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>586.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the forensic psychiatric reports from the chief physicians, which were provided at an official request of the state prosecutor in Copenhagen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>586.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>607.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These reports, which the court indeed is familiar with, cannot leave any doubt as to the professionalism, the expertise, or the validity of the diagnosis given by the chief physician Lubincin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>607.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>616.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His statement is fully consistent with the detailed reports by two other chief physicians at the hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>616.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>628.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I note here that my client was in hospital full time, 24-7, at the hospital for more than four years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>628.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>632.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>March 11 to June 15.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>632.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>636.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Highly qualified specialized staff followed him around the clock.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>639.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>653.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The declaration by Lubincin is fully supported by his testimony under oath in court, both in October 14 and January 15.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>653.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>666.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is fully supported by the detailed medical statements by Adam Ikova in April 13 and Hauge Massen in July 13.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>666.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>669.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I stress, Mr. President, that the medical documentation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>669.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>675.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>in this case is very clear, very strong, and very solid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>675.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>685.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's from the most senior medical expertise, and it's an internationally recognized specialized hospital in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>685.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>698.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'll find it quite surprising if anyone can dispute the professionalism by these three very senior doctors and the qualities of their certificates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>698.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>706.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I saw that Germany talked about in their statement to the court a qualified medical certificate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>706.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>718.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I stressed before the court today that these certificates are exactly the qualified medical certificate that Germany relies on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>718.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>745.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The city court did fully correctly and in full compliance with the jurisprudence of the court, not based their decision merely on availability of medicine and treatment in general in Turkey, but made in accordance with what is required by Article 3, an assessment of the de facto availability for SAVRAN in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>745.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>758.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also note that the Danish authorities had three months from the city court's decision to secure a real possibility of receiving relevant treatment in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>758.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>763.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the authorities did nothing in the three months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>763.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>771.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I emphasize the severity of his mental illness, which is described in the written statements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>771.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>786.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is indeed a very serious illness, and it's officially recognized internationally via specific diagnostics, including by the World Health Organization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>786.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>804.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's also medically well-established that this specific mental illness can be of such a severe degree that inadequate treatment can result in serious, rapid, and irreversible decline of the health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>804.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>818.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This turns to intense suffering, or it results in significant reduction in the life expectancy, and it poses a threat to the patient's own safety and the safety of others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>821.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>845.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The consultant psychiatrist clearly described the importance and the crucial effect of not only medicine, but also other components of his treatment, the regular contact person, the supervision, the ongoing follow-up to prevent relapses for Mr. SAVRAN.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>845.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>879.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will stress today that after seven years in psychiatric intensive care from May 2008 and until 2015, more than seven years, his health did not at any time reach the level of independence from medicine so he could be transferred to an outpatient category not one single day was Mr. SAVRAN outside the 24-7</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>879.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>882.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>at the hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>882.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>891.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I find that the High Court in Copenhagen made an error by stating that he understands his medicine, and then he could get it in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>894.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>908.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I stressed he did not have the mental capacity to ensure treatment for himself, and he did de facto not have access to treatment in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>910.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>918.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From this, I then go on to the case law of the court, and I'll have to be brief on the quotations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>918.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>929.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I start with Tarakel, and I stress that the principles of Tarakel are very relevant in SAVRAN's case. I stress the absence</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>929.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>937.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of appropriate psychiatric treatment would worsen his symptoms and increase the risk of aggressive behavior.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>937.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>952.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I note that the Danish authority failed to secure assurances from Turkey prior to the removal of SAVRAN in June 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>952.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>967.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to paragraph 121 in Tarakel, which requires a detailed and reliable information concerning the specific facility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>967.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>972.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is essential that this was obtained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>972.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>975.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was not obtained by the Danish authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>975.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>985.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I note that the MedCorp report in the case only talks about medication in general terms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>985.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>989.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The call today, Mr. President, is that Denmark failed</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>989.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>995.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to get sufficient assurances before returning him to Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>995.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1006.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They failed to secure that he would be taken care of in a manner adapted to his specific health and mental illness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1006.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1012.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have today to put a few remarks to the MedCorp report.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1012.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1018.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have it here in front of me. It's annex 4 to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1018.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1022.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is an older statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1022.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1026.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is about a female from Belgium.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1026.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1032.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a woman who does not suffer from paranoid schizophrenia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1032.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1037.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She has other less serious mental issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1037.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1044.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also highlight that the patient was not medicated with respidil.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1044.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1048.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The patient was not medicated with Leponix.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1048.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1058.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's a totally different or very different Belgian female case, which is the basis for the decision in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1058.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1068.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also note from the MedCorp that Turkey has the lowest rate of psychiatrists inside all of the European countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1068.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1073.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this further supports that the MedCorp statement is not sufficient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1073.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1076.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not about Mr. Savran.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1076.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1079.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was about another person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1079.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1086.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The call of Tarkel is that Denmark should have secured individual guarantees from Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1086.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1089.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They didn't.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1089.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1096.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I move on to Tatar, another Switzerland case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1096.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1113.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here the court says that suffering associated with relapse and the possibility of self-harm could in principle fall within the scope of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1113.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1135.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court in Tatar emphasized that Switzerland committed to make every effort to secure he would not have a pause in his treatment, and he would have access to medical care he needs in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1135.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1144.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is particularly relevant for my client, and it is obvious that the assurances from Tatar was not given.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1144.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1147.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I go to Papusvili.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1147.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1166.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is clearly established in that case, and I don't need to spend so much time on it, but the core of Papusvili is that it's de facto accessibility of treatment, and it's to consider the particular vulnerability of the person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1166.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1170.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the core of the case today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1170.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1183.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The burden of proof in Papusvili is to secure the government to secure the existence of real and practical access.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1183.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1195.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court says in Papusvili that the authorities has greater investigative resources, and this is exactly the situation here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1195.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1207.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in Papusvili, the court also says that access to medical care cannot be theoretical, but must be real and guaranteed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1207.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1213.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, in this case, the burden of proof does not lie with Mr. Sabran when</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1213.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1222.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>he has presented prima facie evidence in the form of the many forensic declarations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1222.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1231.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's for the government to demonstrate that there are indeed resources available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1231.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1243.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's for the government to dispel the doubts, as the court says in Papusvili, but the high court in Denmark failed to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1243.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1249.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I go to Aswad from 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1249.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1265.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I find it very important that the court seven years ago stated that deterioration of a person's mental health is capable of reaching the Article III threshold.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1265.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1277.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Aswad, the court refers to current medical evidence, and Aswad is also suffering from paranoid schizophrenia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1277.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1288.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court unanimously found in favor of Aswad, and I argue today that Aswad follows Tarakel, Papusvili, and Tata.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1291.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1308.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The importance of family is also mentioned by the court in MT versus Sweden, where it's directly stated by the court that the family was actively assisting him, that they were available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1308.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1313.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The family is there in the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1313.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1318.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sabran had no family available in the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1318.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1326.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will then briefly mention two cases about schizophrenic custody persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1326.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1334.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first one is Musial versus Poland from 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1334.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1339.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Musial was seen by staff on a daily basis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1339.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1349.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court says he was feeling inferior and powerless, and there was required increased vigilance is called for.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1349.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1352.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is exactly what we are having today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1352.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1363.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the court also says in Musial that the detrimental effect on his health is in human degrading treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1363.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1366.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I find Musial relevant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1366.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1383.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same is stated in G versus France from 23 February 2012, where the court talks in G versus France about the extreme vulnerability and uses the phrase hardship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1386.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1394.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>G is subjected to hardship exceeding the level of suffering inherent in detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1394.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1396.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This also shows the standard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1396.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1416.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two more judgments, Ruman versus Belgium from the Grand Chamber in January last year, specifically refers to the 2004 recommendation number 10 of the Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1416.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1430.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That recommendation mentions in Article 12 adequately qualified staff and appropriate individually prescribed treatment plans.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1430.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1437.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A treatment plan is required when you have serious mental illness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1437.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1447.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ruman also shows the increased protection by the European court of the mentally ill inside the convention system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1447.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1455.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The last judgment to mention is Ben Said versus UK.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1455.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1460.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me stress, Mr. President, the facts of Ben Said and Sabran</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1460.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1463.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>are substantially different.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1463.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1471.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ben Said has schizophrenia, but he was not paranoid schizophrenic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1471.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1477.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sabran has been seven years permanently in closed ward hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1477.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1482.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ben Said had been in hospital for a few days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1482.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1492.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ben Said had his parents and five brothers and sisters in Algeria, and he had only lived 11 years in the UK.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1492.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1494.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sabran has no family in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1494.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1502.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He does not speak the language, and he has been away for much longer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1502.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1505.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ben Said is, in my opinion, still valid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1505.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1516.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is still below the Article 3 threshold, Ben Said versus UK, in my opinion, but Sabran is certainly not below the threshold.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1516.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1522.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I then turn to the third party interventions, and I'll come with a few remarks to those.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1522.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1532.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to emphasize the University of Paris-Nanterre's statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1532.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1538.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is very important, and it has a wealth of legal sources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1538.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1551.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also note that they talk about the American Psychiatric Association's guidelines, including the importance of a family intervention for this type of intervention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1551.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1554.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For this type of psychiatric patient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1554.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1563.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a core matter for my client, both under Article 3 and under Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1563.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1573.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will highlight the Gardner versus Canada decision, which is mentioned in there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1573.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1594.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was a paranoid schizophrenic, and there was a violation of the covenant because he was, as the committee said, effectively resulted in an abrupt withdrawal of available medical and family support.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1594.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1607.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the same as in our case, and I find it important that the Human Rights Committee arrives at the same conclusion as the chamber did in Savron.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1607.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1621.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Amnesty International, I also refer to them, especially that they state that mental health is on a par with physical health.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1621.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1628.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they stress that access to medical intervention should be seen as a broader concept.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1628.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1646.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The German intervention in this case, I note that they explicitly state that the practice in Germany is to qualify whether there's a contact person for a mentally ill person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1646.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1653.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So Germany basically says the same as the majority said in Savron.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1653.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1670.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also note that the Netherlands state in their case the Netherlands state in their intervention that having a social or family network may be necessary to effectively access the care.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1670.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1678.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Germany and Netherlands speak about the importance of the family network and a contact person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1680.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1688.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Switzerland, they refer to some cat decision in the Committee Against Torture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1688.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1704.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will highlight, and I send it to the court on e-comms this morning and to the government, AN versus Switzerland, 3 August 2018.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1704.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1712.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was again a person with a very serious mental disease.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1712.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1730.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He provided medical reports and the committee states a violation of the torture convention because of the lack of specialized medical treatment and the absence of any family support in Italy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1730.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1733.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This would prevent his full rehabilitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1736.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1749.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The absence of a stable social environment provided by his brother and the ill treatment would entail a risk of his medical condition being worsened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1749.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1754.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was a breach of the torture convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1754.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1757.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the majority in Savron does not stand alone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1757.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1768.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are together with the Committee Against Torture and the Human Rights Committee in Geneva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1768.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1774.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 8, I don't have much time, Mr. President,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1774.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1792.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>so I'll basically refer to the written comments there, stressing that he was, our client was very much relying on his mother and his sisters and brothers in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1792.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1801.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will then say a few words towards the end about his situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1801.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1804.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I do this together with my colleague, Bollskifte.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1804.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1807.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Savron is very weak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1807.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1812.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He's seriously ill with his paranoid schizophrenic disease.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1812.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1819.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He needs permanent medical treatment, which he does not get at all in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1819.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1824.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He's completely helpless, and he feels inferior and powerless.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1824.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1830.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He is, in fact, in a terrible state, and he is devastated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1830.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1834.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He's alone, and he is on his own.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1834.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1845.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He has no family or relatives in the village, nor in other parts of Turkey, and he lives very isolated as he does not speak the Turkish language.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1845.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1855.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His illness, his limited mental capacity means he cannot learn a new language on a level that can support social engagement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1855.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1857.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He stays inside.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1857.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1870.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He does not know the streets, and therefore he's afraid of getting lost and not being able to find his wake, again bearing in mind his strongly diminished intellectual capacity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1870.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1879.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He found his way to the hospital in Konya for the first time six months after his arrival in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1879.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1886.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was in touch with a doctor for a few minutes and showed a piece of paper describing the medication in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1886.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1900.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The doctor didn't do an examination, a health check, or any kind of follow-up on his development and mental health, and the doctor was a somatic doctor, not a psychiatrist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1900.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1906.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Availability of medicine for him is to a very high degree random and ad hoc.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1906.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1908.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's no follow-up.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1908.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1913.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's no monitoring by professionals of him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1913.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1929.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's no follow-up to see if he fails to show up, and neither does the hospital at all follow up on side effects of the medication, even though his side effects can be of a very serious degree.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1929.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1943.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hospital is not a psychiatric hospital, as the Danish government has stated, but a public hospital that treats somatic illnesses, and the doctor he communicates with is not a psychiatrist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1943.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1949.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At times, the doctor has not been available, and he only gets access to a secretary at the hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1949.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1958.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was last there in March 2020, and he communicated very briefly with a nurse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1958.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1965.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has asked us to present his status, but we cannot, Mr. President,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1965.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1970.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>provide reports of his medical assessment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1970.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1981.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He does not receive any treatment, and he does not even have a contact person or a psychiatric consultant available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1981.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1995.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I note, regarding the burden of proof, that Denmark has not provided any medical status, neither has the Turkish government about Mr. Sabran.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1995.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1999.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn, Mr. President, to my concluding remarks,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1999.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2005.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and I only have two minutes left.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2005.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2012.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government seems to argue that the threshold of Article 3 is lowered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2012.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2023.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We strongly dispute this, and we also dispute that a contact person is only a social measure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2023.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2025.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not only a social measure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2025.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2038.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's an integrated and pivotal element of the medical treatment of a paranoid schizophrenic patient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2038.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2053.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, we highlight Judge Lemons and the other judges' statement in the majority, the essential role of monitoring a follow-up scheme and a contact person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2053.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2075.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And again, I stress that several psychiatric evaluations were produced on behalf of the state prosecutor, so the medical certificates that the court is asking in Papusvili, they were fully in place here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2075.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2096.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, it's a legal forensic declaration inside the official criminal justice system that was given to the courts in Denmark, which also secures their validity, the seriousness of the statements by the doctors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2096.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2099.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Last sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2099.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2114.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From seven years behind closed doors, behind locked doors in a psychiatric hospital, my client had intensive treatment day in and day out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2114.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2130.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From this to the imminent risk of de facto no treatment in Turkey, a fear that was very sadly materialized from June 2015 onwards, and is still today, Mr. President,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2130.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2136.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a devastating reality five years later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2136.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2151.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Close monitoring and follow-up to secure effective treatment was required, and the high court in Copenhagen let him down on this Article 3 protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2151.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2159.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 3 enshrines one of the most fundamental values of a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2159.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2168.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Grand Chamber stated last year in Roman, the city court in Copenhagen secured Mr. Savran</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2168.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2176.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>his Article 3 rights, and I respectfully urge the Grand Chamber to do the same today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2176.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2187.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This in full accordance with the already well-established standards from the court's rich jurisprudence on Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2187.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2187.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2191.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2193.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2193.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2199.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Trier, I confirm that both your audio and video was very clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2199.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2202.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We now turn to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2202.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2203.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Braad, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2203.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2203.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2208.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2211.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2211.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2217.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it's an honor to appear before you again on behalf of the Danish government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2217.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2235.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case before you today concerns the question whether the expulsion of the applicant, a 35-year-old criminal alien suffering from paranoid schizophrenia, was compliant with Article 3 and with Article 8 of the European Convention on Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2235.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2249.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was deported to Turkey on 23rd June 2015 based on a conviction for assault under highly aggravating circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2249.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2259.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the Danish government's opinion, the expulsion of the applicant did not violate Article 3 or Article 8 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2259.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2270.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The main issue at hand is the interpretation of Article 3 in connection with the removal of a mentally ill person to his country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2270.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2285.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The key question is whether absence of a regular and personal contact person in the applicant's home country is sufficient to bring the case within the scope of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2285.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2305.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the answer to that question is yes, it would constitute a very significant broadening of the scope of Article 3 in an area politically very sensitive to many contracting states and with potentially far-reaching resource implications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2305.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2307.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I will start my submission</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2307.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2323.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by focusing on the chamber judgment, and I will then turn to the specific question of the majority's application of the criteria established by the Grand Chamber in the case Papasvili versus Belgium from 2016 and the scope of Article 3 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2323.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2330.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I will then conclude with a few observations on the question of Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2330.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2353.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The majority of the members of the chamber found that the Danish authorities should have assured themselves that upon the applicant's return to Turkey, a regular and personal contact person would be offered by the Turkish authorities as part of this treatment, and that this amounted to a violation of Article 3 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2353.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2365.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government respectfully disagrees with this conclusion and disagrees with the majority's application of the criteria as established by the Grand Chamber in the Papasvili case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2365.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2372.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we also disagree with the applicant's counsel's reading of the Papasvili case as presented here this morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2372.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2383.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And let me explain why by recalling the very specific and the very explicit criteria established in the Papasvili judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2383.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2398.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the crucial paragraph 183 of the Papasvili judgment, the court clarified the meaning of the term, and I quote, very exceptional cases used in the judgment in versus the United Kingdom from 2008.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2398.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2442.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court found that other than imminent death, the term should be understood to refer to, and I quote, situations involving the removal of a seriously ill person in which substantial grounds have been shown for believing that he or she, although not at an imminent risk of dying, would face a real risk on account of the absence of appropriate treatment in the receiving country or the lack of access to such treatment of being exposed to a serious, rapid, and irreversible decline in his or her state of health, resulting in intense suffering or to a significant reduction in life expectancy, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2442.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2456.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, with this clarification, the court established two separate criteria for determining whether a removal of a seriously ill alien to his country of origin would violate Article III.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2456.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2464.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the criteria may be referred to as, one, the severe disease criterion, and secondly, the treatment criterion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2464.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2482.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, it follows from the severe disease criterion that consequences to the alien's health in the event of removal may raise questions under Article III, but only if the alien in question suffers from, quote, a serious illness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2482.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2505.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A further requirement is that in case of removal, a lack of proper medical treatment would expose the alien to, and again, I quote, a serious, rapid, and irreversible decline in his or her state of health, resulting in intense suffering or to a significant reduction in life expectancy, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2505.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2525.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it follows from the treatment criterion that it has to be assessed whether the care generally available in the receiving state is sufficient and appropriate, and also whether the individual in question will actually have access to the care, to such care and facilities in the receiving state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2525.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2547.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And contrary to what the applicant is arguing, it's only when both the disease criterion and the treatment criterion are satisfied that the returning state must obtain an individual and sufficient assurance from the receiving state that appropriate treatment will be available and accessible to the persons concerned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2547.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2550.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, it's very important to note the relationship</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2550.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2555.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>between the severe disease criterion and the treatment criterion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2555.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2564.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The severe disease criterion is, as pointed out by the dissenting judges in the chamber of judgment, it's a threshold criterion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2564.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2574.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The criterion must be satisfied before it's even relevant to assess the treatment option in the event of removal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2574.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2587.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, it's only when the consequences to the applicant's health upon removal reach the level required by the severe disease criterion that the relevant treatment options must be assessed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2590.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2592.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the government would</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2592.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2600.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>challenge the chamber majority's application of the Papu Shvili criteria and would do so based on two grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2600.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2616.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the government submits that the severe disease criterion set out in the Papu Shvili judgment is not applicable in determining whether the removal of mentally ill aliens would be in violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2616.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2631.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In cases involving mental illness, a very high threshold should be maintained in line with the court's previous case law, as for example, in the cases of Ben Said versus the United Kingdom and Tata versus Switzerland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2631.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2650.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is based on the consideration that due to its nature, the symptoms, and possible treatment, mental illness cannot be treated in the same way as terminal or other very serious physical illness that requires continued intensive treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2650.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2658.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I refer to paragraphs 30 to 36 of our memorial for elaboration on this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2658.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2674.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, assuming that the criterion actually does apply in the present case concerning a mentally ill alien, the government submits that the criterion has not been applied correctly by the chamber and not been met in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2677.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2687.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The majority did assess the treatment criterion, but it did not apply the threshold criterion concerning severe disease.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2687.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2698.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also in the assessment of the relevant treatment options, that is the access to a regular contact person, the majority applied a new and a broader reading of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2698.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2703.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I will elaborate on this in the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2703.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2718.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As stated in our memorial, paragraph 13, the Danish courts carefully assessed the impact of the removal of the applicant, the impact on the applicant's health, in light of the information provided by national health authorities and medical experts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2718.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2730.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Obviously, the courts did not take into account the specific published really severe disease criterion, simply because the courts made the decisions before the published really judgment was handed down.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2730.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2754.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, there's absolutely no basis in the medical information presented to the Danish courts or in the Danish courts assessment for concluding that the applicant upon removal would be in risk of consequences exceeding the high threshold established by the severe disease criterion in the published really judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2754.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2771.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None of the medical statements presented before the Danish courts indicated that the applicant would risk, and I quote, intense suffering or, and again I quote, significant reduction in life expectancy in case of removal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2771.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2783.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The medical statements did indicate, inter alia, how the applicant would potentially become aggressive and dangerous to others in case he would not receive his prescribed medication.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2783.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2790.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this is not sufficient to meet the severe disease criterion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2790.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2793.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here the government refers to paragraph 40 of our memorial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2793.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2796.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It describes the medical information presented to the Danish courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2796.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2815.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it appears from this information, inter alia, that the applicant had complete awareness of his illness, was highly motivated for psychiatric treatment, including treatment with psychoactive drugs, and that he clearly acknowledged his need for therapy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2815.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2824.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also appears that he had a good prospect of recovery if subjected to follow up and control in connection with intense outpatient therapy when discharged.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2827.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2851.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This clearly demonstrates that the applicant's situation did not satisfy the threshold criterion, including the requirement that the applicant would risk a serious, rapid, and irreversible decline in his state of health, resulting in, and I quote, intense suffering on his removal to Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2851.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2864.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also recalls that the Danish High Court, in its decision on 13 February 2015, found that the applicant's health did not, in a decisive way, speak against his removal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2864.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2875.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The High Court stressed the information provided on specific treatment options and found that in these circumstances, removal of the applicant was not contrary to Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2878.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2883.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is correct that the Danish City Court had previously reached a different conclusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2883.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2896.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It did so with reference, in particular, to the medical doctor's assessment of the risk of a resumed substance abuse and that the applicant would potentially, again, become aggressive and potentially assault other persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2899.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2906.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So neither of the two decisions gives basis for concluding that the severe disease criterion is satisfied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2911.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2917.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The majority did not consider whether the disease criterion was met in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2917.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2925.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The majority simply stated, in paragraph 63, that returning the applicant to Turkey would cause him, and I quote, additional hardship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2929.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2941.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This clearly does not reach the high threshold established in the Papus-Willi case, where the requirement is, and I quote again, intense suffering or significant reduction in life expectancy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2943.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2949.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the majority then proceeded directly to assess whether the treatment criterion was satisfied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2951.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2954.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now this is a critical point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2954.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2958.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The severe disease criterion is, as I mentioned, a threshold criterion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2958.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2968.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the criterion is not satisfied, there can be no violation of Article 3, according to the court's jurisprudence, and no matter the relevant treatment options.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2971.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2984.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One could ask the question here, whether the majority just dealt with the criterion implicitly before proceeding to apply the Papus-Willi treatment criterion on availability and accessibility of medical treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2984.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2987.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And accessibility of medical treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2989.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3008.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But even if that was the case, then for the reasons that I've already mentioned, there was no basis in the medical information or in the assessment by the Danish courts for concluding that the severe disease criterion was satisfied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3008.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3013.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The medical assessment of the applicant points to the following risk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3013.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3024.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the applicant is not subjected to appropriate treatment, he may resume substance abuse, and this may worsen his psychotic symptoms and may lead to aggressive behavior towards others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3027.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3044.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So while this demonstrates that the applicant does suffer from a mental illness requiring treatment, it does not demonstrate that the applicant would, upon removal, be subject to intense suffering, meeting the high threshold of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3044.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3057.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A conclusion that the applicant would risk intense suffering therefore does not rest on medical grounds, nor does it rest on an assessment by the national Danish courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3057.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3070.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is therefore the opinion of the government that the Chamber acted as a court of fourth instance and that it did not have any new medical basis for reaching its conclusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3070.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3077.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to draw the court's attention to the information provided by the applicant himself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3077.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3088.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It cannot be deduced from this information that he has experienced any relapses or any worsening of his psychotic symptoms after his deportation to Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3088.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3101.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the contrary, according to his own information and what we heard this morning, he has been able to consult a somatic doctor when needed and has received medical treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3101.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3117.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hardship described by the applicant of staying indoors in a village, not speaking Turkish and so on, does clearly not amount to a violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3117.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3141.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also the government would like to add to the information provided by the applicant that he lives in a Kurdish village and that he speaks Kurdish fluently, is also still entitled to, and he still receives his disability pension from Denmark, which is over 1,300 euros every month and after tax.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3141.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3146.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So 1,300 euros every month after tax.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3146.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3167.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant also describes the difficulties and hardships he is facing as, I quote, mentally retarded, but here it's important to stress that according to the medical assessment already back in 2009, the applicant no longer meets the criteria for the diagnosis of mental retardation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3167.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3185.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the latest medical assessments, the applicant suffers from paranoid schizophrenia, but he only has a mild intellectual disability and in addition a cannabis dependence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3185.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3188.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, that brings me to my next point,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3188.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3191.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the treatment criterion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3191.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3205.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government submits that besides ignoring the severe disease criterion, the chamber majority also broadens the scope of Article 3 in its assessment of the sufficient treatment upon return.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3205.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3212.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as I mentioned initially, we believe this is another important issue raised by the case before us.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3212.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3227.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the outset, let me stress that both the Danish courts and the chamber accepted the fact that the applicant would upon return to Turkey have access to the required medical treatment by way of medicine and psychiatric therapy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3227.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3239.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as just mentioned, the applicant also has the economic means to buy his medicine as he continues to receive his Danish disability pension every month.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3239.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3255.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the government's opinion, it's therefore clear that Denmark was not required to obtain an individual guarantee from the Turkish authorities that the applicant would have access to the required medical and psychiatric treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3255.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3273.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, the critical point is whether Denmark should have obtained an individual assurance that upon the applicant's return to Turkey, and I quote, a regular and personal contact with him would be offered to him by the Turkish authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3273.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3281.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber majority found that it did amount to a violation of Article 3 that Denmark did not obtain such an assurance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3281.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3291.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The majority stated that the return of the applicant to Turkey where he had no social network would inevitably cause, and I quote, would cause him additional hardship, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3291.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3296.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And make it even more crucial that the applicant was provided with the necessary follow-up.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3296.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3308.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For that purpose, the applicant would, in the view of the majority, need at least assistance in the form of a regular and personal contact person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3308.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3318.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government is in line with the dissenting judges and would respectfully disagree with this reading of Article 3 and the relevant case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3318.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3322.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reasons for this are the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3322.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3343.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, there is no basis for assuming that the medical treatment provided in Turkey to mentally ill patients, including persons suffering from paranoid schizophrenia, is deficient, and that such persons will not receive the relevant treatment, including follow-up.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3343.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3355.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, even if we did assume that the applicant would not be provided with a contact person and the same extent of follow-up, that would not in itself be decisive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3355.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3367.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The decisive question would remain whether the care available in the receiving state was, quote, sufficient and appropriate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3367.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3376.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the government's opinion, a contact person, as the one in the present case, was not in charge of the applicant's medication.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3376.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3388.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This constitutes a social measure that is not part of the medical treatment, the treatment required for returning a person to his country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3388.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3401.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A lack of an individual assurance that access to the contact person will be provided therefore cannot constitute degrading or inhuman treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3401.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3418.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will also note in this connection that according to Section 85 of the Danish Social Service Act, the municipality must offer assistance to persons in need of this because of significantly reduced physical or mental disabilities or special social problems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3418.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3424.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This assistance covers a wide range of social and other support measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3424.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3431.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And while a person may in some cases be granted a contact person, this is not always the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3431.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3440.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Other relevant measures may be, for instance, counselling and help to carry out daily chores, etc.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3440.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3452.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And allow me also to underline that a contact person is not the same as a social security guardian, the role of which is described in the applicant's appendices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3452.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3467.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If social measures such as a contact person should be considered part of the required medical treatment under Article 3, this would significantly lower the requirements of the Papuswili judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3467.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3473.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I note that similar concerns were raised by the chamber minority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3473.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3487.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, if the applicant would have been allowed to remain in Denmark, but a contact person had not been provided to him, this would not have amounted to a violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3487.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3499.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And when this is the case, then the absence of obtaining an individual assurance from the Turkish authorities when being expelled cannot amount to a violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3499.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3511.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A conclusion to that effect would not be in accordance with the court's case law, for example, Babar Ahmet and others versus the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3511.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3527.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such conclusion would in fact, as I will elaborate in the following, constitute a significant broadening of Article 3 into completely new ground and with far-reaching consequences for the contracting states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3527.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3531.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, to demonstrate this,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3531.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3535.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>let me recall paragraph 189 of the Papuswili judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3535.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3553.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here, the court reiterated the well-established principle that the benchmark is not the level of care existing in the returning state or whether the care in the receiving state would be equivalent or inferior to that provided in the health care system of the returning state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3553.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3576.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the government finds that the majority's conclusion that a contact person constituted part of the required medical treatment deviates from this principle and entails a significant broadening of the scope of application of Article 3 and a broadening with no clear rationale or justification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3576.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3590.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the government's opinion, such a broadening would constitute a significant step towards making the Convention an instrument for alleviating socioeconomic and medical disparities between the contracting states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3590.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3595.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it would clearly go beyond the scope of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3595.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3616.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The majority's interpretation would pave the way for a legal situation where in reality, the contracting states would only be able to remove mentally ill aliens to countries whose mental health care systems are organized in the same manner and reach the same level as that of the returning states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3616.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3633.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Grand Chamber's decision on this matter will therefore have significant practical implications due to different standards of treatment and different political priorities in the health care systems among contracting states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3633.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3646.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should the Grand Chamber uphold the majority's interpretation, this will significantly limit the possibilities of removing inter-alien, mentally ill, criminal aliens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3646.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3660.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this way, it will substantially restrict the right of contracting states to control the entry, residence and expulsion of aliens and to maintain public order and safety.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3660.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3668.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government finds that such an outcome would not be consistent with the purpose of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3668.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3673.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, this is a concern that a number of other contracting states have also expressed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3673.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3682.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the written submissions from France, Germany, the Netherlands, Norway, Russia, Switzerland and the UK.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3682.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3693.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I believe these submissions demonstrate the high importance of the Grand Chamber's judgment in this case to all contracting states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3693.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3705.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for the reasons that I have given, the government respectfully submits that the Grand Chamber should not find a violation of Article 3 in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3705.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3711.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I shall finally focus briefly on Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3711.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3727.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the government does not concess that the order to expel the applicant as a result of the revocation proceedings in 2015 interferes with his private life, as protected under Article 8, Paragraph 1 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3727.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3750.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the government maintains that the expulsion order from 2009 by the Supreme Court, as upheld during the revocation proceedings in 2015 by the High Court, was taken in accordance with the law and pursued a legitimate aim and as such meets the conditions of Article 8, Paragraph 2 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3750.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3759.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the key question then is whether the interference was necessary in a democratic society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3759.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3770.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The general principles applicable to the present case concerning the expulsion of a settled immigrant as the applicant are well established in the case law of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3770.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3773.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer, for example, to Maslow v. Austria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3773.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3787.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the case law, very serious reasons are required to justify an expulsion and in the government's view, such serious reasons clearly are present in the case before us.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3787.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3812.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me add here that the Danish courts, both in the criminal proceedings when the expulsion order was issued in 2009 and in the revocation proceedings in 2015, conducted a full and thorough assessment of the proportionality of the expulsion order and they applied the relevant human rights standards in accordance with Article 8 of the Convention and the related case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3812.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3834.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So having balanced the applicant's rights against the state's interest in protecting public order and safety and preventing disorder and crime, the Danish courts concluded that the order to expel the applicant would not constitute a disproportionate interference with his right to respect for his private life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3834.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3837.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, having regard to the fundamental principles</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3837.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3851.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the supervisory function of the Court, it is the government's opinion that the Court should be reluctant to disregard the outcome of the assessment made by the Danish courts in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3851.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3858.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Court has pointed out in several cases, including earlier the Court's judgment in the case of Ndidi v. UK,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3858.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3874.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the contracting states enjoy a certain margin of appreciation and it's not for the Court to substitute its conclusions for those of the domestic courts unless there are shown to be strong reasons for doing so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3874.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3883.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Danish government submits that no such strong reasons are present in the applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3883.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3894.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me add that while it is true that the applicant was acquitted of punishment due to his mental state, he nevertheless constituted a continuing threat to public safety.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3894.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3908.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government recalls in that connection that the applicant committed assault of a particularly crude, brutal and dangerous nature under highly aggravating circumstances, which led to the victim's death.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3908.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3911.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer the Court to the case of Kahn v. Germany.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3911.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3928.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, the Chamber found that while the applicant, who had committed a crime in a state of mental incapacity, was not criminally guilty of the offence, there was nevertheless a continuing threat to public safety and the case was referred to the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3928.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3938.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in light of all the aspects that I've just mentioned, it is the view of the Danish government that a fair balance was struck within the state's margin of appreciation in the applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3938.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3949.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on this basis, the Government of Denmark respectfully submits that the Court should find that there has been no violation of Article 8 in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3949.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3957.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Could I just very briefly, in conclusion, add a comment to what Applicant's Council mentioned about the Catt decision?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3957.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3964.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The mentioned Catt decision is, in the Government's opinion, not relevant for this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3964.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3974.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Catt case concerned an Eritrean asylum seeker who had been exposed to torture in Eritrea and the transfer of him to Italy under the Dublin Regulation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3974.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3981.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was traumatised and at the time, there was a risk that he would commit suicide.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3987.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3995.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also appeared from the case that in Italy, he would most likely not have access to specialised medical and psychiatric treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3995.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4001.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the case, therefore, cannot, in our opinion, be compared to the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4001.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4004.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And with that, I will conclude my submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4004.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4004.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4006.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4010.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Mr. Braad.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4010.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4014.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both parties have now submitted their initial observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4014.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4020.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to my colleagues on the bench for their questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4020.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4030.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Pastor Vilanova, the party should note that Judge Pastor Villanueva will pose his question in French.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4030.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4030.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>S'il vous plait.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Pere Pastor Vilanova</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4033.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4036.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, M. le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4036.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4039.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je vais poser 2 questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4039.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4042.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Elles sont destinées principalement aux requérants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4043.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4049.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bien entendu, rien n'empêche le gouvernement de donner sa réponse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4049.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4052.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ce qui concerne la 1re question, c'est la suivante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4054.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4060.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quelle était l'implication exacte du requérant dans l'agression du 29 mai 2006?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4060.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4068.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je vous prie de donner tous les détails possibles quant à son degré de participation personnelle dans ce délit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4069.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4072.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et la 2e question est la suivante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4072.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4081.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce que le requérant avait la possibilité d'obtenir la nationalité danoise avant sa condamnation pénale de 2009?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4082.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4088.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Si tel était le cas, pourquoi n'a-t-il pas exercé ce droit?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4088.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4090.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je vous remercie, M. le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4092.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4094.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Vice President Kjølbro.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Jon Fridrik Kjølbro</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4098.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4099.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4099.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4101.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I do have three questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4101.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4104.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first one is addressed to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4104.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4126.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government is arguing that the Papashvili test, as reflected in paragraph 183, does not apply and cannot be transposed to persons suffering from mental illnesses, as, in the view of the government, it only applies to persons suffering from physical illnesses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4126.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4138.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Assuming that the government is correct in its assumption, what is or should, in the view of the government, be the relevant test to be performed by the court?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4138.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4147.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is the protection under Article 3 to be limited to cases where there is a risk of self-harm or suicide?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4147.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4153.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I did not find the government's position very clear on this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4153.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4174.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question, both parties, as well as all the third parties intervening before this court, have addressed and discussed the test established in paragraph 183 of the Papashvili judgment, including how to apply it to persons suffering from mental illnesses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4174.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4199.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From some of the interventions, in particular the intervention from the UK government, referring to the judgment from the UK Supreme Court, it transpires that the Papashvili test, as formulated in paragraph 183, may give rise to some uncertainty when it comes to the right interpretation, and therefore also when it comes to the correct application of the test.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4199.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4218.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, my question is, in the view of the government, is that does the test in practice, or has the test in practice given rise to problems of interpretation and in the affirmative, which elements of the test have given rise to uncertainty?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4218.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4221.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My third and last question is to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4221.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4247.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, the question of removal or expulsion of a foreigner suffering from an illness arose in the context of criminal proceedings, more specifically when the domestic courts, under section 58 of the Aliens Act, were called upon to assess amending the committal order and at the same time the question of revocation of the expulsion order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4247.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4256.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, in this case, Article 3 concerns a foreigner with a prior lawful stay in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4256.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4286.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the issue of removal of a foreigner suffering from an illness, be it physical or mental, may also arise outside the context of criminal proceedings, in particular when assessing requests for residence permits under section 9B of the Aliens Act, based on humanitarian grounds, which, according to the preparatory works as well as domestic practice, would include an assessment in conformity with Article 3 of the Convention, including Pappersville.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4286.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4308.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now my question, is it correctly understood that whatever the court may say in this case concerning the expulsion of a foreigner with a prior lawful stay would also apply equally to cases concerning requests for residence permits, I'm referring to persons without a prior lawful stay in Denmark?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4308.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4308.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4310.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4312.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Judge O’Leary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4314.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4316.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4316.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4320.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Kjølbro's questions related mainly to Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4320.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4325.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mine may be of relevance if the court undertakes an analysis of Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4325.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4329.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the applicant's case, a permanent ban on reentry was imposed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4329.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4331.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my questions are as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4331.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4337.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is there provision under Danish law for the application of a temporary ban on reentry?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4337.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4341.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, in what circumstances would it be applied?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4341.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4351.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And could the High Court in 2015 have amended the permanent reentry ban imposed by the High Court in 2008 to a temporary one?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4351.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4354.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, on what basis?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4354.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4367.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question, and these questions are for both parties, is what was the degree of the applicant's dependence on his family in Denmark when he became an outpatient from 2014?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4367.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4368.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Where did he live?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4368.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4370.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With whom?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4370.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4376.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We know now from the submissions of the Danish government that he continued to receive a disability pension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4376.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4381.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But was he otherwise socially or financially dependent on his family?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4381.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4391.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the reason for this question is because I didn't find these factual details elaborated in the decision of the High Court of 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4391.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4391.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4392.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4394.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Jelić.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ivana Jelić</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4396.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4400.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have to give up my question because it was actually posed by...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4400.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4402.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4403.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4405.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4405.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4410.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I do not see any more requests for...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4410.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4412.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Schembri Orland, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Lorraine Schembri Orland</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4414.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4415.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4415.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4423.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions which are on a factual nature, which can be addressed to both representatives, both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4423.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4432.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question is, the applicant was assigned a curator at Liethem in the domestic proceedings for the revocation of the expulsion order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4433.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4446.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In domestic law, in this case, did this mean that the court considered he lacked mental and legal capacity to take decisions and to defend himself in these proceedings?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4446.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4464.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question concerns some factual discrepancy, which I found in the assessment of the psychiatrists at the first stage during the criminal conviction proceedings and in the revocation proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4464.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4476.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The psychiatrists in the revocation proceedings concluded that the applicant was suffering from paranoid schizophrenia during the period of commission of the crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4476.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4491.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is in contrast with the report of the medical legal counsel at paragraphs nine and 10 of the chamber judgment, which had been submitted to the court for the purposes of the criminal proceedings leading up to the conviction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4491.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4509.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first report had concluded that the applicant did not suffer from a mental disorder at the time of the commission of the crime, that he was mildly mentally retarded, and that his complaints of auditory hallucinations could be regarded as simulation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4509.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4530.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So my question is this, would it have been possible under Danish law to order the applicant's expulsion had the correct diagnosis of diminished mental capacity been submitted at the stage of the proceedings leading to his conviction?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4530.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4531.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4533.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4534.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4537.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4545.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I then suggest we withdraw for 25 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4545.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4551.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We will then reconvene at exactly 11:40 this morning with the buzzer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4551.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4558.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then the parties will have the opportunity to respond to the questions posed by the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4558.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4559.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4579.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4582.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4582.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4584.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We now begin with the replies of the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4584.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4586.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I give the floor to the representative of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4590.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4593.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4593.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4597.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm the co-counsel for Mr. Safran,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4597.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4602.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and I have known Mr. Safran as a client for 14 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4602.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4610.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will answer the two questions from the distinguished judge, Pera Villanueva, from Andorra.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4610.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4615.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question was, what was Mr. Safran's role in the crime</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4615.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4619.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which took place in May 2006?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4619.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4622.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can refer to the annex one from the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4622.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4631.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the sentence ruled by the Court of Appeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4631.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4644.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in that, there is a short description of what activities took place, and it was a number of people, approximately 10 persons, who was attacking another person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4644.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4647.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was a joint activity, so to speak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4647.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4652.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was around 10 persons, and they never found out who did what.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4652.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4653.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Everybody ran away.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4653.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4659.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only one person was caught by the police, and that was Mr. Safran.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4659.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4671.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, therefore, you didn't try to state what was his activity, but he was joined as part of a group of approximately 10 persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4671.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4681.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that time, back in 2006, when this took place, Mr. Safran couldn't have applied for Danish citizenship.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4681.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4692.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was, among other things, because he already, in January 2001, had been sentenced in a criminal case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4692.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4698.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, therefore, it was out of question that he could have had Danish citizenship back at that time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4698.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4703.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, I hope that was an answer for the two questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4703.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4706.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then I'll pass the floor to Mr. Trier, who will answer the other questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4715.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4722.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I turn to the questions by Judge Kjølbro.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4727.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4742.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The main question for me was whether humanitarian residents in Denmark, 9b of the Aliens Act, whether that would also, it would have a consequence for that provision in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4742.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4748.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If, if sovereign majority is confirmed by the grand chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4748.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4764.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is my viewpoint that there will be very, very few cases in Denmark where the sovereign majority will have direct consequences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4764.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4785.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I find it very unlikely that we could establish facts in a humanitarian residents case for a mentally ill person coming into Denmark, because they would not have been seven years behind closed doors permanently in a psychiatric hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4785.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4805.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they would not have the background that we have here, which is a Supreme Court judgment stating that he's insane, stating that he should be under forced medical treatment under the supervision of the courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4805.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4819.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we find it unlikely that there would be any impact or at least a very minor impact from the sovereign majority judgment in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4819.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4826.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a rather unique case with very rather seldom facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4826.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4837.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Colbro is also asking mainly the government about 183 in Papua New Guinea.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4837.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4853.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would just for the applicant stress that for us is evident that mentally ill persons are covered by 183.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4853.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4857.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Papua New Guinea, there's a reference to Aswat.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4857.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4870.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in Aswat, the case was about a person with severity of mental condition, paragraph 57 of Aswat.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4870.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4876.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That judgment was clearly a background for Papua New Guinea.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4876.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4896.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it follows consistently with a judgment such as Musial and G versus France, where the court also protects mentally ill persons from hardship under Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4896.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4901.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Colbro then asks about the uncertainty in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4901.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4910.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And since I'm working in this field in Denmark, I would say that Papua New Guinea has had an impact in Denmark, that's for sure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4910.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4916.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it's also something that Danish authorities have shown that they are able to cope with.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4916.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4927.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are able to deal with Papua New Guinea, just as they are able to deal with the majority verdict of sovereign.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4927.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4936.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With this, I turn to the questions by Judge O'Leary from Ireland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4936.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4950.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the first question from O'Leary was whether there could be imposed a temporary ban by the Supreme Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4950.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4954.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I wait to hear the answer of the government on this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4954.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4961.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it is our analysis that that could not have taken place at the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4961.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4968.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The seriousness of the criminal activity that Mr. Bolsgifter just mentioned</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4968.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4981.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>would preclude at the time the Supreme Court from coming to another conclusion than a permanent ban on living in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4981.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4994.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me add to this that this system is obviously not very helpful under Article 8 and other parts of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4994.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5037.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in 2019, a new law was passed in Denmark whereby it's now left to the judges deciding in the criminal case whether the starting point of a permanent ban of entry into Denmark can now be modified with the court to live up to the criteria established by the European Court in a number of Article 8 judgments where the court has said a temporary ban is OK under Article 8, but a permanent ban is a violation of Article 8, as we argue in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5037.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5045.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So at the time, it was not possible to give a shorter ban than the permanent one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5045.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5048.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would be possible today in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5051.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5058.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge O'Leary also asks about the outpatient situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5058.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5062.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And allow me to perhaps clarify the facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5062.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5070.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Savran was never an outpatient, never for one single day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5070.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5090.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was permanently in a closed mental institution from May 2008 until he was sent to the airport of Copenhagen 23 June 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5090.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5103.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So one year and one month and a little more, and he was never considered well enough medically that he could be an outpatient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5103.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5116.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under the Danish criminal code, you go from the control of the judges, the courts, and then you go to the control of the chief physician at the hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5116.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5120.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chief physician was Mr. Løbentin,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5120.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5125.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and he never found it advisable that he could be an outpatient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5125.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5128.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was too sick.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5128.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5133.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So therefore, we cannot answer about his living conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5133.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5137.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm sure Mr. Savran would have moved in with his mother.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5137.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5156.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We can see he absconded from the hospital a number of occasions, and he was also always running back to his mother in Amager near Copenhagen and then returning to the hospital a day or two later to continue his medication.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5156.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5162.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But he was never living outside the hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5162.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5173.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, we bear in mind his very serious psychiatric disease, paranoid schizophrenia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5173.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5192.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I then turn to the questions by Judge Orland from Malta, and the first question was whether the guardianship means that he lacked mental capacity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5192.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5195.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the answer from the applicant is yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5195.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5206.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He didn't have the mental capacity, and therefore, Rita Briggs was appointed as his guardian.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5206.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5211.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I respectfully refer Judge Orland to paragraph...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5216.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5227.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sorry, to the judgment where her initials are mentioned, R.B. Her name is Rita Briggs,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5227.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5232.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and she was the one bringing the case before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5232.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5236.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Savran did not have the legal capacity,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5236.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5245.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the mental capacity to do so, and therefore, she was the one bringing it before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5245.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5252.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Her logic, she has told me, was initially, he got seven years of prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5252.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5270.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now he's been more than seven years in a closed mental institution in the hospital, behind closed doors, and now it's the time for a judge to revisit whether Mr. Savran should be moved out of the hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5270.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5297.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The last question from Judge Orland was the criminal process, and I very much understand the question because it's a little bit confusing in the case about this in the facts, and that's not on your part, Judge Orland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5297.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5301.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He should not have gotten the seven years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5301.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5307.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was a clear error by the Danish courts, by the city court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5307.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5323.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was corrected by the high court, by the Supreme Court, who then referred the case back to the city court again, where he had the same trial again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5323.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5328.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was stated in 2009 that he was insane.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5328.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5346.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He could not be punished by a normal sanction, and he could only be sanctioned with a mental, by being in a psychiatric hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5346.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5352.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was mentally retarded, and he was also insane.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5352.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5359.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's why he couldn't be convicted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5359.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5383.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So when the judge asks whether there's a, it would have an impact that he has the diagnosis paranoid schizophrenia, I would say it wouldn't have any consequence because he was already found insane by the Supreme Court in 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5383.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5400.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me add to this that the chamber judgment fails to mention on Article 8, the dissenting opinion of the chairman of the Supreme Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5400.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5416.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If you look to the annexes, you would see that Peter Block, the chairman of the Supreme Court chamber, he voted against expulsion using the Article 8 criteria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5416.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5424.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I respectfully request that his votum is also reflected in the judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5424.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5426.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those were the questions, Mr. President,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5426.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5439.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and I now go to my very last remarks in rebuttal to what the government said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5439.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5449.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The core and maybe the crucial point in this case is the severity of Savran's disease.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5449.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5475.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is fully documented in front of the court, and the testimony by the chief physician in the high court, in the city court, in my opinion, clearly fulfills the criteria of Pabuz Vili, of Tatar, of Aswad.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5475.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5483.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a little bit old-fashioned when the government states like there's a difference between somatic illness and mental illness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5483.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5488.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is clearly not the state of the jurisprudence of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5488.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5503.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And again, I refer to the 2019 judgment against Belgium.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5503.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5510.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The contact person, again, it's not a social measure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5510.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5523.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's an integrated part of the expert treatment of my client.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5523.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5541.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And when my colleague from the government in a somewhat dramatic language talks about that Denmark can no longer expel two countries unless they are at the same level as Denmark, this is simply not correct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5541.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5547.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Aswad and Tatar and Tarakel shows this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5547.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5553.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You need diligence by the authorities in the member states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5553.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5559.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This could easily have been done by Denmark vis-a-vis Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5559.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5570.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A professional person could, in my opinion, within one week or two weeks, have clarified who would take care of my client.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5570.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5576.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Who would take care of my client when he arrived in Turkey?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5576.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5579.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Denmark has a large embassy in Ankara.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5579.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5582.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey has a large embassy in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5582.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5595.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's numerous ways of communication in modern times whereby Denmark could have handed over my client to Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5595.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5604.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So Denmark is not going to be the home of those that should be expelled or extradited in the future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5604.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5618.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Careful application of Aswad, of Tarakel, of Papusvili by the Danish authorities could have hindered the Article 3 violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5618.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5627.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Denmark failed to do this, and therefore, there's a violation primarily of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5627.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5634.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the court doesn't follow me on that, the criteria, the argument should be moved down to Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5634.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5636.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this is the situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5636.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5640.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And by this, I close for today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5640.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5642.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And thank you very much for your patience.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5643.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5646.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Mr. Trier.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5646.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5649.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now call Mr. Braad for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5649.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5649.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5652.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5654.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President, distinguished members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5654.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5661.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank you for the pertinent questions and I shall try to respond to them in the order that they were received.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5661.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5671.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think the first question posed by Judge Villanova was directed to the applicants' council, so I will move to the questions asked by Judge Kulpo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5671.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5679.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, there was a question about the Papasvili test.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5679.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5688.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now that we argue that it cannot be applied meaningfully to persons with mental illness, what test should then be applied?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5688.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5707.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, in such cases, we would find that a high threshold should be maintained and that the relevant test should limit the protection of the Convention to situations involving either a risk of suicide or of self-harm.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5707.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5716.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me also add to that that in the present case, we have not seen any documentation of such a risk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5716.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5725.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to Judge Kulpo's second and third question, I will try to respond to them in combination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5725.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5744.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question is whether the interpretation of the paragraph 183 in the Papasvili judgment gives rise to uncertainties in Danish law and whether an alien without prior legal stay in Denmark can apply for humanitarian residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5744.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5763.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Danish law, a person can be granted residence permit if there are substantial humanitarian grounds, including persons who suffer from very serious illness, both physical and mental illness, and persons who cannot receive treatment in their country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5763.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5771.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this applies also to persons who have not had a previous legal stay in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5771.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5780.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The grounds for granting a humanitarian residence permit is in line with the court's case law, with the Papasvili case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5780.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5798.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as I said, the Papasvili test is difficult to apply equally to mental illness, as mental illness is not in itself irreversible but can be treated, and also intense suffering is very difficult to apply when assessing mental illness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5798.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5809.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think I will stop here, but there are no uncertainties really with applying the Papasvili test under Danish law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5809.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5811.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me move on to Judge O'Leary then.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5811.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5829.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a question about whether or not the High Court could have changed the permanent entry ban to a time-limited ban, and the answer to that question is no, it was not possible at the time, according to the Danish Aliens Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5829.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5839.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the relevant Danish legislation has since then been amended in 2018, which also the Applicants' Council referred to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5839.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5850.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So as such, it is now possible to differentiate between various lengths when ordering an entry ban.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5850.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5854.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me then move to the two questions from Judge Hollande.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5854.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5863.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As concerned, the question whether the applicant did have legal capacity during the proceedings in 2008 and 9 and 15.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5863.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5876.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since the applicant solely suffered from mild intellectual capacity reduction, it was not necessary to consider depriving him of his legal capacity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5876.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5886.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's not actually fully correct when the Council for the Applicant states that the applicant was deprived of his legal capacity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5886.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5896.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think he had no legal guardian, but what he did have was what we call a bistandsvære in Danish.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5896.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5907.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was this person, Briggs, who was responsible for supporting the applicant during the revocation proceedings in 2014 and also in 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5907.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5916.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So a somewhat different institution we had to deal with here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5916.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5935.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question from Judge Hollande concerned whether it's correct that during the criminal proceedings in 2008, a forensic report from March 2008 was presented.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5935.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5941.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there it was stated that the applicant's symptoms must be explained as a simulation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5941.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5951.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The High Court concluded that he was not mentally insane at the time of the crime, but just mildly mentally retarded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5951.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5961.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment from the High Court was appealed to the Supreme Court, which did not amend the judgment from the High Court on this particular point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5961.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5975.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What the Supreme Court did was to amend the psychiatric measures from detention in the Hærste Vester institution to a psychiatric ward, the St. John's Hospital.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5975.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5979.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I hope I have answered Judge Hollande's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5979.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5990.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And let me then just very briefly, allow me briefly a couple of few essential points, just to recall a few of the essential points that are already made here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5990.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6006.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The absence of a regular and personal contact person who is not in charge of the applicant's medication but is a supportive social measure cannot constitute degrading or inhuman treatment within Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6006.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6021.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if a follow-up is necessary in the medical treatment of the applicant, it will, as a last resort, be possible for him to hospitalize in a hospital in Konya.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6021.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6032.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the Court found that a violation of Article 3 took place in the present case, it would have a number of severe consequences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6032.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6038.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First it would constitute a new and very expensive and unjustified reading of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6038.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6048.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second it would place significant practical limitations on the State's possibilities of removing criminal aliens, including the mentally ill.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6048.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6056.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third, it would be a step towards making the Convention an instrument for alleviating socioeconomic disparities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6056.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6058.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This would go beyond the scope of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6058.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6061.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would not be what the contracting States intended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6061.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6069.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would have substantial political, economic, and social consequences for the contracting States.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6069.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6069.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6072.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6073.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6073.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6076.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is there also a wish to follow up?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6076.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6077.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge O'Leary?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6079.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6090.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My thanks to the parties regarding the clarification on the issue of permanent and temporary bans and this new information regarding a 2019 law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6090.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6105.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Could I ask the representative of the government to develop a little bit on this question of the law permitting differentiation regarding re-entry bans with reference to what criteria or in what circumstances does it permit differentiation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6105.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6105.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6106.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6107.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6107.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6110.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vice President Turković wants to follow up on a question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6111.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6121.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I just would like to follow up when it was decided to expel Savran outside of Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6121.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6131.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Would it be possible if he would not be expelled at that time just to leave him and to free him from the institution in Denmark?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6131.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6136.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So whether he was at that stage where he could be released actually from the institution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6138.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6139.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6139.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6139.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Seibert-Fohr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Anja Seibert-Fohr</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6142.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6144.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6144.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6170.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to add on the question posed by Judge O'Leary and to inquire from the government agent more clarification on whether the change in the laws of 2018 which have been elaborated on by both sides would allow nowadays the applicant to apply nowadays for reconsideration of the length of the ban.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6170.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6170.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6171.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6172.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6172.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6175.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The questions are posed to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6175.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6180.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I ask the agent of the government to comment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6180.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6186.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the applicant wishes to add, that will be a possibility in a moment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6186.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6187.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Braad, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6187.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6187.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6190.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6192.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6192.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6205.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I will just have to refer to the fact that it's the gravity of the crime that is taken into consideration by the court in determining the time limit of the ban.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6205.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6219.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm not here able to be very specific on this, but that is the crucial criteria that this will evolve around.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6219.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6225.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we can, of course, provide more precise information about this to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6230.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6230.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6235.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6235.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6247.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6247.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6252.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6254.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6254.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6265.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think the second question posed was directed at what would have happened if the deportation did not take place, what would have happened in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6265.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6288.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the most likely scenario would then have been that the applicant would have left the psychiatric ward and would then have been subject to outpatient handling and control according to the regular Danish system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6288.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6293.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that is the likely scenario if no deportation had taken place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6293.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6293.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6294.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6296.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6296.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6315.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I recall that if the government wants to elaborate further on the issue of the temporary or permanent ban, under the rules there is a possibility to do so within the next two weeks by a short written submission limited to that particular point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6315.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6318.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the representative of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6318.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6320.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Trier, do you want to add any final words?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6323.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6327.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6327.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6336.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge O'Leary asked about the new rules from 1819.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6336.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6386.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The way I read the preparatory work, and I can add I was in the Supreme Court of Denmark on Friday about this issue, but the basis for the change of the law is that the Ministry of Justice is reading carefully the jurisprudence of the European Court and have seen in a number of cases under Article 8 that a permanent ban from reentry is a violation of Article 8, where the court is stating that a temporary ban, five years, ten years, would be in accordance with Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6386.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6397.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me mention one judgment, and that's Radovanic versus Austria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6397.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6415.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is one example of this case law where the European Court is stressing the concern about permanent entry ban, especially for younger people with serious crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6415.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6444.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would argue that the change of the law to allow flexibility is exactly to live up to Article 8, and perhaps also to secure the Danish judges the maximum flexibility in terms of ruling about extradition or expulsion from Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6444.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6455.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question from Judge Turkovic, what would happen, could he have been released?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6455.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6493.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the city court judgment or decision would have been the final one here, which I argue it should have been, as all the judges know, then it would be up to the chief physician at the hospital, and he would eventually, I think, have been released to live in the outskirts of Copenhagen with his family, close to his mother, his older sister, his younger sister, his brother, his nephews and nieces here in Copenhagen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6493.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6517.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So my view of the law is that yes, he could indeed have been released to stay with his family, continue treatment as an outpatient, taking medication, going in for blood tests, going in to have follow-up on his medication, continuing with the guardian, Mrs. Breks,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6517.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6518.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and so on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6518.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6523.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So yes, he could have been released in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6523.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6545.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, Judge Seibert IV from Germany asked if he can apply for reconsideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6545.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6556.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I understood the question as it is whether he could do it at this time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6556.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6561.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The way I understand the Danish rules, he cannot do that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6561.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6570.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not possible for him to ask for a reconsideration of the permanent entry ban to Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6570.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6581.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The new rules from 2018 do not apply retroactively for his case, and therefore, he doesn't have that avenue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6581.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6587.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only avenue left for Mr. Savran is the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6587.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6591.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is his only chance in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6591.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6594.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And with this, I rest my case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6594.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6594.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6596.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6598.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Trier.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6598.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6605.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I thank both parties for their submissions and their replies to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6605.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6608.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6608.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6612.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered at a later date.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6612.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6615.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the parties will, of course, be informed of the delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6615.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6617.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank you for this morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6617.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6619.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6619.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6619.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
