<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>5759208_21102015</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>36.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>38.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>46.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>53.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Hutchinson against the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>53.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>63.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on the 10th of November 2008 under Article 34 of the Convention by a British national, Mr. Arthur Hutchinson.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>63.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>71.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the fourth section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>71.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>82.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 3rd of February 2015, a chamber of the fourth section declared the application admissible as regards Article 3 of the Convention and told that there had been no violation of that provision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>82.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>97.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 3rd of March 2015, the applicant requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention, and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on the 1st of June 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>97.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>110.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 27th of August 2015, leave was granted to the European Prison Litigation Network to submit written comments as a third party by virtue of Rule 44, Paragraph 3 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>110.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>128.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Mr. Paul McKell, agent assisted by Mr. Jeremy Wright, QC Attorney General, Mr. James Eadie, QC Counsel, and by Ms. Alison Foulds, Ms. Catherine  Gaskell, and Mr. James Gerard, and Ms. Justine Earl, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>128.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>137.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mr. Joel Bennathan, and QC Counsel assisted by Ms. Katy Thorne, and Mr. John Turner, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>137.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>142.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>142.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>148.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome the following groups of judges who are attending this hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>148.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>182.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Representatives of the Judicial Academy of Azerbaijan, a group of judges from the Russian Federation, judges from the Swiss Canton of Argyle, and judges from other regional courts, namely the African Court of Human and People's Rights and the African Commission, the East African Court of Justice, the Court of the Economic Community of West African States, the Inter-American Court of Human Rights, and the Caribbean Court of Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>182.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>193.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting into the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting into Azeri and Russian has also been authorized.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>193.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>204.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>204.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>212.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>212.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>220.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Bennathan QC for the applicant will speak first, and then Attorney General Wright QC for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>220.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>220.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Bennathan QC.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>225.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>229.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>229.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>231.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>231.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>234.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>this is a case about humanity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>234.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>244.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The idea enshrined in Article 3 that no human being, no matter how awful their crimes, ceases to be human.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>244.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>257.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There must always be the possibility, no matter how remote, of reform, of redemption, of rehabilitation, and of release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>257.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>266.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Vinter, the judgment of this court did not take the law in any new direction or impose a new obligation on the contracting states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>266.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>274.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court instead took up the principles already established in previous judgments, notably in Kafkaris and Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>274.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>287.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That judgment was founded on a wealth of international jurisprudence described in that judgment and described in our written submissions, which I will not repeat and take up the court's valuable time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>287.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>304.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Vinter, this court stressed that to avoid offending Article 3, a whole life order has to be reducible both in theory and, of course, in practice, de jure and de facto.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>304.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>316.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's our submission that in this case, the government of the United Kingdom advances the same argument on de jure as was rejected rightly by this court in Vinter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>316.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>325.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And with granted, de facto, there is, with great respect, simply a deafening silence from the government of the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>325.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>330.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our submissions this morning, we would like to address three subjects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>330.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>346.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, why the United Kingdom is still in violation of Article 3 on the theoretical de jure analysis of the system in place, and therefore, why the English Court of Appeals judgment in McLaughlin simply does not deal with that problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>346.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>357.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, why on a practical basis, the United Kingdom has done nothing to change its practice so as to abide by this court's judgment in Vinter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>357.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>379.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, and finally, why, with great respect, that even if there are delicacies or tensions in the relationship between this court and the United Kingdom, the court should nonetheless, unhesitatingly, declare a continuing violation in this application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>379.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>383.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To start, if I may, with our submissions on de jure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>383.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>385.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The system in theory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>385.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>394.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To remind the court, with respect, of the three qualities that a convention-compliant system requires as described in Vinter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>394.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>402.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, there must be a review mechanism in place not limited to compassionate grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>402.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>408.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the prisoner must be told when the review will take place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>408.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>421.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, the prisoner must be told what he must do to have a prospect of release, and the criteria that the review will apply when considering release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>421.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>453.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The limitation, the first of those problems, the limitation of the review mechanism to compassionate grounds is, we would submit, the one required quality which the Court of Appeal in McLaughlin did at least engage with, holding, as the court will have read, that the Prison Service Order was legally far outweighed by the terms of the statute, the Crime Sentences Act, and the obligation under the United Kingdom's Human Rights Act for the minister to act compatibly with the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>453.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>469.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet, the only basis to release a whole-life order prisoner in the statute remains upon, quote, compassionate grounds, which the Court of Appeal in McLaughlin said must be given, quote, a wide meaning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>469.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>487.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We remind the court, with gratitude, of the words of Judge Pinto de Albuquerque, in his opinion concurring on this point in the second Otchelan judgment, and I quote his honor on the McLaughlin judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>487.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>493.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This opinion raises rather serious linguistic, logical, and legal questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>493.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>508.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What does compassion have to do with risk assessment, the prospect of the offender's resocialization, or the lack of a continuing penological grounds for continued imprisonment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>508.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>518.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is the wide meaning of compassionate grounds so wide it has no connection with the plain meaning of the word compassion?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>518.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>532.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What can be more unpredictable than a discretionary legal provision to release in exceptional circumstances, which is converted into an obligation to release with a, quote, wide meaning, unquote?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>532.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>540.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What can be more unclear than, quote, exceptional grounds with a wide meaning?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>540.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>561.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's our submission that the time has now been reached when this court can, in fact, go beyond, with great respect, the judgment in Kafkaris and Vinter, and say there is now an international consensus that decisions about prisoners' release should be taken by courts, by judges, not by politicians.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>561.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>570.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our basis for that argument is set out in great detail in our written submissions, and I will not take up this court's time by reading them out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>570.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>573.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But simply to add one or two points to that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>573.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>588.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, we say it is of note that the sole direction of travel, the sole direction of development in United Kingdom sentencing policy has been away from the politicians, into the hands of judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>588.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>604.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, we acknowledge at once that in Kafkaris and Cyprus, and indeed subsequently, this court has found no violation of Article 3 in a system that is based upon application to a politician.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>604.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>620.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in Kafkaris, of course, the politician in question was the president in a contracting state, where that post, though under the Cypriot scheme an elected post, might perhaps suggest a politician with no further ambition for promotion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>620.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>622.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He's the president, after all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>622.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>629.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, perhaps to a degree, above the rough and tumble of politics more normally.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>629.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>634.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course, I come forward to de facto, which I will come to in but a few minutes time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>634.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>650.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, above all in Kafkaris, this court had the comfort of knowing that numerous prisoners had been released from supposedly whole life orders over many years before the court's judgment in that case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>650.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>653.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The United Kingdom, of course, has no presidential system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>653.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>658.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have no politician removed above from the daily rough and tumble of politics.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>658.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>664.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course, there's no such de facto comfort as we'll come to in a few minutes times.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>664.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>701.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also on this point finally note in this concurring opinion in this court's decision in Vinter, Judge Marnie, whilst with respect, diplomatically stressing that the method of making the United Kingdom system compatible was a matter for the United Kingdom, went on to suggest that the material before this court suggests, I quote, clear support for the institution of a dedicated mechanism integrated within the sentencing legislation providing for a review of life sentences after a set period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>701.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>707.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do say, and I say with great respect, as Judge Marnie, of course, is part of the court today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>707.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>715.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do say that phrase really does not sound like a system that allows a politician to take that decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>715.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>723.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should stress at once that these are our submissions that the court should go beyond Vinter and beyond Kafkaris.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>723.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>737.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also stress that even if the court stays with the position as decided in Vinter, we make it plain, the United Kingdom has simply failed to adjust, has simply failed to mend the violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>737.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>773.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Above all, we say, the real problem with the Court of Appeals solution, is the evidence analysis, what went wrong in the argument or in the judgment of this court in Vinter?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>773.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>777.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My learned friend, Mr. Eadie, with us today, of course,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>777.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>786.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>told the Court of Appeal in McLaughlin, the court went on to accept, and I quote, the grand chamber was mistaken, unquote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>786.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>796.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The argument, of course, being put forward by the government that the prison order has to be read subject to the Human Rights Act obligation upon the minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>796.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>801.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, with respect, was that really the problem with the judgment in Vinter?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>801.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>806.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It cannot be said that no one mentioned this argument to this court in Vinter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>806.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>816.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The argument was advanced in detail submissions by leading counsel on that occasion of the United Kingdom, my learned friend, Mr. Perry, Queen's counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>816.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>827.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The argument, which is supposed to be the solution in McLaughlin, had been advanced by the Court of Appeal in Beba, which was before this court in Vinter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>827.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>836.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Marnie, in his concurring opinion, specifically dwelt upon these submissions and the case of Beba in detail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>836.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>858.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this court, in its judgment in Vinter, began the judgment by setting out the relevant sections of the Human Rights Act, set out entirely accurately the government's submissions about the Human Rights Act and the way in the prison service rules, and dealt with the argument clearly and effectively at paragraph 128 of that judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>858.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>864.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With all due respect to the Court of Appeal, it's not the comprehension of this court that is at fault.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>864.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>869.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is the United Kingdom's system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>869.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>887.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moving on to what we call the second and third qualities required by Vinter in the de jure position, the Justice neither finds any solution, either in McLaughlin or in any of the many written submissions put forward by the United Kingdom government up until today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>887.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>890.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The timing of the review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>890.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>904.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course it would be absurd to think that any whole life order prisoner can apply at any time, as no system committed to a genuine and meaningful review could cope with such an unrestricted flow of applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>904.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>909.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is a clear international consensus for review after 25 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>909.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>914.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet nowhere in the Court of Appeal's judgment is the timing of the review addressed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>914.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>923.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nowhere in the government's observations, nowhere in the government's written submissions is the timing of when that review should take place set out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>923.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>925.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a requirement of Vinter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>925.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>929.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It simply isn't addressed, even in theory, even to jury.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>929.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>936.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the third quality, the need for whole life order prisoners to know the criteria they must meet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>936.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>945.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would remind the court, with respect, of the judgment of the former fifth section in Trebelsi and Belgium.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>945.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>987.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In finding that the system in the United States, to which an extradition was proposed, in finding the system in the United States amounted to a violation of Article III, the court in Trebelsi at paragraphs 136 and 137 said, the court now comes to the central issue in the present case, which involves establishing whether the provisions of United States legislation governing the possibilities for reduction of life sentences and pardons fulfill the criteria which is laid down for assessing the reducibility of a life sentence and its conformity with Article III.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>987.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>992.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No lengthy disquisitions are required to answer this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>992.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1036.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court needs simply note that while the said provisions point to the existence of a, quote, prospect of release, unquote, within the meaning of the Kafkaris judgment, none of the procedures provided for amounts to a review mechanism requiring the national authorities to ascertain on the basis of objective, pre-established criteria to which the prisoner had precise cognizance at the time of imposition of the life sentence, whether while serving his sentence, the prisoner has changed and progressed to such an extent that continued detention can no longer be justified on legitimate penological grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1036.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1039.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, we say it is, with great respect,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1039.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1046.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a neat and simple encapsulation of the third, the jury requirement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1046.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1057.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Objective, pre-established criteria on which the prisoner had precise cognizance at the time of imposition of the life sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1057.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1063.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After the Court of Appeals judgment in McLaughlin, we know what is no longer the only criterion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1063.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1069.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The whole life order prisoner does not have to be in the last stages of fatal illness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1069.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1075.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are told compassionate grounds would have to be read widely.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1075.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1085.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to what the court in Trebelsie called objective, pre-established criteria, there is simply no clue to be had from the judgment in McLaughlin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1085.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1101.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So once again, we say the United Kingdom's solution to the theoretical problems with the United Kingdom system simply does not address two out of three of the problems identified by this court in Vinter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1101.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1113.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning now to whether the United Kingdom whole life order sentences are de facto reducible, we say the position is even simpler and even starker.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1113.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1118.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The prison service order is still in place unamended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1118.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1126.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To say, as the Court of Appeals said, that its terms cannot bind a minister's discretion is all well and good.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1126.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1145.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But to choose, as the United Kingdom government has done, not to rewrite it so as to reflect even the concessions made by the Court of Appeal, shows, we fear, there is simply no willingness to pay any attention to this court's judgment in Vinter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1145.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1162.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We remind the court, in his concurring opinion in Vinter, Judge Marnie suggested an amendment to these rules as, in effect and with great respect, the least intrusive route to rendering the United Kingdom system compatible with Article 3 on this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1162.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1181.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yet it's now over two years since Vinter and over 18 months since the judgment in McLaughlin supposedly stripped the existing prison service rules, prison service orders of any significance, but the United Kingdom has chosen to leave those rules in place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1181.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1187.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are aware, of course, of the questions the court has posed to the party.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1187.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1190.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We await with interest the government's answer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1190.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1195.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why has the order not been amended in the light of these criticisms?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1195.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1204.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And question two, at the present time, does a whole life prisoner know at the outset of the sentence what he must do to be considered for release?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1204.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1211.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No, it's a simple answer, we fear, but we await the United Kingdom's answer as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1211.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1220.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second problem with the de facto position is to contrast this situation with the case of Kafkaris and the situation in Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1220.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1248.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Kafkaris and Cyprus, this court was able to make a finding of compatibility under Article 3 on the basis of the obvious and powerful demonstration that whole life orders were de facto reducible in Cyprus, as in the 14 years before the hearing of Kafkaris, 12 prisoners serving mandatory whole life sentences had, in fact, been released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1248.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1265.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In all the arguments in this case put forward by the United Kingdom, and as far as we're aware, in all the arguments put forward by the United Kingdom in the Vinter case, there is one argument the government has never sought to rely on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1265.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1274.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is that in reality, in the United Kingdom, whole life orders are reviewed and prisoners are set free.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1274.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1281.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are, with great respect, very pleased that the court has posed the third question to the government specifically.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1281.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1300.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government is requested to inform the court if any prisoners serving whole life sentences are considered for release, is there any example of a whole life prisoner who has been released since the date of delivery of the Vinter judgment?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1300.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1306.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We, like the court, perhaps, await the government's answer with considerable interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1306.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1319.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the government are able to say there are a number of prisoners who have been so released since Vinter, then of course that will be a valuable argument in favor of the government, at least on this part of the difficulties they face.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1319.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1336.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If, on the other hand, the answer is the number of those released is somewhere akin to zero, we would say it is a more compelling argument as to the real nature of whole life orders in the United Kingdom than any words we can say.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1336.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1353.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, in considering the de facto situation, we submit the court cannot ignore the reality of a system, like the United Kingdom's, that gives a politician so central a role in the sentencing decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1353.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1384.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it is to be said, as the United Kingdom must be saying, that there is a real prospect of release by application to the politician who happens to be the Minister of Justice when the whole life order prisoner applies, if politicians are to be brought into the system by the government's argument, then it must be legitimate for us, with respect, to refer the court to the actual attitude of the real politicians when we consider the de facto situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1384.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1399.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our written submissions to the court, we quote the comments of the Lord Chancellor and Secretary of State for the Ministry of Justice, the politician serving at the time of the court appeals judgment in McLaughlin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1399.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1406.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He said this, I quote, this is a timely and welcome decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1406.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1412.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our courts should be able to send the most brutal murderers to jail for the rest of their lives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1412.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1423.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think people in Britain will be glad that our courts have disagreed with the European Court of Human Rights and uphold the law that the United Kingdom Parliament has passed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1427.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1430.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, we suggest there are perhaps three lessons that</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1430.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1433.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>can be drawn from those comments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1433.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1445.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, it illustrates precisely why judges, not politicians, should be entrusted with the review of whole life orders under any convention-compatible system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1445.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1469.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, it makes clear that as far as the United Kingdom government is concerned, and unlike the stance taken by the Court of Appeal, there has not been a misunderstanding in Vinter, all now cleared up by McLaughlin, but that the Court of Appeals judgment, as far as the United Kingdom government is concerned, was a flat rejection of this court's decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1469.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1495.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, how can any whole life order prisoner be expected to commit himself and to work towards his rehabilitation in reform in the hope that he just might one distant day win his freedom if that attitude of a serving politician is what awaits him at the end of all his decades of efforts?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1495.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1499.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our third and final topic, Mr. President,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1499.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1505.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is addressing the margin of appreciation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1505.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1526.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We appreciate this court will often need to pause before making a finding of a violation to ensure it has struck the proper balance between, on the one hand, guarding the rights guaranteed by the convention, and on the other, trespassing into the contracting state's margin of appreciation and making those rights available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1526.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1544.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact there have been well-documented valuable discussions or even tensions between the United Kingdom government and, to a lesser extent, the United Kingdom courts, cannot, of course, sway this court in assessing where that balance lies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1544.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1554.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In our submission, and I will deal with them shortly, I promise, in our submission there are seven reasons why this court should not shy away from declaring a violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1554.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1559.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, Article III is an unqualified right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1559.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1569.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So there is no question of the balancing exercise that this court would very often leave to the contracting states when dealing with a qualified right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1569.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1583.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, in finding a violation, this court would not be imposing any particular system on the United Kingdom, as there are various routes to compliance, and the United Kingdom could choose the one that worked best.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1583.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1588.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, this is not a decision on an individual's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1588.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1603.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If this were an argument about whether the applicant should have his sentence reduced, that decision would and should remain to be taken by judges or politicians, if we must, based on the facts of the individual case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1603.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1607.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is simply not the finding this court is being asked to make.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1607.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1625.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fourth, this court is not being asked, of course, and has never been asked in this case, or indeed in Vinter, to impose any prohibition on the imposition of a whole life order, or even to prohibit prisoners actually serving whole life orders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1625.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1630.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The argument is, of course, just for the possibility of a reduction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1630.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1636.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fifth, it would really not be so great a change to the United Kingdom system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1636.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1646.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The scheme for review after 25 years was the English system, in fact, under different political parties and governments, was the English system for many years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1646.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1666.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All that we suggest needs to be added to what was the English system not so long ago is to empower the parole board to reduce a whole life order to a determinate sentence, and to describe in detail the criteria the parole board would apply upon taking that decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1666.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1671.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sixth, it would not take much to put this right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1671.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1702.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The United Kingdom Parliament's Joint Committee on Human Rights drafted a statutory clause, I think about eight lines long, that simply said, after 25 years, a whole life order prisoner may apply to the parole board, which this court will appreciate, has been treated in other judgments as a court, it's chaired by a senior judge, may apply to the parole board to decide if the prisoner has made such exceptional progress that a whole life order is no longer justified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1702.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1722.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Seventh, the price of not making a finding of a violation in this case, with great respect, would be to cause near chaos in this court's jurisprudence, as it amounts to a profound undermining at least, and in fact a declaration, that a string of cases have been wrongly decided.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1722.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1737.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And would, we say, amount to a declaration that Trabelsi, Ocelan, Vinter, and even Kafkaris had all been wrongly decided, if the court were not to find a violation in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1737.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1740.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the preamble to the European Convention speaks</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1740.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1745.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of a declaration and reaffirmation of a belief in the rights of men and women.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1745.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1751.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it also speaks of the collective enforcement of those rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1751.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1758.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Vinter found a clear violation of one of the rights guaranteed under the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1758.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1764.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That decision has been bluntly rejected by the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1764.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1771.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would submit, with great respect, that the time has come for an equally direct reply from this honorable court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1778.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1783.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Bennathan. I call now Attorney General Jeremy Wright QC.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1784.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1786.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, thank you, members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1786.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1806.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a case that the government of the United Kingdom regards as being of the very greatest importance, touching as it does not merely on the content of Article III rights, but also on the relationship between the convention and domestic legal systems in the context of criminal justice and sentencing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1806.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1809.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The facts can be shortly stated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1809.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1815.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant broke into the home of a family in Sheffield on the night of the 23rd of September, 1983.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1815.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1819.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The family had been celebrating the wedding of one of their daughters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1819.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1822.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant stabbed the parents and one of the sons to death.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1822.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1832.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He then repeatedly raped one of the other daughters of the family, having first dragged her past her father's body into the marquee where the wedding had taken place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1832.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1839.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 1984, he was convicted of three counts of murder, one count of rape, and one count of aggravated burglary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1839.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1846.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was sentenced to a whole life term of imprisonment, pursuant to the process described in paragraph seven of the fourth section's judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1846.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1857.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following the enactment of the Criminal Justice Act 2003, the applicant exercised his right under that legislation to apply to the High Court for a review of his term of imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1857.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1869.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The whole life term was confirmed in May of 2008 by a High Court judge, who concluded that having regard to the sadistic as well as the sexual nature of the offense, a whole life term was the right sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1869.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1873.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In October 2008, the Court of Appeal agreed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1873.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1877.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, it's my submission that a prisoner</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1877.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1892.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>such as this applicant, sentenced to a whole life term, has under domestic law both the prospect of release and the possibility of review, and that that domestic law is compatible with Article III of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1892.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1898.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The key statutory power is in Section 30 of the Crime Sentences Act of 1997.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1898.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1905.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The power to release the prisoner may be exercised by the Secretary of State, and I quote, at any time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1905.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1917.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The basis on which the power may be exercised is also expressly set out in Section 30 as exceptional circumstances which justify the prisoner's release on compassionate grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1917.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1922.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Human Rights Act of 1998 applies alongside Section 30.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1922.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1925.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has two legal effects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1925.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1936.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It means, and this is Section 3 of the Human Rights Act, that Section 30 itself must be interpreted as far as it is possible to do so in a way which is compatible with Convention rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1936.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1951.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also means, and this is Section 6 of the Human Rights Act, that the Secretary of State is bound to exercise his powers, including the power under Section 30, compatibly with the provisions of the Convention, thus including specifically Article III.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1951.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1962.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, there is the Prison Service Order 4700, or Life and Manual, referred to by the Grand Chamber in Vinter, and to which the applicant has also referred.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1962.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1966.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is this document that appears to have led to some confusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1966.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1971.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How do these elements, then, of domestic law and policy interrelate?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1971.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1979.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That question and the significance of the Life and Manual in domestic law were recently reconsidered by the Court of Appeal in the Newell case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1979.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1985.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court of Appeal specifically did so in the light of the concerns expressed by this court in Vinter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1985.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1995.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The seriousness of the issue was reflected in the fact that this was a five-person court presided over by the Lord Chief Justice and including the President of the Queen's Bench Division.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1995.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2002.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The result is that there is no longer any scope for argument about the clear state of domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2002.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2007.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Three points emphasized by the Court of Appeal need to be emphasized also in this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2007.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2015.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, Section 30 empowers the Secretary of State to release a prisoner whenever Article 3 so requires.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2015.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2021.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The concepts of exceptional circumstances and compassionate grounds are to be read accordingly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2021.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2029.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the power it confers must be exercised compatibly with Article 3 rights under Section 6 of the Human Rights Act 1998.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2029.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2038.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the clear and authoritatively stated position under English law, as the fourth section in this case correctly acknowledged.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2038.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2047.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Pinto de Albuquerque questioned the Court of Appeal's reasoning in his dissenting opinion in Ocalan against Turkey No. 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2047.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2051.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His comments are relied on by the advocate and the intervener.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2051.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2060.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But those comments were not joined with by any of his fellow judges in that case or by any of the judges in the fourth section in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2060.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2074.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With the greatest respect to him, whatever difficulties he may have with its reasoning, the Court of Appeal's judgment is clear, coherent, and perhaps most importantly, represents the authoritative statement of domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2074.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2086.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, as the Court of Appeal pointed out, as a matter of basic domestic public law principle, nothing in the life of manual restricts the circumstances in which release can and must occur.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2086.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2093.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The law is in Section 30, interpreted and applied to achieve compliance with Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2093.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2107.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is therefore fundamentally wrong and wholly inconsistent with the clear conclusion of the Court of Appeal to assert, as the applicant does, that the life of manual limits the power to release on compassionate grounds under Section 30.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2107.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2113.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under domestic law, it does not do so, as the Court of Appeal expressly indicated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2113.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2116.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the circumstances of the case must be considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2116.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2123.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Release must be effected if, in all those circumstances, Article 3 requires it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2123.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2132.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court in its first question asks why, given that this is the position under domestic law, the manual has not been altered, and whether it is intended to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2132.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2142.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The short answer is that as a matter of domestic law, it is unnecessary to do so in the light of the clarity of the legal position set out in the Court of Appeal judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2142.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2160.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The references to and guidance on release on medical grounds in it are not exhaustive of the circumstances in which release may be appropriate, although the fact remains that that part of the manual, dealing with medical grounds, continues to provide useful guidance in that medical grounds context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2160.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2169.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the Court also asks whether the law is sufficiently accessible and foreseeable in view of the continued existence of the manual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2169.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2172.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I submit it is plain that it is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2172.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2185.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Court's consistent jurisprudence indicates, the foreseeability requirement comes accompanied by the rider that the legal position shall be foreseeable with appropriate legal advice if necessary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2185.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2188.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The position, as the Court of Appeal indicated, is clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2188.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2194.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A prisoner concerned to ascertain the position would, in any event, not simply go to the manual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2194.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2203.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It sits alongside the legislation, the Human Rights Act, the domestic court's previous jurisprudence, and now the Court of Appeal's judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2203.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2211.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In practice, there are only two scenarios when considering the possibility of release from the prisoner's perspective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2211.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2220.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Either he will take legal advice, in which case the lawyer will tell him that the Court of Appeal has made the position entirely clear and will explain it to him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2220.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2231.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, even if he's not legally represented, he can, and can reasonably be expected, to ask the authorities what the position is, if he's considering an application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2231.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2235.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if the question is asked, we know what the answer will be.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2235.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2238.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We know that because Mr. Vinter, through his solicitor</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2238.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2247.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Simon Crichton, who you might care to note is also the joint author of the intervention from the European Litigation Network, asked the question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2247.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2250.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The response is at annex three to our observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2250.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2255.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it said, you ask when your client may have a review of his detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2255.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2268.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He may apply at any time, setting out the exceptional circumstances in his particular case which have arisen since he was sentenced, such that his detention is no longer justified on penological grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2268.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2270.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third point is this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2270.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2278.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An application for release can be made to the Secretary of State at any time, as section 30 itself expressly provides.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2278.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2285.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When such an application is made, the Secretary of State must then make a reasoned decision in relation to release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2285.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2296.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That decision is subject to judicial review, including in order to challenge a refusal to release as incombatible with the convention, as the Court of Appeal specifically noted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2296.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2311.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If flesh were required to be put on the bones of the concepts of exceptional circumstances or compassionate circumstances or legitimate penological grounds, that judicial review process is the place in which it would be done.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2311.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2325.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is submitted that this court can therefore confidently proceed, and in principle must proceed, on the basis that whatever doubt there may or may not have been as to the precise state of domestic law, that has now been cleared away.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2325.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2329.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Domestic law is clear in each of these respects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2329.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2346.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case is thus a very long way, indeed, from cases such as Ocalan against Turkey number two, which concerned a system under which there was no sufficient possibility of release or review, and in which the prisoner was positively excluded from any release on parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2346.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2354.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The live question is, therefore, whether given that this is so, that domestic legal structures are compliant with Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2354.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2357.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is submitted that they plainly are.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2357.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2375.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Grand Chamber in Vinter concluded in terms that if the clear position in domestic law was that there was a duty to release the whole life term prisoner if it could be shown that continued detention was no longer justified on penological grounds, that was in principle sufficient to render the life sentence reducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2375.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2377.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is what the court said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2377.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2387.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This reading of section 30, ensuring some prospects under the law for release of whole life prisoners, would in principle be consistent with this court's judgment in Kafkaris.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2387.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2404.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it could be established that in the applicant's cases a sufficient degree of certainty existed as to the state of the applicable domestic law to this effect, it could not be said that their sentences were irreducible, and thus no violation of Article 3 would be disclosed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2404.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2408.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that, Mr. President, is precisely where we are.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2408.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2415.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It not merely could be, but now definitively has been established, that that is the state of domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2415.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2417.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the consequence follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2417.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2424.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It therefore cannot be said that the sentence is irreducible and no violation of Article 3 is disclosed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2424.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2428.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it's submitted that this is the right answer in principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2428.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2431.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's an overarching point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2431.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2439.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is properly an area in which the convention and this court should be concerned, I submit, with the setting only of what are genuinely minimum standards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2439.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2447.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sentences have been properly and justly imposed to reflect the extraordinarily serious nature of the crimes in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2447.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2454.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court's jurisprudence has been consistent in the need for some prospect of release and some system of review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2454.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2459.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the nature of those systems is in the field of criminal justice and sentencing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2459.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2466.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, different contracting states can perfectly properly have different ways of achieving those basic aims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2466.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2471.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the intervener's observations demonstrate, such differences do in fact exist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2471.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2479.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is not an area in which it is necessary or appropriate for there to be a prescriptive approach to the nature of those systems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2479.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2493.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Grand Chamber acknowledged in terms at paragraph 120 of VINTA, and has acknowledged in many other cases before and since, there is a margin of appreciation to be afforded to contracting states, as Mr. Benetton has</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2493.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2496.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>said, in matters of criminal justice and sentencing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2496.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2501.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is, I submit, no proper basis for narrowing it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2501.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2506.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And let me address the prospect of and the grounds for release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2506.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2511.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That there is such a prospect, both de jure and de facto, is uncontested.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2511.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2524.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Grand Chamber in VINTA referred at paragraph 122 to a whole life prisoner being entitled to know at the outset of his sentence what he must do to be considered for release and under what conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2524.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2531.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The content of that entitlement is the subject of the second, and to some extent the first, of the court's questions for this hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2531.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2534.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I make three submissions of principle about it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2534.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2542.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My first is that under domestic law, the prisoner knows what he must do to be considered for release and the conditions to be met before release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2542.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2552.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question is whether legitimate penological grounds continue to exist that are sufficient to justify the continuing detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2552.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2559.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Punishment, deterrence, public protection, and rehabilitation were the penological grounds identified in VINTA.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2559.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2577.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Koroshenko against Russia, paragraph 121, the Grand Chamber, unsurprisingly, and continuing the court's analysis to the same effect in VINTA, emphasized the increasing relative importance of the rehabilitative aim of imprisonment, particularly towards the end of a long sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2577.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2578.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So be it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2578.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2584.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As noted by the Court of Appeal, domestic law applies this Article III standard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2584.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2592.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, the concept of exceptional circumstances naturally accommodates exceptional rehabilitative progress by the prisoner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2592.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2608.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So applying domestic law, the prisoner knows that he must satisfy the Secretary of State that exceptional circumstances exist so that his detention can no longer be justified on legitimate penological grounds on account, in particular, of his steps towards rehabilitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2608.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2610.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the test.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2610.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2618.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second submission is that the standard or grounds that this court has set for release is necessarily set at a level of generality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2618.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2624.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is because the circumstances which might affect that standard are almost limitless.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2624.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2627.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They will vary from prisoner to prisoner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2627.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2633.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the circumstances affecting the position of each such prisoner will need to be considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2633.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2639.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No one in this case, and no judgment of the court, has sought to lay down some set of detailed criteria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2639.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2644.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is neither necessary, nor possible, nor even desirable to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2644.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2648.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That does not mean that legal certainty has not been secured.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2648.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2655.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It means that some legal rules must inevitably be set at a relatively high level of generality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2655.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2662.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Doing so gives them the necessary flexibility to react to the myriad of different factual situations they have to cover.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2662.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2665.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is a virtue, not a vice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2665.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2686.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And no doubt for that reason, this court's constant jurisprudence on the requirements of, in accordance with, or prescribed by law, has consistently acknowledged that laws may be set at a level of generality, with clarification and development occurring on a case-by-case basis, for example, through practice or judicial review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2686.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2693.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, we make the positive submission that the convention does not insist on greater specificity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2693.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2701.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Grand Chamber and Vinter referred, as I've said, simply to it being necessary for the prisoner to know under what conditions he may be released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2701.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2722.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Grand Chamber did not indicate, whether expressly or by the use of that general phrase, that domestic law must set out a detailed, prescriptive, or descriptive scheme, seeking, in effect, to delineate the boundaries of what would or might amount to the absence of continuing penological justification, or what the prisoner must do by way of rehabilitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2722.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2731.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It did not do so, no doubt, because it would be inappropriate in principle to do so, having regard to the proper margin to be afforded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2731.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2739.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And because, for all the reasons I have given, this is a context in which such a degree of prescription is a vice and not a virtue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2739.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2757.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In those circumstances, we make the respectful submission that if the section's reference in its highly controversial judgment in Trabelsi against Belgium to objective, pre-established criteria implies something more, and it is far from clear that it did so, that would be a wrong approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2757.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2760.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is nothing in Vinter to warrant it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2760.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2769.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would be inconsistent with the proper emphasis in Vinter on the margin to be afforded for any such added set of rules and structures to be imposed on domestic systems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2769.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2774.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it should be made clear by this court that that is not the position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2774.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2781.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course, Trabelsi was an extradition case, raising a number of issues that do not apply here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2781.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2789.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the facts of this case, the applicant's sentence was reviewed in 2008 by the High Court and Court of Appeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2789.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2792.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They considered that the whole life term was appropriate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2792.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2806.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant has produced no material whatever before this court to suggest that the penological basis for that position is no longer in place, or that his progress has been such that he should now be released applying Article III standards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2806.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2815.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nor has he sought to suggest that even if that were to be properly arguable, he has been prevented in some way from applying to the Secretary of State.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2815.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2823.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More generally, the court asks in its third question what the Secretary of State's present practice is in this respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2823.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2827.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His present practice is consistent with his legal obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2827.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2834.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He must faithfully apply Section 30 using the approach indicated by the Court of Appeal and which I have described.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2834.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2839.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are currently 56 whole life term prisoners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2839.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2848.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some of them, like this applicant, sentenced before the 2003 came into force, have taken the opportunity it afforded for a judicial reconsideration of their sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2848.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2854.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None have been released since the Finter judgment, directly to answer the question asked by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2854.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2860.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that tells one nothing about the domestic system, given the small numbers involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2860.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2864.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As Mr. Finter was told in terms, applications can be</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2864.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2865.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>made at any time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2865.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2872.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the grounds on which such an application can be made are as I have described.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2872.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2876.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning finally then to the process of review and its timing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2876.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2886.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Grand Chamber in Vinter referred to the whole life prisoner being entitled to know at the outset of his sentence when a review of his sentence will take place, or may be sought.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2886.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2889.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is in paragraph 122.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2889.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2900.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That statement sits alongside the express acknowledgment in paragraph 120, that it is not for the court to determine when that review should take place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2900.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2909.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that was precisely for the reason I mentioned a moment ago, namely the proper extent of convention prescription in this area of criminal justice and sentencing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2909.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2919.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also to be noted in considering this aspect of Vinter, that the final sentence of paragraph 122 defined the minimum standard here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2919.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2928.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is breached if domestic law, and I quote, does not provide any mechanism or possibility for review of a whole life sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2928.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2940.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first submission I make is therefore that it is plain that domestic law both provides for such a mechanism or possibility, and allows the prisoner to know when a review of his sentence may be sought.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2940.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2945.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In domestic law, the process or form of review is established and clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2945.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2960.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It involves the Secretary of State applying, as he's required to, Article III standards, and it includes the right to apply for judicial review of the Secretary of State's decision to ensure that they have indeed been applied, and applied correctly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2960.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2970.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Vinter, the court made explicitly clear that applying the margin, it was not the court's task to prescribe the form, executive or judicial, which the review should take.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2970.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2982.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, the courts have an entirely appropriate and proper role in judicial review under the Human Rights Act, ensuring that Article III standards are properly applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2982.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2986.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The timing is likewise clear and established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2986.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2988.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The review may be sought at any time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2988.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2991.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the express provision in section 30.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2991.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3009.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The effect of it is that whenever and as soon as the penological justification has ceased, or to put it another way, whenever and as soon as the Article III standard for continuing detention has dropped away, the prisoner can apply to the Secretary of State, who will then consider his case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3009.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3021.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is, again, to take words from paragraph 122 of Vinter, no obligation to wait and serve an indeterminate number of years before the prisoner can raise the challenge to his continuing detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3021.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3025.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The prisoner is not obliged to wait, either an indeterminate or a fixed period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3025.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3029.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He can apply at any time, as the letter to Mr. Vinter made</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3029.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3030.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3030.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3039.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The requirements in Vinter, whether you take paragraph 122 or paragraph 120, are therefore met.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3039.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3047.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second submission is that it is no part of those requirements to insist that a review happens a fixed time after sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3047.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3059.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So to insist would run directly contrary to the court statement at paragraph 122 of Vinter that the prisoner must know when a review will take place or may be sought.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3059.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3066.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is plain from the word or that it is acceptable for the prisoner to know the circumstances in which he may seek a review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3066.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3078.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court's statement of principle also highlights that the convention does not insist upon a system of review that operates even in circumstances where the prisoner does not seek it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3078.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3091.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, the need for a set or fixed time for review of a sentence might be an interesting debate in a domestic system which had nothing else or which permitted such a review only a very large number of years after sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3091.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3100.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It entirely drops away, however, where the domestic system permits an invitation to review the penological grounds at any time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3100.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3104.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such a system obviates the need for a fixed period, long-stop provision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3104.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3108.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is open to the prisoner to apply throughout his sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3108.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3119.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no requirement to have a system enabling a review to be applied for at any time and also some fixed term system of review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3119.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3130.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, a system permitting a review to occur at any time is more, not less, favorable to the prisoner precisely because it does not insist on any set period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3130.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3146.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it has the added advantage of being more nuanced and better tailored to react to individual cases because it allows for applications whenever there are proper grounds for supposing that the penological basis for detention has dropped away.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3146.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3155.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Grand Chamber in Vinter's proper and express conclusion was that because of the margin, it was not for the court to determine when the review should take place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3155.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3167.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not even prepared to say that 25 years from sentence for the first review would be the outer limit, despite materials suggesting emerging international consensus, which you've heard about.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3167.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3177.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consistently with that position, an entitlement to review only after 30 years under the French LIFER system was found to be sufficient in Bodan against France.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3177.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3189.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is, I submit, impossible to see how, if this is the position, a system providing expressly for a right of review at any time could be considered to be incompatible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3189.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3191.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, Mr. President, my overall and final submission to this</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3191.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3198.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>court is, therefore, that the majority of the fourth section were plainly right for the reasons they gave.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3198.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3207.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their reasoning as to the correct approach under Vinter, as to the reasoning of the Court of Appeal, and as to the facts of this case should, I submit, be upheld by the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3211.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3215.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Attorney General. I turn now to the judges. Are there any questions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3215.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3215.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Pinto de Albuquerque.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3221.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3223.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3223.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3235.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question is put to the government but can also be dealt with by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3235.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3256.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I looked for the position of the UK government on the Internet this morning, and the UK government has a webpage where the issue of the types of prison sentences is clarified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3256.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3277.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I quote from that page on the web, All life term means there is no minimum term set by the judge and the person is never considered for release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3277.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3283.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the position of the UK government on the Internet.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3283.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3290.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The page was last updated on the 12th of November 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3290.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3301.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also looked at the official position of the Sentencing Council for England and Wales and the same statement is made there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3301.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3311.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also looked for the official position of the Law Commission and the same statement is there to be found.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3311.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3320.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In none of these sites is there reference to Bieber or Newell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3320.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3328.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is what is the official position of the UK government?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3328.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3337.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is this clear enough for the UK citizens and for the outside world?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3337.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3348.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How can the UK government clarify this discrepancy between what is on the Internet in these various sources and the position that was presented today to the court?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3348.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3348.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3352.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3353.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Saj.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Andrs Saj</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3357.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3366.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would very much appreciate to learn about the legal nature of the LIFE First manual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3366.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3369.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is the manual a source of law?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3369.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3370.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is it subject to judicial review?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3370.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3374.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would be very helpful to learn about that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3374.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3374.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3377.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3378.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Mahoney.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paul Mahoney</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3383.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3384.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3384.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3389.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question for the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3389.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3403.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's quite long, but there's no need to worry about scribbling down the terms of the question, as a written copy will be given to them at the beginning of the pause.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3403.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3406.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3406.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3434.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What would be the scope of the judicial scrutiny carried out by the domestic courts in applications for judicial review of a negative decision by the Secretary of State in relation to release of a whole life prisoner under Section 30, paragraph 1 of the Crime Sentences Act 1997?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3434.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3441.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, would the scrutiny be as narrow as that suggested by the applicant?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3441.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3447.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Paragraphs 42 to 43 of his observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3447.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3457.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then the second particularity, and I would say this is not part of the written text that you'll get.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3457.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3481.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here I'm thinking of the local authority housing cases, where people are rejected from their housing to failure to comply with the legal conditions, and where the nature of the judicial scrutiny of such administrative decisions under Article 8 of the Convention has been explained by the courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3481.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3507.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the question here is, would the domestic court have to verify that the Secretary of State had actually exercised his statutory power of release under Section 30, paragraph 1, compatibly with the whole life prisoner's rights under Article 3 of the Convention in the particular circumstances of the case?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3507.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3531.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And would the domestic court order the Secretary of State to release the whole life prisoner if the latter could establish that on the facts and circumstances of his case, his continued imprisonment, despite his whole life sentence, is no longer justified on legitimate penological grounds?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3531.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3551.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the third and last indent is, would the domestic court examine such matters as the question, what would amount to a legitimate penological ground in this context, as the government suggests at paragraph 27 of their obligations?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3551.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3551.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3553.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3555.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. Any other questions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3555.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3558.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, Judge Turkovi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ksenija Turkovi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3563.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3564.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3564.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3581.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have heard that none of the prisoners was released, but what I would be interested to hear is whether any of the prisoners since winter has applied, regardless whether he was denied or was not denied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3581.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3604.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So whether he applied and how then, what was the procedure then, and how that was done, and whether any procedural safeguards in connection with that, whether any procedural safeguards are provided once the person, the prisoner, is applying for the review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3604.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3612.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then you have told us then that the prisoner may come whenever.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3612.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3622.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as soon as the Article 3 standard for continuum detention has dropped away.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3622.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3650.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So you have told us and you emphasized several times that a person can apply, but when actually there is obligation really to get a review, not just to apply, but to get a review in terms that you are saying as soon as the Article 3 standard for continuous detention has dropped away.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3650.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3653.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So to what extent is that determinative to get a review?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3653.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3666.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then the question, third question, when the person is entering the prison, is the person getting any information on early release?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3666.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3667.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In general, I'm asking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3667.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3670.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In general, not only for the whole life prisoners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3670.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3679.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And has McLaughlin or Winter changed anything in this respect for life prisoners?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3679.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3680.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So are they told?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3680.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3687.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because European prison rules are requiring that, and I'm not quite sure how the domestic system is regulating that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3687.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3687.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3690.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3691.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3691.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3693.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any other questions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3693.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3700.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we'll have a short break now, and we will resume the hearing at half past ten.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4107.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4107.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4149.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4154.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4154.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4156.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I call Mr. Bennathan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4157.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4159.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4159.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4162.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I deal first with the two questions of the four</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4162.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4170.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that I believe are addressed to the applicant rather than the government, and I start with Judge Marnie, if I may.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4170.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4181.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, the very simple argument to whether our skeleton argument reflects the true position of the United Kingdom, we would say yes, but I will deal with it in slightly more detail, if I may.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4181.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4190.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A judicial review of a minister is not a judge taking the same decision the minister has taken.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4190.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4194.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a review of that decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4194.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4203.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judicial fashions in the High Court come and go as to how close and anxious the scrutiny of a particular decision is.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4203.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4215.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true to say that where convention rights are concerned, the current trend is that the High Court will tend to take a very close look at the minister's decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4215.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4224.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But at no time will a High Court judge be saying, were I the person deciding this, I would decide X, and therefore that must be the decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4224.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4227.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is but a review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4227.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4254.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In theory, again, to deal directly with the Honourable Judge's question, in theory, the High Court could order a release, but we would suggest it is far more likely in the real world of the English High Court, it is far more likely the Court, if they disagreed with the minister's decision, would simply order a reappraisal of the application for the sentence to be reduced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4254.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4259.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two final comments arising from Judge Marney's question, if I may.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4259.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4277.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, if the United Kingdom win this case, then this case will be used, when my learned friend Mr Eadie appears before the High Court resisting review of a minister's refusal to release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4277.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4297.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This judgment, if against us, will be used to say, the Grand Chamber of the European Court of Human Rights has said this is a decision for the minister to take, so you, the High Court, should allow, in effect, a domestic version of the margin of appreciation and not take the decision unto yourself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4297.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4302.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally on this point, to some extent with great respect, we've been here before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4302.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4307.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of the weeks in the United Kingdom, this was an imprisonment case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4307.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4319.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was a case in which this Court found that it was not proper for politicians to be setting the minimum term for underage life prisoners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4319.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4335.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And one of the government's argues was, the politician may take this decision because they are supervised by judicial review, and at paragraph 69 of weeks, this Court made it clear that solution simply did not work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4335.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4342.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Sayo, to deal with that question, the prison service rules are not an act of Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4342.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4343.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They're not a statute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4343.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4346.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are, in effect, issued by a minister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4346.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4351.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The weight they carry, therefore, is subservient to statutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4351.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4357.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If they are inconsistent with the statute, the statute takes precedent, the statute is the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4357.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4366.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are, however, of use in the absence of such a conflict in interpreting what the statute means, how the statute will be brought into force.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4366.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4376.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The point we make, of course, is that such rules can be changed very easily and very quickly, and in this case, they haven't been.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4376.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4385.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Replying then more generally, if I may, to the United Kingdom's submissions by my learned friend, the Attorney General.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4385.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4399.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say, in effect, this Court has been treated to the same arguments that the court in Vinter were treated, save for what appears to be a new policy announcement in the middle of my learned friend's submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4399.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4410.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once more in replying, if I may, I'll consider first the theoretical de jure situation, and then the de facto, the practical situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4410.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4415.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On de jure, we say there is no mechanism in place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4415.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4419.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A judicial review simply does not proffer the help the government suggest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4419.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4423.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But courtesy of Judge Marni's question, I've addressed that already.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4423.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4426.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the letter to Mr. Vinter,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4426.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4431.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>attached to the government's submissions, a suggestion is made to Mr. Vinter,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4431.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4434.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>he may apply at any time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4434.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4439.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My learned friend, the Attorney General, said that the statute says a prisoner may apply at any time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4439.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4441.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In great respect, it doesn't.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4441.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4446.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It says the Secretary of State may at any time release a prisoner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4446.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4449.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is completely silent on the applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4449.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4453.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, if the letter to Mr. Vinter,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4453.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4463.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>combined with the oral submissions of the government today, are the announcement of a new policy, then we are very grateful to receive it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4463.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4483.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's an odd way for a government to issue policy, not to change the Prison Service Order, making this clear, not to change the statute, not to make an announcement in Parliament, not to set it out clearly in their written submissions at two stages of the proceedings before this court today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4483.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4501.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But if the Attorney General is today announcing that any one of the 50-plus whole life order lifers may apply at any time, and apparently as frequently as they like, and it's an extraordinarily liberal policy, we'd invite him to make that clear in his reply.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4501.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4510.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If that's not the real policy, then we revert to what Vinter said, which is we really do need a sensible periodic review after a sensible period in custody.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4510.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4523.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But if that is the new policy, we have learned something today with respect, and we'll be grateful for that to be made absolutely clear so it can be relied upon by lifers in subsequent litigation in the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4523.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4529.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the criteria point, the jury still, no help with respect whatsoever.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4529.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4550.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To say to someone who is starting a whole life order, and the court did find that was a time when the violation commenced, to say, well, in 30 years' time, when you get to the High Court to judicially review a minister having refused you a review of your sentence, then they'll tell you what the criteria are and are not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4550.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4556.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, that simply cannot meet the most basic understanding of this court's judgment in Vinter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4556.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4576.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It can be no use to someone who has to work for 30 years to reform themselves, to totally transform themselves to a different person from the one who committed the awful act, and then after 30 years of that, in litigation, which is the government and the court of appeals solution, they'll find out then what the criteria are.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4576.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4585.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, we say that is, with great respect, absurd, and Trabelsi sets out the proper position in terms of simple clarity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4585.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4591.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, Mr. President, we turn to the de facto position,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4591.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4604.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and we do say the only thing that's become clear is in the government's leading submissions, the submissions we heard just now, the numbers who have actually had their sentences reduced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4604.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4611.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To take the points shortly, the prison service rules, why are they unchanged? Why are the websites unchanged?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4611.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4616.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, the government's replies, well, the prison service rules don't mean what they appear to mean.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4616.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4619.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In effect, they're misleading, so no one need worry about them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4619.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4623.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, if that is really the position, why haven't they been withdrawn?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4623.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4630.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why doesn't the website, if I may touch upon Judge Vinter's question, why doesn't the website say, ignore the prison service rules?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4630.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4631.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are changing them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4631.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4636.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court asks, with great respect, a very sensible question, are you planning to rewrite them?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4636.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4637.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer appears to be no.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4637.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4639.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They will remain what they are.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4639.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4646.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What faith should that give this court, with respect, in the reality of the situation in the United Kingdom?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4646.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4668.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We quoted in terms, we did it in our written submission so it can come as no surprise to the government, we quoted in terms the government's public face on this topic in the United Kingdom, a welcome and timely decision, this is McLaughlin, of course, or Newell, same case, our courts should be able to send the most brutal murders to jail for the rest of their lives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4668.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4677.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, if that is what the relevant minister is saying in public, at home, as it were, what is the reality of the position?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4677.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4690.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What should a whole lifetime lifer think when he hears the minister say that for domestic consumption, or should this court accept what the Court of Appeal says and what the Attorney General says when he comes here?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4690.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4696.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government can, they still can, in their reply, disavow those comments by the Minister of Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4696.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4698.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have certainly not done so to date.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4698.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4712.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we really do say that the acid test, the simple acid test of whether life sentences, whole life sentences are really reducible is has any of them ever been reduced?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4712.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4721.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we say the answer, which was perfectly properly, and not dwelt upon, but touched upon by my learned friend, the Attorney General, is no.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4721.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4734.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No one has had their sentence reduced since winter as far as we are aware, and we invite correction if we are wrong, no one has ever had their sentence reduced save if they are terminally ill.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4734.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4739.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, we do say with great respect that is a simple and obvious test.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4739.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4757.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If everyone, everyone sentenced to whole life term has either died in prison or come out when terminally ill, how then, how then should this court understand whether a whole life term is or is not de facto reducible?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4757.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4777.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To again adopt with gratitude the words of Judge Pinto in his opinion in Otchelan, concurring with the majority on the point I cited earlier, prisons should not be like the gates of hell where the words Dante come true, abandon hope all ye who enter here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4777.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4792.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In terms of the actual system in place in the United Kingdom, we say that is precisely what is faced by prisoners such as the one we represent today, and we invite this court's intervention to guarantee his rights to stop that happening.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4792.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4792.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4796.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4799.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr.  Bennathan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4799.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4801.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call the Attorney General.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4803.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4809.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. President. Can I begin my submissions with the questions asked by Judge Pinto?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4810.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4820.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should say first of all, as I'm sure the court will understand, I haven't had the opportunity yet to check the various references that the learned judge made to websites.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4820.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4823.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But can I say two things nonetheless initially.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4823.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4831.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first of them is that it is of course right that in relation to life sentences no minimum term is specified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4831.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4834.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is certainly the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4834.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4840.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second point though in relation to whether release is never considered, we will have to go away and check precisely what is said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4840.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4846.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would be right to say that release is not considered by the parole board in these circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4846.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4850.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that doesn't of course mean that release can't be considered elsewhere in the ways that I've set out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4850.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4865.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But perhaps the most important submission I need to make clearly is that so far as the government's position as a matter of law, a matter of principle and a matter of practice is concerned, it is as I have set it out to the court today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4865.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4870.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I would return also to the submissions that I made about the practical scenarios here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4870.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4894.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if a prisoner wishes to take advantage of the procedure under section 30, it seems to us inconceivable that either that prisoner would not have legal advice, or that that prisoner would not make a request in a form which would find its way to the Secretary of State and be considered as a request under section 30.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4894.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4902.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can I turn to the questions asked by Judge Sio about the legal nature of the LIFA manual?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4902.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4906.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The LIFA manual of course is an expression of policy as Melinda Trent has said.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4906.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4909.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is neither statute nor judge made law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4909.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4914.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course that means it is subordinate to the provisions of the primary legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4914.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4933.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It may be of assistance if I quote from the Newell judgment in this respect, paragraph 32, where the court said, the manual cannot restrict the duty of the Secretary of State to consider all circumstances relevant to release on compassionate grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4933.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4940.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He cannot fetter his discretion by taking into account only the matters set out in the LIFA manual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4940.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4950.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it is in our submission clear that that is entirely subordinate to the primary legislation and indeed to what the Court of Appeal has said in that judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4950.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4959.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to what itself is reviewable under judicial review process, that is the decision of the Secretary of State.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4959.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4974.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So far as the questions posed by Judge Meoney are concerned, I should say in relation to the first part of those questions, that we do not accept that the scope of judicial review in these cases is as narrow as the applicant suggests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4974.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4991.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The position in principle is that the court would make its own mind up as to whether the Secretary of State's decision was compatible with Article 3 and that is because of the Secretary of State's positive obligation to act in accordance with the convention as set out in the Human Rights Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4991.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4996.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the court will consider the merits of that decision, not merely its rationality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4996.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5004.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that we would submit is indeed reflected in the housing association cases that Judge Meoney referred to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5004.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5008.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the answer to his second question is yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5008.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5025.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In relation to the third question, if the court concludes under the judicial review process that no penological grounds exist for continued detention in accordance with Article 3, then it could indeed order release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5025.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5037.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning finally to the questions asked by Judge Turkovich, the precise information given to prisoners when they arrive in prison we will have to check.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5037.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5045.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it is of course the case that the effect of a life sentence would be explained to a prisoner at the point of sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5045.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5051.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is worth confirming that no prisoners have applied under the Section 30 process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5051.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5062.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in doing so, can I return to the points I made about the way in which a prisoner would take advantage of that process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5062.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5067.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And again it is worth perhaps confirming for the court that there are no formalities required.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5067.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5073.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A prisoner does not have to apply for consideration under that section in any fixed way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5073.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5084.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And any prisoner writing to indicate that they wish to be considered for release would be considered as a Section 30 application by the Secretary of State.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5084.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5089.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as I've said, that decision would then be judicially reviewable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5089.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5102.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That we would submit is a system of greater benefit because that application can be made at any time to the prisoner than one involving a fixed point at which a review would take place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5102.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5104.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I hope that's of assistance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5104.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5104.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those are my submissions on behalf of the Government of the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5110.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5114.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5114.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5120.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5120.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5122.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5122.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5128.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later and the parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5128.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5128.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
