<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>6036708_20042016</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>17.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>18.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>62.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>64.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>71.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>79.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Khamtokhu and Aksenchik versus Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>80.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>89.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first application was lodged by Mr. Aslan Khamtokhu on 22 October 2008 under Article 34 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>89.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>96.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second application was lodged by Mr. Ertyom Aksenchik on 11 February 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>98.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>105.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are Russian nationals who were born in 1917 and 1985, respectively.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>107.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>117.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were allocated to the first section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>117.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>138.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 27 September 2011, a chamber of the first section decided to join the proceedings in the two applications, declared the case partly admissible, and communicated the complaint about the alleged discrimination in the sentencing procedures to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>138.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>142.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 13 May 2014, the court declared the case admissible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>142.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>151.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 1 December 2015, the chamber decided to relinquish jurisdiction in favor of the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>151.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>165.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 7 March 2016, the president of the Grand Chamber granted leave to equal rights trusts to submit written comments as a third party by virtue of Rule 44, Paragraph 1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>167.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>176.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court decided to grant the right to a third party by virtue of Rule 44, Paragraph 3 of the Rules of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>176.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>191.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent government are represented by Mr. Georgy Matyushkin, the representative of the Russian Federation of the European Court of Human Rights, assisted by Mrs. Olga Ocheretyanaya, advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>193.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>208.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Counsel Mrs. Anna Maralyan, Mrs. Nadezhda Yermolayeva, and Mrs. Eleonora Davidyan, who are assisted by Mrs. Karina Moskalenko, advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>209.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>214.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>214.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>227.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome groups of judges and lawyers from Bosnia and Herzegovina, Russia and Ukraine, and the judge from Germany who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>227.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>235.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the representatives of the parties, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>235.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>248.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Matyushkin for the applicants will speak first, followed by Mrs. Yermolayeva and Mrs. Davidyan, and then Mr. Matyushkin for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>249.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>263.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting into Bosnian and Russian has been authorized for the benefit of visiting groups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>263.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>273.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>273.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>275.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call now Mrs. Maralyan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>275.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>275.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>277.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>278.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>278.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>282.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>282.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>289.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>this case involves two Russian nationals, Mr. Aslan Hamtarov and Mr. Arsen Aksyanchuk,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>289.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>297.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>who are serving life sentences imposed in accordance with Article 57 of the Criminal Code of the Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>297.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>305.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This law permits such sentences to be imposed only on men and only between the ages of 18 to 65.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>305.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>329.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants complain that their sentence to life imprisonment contradicts the requirements of Article 14 in conjunction with Article 5 of the Convention, as they, being male convicts of 30 and 26 years of age at the moment of conviction, fell within the category of the persons who could be sentenced to life imprisonment according to the Russian legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>329.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>341.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants claim that there is no objective and reasonable justification for treating them differently from the categories of convicts for whom life imprisonment is not permitted under the national law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>341.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>349.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, treating them differently based on their gender and age is discriminatory and violates the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>349.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>353.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, within the time provided to the applicants,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>353.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>360.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would first demonstrate that the applicants' claim fall within the ambit of Article 5 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>360.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>368.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for that reason, Article 14 requires that the difference in treatment have objective and reasonable justification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>368.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>372.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, I will address the issue of marginal appreciation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>372.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>374.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Next, Mr. Malayeva will demonstrate</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>374.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>383.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the lack of justification for the difference in treatment of men aged 18 to 65 and women, as well as men over 65.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>383.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>386.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Malayeva will also discuss the principle</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>386.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>389.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of individualization of punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>389.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>393.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, Mr. Vidyan will bring to the court's attention</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>393.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>403.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>certain specific features of life imprisonment regime in the Russian Federation that have to be taken into account in resolving the issues presented in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>403.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>410.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As an initial matter, the applicants strongly object to the government's characterization of what the applicants seek in the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>410.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>417.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We reiterate that they do not ask the authorities for the imposition of stricter punishment on anyone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>417.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>430.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rather, since the government has commendedly already extended humane treatment to women, children, and men over 65 years of age, the applicants simply seek the same humane treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>430.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>444.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, it is utterly irrelevant to assert, as the government does, that the applicants cannot claim to be victims of a violation of the convention, as no separate issue rises under Article 5.1A of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>444.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>470.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants do not claim violation of Article 5 of the convention, but rather violation of their rights under Article 14 in conjunction with Article 5 of the convention, as they are excluded solely on the basis of their gender and age from the humane treatment of categories of convicts who are protected from the most severe type of punishment in the Russian Federation, life imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>470.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>482.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We rely on the court's well-established case law, according to which the application of Article 14 of the convention does not presuppose the violation of one of the substantive rights protected by the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>482.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>493.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is necessary and also sufficient is that the facts of the case fall within the ambit of one or more of the articles of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>493.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>510.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case at hand, we claim that the facts of the present case fall within the ambit of Article 5 of the convention, as the court has long recognized that the right to liberty under Article 5 of the convention contemplates the physical liberty of the person.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>510.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>528.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case of Clift versus United Kingdom provides one example that is of particular relevance to the present case, because the court sustained a claim that discrimination as to the length of sentence in a penal institution amounts to violation of Article 5 taken together with Article 14.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>528.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>540.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Equally irrelevant is the government's reference to the case law on Article 3 regarding the life imprisonment, because the applicants did not raise a claim of violation of Article 3 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>540.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>542.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, with your permission,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>542.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>552.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>now I would like to turn to the question whether there has been a violation of Article 14 of the convention taken in conjunction with Article 5.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>552.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>560.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 14 of the convention guarantees enjoyment of rights and freedoms set forth in the convention without discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>560.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>572.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants contend that imposition of life imprisonment only on male convicts aged 18 to 65 is discriminatory on the grounds of age and sex.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>572.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>590.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, under the provisions of Article 57 of the Criminal Code of the Russian Federation, the applicants, due to their gender and age, were treated less favorably than persons who were convicted of similar and comparable crimes, but were of a different gender and of a different age.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>590.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>596.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this constitutes discriminatory difference of treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>596.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>606.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court has ruled in a number of cases that discrimination means treating differently persons in relevantly similar situation without an objective and reasonable justification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>606.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>620.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the government had the burden to demonstrate reasons that could justify the difference in the sentences policies under Article 57 of the Criminal Code of the Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>620.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>627.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whether they discharge this burden will be addressed in detail by Ms. Irma Leiva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>627.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>650.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, and most importantly, the court has established through its case law that the notion of discrimination within the meaning of Article 14 of the convention includes cases where a person or group is treated without proper justification, less favorably than another, even though the more favorable treatment is not called for by the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>650.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>655.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, we refer to the case of Kavkaris versus Cyprus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>655.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>666.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the instant case, the criminal legislation of the respondent state voluntarily prohibits application of life imprisonment in regards of women, children, and men over 65.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>666.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>678.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The non-discrimination principle dictates that the category to which the applicants belong, male between 18 to 65, are entitled to the same treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>678.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>686.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The last issue that I would like to turn to is the applicability of the marginal appreciation as insisted by the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>686.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>701.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the court ruled in a number of cases, including Glore versus Switzerland and Kuytyn versus Russia, the scope of the marginal appreciation of the member state varies according to the circumstances, the subject matter, and its background.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>701.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>708.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And hence, the final decision as to the observance of the court's requirements rests with the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>708.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>720.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, this court held in the case of Rangelov versus Germany that while examining questions of detention, the court should exercise close scrutiny.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>720.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>735.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To assess whether the Russian Federation should enjoy certain marginal appreciation in regard of the issue at stake, we would like to bring to the court's attention the statistics of the Council of Europe member states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>735.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>746.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only three Council of Europe countries, namely Albania, Azerbaijan, and Russia treat differently men and women in regard to life imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>746.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>758.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the difference in treatment between the male convicts aged 18 to 65 and those over 65, only Russia makes the differentiation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>758.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>760.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, now, with your permission,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>760.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>763.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to invite Mr. Malayev</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>763.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>776.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to present our position regarding the adequacy of the Russian government's justifications for the difference in treatment of different categories of convicts in respect of the imposition of life imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>776.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>777.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>779.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>780.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>780.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>781.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, Mrs. Yermolayeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>782.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>784.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>784.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>787.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Charges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>787.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>789.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>as my colleague Ms. Anna Mavralyan indicated,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>789.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>804.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will discuss the issues of lack of justification of the difference in treatment between the applicant and the other categories of convicts in relation to their gender and age under Article 57 of the Russian Criminal Code.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>804.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>816.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that proper consideration of the case requires that each justification offered by the government be scrutinized in relation to each category of convicts separately.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>816.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>831.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the Court held in the case of Abdulaziz Kabalis and Valkandali, very weighty reasons would have to be advanced before a difference of treatment on the ground of gender could be regarded as compatible with the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>831.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>850.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the government failed to demonstrate such weighty reasons, and hence, the difference in sentencing policies applicable to men and women amounts to gender prejudice, and it is nothing but the product of outdated and traditionalist view on the social role of women.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>850.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>858.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This Court attaches much weight to the consensus among the Council of Europe member states regarding an issue at hand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>858.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>870.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The national laws of 44 out of 47 contracting states do not differentiate between male and female convicts regarding the imposition of life sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>870.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>875.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As mentioned, the three exceptions are Albania, Azerbaijan, and Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>875.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>888.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the approach taken in Article 57 of the Russian Criminal Code is not consistent with affirmed European consensus and has little support among the Council of Europe member states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>888.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>901.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is worth noting that outside Council of Europe, only two states have total ban of life imprisonment for female convicts while providing this term of impunishment for male.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>901.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>904.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is Belarus and Uzbekistan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>904.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>915.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In justifying the difference in treatment between male and female convicts, the government dwells to the woman's supposed special social role in comparison with that of man.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>915.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>932.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As reflected in the Court's case law, such prejudice and stereotypes about men's and women's roles in recreation maintenance of families are not sufficient justification for different treatment of men in comparison with women.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>932.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>947.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the grand chamber judgment in the case of Constantine Markin, the court has recognized the gradual but clear evolution of society towards more equal sharing between men and women of responsibilities for upbringing of their children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>947.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>953.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This approach was also enshrined at the international level in Article 5 of CEDAW.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>953.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>965.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the committee recently expressed its serious concern about situation when the stereotypical perception is articulated and promoted by the state authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>965.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>980.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The credibility of the government's position based on perception of social role of women is further undermined by lack of plausible explanation of the balance between the prospective goal of the difference in treatment and means employed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>980.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>995.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, we do not see any possible way that a woman's reproductive function is supported and protected by banning life imprisonment and permitting imprisonment for 30 years on a woman aged 18.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>995.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1003.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is certainly a great psychological difference for those two terms of imprisonment for a person of any gender.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1003.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1015.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it cannot make much difference for a woman's reproductive function if she spends all her childbearing years in prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1015.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1023.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also asserts that women are more psychologically vulnerable than men to the hardships of detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1023.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1031.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the absence of any scientific basis for this generalization, it is nothing but another gender stereotype.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1031.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1035.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not disputed that imprisonment itself is an ordeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1035.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1040.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it is an ordeal for any person, regardless sex.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1040.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1045.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both genders include individuals of different degrees of vulnerability.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1045.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1052.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in particular vulnerable position are the inmates sentenced to life imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1052.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1054.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my colleague, Ms. Eleonora Davidian,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1054.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1057.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>will illustrate this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1057.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1062.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, the government cites Article 6.5 of ICCPR.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1062.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1070.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in fact, this provision, which prohibits imposition of death penalty upon pregnant women, supports the applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1070.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1080.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The focus of these concerns is primarily the future child and then psychological peculiarities of a woman and her situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1080.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1088.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In contrast, Article 57 exempts all women from life imprisonment, whatever their personal circumstances are.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1088.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1103.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The psychological peculiarities of pregnant women and above-mentioned concerns might be the matter of individualization of criminal punishment, rather than legislative generalization of sentencing policies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1103.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1123.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In sum, neither the social role, reproductive functions, nor any special qualities of women as a group can be regarded as justifiable grounds for providing more favorable treatment of all female convicts, but denying the same treatment for males.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1123.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1134.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that the court's concerns, which motivated its findings in the case of Stek and others, are also not applicable to the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1134.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1143.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, we claim that difference in treatment based on age may give rise to discrimination, as in the case of Schwitzgebell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1143.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1148.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here, we distinguish between minors and senior convicts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1148.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1157.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to minor convicts, we acknowledge and accept international standards of criminal proceedings, which prohibit life imprisonment for them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1157.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1174.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Out of the considerations of humane attitude, we by no means call upon the government to impose life sentences on minor convicts, but we do insist that government applies similar humane approach to everyone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1174.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1182.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whereas the difference in treatment in comparison with senior convicts is not supported by any scientific studies and research.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1182.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1191.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government's reference to the alleged diminished responsibility of all persons aged 65 is scientifically null.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1191.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1220.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, if all persons over 65 are considered as irresponsible and unable to foresee duly the consequences of their conduct, the fact that persons over 65 are eligible under Russian law for certain important public offices, such as that of judge of the Constitutional Court of Russia, who can hold their office till 75, also undermines the government's generalization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1220.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1234.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, we refer to the official statistics of World Health Organization, which shows that the average life expectancy in Russia is equal to 65 years for male and 73 years for female.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1234.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1242.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, poor conditions of penitentiary institutions in Russia definitely reduce life expectancy of the inmates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1242.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1254.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, even if the life imprisonment is imposed on a man, for instance, aged 40, he has illusory chances for early release on parole after serving 25 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1254.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1271.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whereas imposition of any term of imprisonment for a particular serious offenses, which is eight years at minimum, and serving this term in specific prison condition, will make the chances of release for the senior person illusory even in theory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1271.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1281.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, we claim that setting the age limit at 65 is arbitrary and does not reflect the social realities of Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1281.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1286.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also refer to the worldwide and European consensus on the matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1286.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1296.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Russia remains the only country among the members of the Council of Europe which has legislative ban on the imposing of life sentence on seniors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1296.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1302.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Similar provisions can be found only in two criminal legislation worldwide.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1302.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1305.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And again, it's Belarus and Uzbekistan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1305.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1316.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to persons over 65, the age may in certain cases be considered as a mitigating circumstance, depending on the individual circumstances of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1316.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1323.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A convict's age may be also considered as a ground for remission from punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1323.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1333.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the goal of individualization of criminal punishment should be achieved by judicial sentencing discretion, rather than legislative generalization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1333.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1343.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We conclude that the applicants do face unjustified difference in treatment as compared with a man over 65.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1343.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1348.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And here, with your permission, I would like to pass the word to my colleague, Ms. Eleonora</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1348.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1348.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pertel-Pizan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1350.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1353.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Ms. Yermolayeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1353.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1355.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now, please, Mrs. Davidyan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1356.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1360.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President, honorable judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1360.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1371.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is necessary to point out once again that the applicants are claimed being discriminated in relations to their rights within the ambit of Article 5 and not Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1371.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1382.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, speaking of the humanitarian approach used for women, minors, and seniors, we have to assess what's left for those outside of the humanitarian approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1382.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1397.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is impossible to consider the applicant's claim without understanding what is at stake for them, without taking into account the context in which the violation is claimed, the context of Russian practices in reality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1397.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1406.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to analyze this Russian context, first allow me to introduce the ways in which the Russian practices differ from other European countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1406.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1412.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>10 countries in Europe and almost 20 more outside Europe don't have the life sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1412.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1425.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In some countries that do have the life sentence, the minimum term of imprisonment after which a convict is allowed to apply for early release on parole starts at as low as 12 years, as in Denmark and Finland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1425.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1432.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Ireland, the average period of detention for those serving life sentences is 12 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1432.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1437.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Austria, release on parole is possible after 15 years of imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1437.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1451.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And statistics show that in 2001, 2013, the average number of life prisoners being released on parole there per year is seven.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1451.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1476.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Germany, in 2013, 93 life sentenced prisoners were released on parole or pardoned, 17 of them after serving over 25 years, 14 after serving 20 to 25 years, 45 were released after serving 15 to 20 years, and another 17 after serving 10 to 15 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1476.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1483.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Returning to Russia, the law provides for possibility of release on parole after 25 years of imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1483.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1491.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unfortunately, there are no official statistics on the number of prisoners serving life sentences who were released early on parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1491.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1496.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although we requested this information from the Russian authorities, no adequate response was provided.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1496.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1511.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the meantime, prominent human rights advocates in Russia who constantly deal with issues regarding prisoners' rights are not aware of a single case of early release on parole of a prisoner serving life sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1511.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1517.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This includes people with serious health problems and those who managed to survive to their 70s.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1517.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1533.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This also includes people who have earned the support of the administration of their penal institutions, as well as the Commission on Pardons, which both recommended that this prisoner should be released on parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1533.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1547.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only example of a change in a life sentence known to us involves the European Court's judgment, which was followed by reconsideration of the case and reduction of the sentence, as the case of Vladijagin versus Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1547.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1553.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, to date, a life sentence in Russia is effectively irreducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1553.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1570.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is evidenced not only by the absence of any actual examples of early release on parole, but also by the fact that nothing in the penitentiary treatment of prisoners serving life sentences shows any intention to provide an opportunity for such release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1570.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1574.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Life prisoners are kept in facilities with an especially strict regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1574.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1581.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are separated from non-life prisoners and subjected to even stricter conditions and limitations than any other category of prisoners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1581.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1591.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This regime has already been criticized by this court in the case of Khoroshenko versus Russia, where it was found disproportionate to the aims of the sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1591.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1597.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Life prisoners can maintain contact with the outside world only by corresponding in writing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1597.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1601.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All other types of contacts are severely limited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1601.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1605.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They cannot make any telephone calls except in an emergency.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1605.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1610.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And their relatives can visit them in person only every six months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1610.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1619.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the visits last for no longer than four hours and with no more than two adult visitors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1619.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1628.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prisoners are separated from their visitors by a glass partition, so they are not able to have any physical contact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1628.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1633.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A prison guard is present and within hearing distance at all times.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1633.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1644.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These restrictions are imposed directly by law and concern the prisoners solely on the account of their life sentence and irrespective of any other factors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1644.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1651.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These restrictions are all combined within one regime for a fixed duration of time and cannot be altered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1651.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1660.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The regime is imposed for a fixed period of 10 years, which can be extended in the event of poor conduct while serving the sentence, but cannot be shortened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1660.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1668.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After spending 10 years in a strict regime facility, in theory, a life prisoner could be transferred to a lighter regime facility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1668.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1672.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in reality, such transfers rarely happen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1672.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1691.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court has already noted that Russia was the only jurisdiction within the Council of Europe to regulate the prison visits of all life sentence prisoners as a group by combining an extremely low frequency of permitted prison visits and the lengthy duration of such a regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1691.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1704.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In all other types of penitentiary institutions, prisoners are involved in different socializing activities and educational programs, but that never happens in the institutions for those serving life sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1704.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1718.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No efforts are made by the authorities to prepare their prisoners for law-abiding life outside of prisons, to encourage remorse or to support their reformation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1718.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1727.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These prisoners are given no chance for social rehabilitation or a possibility to prove that they are capable of living within a society and contributing to it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1727.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1739.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This results in the elimination of any motivation on the part of the convicts to adjust, as they are well aware that they will remain behind bars until the moment of their physical death.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1739.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1746.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Russian law states that the aim of criminal punishment is the reformation of the convicts as well as prevention of crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1746.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1767.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This goal is consonant with the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, as well as several other international instruments, which emphasize that efforts need to be made by the prison authorities for the reintegration and rehabilitation of all prisoners, including those serving life sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1767.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1775.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Russia, however, in reality, the only function of the life sentence the prisoners are serving is retribution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1775.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1784.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is just a substitute for the death penalty, because all that awaits the life prisoners is moral degradation and physical death.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1784.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1792.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To many convicts, their life sentence doesn't seem any less inhumane than the death penalty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1792.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1805.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the above information should be taken into account in conjunction with the fact that, in many cases, the fairness of the trials which led to life sentences remains very doubtful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1805.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1817.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, this court, on several occasions, found violations of Article 6 in such cases, for example, cases of Shumikhin, Shugaev, Moskovets, and Laryagin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1817.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1824.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Human Rights Committee in 2000 considered the petition of Mr. Dmitry Gridin finding violation of fair trial</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1824.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1827.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>with a requirement of his immediate release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1827.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1830.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of these people, except for only Mr. Laryagin,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1830.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1842.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>are still imprisoned with no hope for any chance to be able to return to a somewhat normal life, to be able to spend time with their families, to be able to just to have this hope.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1842.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1850.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Recognizing these stark realities, and the Russian authorities know them better than anyone else, leads us to the core of the issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1850.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1855.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why should the abolition of the life sentence be deemed out of question?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1855.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1862.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While making this flat assertion in their observations to the court, the government did not offer any explanation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1862.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1867.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is the reason making it impossible to contemplate the abolition of the life sentence?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1867.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1877.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government acknowledges that the life sentence is outside of the humanitarian approach that the authorities are exercising towards subgroups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1877.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1883.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we are all in agreement that life sentence is basically inhuman.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1883.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1885.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, in conclusion, I would</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1885.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1892.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>like to underline once again that we are in no way contending that anyone's treatment should be worsened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1892.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1908.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What we are claiming is that if there are people who are entitled to humanism under obligations that the state voluntarily took on, then there should not be people who are excluded from it as a result of discriminatory treatment based on their gender or age.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1908.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1908.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1909.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1912.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mrs. Davidyan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1912.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1915.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I call Mr. Matyushkin for the government, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1925.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1928.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1928.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1944.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>it follows that the present case concerns the issue of imposition of a particular sentence, namely life imprisonment, on the applicants or, alternatively, its non-application to minors, women and elderly men.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1944.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1959.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the issue of the lawfulness of the applicant's conviction or alleged arbitrariness or disproportionality of the specified punishment imposed on them is not the subject of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1959.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1972.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, the government recalled that the Court has specified that a certain margin of appreciation must be accorded to contracting states in their matters of criminal justice and sentencing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1972.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1975.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See Winter and others versus United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1975.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1989.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, in its case law, the Court has reiterated that it is not its task within the context of Article V of the Convention to review the appropriateness of the sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1989.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1993.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See Weeks versus United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1993.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2005.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does not pronounce on the appropriate length of detention or other sentence which should be served by a person after conviction by the competent court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2005.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2008.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See T versus United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2008.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2023.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Matters of appropriate sentencing largely fall outside the scope of the Convention, and it is not its role to decide, for example, what is the appropriate term of detention applicable to a particular offense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2023.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2028.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See Svanuk versus United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2028.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2038.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The above position allows the government to conclude that the applicant's claims in this case fall outside of the scope of Article V of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2038.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2052.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Meanwhile, Article XIV of the Convention may apply only in cases in which specific rights foreseen by other Articles of the Convention are at least involved, if not breached.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2052.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2064.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, in the absence of any issues under Article V of the Convention in this case, there is obviously no basis for the application of Article XIII of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2064.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2078.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government further note that no complaints have been raised by the applicants under Article I of Protocol No. 12 of the Convention that provides for a general prohibition of discrimination</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2078.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2085.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and expands to any rights, even those which are not listed in the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2085.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2091.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Anyway, Protocol No. 12 of the Convention has not been ratified by the Russian Federation,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2091.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2096.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and therefore the applicants may not invoke this provision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2096.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2119.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is more, neither the Convention or the Protocols thereto, nor the Russian legislation, provide for a right of a person convicted of having committed a crime to choose a particular penalty, or even more so, for a right to request a particular penalty to be imposed on others not involved in the proceedings before this Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2119.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2134.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, and taking into account the presumption that life imprisonment itself does not contradict the Convention, these applications appear to be incompatible with the Convention Rationale Materia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2134.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2149.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Along with that, the Court is not designed to review the legislation of the Member States in the abstract when the dispute provision does not actually infringe on any specific rights of the applicants, as in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2149.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2172.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, taking into account the Court's functions, it is not in its task to review the applicants' complaints in the abstract, since they have failed to clarify how exactly possible application of life imprisonment to minors, women, and elderly men would affect their personal situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2172.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2180.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should the Court nevertheless decide to concede the present case on the merits, the Government would like to submit the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2180.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2204.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Court's case law, a difference in treatment would be discriminatory in breach of Article 14 of the Convention unless it has objective and reasonable justification, namely if it pursues a legitimate aim or if there is a reasonable relationship of proportionality between the means employed and the aim sought to be released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2204.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2222.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Government believes that the above criteria have been fully met by the Russian legislators when they were formulating Article 57 of the Russian Criminal Code, which has essentially been contested by the applicants in abstract.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2222.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2232.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, in deciding whether life imprisonment should be applied to various categories of criminals, one should bear in mind the following circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2232.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2247.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Government emphasizes that non-application of life imprisonment to minors, women, and elderly men, which is based on very strong humanitarian grounds, does not exclude their criminal responsibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2247.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2255.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the Russian Criminal Code, persons falling within these groups may be sentenced to fixed terms of imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2255.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2274.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question is, however, whether the continued incarceration such as life imprisonment, should it be introduced, would be justified and would not violate the principle of humanism proclaimed by international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2274.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2280.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let us now consider each category separately.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2280.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2305.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regard minors, it should be noted that international instruments, in particular United Nations Standard Minimum Rules for the Administration of Juvenile Justice, stress that status of children as particularly vulnerable should be their main consideration in all measures taken to deal with them under the penal law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2305.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2316.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The juvenile justice system should treat children with special regard to their age and vulnerability at every stage of the process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2316.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2325.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their welfare and the best interest of the child should be a priority consideration when decisions are being made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2325.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2342.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, children should not be deprived of their liberty unless there is absolutely no other option, and when they are put into custody, it should be for the shortest possible time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2342.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2348.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Institutions for children should be educational and reformative rather than punitive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2348.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2369.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The international human rights instruments require that juveniles should be dealt with in a system that is separate from that for adults, since children are unlikely to understand the process of the court of law and the meaning of the imposition of the punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2369.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2385.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are entitled to special protection because they are vulnerable, they are deemed to carry less personal responsibility for their actions, and they are required to be treated with rehabilitative measures rather than punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2385.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2410.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it comes to sentencing in compliance with the above international instruments, the Rational Criminal Court in section 6 of article 88 provides that punishment in the form of deprivation of liberty may be inflicted upon a minor for a term of 10 years at the most and shall be served in educational colonies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2410.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2430.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is more, out of 19 crimes for which the criminal court allows imposition of life imprisonment, even above 14 but below 16 can be prosecuted only under five of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2430.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2462.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Along with a number of documents of different United Nations bodies and the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe calling for a complete abolition of life imprisonment for minors referred to by the government in their written submissions, it should be taken into account that in 2013 in the case of Mendoza and others versus Argentina, the Inter-American Court of Human Rights found that life imprisonment of minors in Argentina was unlawful and had to be prohibited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2462.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2469.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even third, life and sentence prisoners could apply for parole after 20 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2469.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2484.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court ruled that life sentences by their nature did not comply with the purpose of social integration of children were disproportionate and provoked an extreme psychological impact on them, constituting cruel and inhuman treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2484.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2505.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the European Court in its case of Hawkins and Edwards versus United Kingdom established that imposition of a sentence that is severely disproportionate may constitute cruel treatment in breach of Article 3 of the Convention, and with children that would definitely be the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2505.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2528.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus international human rights instruments and regulations as well as international court's judgments recognize the necessity of a more humane treatment with respect to minors when imposing criminal punishments and thus the imposition of a life sentence on minors would constitute gross disregard of existing international norms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2528.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2550.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the government take notice of the fact that the Equal Rights Trust, which has been admitted as the third party in the present case, has also acknowledged that the exemption of children from a life sentence is considered appropriate and necessary under international human rights law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2550.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2560.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as women are concerned, it is necessary to highlight that women constitute a minority in national prison population.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2560.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2575.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In most prison systems, the number varies from 2 to 9 percent of the total prison population, and they are present only 6.5 percent out of the total prison population of the world.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2575.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2585.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Along with that, females have significantly lower representation than males in serious crime categories.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2585.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2603.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is clear from a variety of sources that females are less involved in serious offense categories, they commit less harm, and recidivism rates among them are quite low.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2603.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2615.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, it should not be overlooked that a significant number of women prisoners come from impoverished and marginalized parts of society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2615.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2625.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They tend to have a background of physical and emotional abuse, mental health problems, and alcohol and drug dependency.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2625.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2640.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Women's imprisonment is closely related to poverty and discrimination, both as the reason for women's offenses and because women often cannot afford legal services or payment of fines or bail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2640.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2666.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government further noted that the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights requires that all persons deprived of their liberty shall be treated with humanity and with respect for the inherent dignity of the human persons, and that the penitentiary system shall compromise the treatment of prisoners, the essential aim of which shall be their reformation and social rehabilitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2666.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2688.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the United Nations Human Rights Committee has pointed out, this imposes on states a positive obligation towards persons who are particularly vulnerable because of their status as persons deprived of liberty, and complements for them the ban on torture or other cruel, inhuman, or degrading treatment or punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2688.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2695.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prisoners may not be subjected to any hardship or constraint other than the resulting from the deprivation of liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2695.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2703.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Respect for the dignity of such persons must be guaranteed under the same condition as for that of free persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2703.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2711.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These provisions are enforced by the Convention of the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2711.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2727.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the United Nations Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women states that the violence against women includes physical, sexual, or psychological violence perpetrated or tolerated by the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2727.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2745.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Specific standards that recognize the special needs and circumstances of female prisoners are also included in the body of principles for the protection of all persons under any form of detention or imprisonment adopted by the General Assembly of the United Nations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2745.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2759.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is remarkable that these principles directly state that measures applied under the law and designed solely to protect the rights and special status of women shall not be deemed to be discriminatory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2759.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2789.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the World Health Organization Regional Office for Europe and the United Nations Office on Drug and Crime, in their Declaration on Women's Health in Prison, also pronounced that all policies affecting women in the criminal justice system must recognize the gender-specific needs of women and the significant variations in needs that can exist between different groups of women.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2789.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2813.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, the European Parliament also, in its resolution of March 13, 2008, on the particular situation of women in prison and the impact of the imprisonment of parents on social and family life, considered that women prisoners belong to one of the vulnerable groups that have specific needs and requirements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2813.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2831.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The resolution highlights in particular that the specific needs and circumstances of women in prison should be taken into account and that visible measures adapted to the specific needs of women should be put in place, including the application of alternative sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2831.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2860.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It further notes that it is known today that a large number of women prisoners have been the victims of violence, sexual abuse, or mistreatment by their family or partner and suffered a state of deep economic and psychological dependence, which has directly contributed to their criminal record and brought physical and psychological consequences, such as post-traumatic stress.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2860.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2877.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, as it was pointed out in one of the documents prepared by the Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights, the concept of equality means much more than treating all persons in the same way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2877.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2889.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Equal treatment of persons in unequal situations will operate to perpetrate rather than eradicate injustice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2889.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2904.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore international standards acknowledge particular vulnerability of women and necessity of their special treatment, and it would be extremely severe to apply to them such a strict punishment as life in prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2904.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2922.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government considers that allowing the general link criteria is not the same as toleration of discrimination, but is the realization that some features of lives and natures of men and women may differ and ought to be acknowledged in sentencing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2922.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2934.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With regard to elderly persons, the government knows that the recent studies have shown that world penal systems are struggling to cope with the rising number of older persons, prisoners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2934.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2943.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in the United States, the aging prison population has become a real problem and led to a crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2943.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2957.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore many advocacy groups as well as politicians have been concerned about rising health care and other costs in the prison system and even campaign for the release of elderly prisoners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2957.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2980.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the report of 2012 concerning the issue of aging prison population in the United States, Human Rights Watch noted that continued imprisonment of elderly offenders does not fulfill the principal purpose of punishment such as retribution, incapacitation, deterrence, and rehabilitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2980.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2992.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With respect to the purpose of retribution, the government considers that in order to achieve this purpose, it would be sufficient to sentence an elderly criminal to a fixed term of imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2992.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3027.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regard the purpose of incapacitation and deterrence, the government believes that in spite of the fact that accountability for a crime is an indispensable component of a just criminal justice system and that extremely serious crimes warrant long prison sentences, at the time passed and most of elderly prisoners become physically incapacitated and mentally impaired, they threaten society and public safety and the justification for their continued imprisonment diminishes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3027.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3041.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Continued imprisonment has very small deterrent impact on the older offender who, by virtue of age and infirmity, already poses a negligible threat of reoffending.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3041.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3052.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, further imprisonment of elderly offenders is unlikely to advance their rehabilitation and reintegration into society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3052.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3064.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, human rights law requires that the imprisonment should not be purely retributory and that efforts should be made in order to rehabilitate prisoners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3064.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3073.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After providing that, all persons deprived of their liberty shall be treated with humanity and with respect for the inherent dignity of the human persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3073.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3091.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights in Article 10 further mandates that the penitentiary system shall comprise treatment of prisoners, the essential aim of which shall be their reformation and social rehabilitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3091.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3104.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore it is hard to see how the continued imprisonment of elderly could meaningfully serve any of the purposes for which their sentence were originally imposed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3104.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3120.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is more, disproportionately lengthy prison terms may constitute arbitrary deprivations of liberty in violation of the rights to liberty provided for by Article 9 of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3120.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3135.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In a number of cases challenging life sentences, the European Court of Human Rights has recognized that sentences which are arbitrary or disproportionately lengthy may violate Article 5 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3135.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3140.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They may also constitute cruel and inhumane punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3140.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3152.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus Article 7 of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights provides that no one shall be subjected to torture or cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3152.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3169.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In turn, the European Court of Human Rights has recognized that disproportionality severe sentences can be incompatible with the prohibition of inhuman punishment envisaged in Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3169.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3179.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court ruled that life sentences without the possibility of review have been deemed to constitute cruel or inhuman treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3179.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3190.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2013, in the case of Winter and others versus United Kingdom, this Court found that human dignity requires for prisoners to have a hope of release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3190.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3202.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court held that some mechanism needs to be in place for reviewing the sentence at least every 25 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3202.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3222.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Applying the above positions, the government believed that imposition of life imprisonment on persons who are over 65 years old would put them into an equal position with younger persons who, according to Section 5 of Article 79 of the Russian Criminal Court, may count on release after 25 years of imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3222.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3238.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, for defendants who are older than 65 years, such prospects can be fulfilled only after they reach 90 years, which, taking into account their life expectancy rates, makes it almost unachievable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3238.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3247.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In light of the above, the government is convinced that exemption of certain groups from life imprisonment is fully reasonable and substantiated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3247.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3267.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, the government considered that the amendment of Article 57 of the Criminal Court of the Russian Federation to allow application of life imprisonment to minors, women, and elderly men will not affect the applicant's personal situation and by no means would restore their allegedly violated rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3267.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3298.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, the government would like to note that, according to the updated statistical data presented by the Federal Penitentiary Service of Russia as of March 1, 2016, out of almost 600,000 of inmates serving their sentence in the form of imprisonment, only about 42,000 are female and slightly more than 1,500 are minors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3298.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3307.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, only 1,957 persons out of that total number have been serving a sentence in the form of life imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3307.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3325.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides, given the average lifetime for men in Russia, which is only 59 according to the recent World Health Organization data, it is highly unlikely that there will be any criminal over 65 years old who can potentially be sentenced to life imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3325.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3339.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, according to various researches, even in those countries where life imprisonment is imposed on women, the number of females serving life in sentence is extremely low in comparison to men.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3339.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3357.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, it is manifestly unfeasible from the economical standpoint to alter the legislation and to introduce life imprisonment to other very limited groups of criminals when they are so small in numbers and so much additional work is required to accommodate them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3357.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3367.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While available, ordinary imprisonment may be considered sufficient to ensure that all the purposes of punishment are fulfilled in respect of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3367.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3388.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lastly, as regards another proposal of the applicants to consider gender and age as second instances mitigating punishment, the government are convinced that it will not change the situation but will only shift the burden of application of life imprisonment to certain groups of criminals from legislators to judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3388.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3405.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the criteria for the deciding on whether life imprisonment should be applied to a particular criminal will not change at all and will remain in practice as discriminatory as in the applicants' opinion they currently are.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3405.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3417.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this context, the government would like to reiterate that the applicants seek a change in the legislation in abstracta and the examination of their proposal should be considered by the domestic legislative bodies and not by this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3422.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3424.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mr. Matyushkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3424.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3428.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3428.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3437.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I turn to my colleagues in order to invite them to put to the parties the questions they may wish to ask.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3437.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3438.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I see Judge Mrti, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3438.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3438.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Mrti Mits</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3442.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3445.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3445.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3466.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the context of differential treatment on the basis of gender, so male convicts compared to female convicts, both parties address one of the possible scenarios where the violation of Article 14 in conjunction with Article 5 may be established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3466.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3471.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the question for both parties will be in this context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3471.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3489.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the government in their observations in paragraph 29 states that, I quote, such finding of a violation would call for worsening of the situation of a great mess of other people not involved in the proceedings before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3489.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3514.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I kindly ask to explain how and why the situation of other people would necessarily be made worse and whether the government doesn't see a way of complying with such a possible ruling without worsening the situation of other people in line with the European Convention of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3514.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3534.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the applicants, applicants in their observations in paragraphs 52, 53, refer to the individualization of punishment as the best solution and a general principle in sentencing policy that should be applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3534.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3572.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would kindly ask to clarify whether the applicants mean the characteristics which are listed in Article 60 of the Russian Criminal Code, namely, which have to be taken into account when the punishment is inflicted, namely the convict's personality, influence on the rehabilitation and impact on living conditions of the convict's family, or you mean extension of the same article to female offenders or maybe both.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3572.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3572.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3573.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3575.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Mits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3575.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3578.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now it's Judge Pinto de Albuquerque, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3579.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3581.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3581.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3591.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is addressed to the government, but of course the applicants can also take a position on this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3591.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3599.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, it's a group of three different points that I would like to raise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3599.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3624.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is scientific evidence that demonstrates that the suicide rate and the insanity rate among prisoners sentenced for life is higher than among prisoners sentenced for prison terms of fixed duration, and much higher among men than among women.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3624.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3643.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Male prisoners sentenced for life tend to commit suicide or become insane more often than women sentenced for life, and much more often than people in freedom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3643.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3653.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Male offenders between 18 and 65 commit more often suicide and become more often insane than women, minors and seniors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3653.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3660.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this occurs especially when they are serving life or indeterminate prison terms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3660.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3670.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question to the government, do you have any statistical data in Russia to contradict this evidence?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3670.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3682.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second question, is there any scientific evidence in Russia of a correlation between the sex and age of the offender and the gravity of the offense?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3682.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3704.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can you prove to this court that men, and particularly men aged between 18 and 65, commit more serious crimes than women offenders or male offenders under 18 or male offenders over 65?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3704.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3718.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Final question, is there any scientific evidence, statistical evidence in Russia of a correlation between life imprisonment and lower crime rates, or at least lower violent crime rates?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3718.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3731.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can you prove to this court that this Russian life imprisonment sentencing policy has produced lower crime rates and particularly lower violent crime rates?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3731.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3746.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can you prove to this court that the prohibition of life sentence to female, juvenile and senior offenders has caused lower crime rates among the Russian female, juvenile and senior population?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3746.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3746.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3747.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3750.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Pinto de Albuquerque.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3750.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3751.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now, Judge Lpez Guerra, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Luis Lpez Guerra</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3756.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just a brief question to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3756.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3770.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government states in its observation that the Russian criminal code provides for only 19 types of crimes punishable by life imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3770.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3781.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then the government states that life imprisonment is not imposed in a person automatically for the commission of the above crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3781.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3788.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I understand it means that there is the life imprisonment is not mandatory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3788.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3791.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's not mandatory in any of these 19 cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3791.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3798.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like the government to confirm this statement if really this is the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3798.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3800.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think it's an important point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3800.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3800.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3800.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3804.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Lpez Guerra.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3804.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3807.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there are no more questions, now the court...</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3807.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3809.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm sorry, Judge Dedov, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Dmitry Dedov</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3813.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3820.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. I would like to ask the applicants to clarify to the court what kind of measures</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3820.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3838.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the authorities would have to implement to restore the rights of the applicants, I would say to avoid discrimination in case we find a violation of Article 14 in conjunction with Article 5 of the convention. Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3836.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3839.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much judge Dedov. Judge Nuberger please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nuberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3840.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3841.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just a short question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3841.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3847.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have heard that the conditions for life prisoners are much worse than for others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3847.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3856.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I just would like to understand better why is it not only the time that is different, but also the conditions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3856.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3860.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because that means that for women, you have basically always different conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3860.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3860.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3861.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3864.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3864.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3866.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no more questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3866.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3878.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now the court will rise for 10 minutes, following which the parties will return for the second round of short pleadings to respond to the submissions in the first round to the judges' questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4185.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4186.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4226.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4228.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4228.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4233.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is now resumed and I call the applicants now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4233.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4234.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Davidyan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4238.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4241.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4241.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4253.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, I would like to thank you for the questions which raise very important issues and help us to elaborate the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4253.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4259.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to start with a remark regarding the government's arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4259.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4290.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in terms of margin of appreciation to which the government has been referring, I would like to note that in this particular issue, the margin of appreciation of the government would be significantly narrower than we could see, for example, in the case of Stak versus UK.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4290.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4300.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, the issue is not within the economical or social welfare sphere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4300.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4312.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the issue itself questions the life of life prisoners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4312.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4325.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we believe that the reasons for differentiation and treatment should be extremely more weighty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4325.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4347.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in this case, the positive discrimination cannot be used because women are not in unfavorable position in this case and unequal to use the positive discrimination to equalize their position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4347.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4361.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only legitimate aid that the government provided was humanism that was applied to women and minors and seniors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4361.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4369.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we believe that humanist cannot be a justification for different in treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4369.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4389.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, that should be the approach that should be applied to all people without any discrimination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4389.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4408.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the question about statistics of the government, we would like to support this question because we were also not able to find any available statistics that would have shown some correlative figures rather than absolute figures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4408.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4418.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that absolute figures do not show the ratio of grave violations that are being committed by men and women.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4418.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4436.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, we are not able to comment on this issue, not being able to operate with the not absolute but correlative numbers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4436.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4461.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In terms of question about mitigating circumstances that can be taken into account while imposing a sentence, we absolutely support the approach of individualization of punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4461.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4476.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We in no way believe that worsening of situation of women and minors and seniors could resolve the issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4476.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4484.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that individualization of punishment is an absolute standard that should be followed by the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4484.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4512.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we would like to note that in Russian law, the list of mitigating circumstances is open, which means that anything can be taken into account, starting with the personality of the convict and finishing with their family situation and their obligations to raise their children and things like that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4512.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4521.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to also thank for the question about conditions of detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4521.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4535.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we support this question because the court has already found on many occasions that conditions of the detention should not be part of the punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4535.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4558.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it is clear that the specific conditions of detention of life prisoners are exactly part of the detention because they're used directly by law, regardless of anything except for the sentence itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4558.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4572.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would like to also note that, once again, lowering of standards that are being applied to all the convicts is unacceptable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4572.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4582.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we would like to refer to the amicus curiae submitted by Equal Rights, who brilliantly explained this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4582.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4600.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in terms of measures which should be taken to avoid discrimination, we would like to note that there are several avenues, and it is completely up to the government which avenue to take.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4600.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4604.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that there's definitely more than one available avenue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4604.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4621.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to also mention that the government, yes, at this point, we cannot claim that there is a consensus among European countries about abolition of life sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4621.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4628.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the question is, does there have to be a consensus at this point?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4628.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4633.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>10 European countries have already abolished a life sentence without any consensus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4633.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4638.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so did 20 other countries outside of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4638.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4646.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, Russia has already abolished life sentence for women, as well as minors and seniors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4646.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4660.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Russian government, in their memorandum, stated that one of the reasons for the abolition are the principles of justice and humanism that are of utmost importance in a democratic legal state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4660.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4679.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to quote that the government noted, humanism is the concept of high moral standards produced during the evolution of the mankind, social meaning of which consists in recognition of a person, his or her interest, dignity and honor as a superior value protected by the state and the society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4679.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4689.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We praise and support with all our hearts this reasoning and approach and believe that humanism is the engine of the development of civilization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4689.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4700.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we are calling upon the government to extend the application of this humanitarian policy on all people in its jurisdiction without any exclusions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4700.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4707.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that Russia doesn't have to wait for other countries to press it to use the humanitarian approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4707.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4708.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It already uses this approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4708.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4716.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is a powerful enough country to lead the high moral standards and promote them among others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4716.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4716.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4718.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4721.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mrs. Davidyan and Mr. Matyushkin, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4732.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4751.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Respectable judges, answering the first question, the question of Honorable Judge Meads, I should tell that it's just, from my point of view, the problem of misinterpretation, misunderstanding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4751.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4773.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We just want to say that changing of practice in life imprisonment to spread the life imprisonment to minors, these vulnerable groups of persons, will worsen their status and will spread their population in prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4773.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4816.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Answering the question of Judge Albuquerque, the first question, I should tell that we took the data from a report of World Health Organization, which provides that the women and young people commit more often suicide and suffer from different mental diseases being in prison, more often than men.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4816.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4841.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And answering the second question of Judge Albuquerque, I should answer that the statistic which we provide that the prison population of women in Russia is just 6.5% from all prison population</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4841.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4855.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>itself shows the correlation between the men and women.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4855.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4881.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I told you today, Hrin, that by our statistic, the crimes which women commit compared to men are not so hard and not so offensive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4881.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4888.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And answering the third question, I should tell that for now we do not have data.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4888.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4899.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if we will have, if we will find the statistical data later, we definitely provide this court with this data.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4899.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4916.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Answering the question of Honorable Judge Guerra, I should tell that life imprisonment by Russian law and court practice of Russian judges are not mandatory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4916.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4937.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And courts are taking in consideration all circumstances of case and the person which commit the crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4937.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4948.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the punishment should be just not life imprisonment, but some definite term.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4948.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4949.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's up to the judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4952.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4962.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And judges have split marginal position in these cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4962.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4979.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, I want to refer some statement which provided us today the Honorable Representatives of Applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4979.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4994.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to note that the applicants misinterpreted the Russian government's position with respect to references to Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4994.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5006.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government only noted that the issue of life imprisonment was considered by the court mainly from the standpoint of Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5006.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5020.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And life imprisonment has been found to be in compliance with the Convention, provided that the legislation envisages for a possibility of parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5020.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5035.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Russian criminal court provides for such a possibility more than the majority of the countries still have in their criminal law such punishment as life imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5035.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5052.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, taking into account the above said and in absence of European consensus of the issue of life imprisonment, the Russian Federation has no grounds to abolish such type of punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5052.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5073.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, I should tell that the condition of detention itself of life prisoners are out of scope of this definite case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5073.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5077.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's out of scope of this procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5077.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5077.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5079.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5083.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Matyushkin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5083.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5086.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5086.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5092.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the Court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5092.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5096.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court will now deliberate on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5096.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5099.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5099.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5103.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5103.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5103.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
