<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>6056114_15052019</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>22.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>23.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>65.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>66.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>78.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>86.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of S.M. versus Croatia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>86.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>98.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on 27 August 2014 under Article 34 of the Convention by a Croatian national, Mrs. S.M.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>98.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>107.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the first section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>107.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>113.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was communicated to the government on 9 February 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>113.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>121.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 19 July 2018, a chamber of the first section delivered its judgment in the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>121.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>133.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By a majority, it declared the application admissible and held by six votes to one that there had been a violation of Article 4 of the Convention in its procedural limp.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>133.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>145.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 19 October 2018, the government requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>145.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>151.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on 3 December 2018.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>151.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>172.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 6 February 2019, the president of the Grand Chamber granted leave to the Council of Europe Group of Experts on Action Against Trafficking in Human Beings, GRETA, to submit written comments in the proceedings as a third party by virtue of Rule 44, paragraph 3 of the rules of court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>172.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>187.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 4 March 2019, the president also granted leave to submit written comments in the proceedings as third parties to, first, Clinique Doctorale de Trois Internationales des Trois de l'Homme de la Faculté de Trois d'Aix-en-Provence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>187.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>195.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the research center, l'Altro Dirito, from the Department of Theory and History of Law of Florence University.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>195.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>202.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third, to the group of researchers, Mrs. Bénédicte Bourgeois from the Michigan University,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>202.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>206.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Marie-Xavier Cato from the University of Paris 1</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>206.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>210.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pontillon-Sorbonne, and Mr. Michel Herpelding</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>210.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>213.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from the Max Planck Institute in Luxembourg.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>213.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>220.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Ms. Štefica Stažnik, assisted by Mrs. Nikolina  Katić</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>220.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>224.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. Krešimir Nikolić, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>224.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>228.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mrs. Sanja Bezbradica Jelavić</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>230.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>235.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>235.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>258.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome the following groups of judges who are on a study visit to the court, a delegation of judges and prosecutors from the European Judicial Training Network, a delegation of Russian judges, a delegation of Portuguese judges from the High Court of Auditors, and a delegation from the National School of Judges of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>258.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>268.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>268.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>271.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Jelavić for the applicant will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>271.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>275.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mrs. Stažnik for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>275.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>290.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting into Russian has been authorized for the benefit of a group of judges from Russia attending this hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>290.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>300.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>300.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>300.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mrs. Jelavić.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>310.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>328.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable President and honorable judges, members of the Grand Chamber, the position of this applicant, but also of other victims of human trafficking for the purposes of sexual exploitation after they have been identified as victims and during the court proceedings are very specific.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>328.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>341.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Victims do not enjoy effective protection from various forms in which such gender-based violence appears due to patriarchal patterns deeply rooted in the existing legal framework and particularly in practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>341.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>353.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I do not dispute the fact that in the past period, the national legal framework has been undergoing some positive changes aimed at protection of victims' rights in general, including the victims of human trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>353.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>371.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, application of law, especially of standards arising from international treaties, requires further work since the respondent state, as we speak, and I quote, does not meet even the minimum standards of human rights protection required by those treaties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>371.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>405.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Working as an attorney at law representing victims and also as expert associate of non-governmental organization that focus their work on improvement of legal frameworks and practices, one can notice a significant difference between, on one hand, the principles of constitution of the respondent state and the conventions they are subject to this procedure, and on the other hand, the practices of professional which arise from this deeply rooted conscience that doesn't acknowledge the gender-based violence in its true sense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>405.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>418.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is why in the criminal proceeding conducted in the applicant case, sexual exploitation wasn't recognized as a form of human trafficking despite all these grave consequences for this victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>418.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>433.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a victim of human trafficking for purpose of sexual exploitation, the applicant was subjected to abuse of her position of vulnerability, details of which are visible in the file of the case, and is strongly marked by experienced traumas and her former way of life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>433.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>443.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to humiliation, infirmality, and interpersonal violence she experienced, the applicant, as well as other victims, trust in people is gravely disrupt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>443.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>450.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She did not trust the system either, and that's why she did not file criminal charges earlier to protect herself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>450.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>456.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She reached because a new fear and threats to her sister and her family from TM.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>456.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>467.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was necessary to build a relationship of trust with this victim in order to provide her with the desired legal assistance during this proceeding in the national court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>467.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>480.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the duty of a victim legal representative, but also of the state authorities as a part of their positive obligation arising from Article 4 of convention, as well as other treaties regarding human trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>480.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>507.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once the state authorities receive information that triggers suspicion of human trafficking, which is in the applicant case, was the moment when she came to the police station, the conduct of professional in the police, the state attorney office, and at the courts towards this victim was shaped by conscious or unconscious stereotypes and prejudice that are related to sexual exploitation and exploitation of prostitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>507.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>522.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This prejudice often leads to absence of any criminal proceedings, less degree incrimination, or absence of effective investigation, which leads to suspension of investigation or acquittals, like in applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>522.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>531.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides prejudice associated with prostitution, the victim trauma is revealed in a way that it becomes another victim disadvantage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>531.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>556.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When reading the descending opinion, the new positions of the government, and allegations made by third parties, the applicant considered it is essential to debate on three important points of this hearing, first being the applicability of Article 4, second being the applicant activity in the national proceedings, and third being the impact of trauma on the testimony of this applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>556.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>570.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the applicability of Article 4 to the present case, the applicant states that responded state explicitly acknowledge that the applicant had, in her statement of fact, evoke a violation of Article 4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>570.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>584.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, in paragraph 60 of the same observation from 2015, the government pointed out that domestic authorities had granted the applicant the status of victim of human trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>584.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>593.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government explicitly stated that grant of this status indeed mean an acknowledgment that there has been a violation of Article 4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>593.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>603.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the government, the application was inadmissible precisely because the respondent state had already acknowledged the violation of applicant's right under Article 4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>603.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>617.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was the further course of this proceeding, precisely the descending opinion of Honorable Judge Costello, that led to a new and essentially altered position of the government in this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>617.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>621.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This calls for a need to clearly state the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>621.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>632.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant first invoked a violation of Article 4 when she filed a criminal report in the police station, precisely when she was describing the events which triggered the police to suspect of human trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>632.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>637.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to this suspicion, the police identify the applicant as a victim of human trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>637.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>648.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then, when the applicant was describing what she had gone through in the state attorney's office and later before the domestic court, she repeatedly described the violation of Article 4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>648.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>657.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant invoked a violation of Article 4 for the fourth time in her application to this court, precisely in point 2 of her statement of facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>657.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>668.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court followed by giving this a legal qualification in accordance with the principles of its earlier decisions, such as Radomirja versus Croatia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>668.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>677.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The criminal proceedings which initially arise from the suspicion of human trafficking was nevertheless conduct for the pandering, as well as ended with acquittal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>677.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>693.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is all due to the fact that neither the prosecution authorities nor the judicial authorities had fulfilled their positive obligation or which the applicant spoke in a legal argumentation of her application, and particularly in her observations from 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>693.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>700.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its new observation to the grand chamber questions, the government significantly changed the argumentation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>700.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>711.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They redrew its acknowledgment from previous submissions to the court regarding the effect that identifying a person of a victim of human trafficking has.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>711.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>728.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the government claims that identifying a person as a victim of human trafficking is a purely administrative character merely served purposes of providing medical, psychological, and other aid, so does not automatically redraw application of Article 4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>728.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>743.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant holds that by such claim, the government de facto acknowledged that the relevant criminal law mechanism were defective to the point of constituting a violation of respondent state positive obligation under Article 4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>743.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>753.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Precisely for this and similar reasons in many other cases, the High Commission of Human Rights expressed concern about the problem of human trafficking in the respondent state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>753.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>760.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>State Department and the CEDAW committee expressed their concerns and made recommendation, I quoted, it is in the file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>760.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>774.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The new report, a relevant part of the latest 2018 country reports of human rights practices, stated that, and I quote, the government of Croatia does not fully meet the minimum standards for the elimination of trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>774.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>791.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Recommendation for 2018 are the same, forcefully investigate, prosecute, and convict traffickers, and impose strong sentences, train judges to understand the issue of secondary trauma on the sex trafficking testimony, among other things.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>791.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>800.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issues and questions that arise from this case and similar ones lead to concerns and current recommendations that were given to the respondent state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>800.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>814.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that the government has still not fulfilled the special obligations arising from the convention and the given recommendation, even six years after this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>814.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>834.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In accordance with recommendation and national laws, the applicant claims to the grand chamber that the procedure for identifying the victim of trafficking in human beings does not have and must not only have an administrative character for the purpose of assisting victim of violence and its integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>834.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>844.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This procedure must also imply the duty of state authorities to be effective and to carefully carry out an investigation by the state attorney office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>844.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>854.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, it must apply the duty that the whole subject is carefully evaluated by the court, which in the particular case did not happen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>854.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>867.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not disputed that Ministry of Eternal Affairs identified the victim of human trafficking immediately after suspicion of a potential trafficking case, as it is prescribed by the relevant protocol.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>867.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>881.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This suspicion of a particular criminal offense, therefore, direct whole system to one, helping the victim, as government claims, but also an efficient and effective investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>881.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>893.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Criminal Procedure Act stipulates that if there are grounds for suspicion that a criminal offense prosecuted ex officio is committed, the police is obliged to take necessary measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>893.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>902.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on the basis of collected information, the police compile the criminal report and submit it to the state attorney's office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>902.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>912.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the police and state attorney office received from the applicant all the information that was useful for successful conduct of a criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>912.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>920.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But from the total of five possible witnesses mentioned in this court decision, they decide to hear only one witness during the criminal proceeding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>920.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>929.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Other objects were fined, an arsenal of weapons in a context of coercion, cell phones and condoms in a context of exploitation of prostitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>929.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>945.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But they have not been used in a criminal proceeding with a goal to successfully conduct the proceeding through the conviction or through further, heavier incrimination, trafficking in human beings, illegal possession of weapons, or others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>945.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>953.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the investigation was supposed to be more effective in order that more evidence collected could lead to a conviction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>953.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>961.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, irrespective of above, the file of this case gave the national court enough elements to make the conviction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>961.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>968.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the court did not recognize and understand the impact of trauma and secondary trauma to this victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>968.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>974.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the national court considered the applicant testimony to be inconsistent with the testimony of the only witness heard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>974.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>981.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this inconsistency can be found only in irrelevant details.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>981.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>987.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The result of all this was a quitting judgment with all the consequences it brings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>987.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>991.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for this reason, we stand today in front of the grand chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>991.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1007.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, when the court consider an issue such as violation of Article IV, the court does not take over the role of a four-instance court or the state attorney office as stated by the government in its observation to the grand chamber this year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1007.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1026.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By examining this case like any other case before the court, the court compares the actual evidentiary proceeding with the expected evidentiary proceeding in order to draw a conclusion as whether the investigation and the criminal proceedings as a whole were effective or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1026.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1058.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So when the applicant states in her statements of facts that she was identified as a victim of trafficking in human beings and that proceedings were conducted with acquittal, and then in the legal arguments that the obligation of the state was to carry out an effective and efficient investigation, then it gave a sufficient element to this court that it considers the application in the scope of Article IV in accordance with the principles set forth in the judgment Radomila v. Croatia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1058.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1065.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the context of this case, it is important to point out that these two elements from Radomila v. Croatia principles,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1065.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1077.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the facts and legal arguments, intervene with each other since the facts to which it's objected must be considered in the light of the above legal arguments and vice versa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1077.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1088.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no talk of decision making beyond the scope of this case if, by applying the principle of jura novit curia, the court gives a new characterization to the facts objected to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1088.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1102.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this case, the court, by applicant meaning, with justification estimated that it was in the interest of the court and of the justice to determine the violation of Article IV.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1102.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1124.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding applicant's activity, considering this case under the pretext of separate opinion and objections of the government, a new issue emerged, the question of the applicant activity during the criminal proceedings, which even though the applicant was represented by an attorney at law, she didn't propose evidence itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1124.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1126.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant claims she was not passive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1126.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1136.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She has given statements three times and provided detailed information about the event and also identify all possible witnesses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1136.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1144.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the meantime, she tried to gather broken pieces of her life and restore feeling of self-esteem and trust in people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1144.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1150.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant asked for assistance of an attorney the day before the hearing in which she was to testify.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1150.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1152.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The evidence is in the file.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1152.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1161.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was her mother who called the counseling center of autonomous woman house Zagreb, where she was aided as a victim of violence herself in the past.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1161.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1170.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was then further connected with an attorney and another non-governmental organization, Center for Women Victims of War, ROSA.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1170.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1182.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The attorney was not provided by the respondent state as a free legal aid to the applicant, in this case, even the cases regarding fundamental values of democratic societies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1182.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1188.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nor did the government gave enough funds to finance NGO for their activities regarding trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1188.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1199.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, as to the new information collected from NGOs, the government don't finance ROSA or any other NGO regarding trafficking for the last four years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1199.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1206.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is the reason why the applicant asked for help from this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1206.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1214.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is evident from the case file that applicants spoke with the Red Cross 10 days before the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1214.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1227.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This only meant that this help and support, which was being provided by the system and which is being highlighted in this case, was actually missing in the context of criminal proceeding and positive obligation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1227.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1230.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was the applicant mother who find her an attorney.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1230.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1234.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Through the Red Cross, the applicant was getting financial aid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1234.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1252.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So despite all the conventions, strategic documents, and positive changes, despite 2012 European Union Victims Directive, the applicant was in effect left to her own capabilities and to the trusting relationship then she established with her attorney.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1252.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1258.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant asked for the assistance of the attorney because she was afraid to go to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1258.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1262.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She didn't want to go to court, to the hearing alone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1262.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1271.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was unable to testify in the presence of TM, hadn't been consulted before, nor provided adequately support through the system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1271.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1294.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be emphasized that the state attorney office is dominoes litis of a criminal proceeding in a respondent state, and that it is not reasonable to expect that the victim undertakes those actions that the police, the state attorney office, and the court are obliged to take by the law, regardless or not she have an attorney or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1294.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1303.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The attorney's activity is the activity of victim, and TM, by the facts from this case, was obsessed with the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1303.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1306.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the witness statement, she was afraid of him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1309.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1313.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the activity of the victim is her right, but not her duty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1313.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1330.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Especially, this should be kept in mind if the victim is highly traumatized person who has been subjected to intensive inhuman treatment, involving severe forms of physical and psychological violence and humiliation in the intensity that changes the chemistry of her brain.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1333.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1345.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From victim of such conduct, also the applicant, it is not reasonable to expect active participation in a criminal proceeding, as well as from any other victim who has experienced interpersonal violence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1345.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1353.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These victims tend to avoid anything that evokes memory of trauma, because these memories are painful, both emotionally and psychologically.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1353.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1367.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They often have enormous difficulty subsequently reconstructing the details of traumatic experience, and they demonstrate cognitive symptoms such as confusion and disorientation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1367.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1380.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One should appreciate the courage of the applicant who testify in details about everything she has been through to the complete strangers three times, first before in the police, then in the state attorney office.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1380.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1386.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then before the court, more than two hours each time, six hours in total.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1386.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1392.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The victim gave a precise and accurate referral of witnesses and description of the events.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1392.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1396.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These descriptions led to arrest and search the defendant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1396.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1408.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During this search, the police found objects that can be brought in connection with trafficking of human beings and forced prostitution, different phones, an arsenal of weapon, and a large amount of condoms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1408.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1423.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not the victim's duty to propose that police should conduct the search of these found phones, contact the persons in the directory and with whom the defendant has often come into contact, or try to determine the origin of seized weapon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1423.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1429.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such role of a victim in a pretrial proceeding is not possible under domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1429.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1436.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In a main hearing, it is not reasonable to expect the victim to take over the role of state attorney office and the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1436.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1453.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the applicant points out that the state authorities have failed to subject this case to the careful consideration so that deterring impact of the criminal justice system wouldn't be questioned, as well as its role in preventing human rights violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1453.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1463.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, since the state authorities hadn't fulfilled their positive obligation, the applicant considers this court's first instance judgment to be fully justified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1463.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1471.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She considered domestic legal mechanism effective to the point that constituting a violation of Article 4 of convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1471.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1476.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third being regarding vulnerability of applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1476.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1495.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This applicant and other victim of human trafficking for purposes of sexual exploitation are not so-called ideal victims, stable persons with a role model behavior in a previous life, who can clearly articulate their emotions, summarize the events, and reproduce all of that without any change over time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1495.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1502.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When testifying, the applicant, as well as other victims of sexual exploitation and violence, often fail to be concise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1502.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1514.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They stutter, seem confused, avoid issue, and sometimes in the cases of severe trauma, their emotional expression isn't compatible for what are they saying.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1514.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1518.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And sometimes they are incapable to testify.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1518.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1524.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Numerous psychological and medical studies have been written about how brain process trauma.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1524.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1533.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The amygdala, the part of the brain that plays a key role in recognizing, conditioning, and expressing fear, can experience changes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1533.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1541.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court failed to recognize these changes, failed to recognize the impact of trauma on the victim testimony.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1541.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1559.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the time of sexual exploitation, the applicant was 20-year-old girl, twice her age, former special forces police officer who know her parents, her father for wartime, a manipulative, already convicted person with an arsenal of weapons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1559.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1561.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She met him in the courtroom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1561.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1572.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This courtroom, the defendant said, in this courtroom, the defendant sat behind the back of the victim at a distance of about one or two steps before he was brought out.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1572.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1581.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The victim was turned face towards to the court and could hear the sounds produced by the defendant without them being heard to other distant participant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1581.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1585.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or even some of them heard the sounds, they didn't mean anything to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1585.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1589.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant stated the above mentioned in the application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1589.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1609.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The coherence of her statement did not only depend on survived trauma and the position of powerlessness that was exploited, but also on the structure of her personality, conditioned by birth, education, social conditions of life, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1609.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1616.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court did not carefully consider all these important circumstances, nor in the appeal procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1616.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1623.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Fairly and carefully conducted court proceedings have importance not only in criminal justice sense.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1623.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1635.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They help in healing the consequences of survived trauma to the victims, because fairly and carefully executed procedures restore the victim's trust in the system and faith in humanity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1635.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1641.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The frustration of this victim caused by the acquittal of defendant was enormous.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1641.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1654.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be kept in mind that the reasoning of acquittal clearly shows that the justice system did not believe the victim without having awareness or knowledge of the impact of trauma on her testimony.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1654.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1667.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in conclusion, the applicant kindly asked the grand chamber that in the light of all the circumstances of this case, it's established a violation of Article 4, as this court already did.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1667.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1679.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant considered that this court has not gone beyond the scope of this case, because the fact statement and the legal arguments of the application, according to the adopted principles of the court, interfere with each other.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1679.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1686.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And according to the principle, jura novit curia, court gave a new characterization to the facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1686.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1702.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant considers that chamber judgment, according to which trafficking of human beings for the purpose of sexual exploitation, as well the exploitation of prostitution, come within the scope of Article 4, is strong and very important in its effects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1702.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1724.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Trafficking in human beings for the purpose of sexual exploitation and exploitation of prostitution endanger human dignity and fundamental freedoms that are incompatible with the values of the Convention and the civilization progress regarding human rights, in a particular, human rights of women, which are disproportionately affected with these violations of law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1724.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1730.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Raising awareness about the importance of women's human rights leads to full equality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1730.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1739.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Convention of Suspension of the Trafficking in Persons and the Exploitation of Prostitution of Others was adopted 70 years ago.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1739.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1753.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Numerous other conventions that aim at elimination of all forms of discrimination against women have normatively followed the set foundation, and the EU Charter incorporated them into their principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1753.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1764.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the purpose of comparison, I would point out that in the same period of time, the 70 years, science has undergone enormous progress in almost every discipline.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1764.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1775.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As science progress on a daily basis, we must allow the practice in the field of human rights protection to do the same and reach its full potential.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1775.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1794.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this sense, the court judgment in the case naturally leans on and further evolves the foundation established many years ago, which is the principle that human trafficking and exploitation of prostitution indeed treat human bodies as commodities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1794.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1803.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With the existing judgment, the court once again showed that convention is a living instrument which must be interpreted in the light of present day conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1803.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1805.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1805.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1805.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1807.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1809.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call on Mrs. Stažnik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1817.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1818.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1818.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1831.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable Madam Vice President, honorable judges of the court, dear colleagues, I would like to begin with this pleading with acknowledgment that the trafficking in persons is a serious crime and a grave violation of human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1831.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1838.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Every day, thousands of men, women, and children fall into the hands of traffickers in their own countries or abroad.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1838.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1842.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Republic of Croatia is seriously dedicated to combat this modern day slavery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1842.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1860.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It endorses the court's strong devotion to protect the rights of victims of this serious crime to the application of national laws and policies in the convention compliant manner while observing carefully the development of the court's case law, especially under Article IV of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1860.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1878.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent state agrees with the statement that today's world of constant and widespread migration and globalization, the court should take the clear stance on the trafficking in human beings and define the scope of this issue in its case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1878.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1894.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So far, the court case law has defined the positive obligations of the member states under the Article IV but has not defined the substance of trafficking in human beings or the material aspect of Article IV of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1894.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1910.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the respondent state deems that circumstances of this particular case before the court are not suitable for the application of Article IV of the convention, neither for widening of its scope, and that is for several particular reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1910.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1928.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, we should all bear in mind the scope of this particular case as it is defined in the present application to the court and by the single judge decision declaring part of it inadmissible before culminating into the respondent state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1928.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1939.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, each complaint to the court should consist of two crucial elements, factual allegations and legal arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1939.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1958.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is not only required to invoke a legal norm but also to indicate the factual basis of the complaint and the nature of the alleged violation which is connected to the name legal norm and to the right, the protection of which she is seeking before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1958.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1968.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In her application to the court, the applicant did not raise any factual or any practical or legal issue under Article IV of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1968.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1977.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, she barely made any complaint that is admissible under the convention in general and under the existing court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1977.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1985.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In her application, the applicant essentially complained about the outcome of the domestic criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1985.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1993.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She did not ask for the application of Article IV, nor did she request the widening of the court's case law in any respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1993.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2000.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She did not object to the way the competent authorities conducted the investigation in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2000.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2005.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She did not object to the level of protection she received as a victim on domestic level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2005.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2010.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She even did not object to the way the domestic criminal proceedings were conducted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2010.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2014.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She simply objected their outcome.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2014.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2023.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent state deems that there is no right under the convention which guarantees the conviction of a particular person in a criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2023.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2032.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such a claim doesn't trigger the application of any conventional rights, nor even the application of Article IV of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2032.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2040.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just like national courts, the court has the obligation to protect the rule of law and to secure the proper administration of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2040.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2047.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ruling the decisions outside the scope of the case would not be in accordance with this rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2047.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2055.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the grand chamber established case law, it is of fundamental importance to rule within the scope of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2055.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2075.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because if the court were to base its decision on facts not covered by the complaint, it would rule beyond its competence and exceed its jurisdiction by deciding matters which were not referred to it within the meaning of Article 32 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2075.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2085.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent state strongly advocates that questions which may attract application of Article IV of the question were not referred to by the applicant in her application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2085.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2092.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, they do not form the scope of the present case before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2092.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2104.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second reason why this case is not suitable for application of Article IV of the convention is that it lacks at least one of the crucial elements of trafficking in human beings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2104.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2115.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The definition of trafficking in human beings, which is agreed among the states on international level, makes an integral part of the Anti-Trafficking Convention and the Palermo Protocol.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2115.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2123.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the basis of the definition given therein, it is evident that trafficking in persons has three constituent elements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2123.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2130.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First one relates to the act, the recruitment, transportation, transfer, harboring, or receipt of persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2130.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2148.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second one relates to the means, threat, or use of force, coercion, abduction, fraud, deception, abuse of power or vulnerability, or giving payments or benefits to a person in control of the victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2148.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2152.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the third one that relates to the purpose, exploitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2152.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2156.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of these elements have to be cumulatively fulfilled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2156.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2164.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, there is no trafficking in human being if one of the crucial elements is missing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2164.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2175.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the national courts determined that the applicant was not coerced into prostitution, as there was not enough evidence to support this claim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2175.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2181.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was not proven beyond reasonable doubt that elements of coercion existed in the applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2181.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2186.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These conclusions of domestic courts were not arbitrary or unfounded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2186.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2197.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were based on the interpretation of all the evidence presented in the course of the criminal proceedings, including the evidence presented by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2197.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2202.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the applicant was never deprived of her documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2202.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2204.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was never deprived of her liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2204.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2209.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She had her personal mobile phone with her the whole time, and she was free to use it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2209.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2214.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And she did, indeed, use it to contact her friend on several occasions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2214.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2216.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was not left without money or income.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2216.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2223.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She clearly said in domestic proceedings that she equally split the amounts earned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2223.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2234.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent's claim deems that the lack of coercion and lack of exploitation element exclude the application of Article 4 of the Convention in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2234.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2248.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If this wouldn't be so, if the scope of Article 4 would be widened to the cases with no elements of coercion, it would bring confusion in the application of the Convention by the state parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2248.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2258.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the court would abandon and further itself from the international standards adopted on this issue, as well as its established case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2258.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2273.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its case law, particularly in the Ronstadt case, the court considered that trafficking in human beings by its very nature and aim of exploitation is based on the exercise of powers attaching to the right of ownership.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2273.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2281.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, it considered the element of coercion or force as being crucial ones for the application of Article 4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2281.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2286.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent states there is no reason for the court to depart from this conclusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2286.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2304.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, if Article 4 would widen to the cases where there was no force, intimidation, or duress found, there would be practically no difference between Article 4 and Article 3 and or Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2304.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2310.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would then, in fact, declare all forms of prostitution a criminal act identical to slavery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2310.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2315.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But was that the intention and aim of Article 4?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2315.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2331.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Would the application of Article 4 to the cases with no exploitation elements and no control of the victim be in the light and for the purpose of prohibition of slavery prescribed by this conventional right?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2331.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2336.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent state deems not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2336.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2358.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For that reasons, it is the respondent state opinion that the court should be very careful in such an expand of the scope of Article 4, having in mind the endorsed international standards and the fact that not all member states of Council of Europe have criminalized prostitution and that there is no international consensus on this matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2358.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2366.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, such a departure from the previously adopted standards could be problematic from the stance of the protection of the victims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2366.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2382.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The widening of the scope of Article 4 of the Convention to cases without all elements of trafficking in situation where all member states have not criminalized prostitution could create a gap in which victims could end up unprotected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2382.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2395.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The potential victims of violation of Article 4 would then have to prove prima facie that they have suffered a wrongful act which can be seen identical to slavery, servitude, or forced labor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2395.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2416.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the wide material scope of Article 4 with no clear definition of its scope could pose an excessive individual burden on victims since it would require special and detailed legal knowledge and understanding of the court's case law to present such a case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2416.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2434.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the national level, it would be left to the interpretation of the competent authorities whether a case with no elements of coercion and no exploitation can, in fact, nevertheless be considered to fall within the ambit of Article 4 and could left the victims unprotected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2434.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2452.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Respondent's Team deems that victims of wrongful acts connected to prostitution or which were exploited for prostitution but without elements of coercion or force enjoy sufficient level of protection under the existing case law within the Article 3 or 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2452.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2458.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In each of these cases under named articles, the material scope of these rights are clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2458.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2468.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In each of these cases under the named articles, the states have the positive obligation to conduct effective and thorough investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2468.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2476.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have the obligation to conduct the criminal proceedings and to convict the perpetrators if proven guilty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2476.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2487.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the states have the obligation to ensure the efficient legal framework for protection of victims and to carry out the needed preventive measures to protect the potential victims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2487.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2503.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable Judges of the Grand Chamber, in this respect, the Republic of Croatia makes continuous efforts to strengthen administrative and operational capacities aimed at enhancing the fight against trafficking in human beings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2503.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2517.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Respondent states and endorses the Chamber's finding that the Republic of Croatia created and implemented an efficient legal framework for the protection of the victims of trafficking in human beings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2517.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2527.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it can be seen from the case at hand, the applicant received every possible aid she required.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2527.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2531.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was immediately recognized as a victim of trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2531.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2542.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regardless of the outcome of the criminal investigation and the criminal proceedings, she was offered with legal, medical, and financial support to carry out the investigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2542.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2550.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was offered with legal, medical, and psychological aid along with food, clothes, and shelter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2550.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2555.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All that was in accordance with the recommendations made by Greta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2555.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2575.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I want to point out that when she used the Center for Women, War Crimes, ROSA, that this particular NGO organization was within the state-organized national system of cooperation in combating human trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2575.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2579.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the NGO was an extended hand of the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2582.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2602.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another point I want to make is that during the domestic proceedings, or even widely said, on the national level, the applicant had no objections to these issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2602.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2611.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The system of combating trafficking in the Republic of Croatia is based on the humanitarian and legal approach to the victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2611.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2616.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Newly identified victims through an organized program receive first forms of aid and protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2616.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2627.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It includes temporary accommodation, interception centers, legal, medical, and other forms of care and protection, safe accommodation, and return to their country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2627.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2643.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the process of identification, support, and protection of victims of human trafficking, representatives of the state administration bodies and civil society organizations are involved based on mutual partnership.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2643.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2653.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The responded state is constantly and further investing into the development of the legal and legislation framework for the protection of victims of trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2653.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2664.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So far, a total of 117 judges and prosecutors finished the specialized trainings provided by the Judicial Academy related to combating trafficking in human beings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2664.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2672.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Trainings are also provided for the border police officers and implemented within the border police training system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2672.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2681.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Continuous education on this topic added to achieving the goal of rising awareness of the border police on the issue of trafficking in human beings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2681.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2688.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the topic of trafficking is incorporated also in the basic police training.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2688.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2697.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A multidisciplinary national referral mechanism provided standard operating procedure for identifying and referring victims to services.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2697.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2711.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2002, a total of six national plans for combating trafficking in human beings were brought, all followed by the operational plans for each year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2711.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2722.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, a number of projects have been implemented in the legal system, having focused identification and the protection of victims of trafficking, all based on the greater recommendations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2722.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2740.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, a national protocol on identification, assistance, and protection of victims of human trafficking was brought in order to determine all the responsible parties and methods of procedures during identification and assistance to victims of human trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2740.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2751.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, I would like to point out that a number of prosecuted criminal acts of trafficking in human beings have increased over the last couple of years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2751.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2763.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Since 2014, a number of convictions have increased by 60%, and the number of identified victims of trafficking in human beings increased by 48%.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2763.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2771.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These numbers clearly show the strong dedication of the Republic of Croatia in combating trafficking in human beings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2771.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2776.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The honorable judges of the court, colleagues, I thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2779.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2781.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2781.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2786.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now invite the judges of the Grand Chamber wishing to do so to put their questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2786.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2791.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2791.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2791.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Kjølbro.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Jon Fridrik Kjølbro</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2795.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2796.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Madam President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2796.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2797.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have one question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2797.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2804.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is addressed to the government, and it concerns the applicability of Article 4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2804.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2819.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government is, in their observations, recognizing that human trafficking, as well as forced prostitution, fall under Article 4, and that in such cases, the state has positive and procedural obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2819.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2821.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is how I understand the government's position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2821.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2830.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But then, in the specific case, the government is arguing that Article 4, in the specific circumstance of this case, is not applicable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2830.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2844.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in doing so, the government is relying on the outcome of the criminal proceedings, saying that after the assessment of all the evidence, the domestic courts reached the conclusion that there was no exploitation, force, abuse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2844.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2846.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, Article 4 is not applicable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2846.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2848.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That seems to be the logic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2848.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2866.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But my question, then, to the government is, can the applicability of Article 4 depend upon the outcome of the domestic proceedings, or does it rather depend upon the allegations made by the applicant or the victim when he or she comes to domestic authorities?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2866.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2888.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, in the view of the government, if we were to rely upon the allegations or the complaint made by the applicant to the domestic authorities, would Article 4 then be applicable, or to put it in another word, would there at least be an arguable complaint that this would fall in within the ambit of Article 4?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2888.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2888.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2890.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2891.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Turković.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2893.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2900.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have mentioned that in Croatia, 170 judges have gone through education.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2901.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2911.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm interested whether you have the information whether the particular judges and particular prosecutors and policemen who were involved in this case went through education prior working on this case. Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2915.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2916.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Elósegui.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>María Elósegui</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2920.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2923.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2923.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2932.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I want to ask one small question to the applicant and later another to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2932.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2948.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the applicant, just to show or to demonstrate that there is a forced prostitution, because we know, as the government said, that prostitution itself is not prohibited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2948.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2951.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we are talking about forced prostitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2951.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2965.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then in her observations, the applicant, she said that she did not want to take proactive actions because of the fear she felt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2965.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2975.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is, could you please explain in which manner she has received these threats from TM?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2975.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2984.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also, if she could offer proofs of it or not of these threats?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2984.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2998.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to the government, only a very concrete question, why during the process the national authorities not call more to more witnesses?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2998.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3015.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or for instance, the applicant has shown that there were other groups like whip-ons or condoms in the possession of TM.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3015.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3021.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And why in the court, domestic courts, they don't use it as proof or evidences?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3021.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3023.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is my question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3023.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3023.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3026.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3027.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge O’Leary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3028.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3031.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3031.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3038.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In her application form, the applicant referred to the fact that she had been recognized as a victim of human trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3038.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3051.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And during the course of proceedings, significance was attached to this recognition by the applicant in the chamber judgment and today by the applicant's representative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3051.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3062.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to ask both parties to address this issue, address it from a factual point of view, explaining to us the procedure which took place in Croatia and from a legal point of view.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3062.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3064.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'll start with the legal aspect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3064.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3081.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In paragraph 115 of J and others against Austria, the court said that it does not consider that the elements of the offense of human trafficking had been fulfilled merely because the Austrian authorities treated the applicants as potential victims of human trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3081.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3091.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such special treatment did not presuppose official confirmation that the offense had been established and was independent of the authorities' duty to investigate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3091.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3098.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed potential victims need support even before the offense of human trafficking is formally established.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3098.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3102.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise this would run counter to the purpose of victim protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3102.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3108.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And of course, with a criminal trial pending, questions of presumption of innocence arise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3108.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3121.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I would like both parties to address the significance that can or cannot be attached to recognition by an administrative authority of the status of human trafficking in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3121.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3126.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The factual aspect of my question relates to the case itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3126.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3137.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as I understand, this victim status is recognized by the Minister of the Interior or by an operative team of the National Board for the Suppression of Human Trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3137.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3142.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As far as the information that I have available, this is a multidisciplinary body.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3142.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3150.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it has representatives of the State Attorney's Office and the police, if I'm not mistaken, but please clarify that if possible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3150.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3154.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on what basis does this body take its decision?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3154.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3155.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At whose initiative?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3155.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3162.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is this on the basis of information passed by the police, the investigating authority, to the specialized body, or is it not?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3162.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3166.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we need some clarification on this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3166.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3170.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And crucially in this case, I'd like you to address a temporal issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3170.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3174.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant brought her complaint in September.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3174.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3179.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>TM was questioned, the applicant was questioned, and the other key witness, MI, was questioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3179.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3184.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The indictment was laid on the 6th of November, 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3184.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3189.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the victim status was recognized only on the 21st of December.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3189.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3197.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So are we looking at a situation here that the investigating authorities acted too quickly?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3197.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3210.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because they investigated her allegations brought to them in the police station, and they laid down the indictment before she was recognized as having this status of a potential victim of human trafficking?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3210.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3216.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or what actually is the significance of this recognition in a case such as this and in this particular case?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3216.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3219.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I'd like both parties to answer these questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3223.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3234.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now withdraw for 20 minutes, following which the parties will be able to submit brief observations in reply to each other's submissions and reply to questions from the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3489.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3489.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3532.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3534.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3541.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3544.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3544.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3546.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mrs. Jelavić.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3551.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3554.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you for your questions for the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3554.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3572.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding the first question, I have to say that, to clarify, prostitution is forbidden in a respondent state and it is a misdemeanor act in the respondent state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3572.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3576.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the persons in prostitution can be punished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3576.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3609.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the study, which were done in 2004 until 2008 from the ungovernmental organizations, by studying the judgments of misdemeanor courts, county courts, and all courts in Zagreb, there was in a five-year study, there was 841 misdemeanor proceedings against women in prostitution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3609.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3613.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So 841 misdemeanor proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3613.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3639.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 97% of these proceedings, the defendants were women in prostitution and they are all convicted with convictions in basis of prostitution in 776 cases with unconditional jail imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3639.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3654.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the same time, there were only 44 misdemeanor proceedings against those who organized prostitution and in only 12 cases, the jail time was given on probation for these persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3654.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3674.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also, in the same time of five-year period, there was only 50 criminal proceedings for pandering and in 39 cases, probation jail sentence were adopted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3674.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3683.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that's to have a view on the situation regarding women in prostitution in Croatia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3683.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3690.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it is a misdemeanor act and most women are convicted of it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3690.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3708.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And regarding the threats that applicants receive, she received threats from TM that he will recruit her younger sister into the prostitution as some kind of retaliation to the applicant and to her mother.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3708.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3723.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are elements from the testimony of other witness in the court that that defendant was obsessed in a way with that family, particularly with the woman from this family.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3723.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3736.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's the reason why she reacted and asked for help because she was afraid for the rest of her family, for her mother and for her younger sister.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3736.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3745.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's the reason why she went to the police and report these criminal offenses towards her.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3745.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3752.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And she spoke about it in the police office and in the state attorney office and in the front of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3752.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3755.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I hope that I answered your question in full.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3755.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3765.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And regarding other questions, thank you very much, about what identifying a victim of human trafficking, the meaning of it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3765.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3773.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The victim is identified by the police when she reports a criminal offense and asks for help.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3773.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3780.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But sometimes there are situations that victims go to, for example, NGOs to ask for help.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3780.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3789.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then NGOs ask operational team to give that person the status of the victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3789.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3794.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It always includes obligation of the state to investigate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3794.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3803.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the team, but the team, sometimes have other questions for what is the purpose of identification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3803.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3808.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have one client when she asked NGOs for help.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3808.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3816.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was after that defendant was already convicted for pandering in the case of that lady.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3816.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3836.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But she asked to be identified because during this period of time when she was used as a victim of human trafficking, he was coerced to sign some contracts with banks for credit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3836.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3849.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the status was needed to start court proceedings in order to cancel these contracts in the front of the court because she signed those contracts under caution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3849.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3855.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that was after the criminal proceeding was already done and it was over with the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3855.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3879.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in every case when proceeding is still going on, the purpose of identifying a victim is to help her on the one hand, of course, which government in this situation did by contacts with the Red Cross in which applicant have some help through money.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3879.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3887.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But also the duty of the state to investigate ex officio the reported crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3887.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3890.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I hope that I answered your question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3890.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3911.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And sorry, this is a good point because this victim was identified three months later, which is obviously by applicant's opinion the reason why we can say that the mechanisms, criminal mechanisms are defective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3911.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3918.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that's the reason why we ask the court to consider this application under Article 4.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3918.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3918.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3918.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3918.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3920.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3921.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Ms. Stažnik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3925.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3933.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges of the court, I will answer the first and second question, and Ms. Studding will answer the others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3933.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3951.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So firstly, to answer Judge Kjellbro's question, the admissibility or applicability of Article 4 in government's view depends on the facts determined by the competent domestic authorities, especially domestic courts in criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3951.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3955.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, if we talk about the trafficking in human beings as a criminal act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3955.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3971.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, the victims can obtain the status of victims of trafficking in a separate administrative set of proceedings on their own request, such as the applicant requested and she obtained the status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3971.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3983.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The recognition of this status does not indicate nor influence the outcome of the criminal proceedings, nor does it, in the state's view, automatically trigger the application of Article 4 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3983.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3991.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It simply provides necessary aid to all potential but not yet established victims of trafficking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3991.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4011.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the second question of Judge Turkovic, we have to say now that at this moment we don't have information about the particular judge and particular prosecutor obtaining the named education, but we will provide it in written after this hearing, after checking out with the competent authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4011.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4011.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4021.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4047.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regard the question from Honorable Judge Elosegi, why during the process national authorities didn't collect more evidence, I would like to say that competent authorities collected all possible evidence, including the witness statements from the persons who had or could have had any direct knowledge of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4047.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4064.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Persons who did not have direct knowledge but had a sort of contact with the applicant were not heard because they could not significantly contribute to the evidence or the criminal proceedings in general or the particular criminal act in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4064.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4084.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any case, the respondent state notes that the applicant did not, in domestic proceedings nor in the proceedings before the chamber, complain about the lack of the investigation or criminal proceedings in respect of evidence collected, but had simply complained about the outcome of the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4084.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4086.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is as regards your question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4086.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4090.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then I would turn to the question of Honorable Judge O'Leary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4098.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4114.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the administrative authority that decides on the applicant's status as a victim of trafficking, regardless of the proceedings or even prior to the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4114.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4130.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the fact that the state gives the applicant the status of victim of trafficking in a separate administrative set of proceedings is of no relevance to the application of Article IV of the Convention, nor it is in any connection with the domestic criminal proceedings and its outcome.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4130.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4137.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a different procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4137.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4158.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The police, in this particular case, the police, after taking statements from the applicant, proposed to the Office for Human Rights, which is a body within the central body for the, also for combat against trafficking in Croatia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4158.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4175.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so the police contacted the office and they proposed to the office to consider giving the applicants the victim status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4175.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4198.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards to multidisciplinary body, what I would like to say, we were referring to the multidisciplinary measures that were given as assistance to the applicant, not the authority as such.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4198.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4227.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But what I want to say that there is no multidisciplinary body where we would have also a police in this body that would be in any way or prosecutor for that matter involved into a process of giving the victim, the potential victim of trafficking, prior to the criminal proceedings, give the status of a victim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4227.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4232.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope I answered your question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4232.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4240.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is an administrative proceedings completely without any connection to the criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4240.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4241.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4241.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4250.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, if you allow me, Honorable President, I would just like to make a couple of concluding remarks, if time allows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4250.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4263.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What I would like to say that, once again, applicant did not raise any issues regarding the effectiveness of investigation, nor the conduction of criminal proceedings in her case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4263.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4269.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That the applicant was recognized as a victim of trafficking in administrative proceedings by the administrative body.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4269.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4273.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That she was offered with food, shelter, and financial aid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4273.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4276.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was given psychological and legal aid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4276.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4281.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was not secondary victimized in the course of criminal proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4281.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4286.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When she gave her statement, the accused was escorted out of the courtroom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4286.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4290.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All the evidence proposed by the applicant in the criminal proceedings were admitted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4290.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4293.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was never deprived of her liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4293.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4296.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was the one who rented the named apartment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4296.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4299.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She was the one who paid the rent for the apartment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4299.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4303.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She even came back to pay the rent death to the landlord.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4303.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4307.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was never deprived of her documents or her personal belongings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4307.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4310.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She had a mobile phone of her own all the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4310.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4316.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was not determined, beyond reasonable doubt, that the applicant was ever forced to anything.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4316.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4324.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was also not proven beyond reasonable doubt that the applicant was ever in a situation compared to slavery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4324.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4328.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the applicant was never reduced to an object.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4328.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4334.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these circumstances, we see no room for application of Article 4 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4334.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4334.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4336.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4343.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing. I thank the parties for their submissions</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4343.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4348.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and answers to the court's questions. The court will now deliberate. The judgment will</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4348.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4354.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>be delivered later. The parties will be informed of the date of delivery. I declare the hearing</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4354.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4354.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
