<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>6141115_18042018</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>16.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>17.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>53.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>55.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>67.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>74.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Z.A. and others versus Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>74.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>102.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The four applications were lodged with the court on 12 December 2015 and 14 January 2016 under Article 34 of the Convention by four applicants, Mr. Z.A., an Iraqi national, Mr. MB, who holds a passport issued by the Palestinian Authority, Mr. AM, a Somalian national, and Mr. Hassan Yazian, a Syrian national.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>102.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>112.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were allocated to the third section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>112.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>120.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were communicated to the government on 16 December 2015 and 15 January 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>121.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>131.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 28 March 2017, a chamber of the third section delivered its judgment in the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>131.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>149.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 27 June 2017, the government requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention, and the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on 18 September 2017.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>149.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>166.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The respondent government are represented by their agent, Mr.Mikhail Galperin, representative of the Russian Federation at the European Court of Human Rights, assisted by Mrs. Yana Borisova and Mrs. Olga Ocheretyanaya, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>166.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>173.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mrs. Eleonora Davidyan, counsel, assisted by Mrs. Daria Trenina and Mrs. Kirill Zharinov, counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>176.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>180.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives of the parties in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>180.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>187.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome the group of Swedish judges who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>187.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>196.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>196.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>207.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Trenina for the applicants will speak first, followed by Mrs. Zharinov and Mrs. Davidyan, and then Mr. Galperin for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>207.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>208.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mrs. Trenina.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>208.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>208.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP3</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>211.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>215.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President, distinguished members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>215.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>230.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case involves four applicants, an Iraqi, a Syrian, a Somali, and a Palestinian, claiming that they had been unlawfully detained in the transit zone of Moscow Sheremetyevo Airport and that the conditions of their detention constituted an affront to human dignity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>230.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>235.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, within the time provided, I will address the nature of the applicants' confinement</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>235.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>240.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and show that they did not choose to stay in the airport and were not free to leave it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>240.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>246.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Next, Mr. Zhirinov will discuss the specific regulations applicable to the applicant's situation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>246.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>250.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the procedure that have been followed by the Russian authorities according to law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>250.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>254.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, Ms. Davydenko will dispute the government's arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>254.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>261.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I will first describe the reasons why the applicants found themselves in the transit zone,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>261.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>265.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>why they requested asylum and what followed their requests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>265.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>271.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that none of the applicants chose Moscow as their destination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>271.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>283.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants requested asylum from the Russian authorities as they found themselves confined in the transit zone in appalling conditions with no access to basic facilities, medical and legal aid, or even postal offices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>283.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>293.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All four of them faced substantial difficulties in getting access to asylum proceedings due to absence of offices of the migration authorities in the airport.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>293.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>301.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The law provides that the asylum requested at the border is to be lodged through a border guard service that shall transmit it to a migration authority.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>301.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>313.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, there is no information about the procedure in the airport, and the service officers refuse to speak foreign languages, provide information, or even accept asylum requests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>313.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>319.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants also faced significant delays in examination of their requests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>319.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>323.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, they were deprived of the identity documents of asylum seekers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>323.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>331.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The examination certificates with which the law links certain rights, such as the right to temporary accommodation, as will be addressed by my colleague.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>331.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>340.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What's worse, the applicants' passports were seized by the border guard service for the duration of their stay in the transit zone without any formal procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>340.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>346.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Though the government denies it, this fact is confirmed by the documents they provided to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>346.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>351.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus the decisions concerning Mr. Yassin and his interview report with the migration officer</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>351.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>357.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>expressly state that his passport was kept by the border guard service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>357.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>362.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the case of each applicant, I would like to start with Mr. Zia and Mr. Eyam, transit</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>362.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>367.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>passengers deported to Moscow from their final destinations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>367.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>374.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Zia fled Iraq for Turkey in June 2014 due to coercion from ISIS to cooperate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>374.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>382.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He immediately registered himself with the UNHCR and applied to the local authorities for refuge, but obtained no response.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>382.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>394.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His registration with the UNHCR helped the applicant to avoid removal to Iraq for a year, but for absence of a durable solution, he was forced to leave.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>394.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>399.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant was able to gain a short-term Chinese visa, so he left for Beijing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>399.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>406.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While in China, the applicant could not enjoy international protection from the country's authorities as suggested by the Russian government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>406.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>415.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although China is a party to the Refugee Convention and Protocol there too, there are no regulations governing the granting of asylum in the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>415.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>427.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As his Chinese visa expired, the applicant was forced to leave again and took a flight back to Turkey with a stopover in Moscow, for Turkey was the only place he could possibly return to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>427.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>433.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the time, the Iraqi nationals traveling by air were able to obtain Turkish visas at the border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>433.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>436.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the applicant was not issued a Turkish visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>436.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>442.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was sent back to the airport of transit and requested international protection from the Russian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>442.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>452.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As he was a removed alien with no grounds to seek entry to Russia, his passport was collected by an air company and then seized by the Border Guard Service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>452.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>461.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It took the migration authorities almost two months to interview the applicant, whereby the asylum proceedings were officially launched.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>461.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>469.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the interview, he was in fact in a vacuum, not entitled to rights of asylum seeker, not protected from reformers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>469.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>474.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He however was deprived of those rights thereafter as well, as my colleague will show.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>474.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>488.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the interview, the applicant stated that in Iraq he would run the risk of twofold persecution, first by ISIS because he refused to join them, and second by Iraqi government forces because he was a Sunni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>488.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>491.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant's fears were reflected in the decisions of the migration authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>491.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>501.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, they addressed them in a summary fashion, confused Iraq with Afghanistan, and concluded that he did not provide convincing evidence of persecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>501.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>505.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It took five months to adopt those decisions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>505.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>508.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant remained in the transit zone for almost eight months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>508.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>517.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In February 2016, the UNHCR recognized him as in need of international protection, and in March 2016, resettled him to Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>517.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>520.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Iraq had agreed to accept him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>520.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>527.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant left Sheremetyevo airport before the Russian court examined and rejected his complaint concerning refuge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>527.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>533.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Ayem, a Somali journalist in possession of a Yemeni passport, fled Somalia in 2012</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>533.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>542.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>for Yemen due to the threats from the Al-Shaab militant group to force him to broadcast terrorist acts and extrajudicial executions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>542.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>551.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then in March 2015, due to escalated hostilities in Yemen and a personal conflict, the applicant fled once again, now to Cuba.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>551.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>554.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Heading to Havana, he took a flight with a stopover in Moscow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>554.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>564.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A month later, in the beginning of April, he was deported back to Moscow from Cuba, whose authorities had denied him access to asylum procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>564.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>570.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His passport was also collected by the air company and then seized by the Russian border guard service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>570.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>573.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant requested asylum within 24 hours after his deportation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>573.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>582.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it took the authorities almost three months to adopt a procedural decision on admissibility of the request only.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>582.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>588.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant remained in the transit zone for almost two years, waiting for his request for asylum to be examined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>588.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>595.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the duration of his stay, the applicant could not fly to Yemen due to air blockade of the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>595.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>599.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He could not return safely to his homeland either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>599.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>606.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government noted that during the interview with the migration officer, the applicant agreed to return to Somalia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>606.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>612.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, the applicant's handwriting says, I agree if it is safe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>612.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>631.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant did return to Mogadishu in September 2017, after the final rejection of his claims, that is in five years after his escape in 2012, having abandoned the journalist profession, having spent three years in Yemen and almost two years in Sheremetyevo Airport.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>631.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>636.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unlike the two applicants above, Mr. Ambi and Mr. Yassin had stayed in Russia before</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>636.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>637.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the events at issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>637.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>641.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They actually attempted to leave the country but could not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>641.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>646.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just as to others, they were returned to Sheremetyevo Airport against their will.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>646.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>651.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Yassin, a Syrian national from Aleppo, had been visiting Russia for business purposes</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>651.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>653.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>since 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>653.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>658.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the end of 2012, the applicant was no longer able to stay in Syria due to hostilities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>658.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>662.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He left for Lebanon and applied for asylum there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>662.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>669.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having received no response in 2013, he obtained his last Russian visa and traveled to Moscow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>669.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>679.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2014, the applicant requested international protection from the Russian authorities, referring to the civil war in Syria, but his request was denied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>679.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>686.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In mid-August 2015, the applicant's removal from Russia was ordered, and he took a flight to Antalya, Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>686.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>695.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Due to this expulsion order, his entry to Russia was banned, and the border guard service resized his passport as he crossed the border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>695.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>707.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the border guard service did not return his passport even when he was about to board but handed it over to the aircraft crew, the Turkish authorities denied the applicant's entry to the country and sent him back to Moscow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>707.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>715.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Upon the applicant's arrival, the Russian authorities returned him to Antalya, but then again he was removed to Moscow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>715.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>724.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus though he traveled to Russia on many occasions and requested asylum there before the events at issue, for the mentioned two times, Mr. Yassin did not choose to go to</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>724.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>726.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moscow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>726.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>732.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In mid-September 2015, the applicant applied for refugee status in Russia from the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>732.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>741.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As nobody had come to interview him, he lodged a new request on 5 October, but only on 3 November was the applicant interviewed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>741.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>748.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He argued that he was unable to return to Syria due to the ongoing armed conflict in the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>748.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>765.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His request was examined as a request for temporary asylum, not as a request for refugee status, after the applicant signed a new paper in Russian, offered to him with no interpretation or explanation of the legal consequences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>765.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>773.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This deprived the applicant of the protection from reforming, as the law expressly provided only to refugee status seekers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>773.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>784.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having received a notification that he had been denied temporary asylum, the applicant submitted a new request for refugee status in the end of December 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>784.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>789.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It appears that this request was not even transmitted to the migration authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>789.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>801.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant attempted to resubmit it, but the Russian border guard service officers refused to accept the paper in English until it was translated to Russian by his lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>801.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>804.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it was not examined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>804.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>813.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While the temporary asylum proceedings lasted for eight months, including the judicial stage, and ended long after the applicant had left the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>813.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>822.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2016, he was recognized as in need of international protection, and in May 2016, resettled to Sweden by UNHCR.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>822.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>827.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Ambi, a Palestinian, left the Gaza Strip in 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>827.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>834.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He had obtained a Russian visa valid until February 2014, and traveled to Irkutsk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>834.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>842.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant claims to have attempted to apply for asylum to the Irkutsk Region Migration Authority, but was denied access to the procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>842.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>856.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows that because of the hostilities, resulted in the constant closures of the Rafah crossing point, the only available route to the Gaza Strip, the applicant was unable to return home after the expiration of his visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>856.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>864.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In August 2015, the applicant's expulsion from Russia was ordered, and in pursuance of that ruling, the applicant took a flight to Cairo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>864.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>869.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian border guard service seized his passport as he crossed the border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>869.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>878.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the said crossing point was again closed by the Egyptian authorities, and they sent the applicant back to Moscow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>878.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>887.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the beginning of September, having stayed for three weeks in the transit zone, with no prospects of getting out of there, the applicant applied to Russian authorities for refuge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>887.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>892.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, he was interviewed only on 14 November 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>892.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>909.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His request and further appeal to the federal level migration body were dismissed as ill-founded, though the Federal Migration Authority characterized the situation in the Gaza Strip as extremely unstable, with military operations resulting in mass civilian casualties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>909.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>913.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I will now discuss the alleged by the government possibility of the applicants</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>913.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>916.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to freely leave the airport to any destination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>916.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>925.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While in the transit zone, all four applicants were in a situation of asylum seekers whose requests had not yet been considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>925.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>936.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All three of them did not have the option of entering the state other than that of their destination of their nationalities where their lives were in danger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>936.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>939.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Ambi did not have even this option.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>939.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>943.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, they recalled that their passports were taken from them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>943.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>962.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a common practice, long evidenced by the Russian UNHCR, that passports of deported persons or aliens whose entry is not permitted are collected by the security department of an airline and then seized by the Russian Borograd Service for the duration of the person's stay in the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>962.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>969.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian UNHCR confirmed this information in their letter we provided to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>969.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>974.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also the interview report of Mr. Ambi provided by the government says that at the time of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>974.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>980.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the interview, the applicants passed the passport at the security department of an air company.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>980.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>988.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As concerns Mr. Ambi, who returned to Somalia, not until the UNHCR obtained agreement of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>988.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1000.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkish airlines to carry him and provided him with a ticket did the officers of the Borograd Service agree to transmit his passport, but then again only to the aircraft crew.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1000.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1003.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The same happened in cases of all other applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1003.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1009.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, as such, practically the applicants could not travel to any country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1009.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1015.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Actually none of them held other nationality or right of residency in a safe third country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1015.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1023.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is clear that there were no safe and accessible countries that could have accepted the applicants without the resettlement procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1023.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1032.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the applicants took intensive efforts with the help of UNHCR to identify countries they could leave for.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1032.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1047.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However these efforts proved fruitless, not only because even visa-free countries demand additional requirements to allow entry, but also because air companies refused to take the applicants on board due to their situations and the countries of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1047.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1054.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, the applicants claim that they did not choose to stay in the transit zone of Shurmet airport.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1056.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1059.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mrs. Trenina. Now I call Mr. Zharinov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1063.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1066.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1066.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1081.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now discuss the legal regulation governing the stay of asylum seekers in airport transit zones in Russia, the procedures for applying for asylum at the transit zones and at the border, and for consideration such applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1081.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1090.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, I would like to say that the Russian law does not contain any provisions governing the stay of asylum seekers in airport transit zones.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1090.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1097.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither does the law provide any specific procedure for applying for asylum in such zones.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1097.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1106.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the Refugees Act does provide some general rules for applying for asylum at the border control, regardless of the type of the border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1106.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1114.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, an alien may submit an application to the border guard service as he crosses the Russian border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1114.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1126.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When an asylum seeker is forced to illegally cross the border, fleeing from persecution, he must submit an application to the authorities within 24 hours after crossing the border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1126.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1143.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the government's claim that the applicants in the present case violated the procedures and exceeded the 24-hour time limit for applying for refuge is irrelevant, as this time limit applies only to those who have already crossed the border illegally.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1143.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1155.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, I would like to stress that the law does not provide detailed rules for regulating the procedure of lodging an application for refuge with the border guard service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1155.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1162.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In practice, the border guard service officers enjoy significant discretion whether to accept an application or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1162.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1167.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And their arbitrary powers are not subject to any control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1167.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1175.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For instance, the officers refuse to accept applications written in foreign languages, which happened in the case of Mr. Yassin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1175.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1186.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even if the officers do accept certain applications, they often refuse to register them, which is necessary to confirm that the applications have been lodged.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1186.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1197.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding Sheremetyevo Airport, the situation is made even worse by the fact that the border guard service registry office is located outside the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1197.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1207.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the asylum seekers cannot file any complaints through the registry, nor can they send a complaint by mail, as there is no post office either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1207.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1216.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, asylum seekers lack any guarantees about mere acceptance of their applications in transit zones.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1216.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1225.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the border guard service finally accepts an application, they must transmit it to a migration authority within three working days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1225.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1234.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The migration authority then shall conduct its preliminary examination that includes interviewing the applicant within five days.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1234.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1239.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, this rule was grossly violated by the authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1239.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1246.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It took 45 days to interview Mr. Yassin, 50 days for Mr. Zia,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1246.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1252.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>62 days for Mr. MB, and 82 days for Mr. AM.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1252.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1261.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Upon preliminary examination, the migration authority shall decide whether to consider the application on the merits or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1261.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1268.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it decides to consider it on the merits, the asylum seeker shall be provided with an examination certificate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1268.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1274.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under the Refugees Act, any asylum seeker granted such certificate has a number of social rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1274.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1282.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, he is entitled to be allocated to a temporary accommodation center with food and medical assistance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1282.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1287.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are no exceptions to this rule for asylum seekers in transit zones.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1287.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1293.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And indeed, there have been examples when such asylum seekers were allocated to accommodation centers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1293.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1304.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, in 2015, a family of Syrian refugees who did not have any visas submitted applications for refuge in the transit zone of Sheremetyevo Airport.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1304.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1311.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they were accommodated at the special center Serebreniki in Tver region.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1311.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1317.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, in the present case, the applicants were not provided with examination certificates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1317.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1334.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If such certificates were indeed issued in their names, as claimed by the government, it is likely that they were retained by the migration authority, for it is a well-established practice to issue but not deliver certificates to asylum seekers in detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1334.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1340.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are just kept at the Migration Service Office together with the case files.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1340.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1347.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Throughout the asylum proceedings, the applicants requested the migration authorities to issue and deliver the certificates to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1347.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1350.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, such requests were completely ignored.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1350.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1354.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And further complaints were completely ignored as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1354.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1360.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither did the migration authority object to such arguments before the national courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1360.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1373.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And no copies of the certificates or receipts signed by the applicants were provided by the government to the court, although those certificates are normally delivered against receipts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1373.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1378.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moving further, I would like to cover the maximum time limits for the asylum proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1378.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1388.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The administrative stage of the proceedings, including consideration of the appeal by the Federal Migration Authority, shall not exceed about five months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1388.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1392.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An asylum seeker may further challenge the denial before a district court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1392.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1395.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That shall consider the case within one month.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1395.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1400.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the appellate court must examine the appeal within two months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1400.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1407.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the cases of all four applicants, the maximum time limits for the judicial stage were not complied with.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1407.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1411.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards Mr. AM, who was still confined in the transit zone,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1411.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1424.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>expecting the final decision on his refugee status, it took the district court more than eight months and the appellate court more than four months to consider his case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1424.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1433.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is also important to underline that neither the Federal Migration Authority nor a court is entitled to grant refugee status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1433.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1448.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the refusal of the local migration authority has been quashed, it is only required to re-examine the case, which may last for a few more months and result in another refusal on some new grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1448.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1453.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To sum up, the Russian law does not ensure enough speediness of the asylum procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1453.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1467.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in the present case, the authorities fail to comply even with the existing standards, let alone their failure to consider the applicants' requests more speedily, taking into account the circumstances of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1467.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1467.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1468.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1471.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Zharinov.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1471.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1473.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now I call Mrs. Davidyan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1473.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1473.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please fill the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1475.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1476.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1476.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1479.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable judges, it</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1479.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1495.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>is well-established case law of the court that confinement of aliens in an international zone of an airport is acceptable only if it is accompanied by safeguards for the persons concerned and is not prolonged excessively.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1495.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1500.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, a mere restriction on liberty turns into deprivation of liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1500.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1514.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not disputed that the applicants stayed in the transit zone for extremely long periods of time in appalling conditions, and their confinement was not regulated in accordance with the Article V guarantees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1514.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1521.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the main issue to be assessed is whether the applicants consented to the deprivation of liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1521.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1535.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe that the facts of the case clearly show that the applicants did not choose to stay in the airport transit zone and had no opportunity to leave it without risking their lives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1535.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1542.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, we would like to address the main points of the government's arguments presented in their submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1542.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1552.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will start by noting once again that there is no such legal concept as genuine or fake asylum seeker for the purpose of the Refugee Convention or domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1552.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1556.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Individuals either seek asylum or they don't.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1556.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1557.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants did.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1557.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1559.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1559.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1564.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None of them were aiming to enter Russia, especially in violation of migration rules.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1564.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1568.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>None of them chose Russia over any other destination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1568.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1578.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They found themselves in Sheremetyevo Airport against their will, not being able to return to their home countries or take a flight to any other country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1578.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1582.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Three of them were fleeing from threats to their lives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1582.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1586.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fourth was unable to return home due to no access.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1586.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1601.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, applying to the Russian authorities for asylum was their last chance, not to enter Russia, but to prevent forced return and to get out of the limbo, legal and physical, of the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1601.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1607.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants believed that they were refugees and should have been granted asylum under the Russian law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1607.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1613.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, they did not complain that the refusal to grant them asylum violated their convention rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1613.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1623.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants did not claim that they had a right to asylum, did not demand any benefits of a refugee or any special care from the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1623.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1630.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The present application does not depend on whether the applicants should have been granted status as refugees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1630.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1646.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants only demanded respect for the rights that were provided by Russian law, the right to apply for asylum, and the rights and procedural guarantees of an asylum seeker, including the right not to be arbitrarily confined in inhuman conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1646.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1657.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government is persuading us that they did not have any obligations in respect of the applicants, as their applications for refuge were, quote, artificially created.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1657.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1666.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the authorities did accept the applications and considered them on the merits, thus establishing the applicant's status as asylum seekers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1666.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1677.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The authorities did not refer to any provision of domestic or international law which would have permitted to refuse to take a decision on the applicant's refugee claims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1677.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1687.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Russian government, and following them the Hungarian government, were quick to accuse the applicants of violating procedural rules when applying for asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1687.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1690.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, as my colleague explained, none of the rules were violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1690.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1697.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the authorities did not raise this argument at any stage of examination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1697.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1713.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Despite the fact that there was no information in the airport on procedures for applying for asylum, and border guard officers refused to provide any help, the applicants managed to submit their applications for refuge as the law required them to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1713.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1719.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With the help of the UNHCR, the applicants strove to find countries they could live for.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1719.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1722.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Yassin even managed to purchase a ticket</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1722.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1727.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and try to travel to Lebanon in September 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1727.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1738.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the Lebanese authorities denied him entry, apparently because his passport seized by the Russian border guard service was handed not to him, but to an aircraft crew member.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1738.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1746.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All in all, we can confidently claim that the applicants did try to solve their problems themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1746.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1770.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government suggests that, I quote, the only way for a government to avoid the violation of Article 5 of the convention is to let any person, even that pretending to be an asylum seeker, to enter their territory and to allow them to move freely without any obstacles, as any placement of a person, whether to a hotel or a special center, would in fact constitute the deprivation of liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1770.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1773.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have to disagree with this argument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1773.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1777.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, not every deprivation of liberty violates Article 5.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1777.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1781.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only an unnecessary, unlawful, and arbitrary one does.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1781.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1795.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, a great way for a government to avoid the violation of Article 5 is to execute restriction or deprivation of liberty in compliance with clear and foreseeable law with access to timely judicial review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1795.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1810.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, a placement of the applicants to a hotel or a special center in a lawful manner would have not only not violated Article 5, but also would have met most of the applicants' needs pending the consideration of their applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1810.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1820.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lastly, letting an asylum seeker enter the territory of the country is not at all necessary to avoid violation of their rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1820.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1827.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the applicant's case, it was the most logical, simple, and the only available option provided by Russian law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1827.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1856.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But although it is still unclear what exactly was that certain reason the government mentioned not to let the applicants enter the country in this case, as we know of cases when asylum seekers were let in without any damage to state sovereignty, the provisions of Russian law that should have been applied to the applicants are actually beyond sufficient to observe the rights of asylum seekers at the border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1856.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1876.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Basic legal due process guarantees, simplest accommodation facilities in the transit zone, and speediness of review would have enabled the authorities to avoid the necessity of permitting asylum seekers to enter the country without violating international obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1876.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1883.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the arguments of the Hungarian government's intervention, we would like to note the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1883.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1887.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Governments adopt international regulations to control migration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1887.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1899.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And when these regulations fail to serve their purpose and the public perception of those failures is concerning to the politicians in power, it is hardly the refugees' fault.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1899.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1912.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither is it the fault of international organizations and institutions created by the governments in order to observe and control compliance with the fundamental human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1912.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1917.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, honorable judges, on the basis of the foregoing,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1917.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1933.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>we respectfully ask the court to uphold the chamber's findings and to declare that the applicants were deprived of their liberty in violation of Article 5 and the conditions of their confinement constituted an infringement of their Article 3 rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1933.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1933.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1934.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1938.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mrs. Davidyan. Now I call Mr. Galperin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1940.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1941.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1941.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1949.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants' counsel tried to get the court's sympathy by raising new points, which we never had before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1949.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1959.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, that there was a persecution in Iraq for one of the applicants for religion, and also that the Islamic State organization treasoned him, really.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1959.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1970.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, applicants never submitted that they were not able to leave Russia on the reason of the absence of the documents which were seized by the Russian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1970.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1973.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, Honorable Judges of the Court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1973.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1988.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>recent years, especially 2015, when really these events in question occurred, have been marked by a tremendous flow of refugees to Europe and resulted in what is now known as refugee crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1988.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1995.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It affected not just a handful of countries, but in the whole European continent and became a matter of growing concern.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1995.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2010.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Increasing number of refugees has made the receiving countries to adopt several quite burdensome measures aimed at resolution of this problem and resettlement of the refugees and their integration into the European society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2010.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2031.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, some experts report that the massive influx of refugees resulted in such devastating consequences as violent cultural crisis, increase of crime rate and harassment against women, growing number of terrorist attacks, creation of camps such as jungle in Kale, and so on other so-called no-go zones.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2031.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2038.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, significant amount of these people are not refugees, but migrants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2038.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2042.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pretending to be refugees, they leave their countries in search of a better life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2042.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2049.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, some states were first to adopt harsh measures to deal with the wave of asylum seeking migrants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2049.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2072.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such measures include, in particular, acceleration of the expulsion of migrants who do not qualify for asylum and making illegal border crossing a criminal offense, limiting aid for asylum seekers and refugees, reintroduction of border controls, and deployment of armed troops on the borders, limitation of family reunification, and other measures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2072.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2080.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is remarkable that sometimes these measures even run counter to the state's obligations under relevant agreements and regulations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2080.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2097.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This huge income of aliens also required from the countries to pay closer look to the personal circumstances of each person and to assess individually their applications when deciding whether a person is indeed a refugee under the UN Refugee Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2097.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2106.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, this case raises in clear terms the distinction between refugees and economic migrants, which the applicant sides try to reject.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2106.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2109.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That distinction is important to maintain.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2109.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2122.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unless states are allowed to distinguish between people genuinely trying to escape oppression and people seeking economic benefits, very serious consequences will result across the European continent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2122.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2127.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Relief for real refugees will be delayed and obstructed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2127.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2133.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Host populations will be antagonized, and politics will become more extreme.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2133.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2146.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The executive committee of the High Commissioner's Program recognized, and I quote, the importance of making the necessary distinction between the situation of refugees and asylum seekers and that of other aliens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2146.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2160.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the UN Refugee Convention and Correspondents Clarification, a refugee is someone who has been forced to flee his or her country because of persecution, war, or violence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2160.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2172.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A genuine refugee has a well-founded fear of persecution for reasons of race, religion, nationality, political opinion, or membership in a particular social group.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2172.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2178.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such people focus on escape from oppression rather than choice of destination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2178.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2186.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Accordingly, the EU Dublin regulation proclaims that refugees are supposed to apply for asylum in the first European Union country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2186.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2197.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They must also apply for asylum promptly, as would be expected of genuine refugees, and they must demonstrate a well-founded fear of persecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2197.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2204.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That requires them to show a good reason for fearing persecution if they are sent home.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2204.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2213.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>States are entitled to assess whether a potential migrant is a genuine refugee rather than someone who merely seeks better economic opportunities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2213.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2227.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, while the Refugee Convention obliges states to guarantee the protection of genuine refugees, issues relating to migrants and assessment of their status are national prerogatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2227.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2239.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I shall demonstrate, Russia has made a fair assessment, well within the margin of appreciation of the Russian authorities, that the applicants in the present case were not genuine refugees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2239.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2242.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I deal first with Mr. Z.A., concerning whom</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2242.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2250.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the key facts are the following, and they were also briefly structured by my opposite counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2250.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2251.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First is Mr. Z.A. is from Iraq.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2251.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2254.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After leaving Iraq, he went to Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2254.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2257.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He then lived in Turkey for almost one year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2257.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2261.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no suggestion that he faced any oppression in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2261.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2269.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During his stay in Turkey, he claims that he registered at the office of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees and applied for asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2269.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2278.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He said that he was never called to an interview to assess his status in Turkey, but he doesn't suggest that he pressed at any time to have his application considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2278.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2286.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After Turkey, he traveled to China for the admitted reason that he wanted to find a job there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2286.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2293.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no suggestion that he faced any persecution in China also, but he failed to apply for assignment there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2293.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2299.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He claims that there were no established procedure for him to do so, but this statement is ill-founded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2299.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2310.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no suggestion that he made any approach at any time to any relevant authorities in China, including the police or immigration authorities, in order to seek asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2310.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2314.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Eventually, Mr. Zia decided to go back to Turkey from China.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2314.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2321.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He traveled back via Russia, and during his transit in Russia, he didn't seek asylum also.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2321.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2323.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But then Turkey refused his entry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2323.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2331.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is unclear whether at this point he sought to assert refugee status or to revive any early application for asylum in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2331.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2334.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Turkey sent Mr. Zia back to Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2334.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2342.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Facing immigration obstacles in Russia after two days, he finally came up with the idea of claiming refugee status in Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2342.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2351.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turkey may or may not have discharged its obligation properly under the Refugee Convention when allegedly called upon to assess his status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2351.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2359.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the key point for present purposes is that he was safe in Turkey, but he chose not to stay there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2359.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2363.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was safe in China, but chose also not to stay there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2363.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2380.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On these facts, the Russian authorities were quite plainly entitled to assess, reasonably, that he was not a genuine refugee entitled to protection under the Refugee Convention, and contrary to my opponent's allegation, that really the destination meant for them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2380.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2386.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Russia has no obligation to accommodate people who face no persecution where they came from.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2386.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2393.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Russia has no obligation to accommodate people whose trips are determined by their economic prospects rather than oppression.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2393.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2396.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn now to Mr. M.B. In this case,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2396.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2399.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the KFX are the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2399.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2402.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. M.B. apparently left Palestine for Russia</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2402.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2409.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because of the difficulties of life there, but not because of any particular oppression of him as an individual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2409.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2412.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He obtained a business visa for one year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2412.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2418.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On this basis, he spent almost a year in Russia with a string of regular jobs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2418.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2424.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then, one month after the expiry of his visa, he applied for temporary asylum in Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2424.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2431.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At no point did he articulate any basis for fearing any specific oppression in Palestine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2431.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2439.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He failed also to explain why he had failed to apply to extend his visa or to legalize his stay in Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2439.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2448.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unsurprisingly, the applicant was found guilty of violation of immigration rules, and his expulsion in the form of controlled unassisted departure was ordered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2448.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2457.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant decided to go back to Palestine, which confirms that he didn't fear any particular oppression there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2457.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2465.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, there are far crossing point, as it was pointed, when the Egyptian border was closed, and the applicant was returned from Egypt to Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2465.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2469.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no indication that he applied for asylum in Egypt also.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2469.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2476.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Russia, the applicant faced immigration obstacles because of his prior history and his absence of any valid visa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2476.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2483.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Three weeks after his arrival in Russia, he came up also with the idea to apply for refugee status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2483.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2488.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Eventually, the far crossing point was opened, and Mr. Mb returned to Palestine,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2488.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2491.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>where it appears he continues to reside.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2491.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2496.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He makes no case that he has faced any persecution since his return there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2496.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2503.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That again demonstrates the absence of any reason for fearing persecution when he claimed asylum in the first place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2503.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2511.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On these facts, once again, I respectfully suggest that Russian authorities were entitled to conclude reasonably that Mr. Mb was not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2511.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2513.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a genuine refugee also.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2513.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2516.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Distinguished judges, I turn to Mr. Am now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2516.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2520.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In his case, the facts are the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2520.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2523.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Am fled from Somalia to Yemen</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2523.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2526.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and was granted refugee status there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2526.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2534.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Subsequently, he obtained a residence permit in Yemen, and eventually Yemen nationality and Yemen passport.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2534.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2540.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Eventually, due to a dispute with the private party, he decided to move to Cuba.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2540.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2545.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no suggestion that he faced any oppression from the state authorities in Yemen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2545.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2551.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no suggestion either that he sought any protection from them in relation to his private difficulties there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2551.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2556.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Am claims that he applied for asylum when he went to Cuba,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2556.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2559.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>but that his application was not persist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2559.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2563.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no suggestion that he faced any oppression in Cuba also.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2563.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2566.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then apparently, he decided to travel to Ecuador now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2566.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2571.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, he claims that he applied for asylum, but that his application wasn't persist.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2571.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2576.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Eventually, he was sent back to Cuba, and Cuba sent him to Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2576.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2583.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Facing immigration obstacles in Russia, Mr. Am also alighted on the idea of claiming asylum in Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2583.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2593.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, the government respectfully submit that the Russian authorities were quite plainly entitled to determine that Mr. Am was not a genuine refugee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2593.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2596.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was not coming from any situation of oppression.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2596.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2605.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He failed to make out any case of political oppression at any stage after his arrival and naturalization in Yemen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2605.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2607.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I turn now to the case of Mr. Yessen finally.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2607.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2609.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He is national of Syria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2609.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2615.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He has traveled occasionally to Russia to do business since 2004.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2615.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2620.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2011, he left for Lebanon, where he allegedly applied for asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2620.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2624.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having received no reply, he returned to Syria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2624.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2634.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After that, he traveled several times to Lebanon from 2010 to 2011, and from 2013 to 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2634.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2642.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He doesn't say that he tried to apply for shelter in Lebanon, which houses the biggest camp of refugees from Syria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2642.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2650.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He frequently journeys back to Syria suggests that there would have been little basis for him to do so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2650.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2652.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, Mr. Yessen traveled to Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2652.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2659.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He didn't have a proper visa and was found guilty of breach of immigration rules, and his expulsion was also ordered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2659.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2664.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only at this point did he light on the idea of claiming assignment in Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2664.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2666.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Yessen's application was refused,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2666.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2670.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. Yessen didn't lodge any appeal on that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2670.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2674.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, he simply stayed in Russia illegally.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2674.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2676.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Eventually, a further order was made for Mr. Yessen</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2676.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2678.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to control unassisted departure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2678.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2686.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, he didn't challenge the decision, and he traveled to Turkey and then to Lebanon, but both countries refused him entry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2686.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2691.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Even so, it appears that he didn't apply for asylum in either places.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2691.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2696.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And instead, he was returned to Russia, and he claimed asylum there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2696.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2702.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once more, therefore, the Russian authorities were entitled to take the view that Mr. Yessen was not</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2702.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2704.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>a genuine refugee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2704.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2711.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His frequent visits to Syria contradicts any suggestion that he faced any particular persecution there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2711.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2721.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His failure to seek or to press for refugee status elsewhere is also inconsistent with any suggestion that he was fleeing persecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2721.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2729.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quite simply, he made his claims to refugee status as a last resort when he ran out of options in Russia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2729.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2733.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of these cases under consideration, therefore, have some common factors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2733.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2737.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In all cases except for Mr. Z.A., the applicants,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2737.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2747.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>when crossing the territory of Russia for the first time, had valid visas, business or transit, and didn't immediately claim asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2747.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2756.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In each case, they had come through states where they could have applied for asylum and where, in any event, they faced no persecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2756.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2764.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In each case, the applicant failed to make out any convincing case of anticipated persecution in their country of nationality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2764.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2771.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In each case, they were refused entry to Russia at Moscow Sheremetyevo Airport, but they were in no way detained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2771.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2776.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They could return home or fly to any country that would accept them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2776.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2783.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is said on the applicant's behalf that they had run out of money and couldn't afford to fly elsewhere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2783.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2792.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That may well have been the result of their own desperation in flying around the world without proper visa and financial arrangements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2792.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2798.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, their thoughtlessness doesn't cast upon Russian government the burden of looking after them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2798.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2812.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were free to apply to the diplomatic representatives of their home countries in Moscow for whatever support these countries may provide in such circumstances, but there is no evidence that they did so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2812.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2833.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please let me note that also according to Annex 9 to the Convention of International Civil Aviation, custody and care of the applicants is the responsibility of an aircraft operator, and it was the aircraft operator who took them to the airplane abroad without proper travel documents to enter Russia, and to whom also the applicants could have applied for support.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2833.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2844.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, confinement to the transit zone where a person has brought themselves by their own actions doesn't amount to detention by a state in breach of Article 5.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2844.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2853.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any other conclusion would totally undermine the sovereign prerogative of the states to control their own borders and ensure security.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2853.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2867.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That would be a very grave step indeed when it would be likely to prompt measures that would prevent even genuine refugees from boarding a plane in another state for fear of an obligation to admit anyone arriving in a transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2867.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2882.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And moreover, as it was correctly pointed by the applicant side in the morning hearings, neither the Refugee Convention nor the Convention on the Human Rights provide for a right to enter the state itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2882.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2890.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the court's case law, the deprivation of liberty under Article 5 contains both objective and subjective elements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2890.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2900.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An objective element means that a person is held in a particular restricted space for a considerably long time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2900.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2914.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Relevant objective factors include the possibility to leave the restricted area, the degree of supervision and control over the person's movements, the extent of isolation, and the availability of social contacts there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2914.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2922.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A subjective element presumes that the person has not validly consented to the confinement in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2922.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2931.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is therefore unreasonable to come to any conclusions about the deprivation of liberty solely on the ground of subjective criterion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2931.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2951.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, it would lead to such an absurd situations when a person whose flight or train was delayed or canceled could claim to be deprived of his or her liberty on this account that he or she voluntarily consented to keep on waiting at the airport or a railway station.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2951.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2960.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, it is quite clear that these applicants never lost their liberty by any objective criterion according to the court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2960.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2966.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were free to depart at any time as necessary with the assistance of their home states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2966.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2969.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were not held in any restricted space.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2969.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2972.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were never deprived of human interaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2972.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2975.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were not treated in any cruel way at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2975.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2979.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Objectively, therefore, the applicants were free.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2979.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2983.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had access to shops, cafes, hotel with facilities there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2983.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2990.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were visited by representatives of the UN High Commission for Refugees and communicated with the lawyers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2990.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2997.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To the extent that subjectively they felt themselves confined, that was only because of their own misconduct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2997.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3005.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They must be taken to have consented on the court's subjective test to the situation in which they found themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3005.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3010.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, the Russian authorities didn't confine the applicants at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3010.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3023.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As was confirmed by the Office of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees in its written submissions on the present case, Russian border control doesn't make a decision to keep a person in the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3023.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3028.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It simply does not allow the person to cross the border and let the person inland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3028.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3040.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, the restriction of the applicant's freedom of movement doesn't fall under Article 2 of Protocol 4 since it is applicable only to persons lawfully within the territory of a state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3040.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3044.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the applicant's status was yet to be verified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3044.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3053.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows that a request for asylum doesn't create a right to enter the state because the request only begins a process of verification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3053.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3061.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The perpetrated seizure of the applicant's documents is a part of this process of such verification and doesn't constitute detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3061.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3068.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As soon as the applicants decided to leave Russia, they received their documents and nothing precluded them from doing so.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3068.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3081.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that two of the applicants eventually safely returned to their home countries also testifies that not only could they leave for third countries, but also to go back to their homes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3081.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3084.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, any other result will be absurd.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3084.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3089.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please imagine that an alien need not follow ordinary immigration procedures.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3089.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3103.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He needs only file an application for refugee status, even a completely fake one, and gain admission to the territory of Russian Federation or in any other member state and require housing, protection, and financial support.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3103.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3115.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When a person voluntarily applies for admission to the jurisdiction of the state, then person consents to the process of verification of his or her status under the law of this host state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3115.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3119.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It can be said that on this ground, the person is detained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3119.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3124.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The confinement in a transit zone is therefore not a limitation of freedom of movement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3124.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3132.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is clear choice of the applicants, and it could only be a limitation if it were involuntary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3132.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3139.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, before finding a restriction of liberty, it is necessary to consider the nature of limitation of restriction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3139.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3146.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Logic indicates that there can only be a limitation of restriction where there was a pre-existing liberty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3146.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3154.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The refugee conversion, once again, provides no liberty to enter the territory of a state before the process of verification is complete.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3154.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3162.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It provides no such right where an applicant doesn't arrive directly from the state where they were persecuted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3162.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3169.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It provides no such right to people who were not under immediate threat and who simply wanted to choose a better life in Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3169.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3176.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the length of time that the applicants spent in the transit zone, it is appropriate to consider two things.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3176.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3188.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First is the clear lack of legal grounds for granting of asylum for applicants in Russia, the fact which they should have known from the very beginning from the qualified lawyers who advised them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3188.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3196.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second is, therefore, the series of hopeless domestic appeals on which they, by their own choice, embarked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3196.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3201.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That extended their time in the transit zone until they eventually left.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3201.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3204.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of this raises a fundamental point of principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3204.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3216.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It wasn't being argued on behalf of any of the applicants that they were in any way unable to make choices as experienced adults, human beings, and also assisted by the lawyers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3216.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3227.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Refugee Convention, as well as Convention of the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms, do not protect them from the consequences of their own wrong choices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3227.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3235.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are not entitled to tear down international and domestic immigration law because they do not like the consequences of the choices they have made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3235.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3246.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In conclusion, the government respectfully asks the Grand Chamber to reconsider the Chamber's judgment and to decide that there are no violations of the Convention in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3246.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3254.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, any person who doesn't wish to return to his home country for any reason has a golden opportunity now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3254.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3264.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They need only turn up unannounced in the transit zone, get stuck there, protest their hardships, and appeal to allege Convention rights in this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3264.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3271.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Convention would be a dead letter, and the sovereign right of the state to control their borders would be gone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3271.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3277.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is not a sustainable position in law or in terms of the political consent of signatory states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3277.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3277.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3279.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3286.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Galperin, and I thank both parties for their submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3286.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3294.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I invite my colleagues, the judges of the Grand Chamber who wish to do so, to put their questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3294.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3295.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Are there any questions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3295.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3295.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Lemmens, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3298.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3301.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3301.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3310.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question, I think, primarily for the government, but the applicants can also, of course, reply to it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3310.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3319.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government said that deprivation of liberty is characterized by a number of objective and subjective elements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3319.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3332.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to link that to an element that has been invoked by the applicants, namely the fact that their passports were retained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3332.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3343.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You did not speak about that when you were discussing the elements, but then I would like to ask you, is this an element that is relevant?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3343.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3356.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, would it be possible to explain to us a bit more about the rules that govern the taking and the returning of passports?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3356.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3365.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Which are the categories of persons of which the passports can be taken, and what are the circumstances in which passports are returned to them?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3365.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3365.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3366.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3368.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Dedov, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Dmitry Dedov</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3374.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3375.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3375.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3389.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question follows Judge Lehman's question, whether the passport was claimed back by the applicants and whether the authorities refused to do that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3389.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3393.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also would like to clarify that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3393.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3401.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would thank both parties for their very valuable information was given to us regarding the domestic law, especially.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3401.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3404.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is about the domestic law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3404.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3416.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants' representative mentioned about the 24 hours rule when the person, when he illegally entered the territory of the Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3416.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3419.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He should apply for this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3419.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3437.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But isn't you apply this rule or refuse to apply this rule for the present case in a mechanical way, I would say, or formalistically.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3437.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3451.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would ask you what would be the consequences that if the applicants would not comply with this rule, would not apply within 24 hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3451.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3463.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whether we can use this provision of the domestic law in this situation, because they were in the urgent situation, for example, as a criterion which could be used.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3463.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3468.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question is about the difference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3468.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3489.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Would you provide the example that the Syrian family was granted asylum and provided the opportunity to have access to social services and so on, which was provided by the Russian authorities in 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3489.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3502.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But can you accept that there is a difference between the situations of the applicants in this case and those Syrian family?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3502.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3511.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my question is about whether the applicants arrived in the Russian border with their families or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3511.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3519.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the last question is about the application in the third countries.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3519.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3521.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both parties mentioned that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3521.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3557.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And my question is whether there is a requirement under the domestic asylum procedure, for example, when the person apply for asylum, should the authorities question about his previous experience and application in third countries, whether the applicant should provide any documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3557.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3589.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if not, if the documents are not provided, whether this failure to inform the country authorities about the third country's application, it leads to the delay in examination of the application of the asylum seeker in that case, in this case, in the Russian Federation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3589.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3602.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I mean, the question is whether there is, there are any circumstances that could prove that the delay was also provoked by the applicants themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3602.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3602.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3604.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3606.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3606.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3609.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, Judge Kjlbro, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Jon Fridrik Kjlbro</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3612.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3614.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3614.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3620.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also have some questions to the government, but the applicants' representative is most welcome to also address them if they so wish.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3620.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3626.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first question is also a follow-up to the question by Judge Lemmens and Dedov concerning the passports.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3626.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3631.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to the applicants, the Russian authorities seized their passports.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3631.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3634.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In their observations, the government have argued to the contrary.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3634.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3639.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, my question is, were the applicants' passports seized at any time by the authorities?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3639.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3643.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if so, what was the legal basis for doing so?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3643.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3645.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And what was the purpose of the measure?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3645.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3655.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>More specifically, was it a precautious measure to ensure the necessary traveling documents at the moment the applicants would have to leave Russian territory?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3655.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3663.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, did the seizure in practice prevent the applicants from leaving the country in case they should so have wished to do?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3663.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3674.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question to the government concerns the distinction between genuine asylum seekers and ordinary migrants, which is one of the core arguments of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3674.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3697.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the government argues that the applicants were accepted for assessment under marriage and were dismissed after rather lengthy proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3697.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3715.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, in view of the government, can the state's obligation under Article 3 and under Article 5 be depending upon the outcome of the asylum proceedings, more specifically as regards material conditions for the stay in the airport zone?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3715.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3728.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government is arguing that it had no positive obligations under Article 3 to meet the applicants' basic needs during this period as they were not genuine asylum seekers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3728.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3735.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, whether they were entitled to international protection or not was exactly what Russian authorities had undertaken to assess.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3735.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3746.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So once again, my question is, can the state's obligations towards asylum seekers depend upon the outcome of the asylum procedure?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3746.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3750.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My last question also to the government concerns the open door argument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3750.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3762.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under Article 5, the government is emphasizing the fact that the applicants were free to leave Russia at any time and that nothing prevented them from leaving Russian territory earlier.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3762.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3767.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, the government is invoking an open door argument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3767.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3786.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, my question is, how realistic is this suggestion in view of the fact that the applicants claimed that they risked ill treatment in a country of origin, a claim which the Russian authorities accepted to examine under marriage, and apparently no other country was willing to accept them?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3786.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3792.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, no steps to facilitate such an acceptance would appear to have been undertaken by Russian authorities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3792.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3792.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3793.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3796.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3796.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3812.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there are no more questions, the court will now withdraw for 20 minutes, following which the parties will be able to submit brief observations in reply to each other's submissions and reply to questions from the judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3812.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3814.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4312.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4312.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4347.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4362.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated. The hearing is resumed. And now I call Mrs. Davidyan. Please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4364.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4363.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4367.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4372.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to thank all the judges for the questions that help us elaborate the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4372.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4384.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I will start with responding to the government's claim that the arguments about the risk of persecutions of Mr.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4384.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4391.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Zia based on his religion were allegedly not claimed before.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4391.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4393.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that is not true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4393.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4397.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These arguments can be found in our application.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4397.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4414.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it can be found in the decision of the Federal Migration Office refusing the applicant's appeal against refusal to grant him asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4414.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4424.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the questions of the court, I will start with the question which all the judges asked about the passports.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4424.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4431.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will start by saying that there is no legal basis for retention of passports by the border guard service.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4431.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4435.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And there were no formal decisions made on that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4435.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4460.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, according to the Refugees Act, the migration authorities are supposed to retain the passports in return to the examination certificates when the applicants are applying for the asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4460.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4468.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the applicants in this case were not trying to request their passports back.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4468.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4477.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as their status was established as asylum seekers, they were asking to provide them with the examination certificates rather than return their passports.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4484.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4494.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also, I would like to stress once again that the applicants were having a hard time finding a country to live for.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4494.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4504.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we already mentioned this, it took an intensive effort with the help of the UNHCR to find countries that would agree to accept the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4504.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4509.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, having the passport on hand was a secondary question for them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4509.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4512.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were trying to first find a destination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4512.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4528.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they then would have asked for their passports to return, which the passports were returned when the applicants were ready to leave for another country, when they already found the country that was ready to accept them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4528.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4533.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as we already mentioned, it was done with the help of the UNHCR.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4533.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4541.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the passport was only handed to the aircraft crew member, not to the applicants themselves.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4541.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4550.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the question of Judge Dyadov as regards the 24 hours time limit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4550.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4566.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So this limit by law is provided for lodging and asylum application only for those applicants which were forced to illegally cross the border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4566.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4575.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, this rule is not applicable to the present case because the applicants did not cross the border at all, not legally, not illegally.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4575.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4581.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were in the transit zone, and they were not able to cross the border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4581.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4599.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If hypothetically, one does violate this rule, crosses the border illegally, and does violate the rule of applying for asylum within 24 hours, there is a criminal prosecution provided for this violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4599.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4603.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it is criminal prosecution for the fact of illegally crossing the border.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4603.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4616.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in terms of not applying for asylum within 24 hours, it would be a basis for the migration authorities to refuse to consider the application for asylum on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4616.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4626.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So such application would have been declared inadmissible, which, as we know, has not happened in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4626.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4629.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And all the applicants' applications were considered on the merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4632.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4656.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the question on the Syrian family by Judge Dyadov, what was the difference between the case with the Syrian family that was allowed to enter the country and the present case, it is obvious for us that the difference was in the public perception of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4656.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4664.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Syrian family did have minor kids with them, and there was a public response to the coverage of the story in the media.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4664.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4673.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, this family was allowed not to stay in the appalling conditions of the transit zone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4673.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4682.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the law does not provide any difference for cases which involve or don't involve minor kids.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4686.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4696.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And basically, that once again confirms their arbitrariness of the authorities in considering cases like this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4696.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4716.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Turning to the question about informing the authorities about third countries where the applicants have been, the applicants are supposed to inform the migration authorities when they are applying for asylum, when they're being interviewed for asylum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4716.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4726.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicants in the present case did inform about all their previous places of residence or even presence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4726.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4732.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in fact, their passports showed all the places they've been to because they were all stamped in there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4732.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4740.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And however, the main delay in this case is it happened before the applicants were interviewed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4740.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4750.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the main delay happened before the applicants had a chance to tell anybody about any third country they have ever been to or applied to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4750.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4761.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the applicants claimed that they did not contribute to the extended delays of examination in any way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4761.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4779.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In response to the government's claims and also endorsing the question of Judge Kilbrough, we would like to note that the government said that they don't have any obligations to accommodate people who face no persecutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4779.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4785.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the government has to assess first whether people are facing persecutions or not.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4785.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4792.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is exactly the procedure of consideration of asylum applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4792.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4798.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And asylum applications are provided with certain guarantees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4798.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4801.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And those are the guarantees that the Russian law provides.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4801.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4806.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, the government does have obligations in these cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4806.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4828.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further, I would like to note that also the government was mentioning that delays and obstructions are happening in consideration of genuine asylum seekers as a result of too many ordinary migrants' applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4828.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4850.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, while the Russian practice shows that delays and obstructions are still happening even without any mass influx of refugees, Russia is not one of the countries which is facing the mass influx of refugees that we've been talking about.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4850.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4866.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in conclusion, quoting our honorable opponents, I would like to note, though certain things stand as unquestionable truth, a need to put them in remembrance tends to appear from time to time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4866.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4878.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It must be recognized by the governments that state sovereignty and public perceptions cannot be maintained at the expense of fundamental, absolute individual rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4878.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4880.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>History has witnessed examples of the opposite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4880.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4885.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this court has been created precisely to prevent them from recurring.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4885.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4885.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4886.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4889.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mrs. Davidyan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4889.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4891.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now Mr. Galperin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4891.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4891.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4892.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4893.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4893.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4904.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will start with directing on my learned opposite council allegation that Russia is not the subject of massive influx of migrants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4904.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4914.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I would like to point that in the same year, 2015, 2.6 million refugees came to Russia from east of Ukraine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4914.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4925.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is why it also, answering to the Judge Dedev question, it also much influenced the time limits for the relevant applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4925.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4975.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Answering on the questions of the judges Lemans, Dedev, and Kerbero regarding the passports and the procedures established on the passports of the migrants, and according to the internal legal regulations by the border service of the Federal Security Service of the Russian Federation, and in particular, point 494 of the so-called approved technological scheme of the organization of the passing of the Russian state border in the airport, it is the legal act, the applicant with their passports were transferred to the jurisdiction of the Aeroflot, which was the air company which put them to Russia with their passports to ensure that they will be returned to the states ready to receive them by their air company.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4975.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4987.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Subsequently, under the point 4910 of this domestic act, the passports were handed over by the air transport carriers to the relevant state officials to be deposited there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4987.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5000.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, I underdo the attention of the respective judges that the applicant could leave the territory of the Russian Federation at any time, having requested their passports from the border control service via the air transport carrier.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5000.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5004.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, they have failed to request their passports to be returned to them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5004.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5026.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as we know, just several minutes ago from the applicants' counsel, that they really didn't request their passports and didn't want them to be requested, since they wanted some refugee certificates to be received, but not passports, which give them the opportunity to leave the country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5026.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5043.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, there are no grounds to believe that this period of the absence of passport is attributable to Russian government and to amount to derivation of their liberty and detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5043.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5069.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding Judge Kerbero's question about the classification of the detention conditions depends on the outcome of the case regarding the Genean refugee or migrant, I would say that under the Russian law, there is not any differences in legislation and detention conditions, since in our case, then, we're not detained.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5069.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5070.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were just free people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5070.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5077.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And all basic conditions were provided for them as to the free people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5077.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5080.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I mean that they can live in the hotel for their money.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5080.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5083.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They can go to the cafe to eat.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5083.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5085.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had access to the toilets.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5085.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5095.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as any of us do when staying in the transit zone of the airport or in the airport, so we can do everything of that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5095.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5097.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they were not detained there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5097.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5098.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5098.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5098.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5099.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5102.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mr. Galperin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5102.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5106.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank both parties for their submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5106.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5108.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have come now to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5108.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5113.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank again the parties for their submissions and their answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5113.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5116.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5116.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5119.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered at a later stage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5119.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5123.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5123.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5123.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
