<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>6606909_28112012</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>38.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>39.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>43.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>51.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Vinter and others against the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>51.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>62.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case covers three applications which were lodged with the court under Article 34 of the Convention by British nationals, Mr. Douglas Gary Vinter, Mr. Jeremy Neville Bamber,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>64.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>69.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Mr. Peter Howard Moore between the 11th of December</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>69.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>73.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>2009 and the 6th of January 2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>73.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>82.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applications were allocated to the fourth section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph one of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>82.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>87.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They were communicated to the government on the 1st of February 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>87.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>94.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the 17th of January 2012, a chamber of the fourth section delivered its judgment in the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>94.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>105.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber decided to join the applications and told in respect of all three applicants that there had been no violation of Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>105.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>116.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 12th of April 2012, the applicants requested that the case be referred to the grand chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>116.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>124.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the panel of the grand chamber accepted the request on the 9th of July 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>124.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>127.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Ms. Laura</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>127.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>131.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dauban, assisted by Mr. David Perry, QC leading counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>131.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>135.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Louis Mably, counsel, and by Mr. John Guess and Ms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>135.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>138.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alison Foulds, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>138.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>142.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants are represented by Mr. Richard Horwell, QC,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>142.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>147.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Pete Weatherby, QC, and Mr. Luke Hindmarsh, counsel,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>147.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>152.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Mr. Simon Creighton, Mr. Barry Woods,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>152.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>156.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Professor Dirk van Zyl Smit, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>156.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>163.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>163.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>173.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to welcome a delegation from the Turkish Council of State and the Italian Superior Council of Military Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>173.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>183.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representatives of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>183.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>188.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Perry for the government will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>188.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>193.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mr. Pete Weatherby, QC, for the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>193.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>210.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting in Turkish and Russian has been authorized for the benefit of the Turkish delegation and the Belarusian delegation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>210.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>224.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcriptions of the oral translations will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>224.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>224.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Perry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>228.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>232.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>232.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>245.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the applications before the court raise issues which are of profound importance to the government of the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>245.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>255.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In England and Wales, the mandatory sentence for murder is imprisonment for life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>255.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>272.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the length of time the offender must spend in prison before he is considered for parole is fixed by the sentencing judge as a matter of discretion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>272.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>287.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This discretion is exercised in accordance with structured guidance set out in statute and always on the facts of the individual case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>287.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>305.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In cases of the most extreme and unusual gravity, the sentencing judge may order that for the purposes of pure punishment and deterrence, the offender is to spend the rest of his life in prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>305.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>326.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such an order will only be made where the judge is satisfied having taken into account all the features of aggravation and mitigation that the element of just punishment and retribution requires its imposition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>326.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>334.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not a mandatory sentence, nor is it an automatic sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>334.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>344.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is important to emphasize that a whole life order is reserved for the most serious cases known to the criminal law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>344.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>360.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a sentence of last resort, the rarest of the rare, and the government submit that the imposition of such a sentence does not involve a violation of Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>360.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>374.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government wish to emphasize at this early stage their commitment to the values contained in Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>374.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>388.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the government submission, these values are not inconsistent with the principle that just punishment is appropriate for those convicted of criminal offences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>388.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>405.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it follows in the government submission that in an appropriate case, it would be neither inhuman nor degrading treatment or punishment for a person to serve a whole life term.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>405.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>416.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Significantly, there is a lack of consensus among member states in this area of sentencing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>416.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>423.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was a point recognized by this court in the Kafkaris case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>423.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>447.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And while the government note that in many member states there is no power to impose a whole life sentence, and it is evident that many member states consider that there is a maximum sentence of imprisonment that can be justified by way of punishment, that is not the policy of the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>447.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>462.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The policy in the United Kingdom is that some crimes are so serious that they require, as a proportionate response, lifelong incarceration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>462.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>472.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This policy is long-standing and has been supported by many eminent jurists.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>472.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>495.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, Lord Bingham of Cornhill, when Lord Chief Justice, said there was no reason in principle why a crime, if sufficiently serious, should not be regarded as deserving of lifelong incarceration for the purposes of pure punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>495.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>502.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The policy of the United Kingdom is now enshrined in statute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>502.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>515.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Importantly, this recently enacted statute reflects the settled will of the United Kingdom's democratically elected parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>515.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>528.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Importantly, the domestic courts have consistently held that it is lawful and compatible with Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>528.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>542.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This includes the recent decision of the Court of Appeal, specially constituted to consider four cases in which whole life terms had been imposed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>542.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>559.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court presided over by Lord Judge, Chief Justice, comprised four other senior judges of the Court of Appeal, including the Vice President of the Queen's Bench Division and the Vice President of the Court of Appeal Criminal Division.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>559.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>577.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the judgment has been provided to the court by the government, and the government invite the court to consider in particular the analysis contained in paragraphs 1 to 30 of the Court of Appeal decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>577.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>601.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Similarly, the government rely on the jurisprudence of this court, which is clearly and consistently to the effect that the imposition of a whole life sentence and the serving of such a sentence does not in and of itself raise an issue under Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>601.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>615.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government rely on the Kafkaris decision, the Harkins and Edwards decision decided earlier this year, and the Barbara Ahmed decision also decided earlier this year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>615.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>648.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In submitting that the domestic approach is longstanding, enshrined in statute, consistently upheld by the domestic courts, and in noting the lack of consensus amongst member states, and this court's repeated observation that matters of appropriate sentencing policy largely fall outside the scope of the Convention, the government wish to make what they consider to be a very important submission, and it is this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>648.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>658.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The policy, the sentencing policy of the United Kingdom, is based on a settled democratic consensus.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>658.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>675.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a democratic consensus in respect of an issue which at its core concerns questions of punishment, retribution, justice, humanity, and atonement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>675.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>684.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These are questions which have long been the subject of ethical, political, and philosophical controversy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>684.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>691.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are the subject of continuing rational argument and civilized disagreement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>691.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>714.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The assessment of what should be deemed to constitute just punishment or inhuman or degrading punishment in a particular circumstance can legitimately produce different answers in different countries, and indeed different answers at different times in the same country for historical and cultural reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>714.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>727.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in the government submission, it is legitimate for these differing views to be resolved in national communities by arbitration through the democratic process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>727.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>755.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As Lord Hoffman noted in the Wellington case, when considering Parliament's preservation of the whole-life sentence in the United Kingdom, he emphasized the democratic nature of member states and noted that this was an important factor to be taken into account by the courts when considering the scope and application of Article III.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>755.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>771.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government submit that this factor is particularly relevant when the court is invited to extend the reach of Article III, as is the case in each of these applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>771.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>786.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I turn to deal with the distinction drawn by the Chamber between the three different types of life sentence, the three different types of life sentence analyzed by the Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>786.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>797.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, a life sentence with eligibility for release after a minimum period has been served.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>797.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>804.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, a discretionary sentence of life imprisonment without the possibility of parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>804.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>811.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And third, a mandatory sentence of life imprisonment without the possibility of parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>811.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>831.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government agree that as the Chamber held, the first type of life sentence is clearly reducible and no Article III issue arises, subject of course only to the question of gross disproportionality.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>831.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>849.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moving to the second and third type of sentence, it is important to emphasize that in the United Kingdom, the third type of sentence, a mandatory whole life order, is simply not available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>849.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>853.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is not available to the sentencing courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>853.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>876.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is because whilst in the case of murder, the life sentence itself is mandatory, the decision as to whether to impose a minimum term and its length or a whole life order is a matter of judicial discretion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>876.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>890.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the first instance, it is imposed by the sentencing judge and it is subject to review on an appeal against sentence by the Court of Appeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>890.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>904.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judicial decision in question is made in accordance with the detailed guidance set out in Schedule 21 to the Criminal Justice Act 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>904.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>917.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This schedule provides a comprehensive and carefully constructed framework for assessing the seriousness of a particular murder or murders.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>917.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>931.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And all the factors set out within the schedule are commonly accepted factors for assessing the degree of harm occasioned by the offence and the culpability of the offender.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>931.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>939.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They include commonly accepted mitigating factors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>939.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>953.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is apparent from the legislation that a whole life order may only be imposed where the seriousness of the offending is exceptionally high.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>953.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>983.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, multiple murder involving a substantial degree of premeditation, the abduction of the victim or sexual or sadistic conduct, or the murder of a child involving abduction or sexual or sadistic conduct, or murder for the purpose of advancing a political or religious cause, or murder by an offender previously convicted of murder.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>983.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>993.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Court of Appeal has emphasised that the language of Schedule 21 is not prescriptive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>993.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1004.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judge is not required to impose a whole life order if it would be contrary to the interests of justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1004.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1027.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it has been made clear by the domestic courts that a whole life order should only be imposed where the seriousness of the offending is so exceptionally high that just punishment requires the offender to be kept in prison for the rest of his life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1027.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1042.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The crucial point in this analysis is that the decision-making process is concerned purely with punishing the offender according to the seriousness of his crime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1042.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1048.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not concerned with an assessment of the offender's dangerousness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1048.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1060.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The minimum term, or as the case may be, a whole life term, is ordered purely for the purposes of punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1060.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1071.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Following on from this, there are two points of significance in relation to the sentencing exercise, which the government would wish to emphasise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1071.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1081.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the making of the order is an entirely judicial process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1081.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1097.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, at the time the sentence is imposed, consideration is given to all material circumstances, including any mitigating factors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1097.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1123.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is in contrast to the position in Kafkaris, where the sentence was in effect a mandatory whole life term, and where the assessment of commonly accepted sentencing considerations was not carried out at the time the sentence was imposed by the independent and impartial judicial officer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1123.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1137.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Instead, in that case, matters of aggravation and mitigation were considered years later by the executive when determining whether to order discretionary release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1137.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1147.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this court held that that post-sentence review of detention was sufficient to render the sentence reducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1147.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1160.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the United Kingdom, in response to decisions of this court, executive review has no place in the sentencing process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1160.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1190.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has been concluded, and the government submit properly concluded, that it is exclusively for the independent judiciary to assess and evaluate the commonly accepted sentencing considerations and to determine the just and appropriate sentence, whether sitting as sentencing judges or in the Court of Appeal or in the High Court in transitional cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1190.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1215.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In summary, therefore, in relation to the type of sentence, the government emphasised these applications are concerned with discretionary sentences of life imprisonment, judicially imposed, where the possibility of parole has been excluded by judicial order, having taken into account all relevant factors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1215.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1226.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I then turn to address the question of when an issue under Article 3 may arise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1226.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1244.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A central aspect of the Chamber's judgment was its conclusion that an Article 3 issue cannot arise at the moment a discretionary whole life sentence is imposed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1244.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1260.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such an issue may only arise at some later point in time if it can be shown that continued imprisonment is no longer justified and that the sentence is irreducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1260.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1267.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government submit that the conclusion of the Chamber is correct.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1267.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1275.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is consistent with this court's jurisprudence and also the decisions of the domestic courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1275.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1282.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It correctly identifies the true reach of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1282.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1298.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The key point, the essential point, is that a proportionate sentence cannot be inhuman or degrading at the moment it is imposed or whilst it is being served.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1298.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1319.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows, as a matter of consistency and logic, that it is not contrary to Article 3 for an offender to know that his offending deserves lifelong incarceration for the purposes of pure punishment and that he must serve such a term.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1319.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1347.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government also submit that the Chamber was entirely correct to conclude that if a situation arises where continued detention can no longer be justified, what gives rise to an Article 3 issue is not the sentence itself, but the prisoner's unjustified continued detention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1347.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1357.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whether such a situation will arise cannot be determined at the point at which the sentence is imposed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1357.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1372.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The possibility of justified detention becoming unjustified at some unknown point in the future for some unknown reason, the government submit, is speculative.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1372.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1379.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in the submission of the government, it is in fact unlikely to arise in any case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1379.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1389.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Certainly, no question of unjustified detention arises on the facts of the applicant's cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1389.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1394.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is not the applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1394.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1418.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason for the analysis which the government supports is that the justification for the sentence is the seriousness of the offence, and the seriousness of the offence is a factor which remains constant over time and which does not diminish.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1418.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1441.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having regard to the fact that the offending by definition will have been of exceptional gravity, calling for a whole life order, it is unrealistic to suppose that subsequent events could ever be sufficient to render continued detention unjustifiable on penological grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1441.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1455.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By way of contrast, the chamber minority held that Article 3 required there to be a suitable review mechanism in place from the outset of the sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1455.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1471.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The minority's reasoning was that an Article 3 issue arises not merely from keeping a prisoner detained longer than would be justified, but also in circumstances where a prisoner is deprived of any hope of release in the future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1471.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1476.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In response to that analysis, may we make six points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1476.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1493.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the approach of the minority represents only one view on the ethical, political and philosophical question of what just punishment requires in the case of those who commit the most appalling crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1493.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1501.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not the only view, and there is no settled consensus that it is the right view.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1501.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1513.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the United Kingdom, the domestic courts have consistently rejected it, and it does not reflect and never has reflected the will of the United Kingdom's Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1513.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1519.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, the views expressed by the minority have never prevailed in any case before this Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1519.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1529.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the differing approaches between states in this area is also reflected in the law of the European Union.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1529.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1533.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Article 5.2 of the Council Framework Decision</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1533.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1562.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the European Arrest Warrant provides that the execution of a European Arrest Warrant in respect of an offence punishable by lifetime detention may be subject to the condition that the issuing member state has provisions in its legal system for a review of the sentence at the latest after 20 years or for the application of measures of clemency aimed at non-execution of the sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1562.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1586.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that the condition is optional rather than mandatory not only acknowledges that there is no consensus among member states of the European Union in respect of life sentences, but also implies that lifetime detention orders without review do not of themselves amount to inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1586.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1603.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If it were otherwise, the surrender of an accused or convicted person from one member state of the Union to another would not be possible in cases where a sentence of 20 years' imprisonment had been imposed or where such a sentence was likely.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1603.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1621.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third point, as the chamber majority held, in any case of murder where the seriousness of the offending is very high, the offender will inevitably serve and expect to serve a very long prison sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1621.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1629.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the United Kingdom, minimum terms in such cases are often in excess of 30 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1629.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1640.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of Oakes recently considered by the Court of Appeal, one of the appellants was sentenced to life imprisonment and a minimum term of 40 years was imposed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1640.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1654.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a very severe penalty, but no question of a review could realistically arise before the offender has served the period imposed for the purposes of pure punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1654.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1657.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fourth point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1657.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1674.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It may be asked in the context of an offender who has committed a murder of a most terrible kind, of what practical value is the review mechanism contemplated by the chamber minority?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1674.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1681.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we have already submitted, the seriousness of the offending is a factor which remains constant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1681.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1700.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government submit it's unfeasible to proceed on the basis that circumstances may arise which could displace a determination reached by an independent and impartial judicial officer that a crime is so serious that just punishment requires lifelong incarceration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1700.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1702.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fifth point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1702.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1713.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber minority acknowledge that in these circumstances, any hope of release offered by a review mechanism would be tenuous.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1713.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1728.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government submit that compliance with Article 3 does not and should not depend on the provision of a tenuous, unrealistic or false hope of release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1728.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1746.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The true position in the government submission is that compliance with Article 3 does not require the creation of false expectations and in a case of truly exceptional gravity, a whole life sentence may be justified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1746.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1755.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows from this that neither the imposition nor the serving of a whole life sentence is inhuman or degrading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1755.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1757.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The sixth point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1757.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1773.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The approach of the chamber majority is identical to the approach which has been taken by the court in the extradition context and in particular in the context of extradition to states outside the Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1773.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1789.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See for example the decision of this court in Barbar-Armand where the applicants face extradition to the United States on charges which carried sentences of life imprisonment without parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1789.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1795.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On this basis, to adopt the minority's approach in the present case would have two results.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1795.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1805.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, it would undermine the approach which the court has thus far taken in respect of whole life sentences in the extradition context.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1805.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1833.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government submit that such a result would be inconsistent with the principle that the court has repeatedly stated and which it sought to underline in the Barbar-Armand judgment, namely that the convention does not purport to be a means of imposing convention standards on other states and in particular in respect of states which have a long history of respect for democracy, human rights and the rule of law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1833.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1845.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second result is that it would create an inconsistency of approach to such sentences as between domestic cases and extradition cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1845.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1864.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The result of such an inconsistency would result in the curious position that a person facing a whole life term could not be extradited between Council of Europe states but could in the same circumstances be extradited from a member state to, say, for example, the United States.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1864.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1869.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I turn finally to the issue of reducibility?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1869.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1886.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on making our submissions on this issue, we first make the point that the conclusion reached by the chamber majority, which the government support, is that subject to gross disproportionality, no Article III issue arises at the time the sentence is imposed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1886.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1894.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so the compatibility of the sentence with that article is not dependent on whether it is reducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1894.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1903.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber concluded that the question of de facto reducibility did not arise for examination in the present case for two reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1903.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1910.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the applicants had not sought to argue that the whole life orders were grossly disproportionate on the facts of their cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1910.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1915.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And given the gravity of the murders, the chamber did not find that they were.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1915.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1926.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And secondly, the court considered that none of the applicants had demonstrated that their continued incarceration serves no legitimate penological purpose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1926.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1934.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the sake of completeness, may the government clarify three points on the question of reducibility.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1934.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1949.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the government note that without deciding the issue, the chamber doubted whether the release provisions in Section 30 of the Crime Sentences Act 1997 were sufficient to render a whole life sentence reducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1949.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1965.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By way of clarification, the government submit that the possibility of executive intervention in the operation of a judicially imposed sentence is necessarily and properly to be limited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1965.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1980.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in Bieber, the Court of Appeals stated that the Section 30 power must be exercised compatibly with Article 3, and this is mandated by the terms of the Human Rights Act 1998.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1980.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1991.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows on this analysis that if a life sentence prisoner's detention is no longer justified on any penological grounds, there is a power of release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1991.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2004.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the government wished to make clear that there are two reasons why the sentencing scheme under the 2003 Act does not contain a review provision in relation to life sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2004.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2012.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the scheme provides that the setting of the appropriate term is entirely judicial and removes the part played by the Secretary of State.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2012.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2023.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And second, the scheme ensures that all matters relevant to sentence are considered at the outset by the sentencing judge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2023.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2029.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, the third matter by way of clarification, the prerogative of mercy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2029.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2037.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In England and Wales, the prerogative of mercy still exists and may be exercised in a variety of circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2037.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2060.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the context of review and release from a life sentence on Article 3 grounds, the government submit the existence of the prerogative could add nothing to Section 30 of the Crime Sentences Act 1997, which as we have made clear, provides for release should the need arise on Article 3 grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2060.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2078.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In conclusion, based on the court's consistent and settled case law, the government submit that it is open to member states to make statutory provision for the discretionary imposition of a whole life order and in appropriate cases for the sentencing court to make such an order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2078.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2092.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For these reasons and the reasons contained in the government's written observations, we invite the court to conclude that the decision of the chamber is correct and that there has been no violation of the convention in the applicants' cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2092.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2094.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, those are the submissions</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2094.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2094.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on behalf of the United Kingdom government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2098.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2100.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. Perry.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2100.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2101.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call now Mr. Weatherby.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2104.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2108.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court, good morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2108.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2113.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issue raised in these applications can be simply stated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2113.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2120.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can a state party detain a serious offender for the rest of their life without any hope of release?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2120.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2135.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or is such a sentence necessarily a breach of Article 3 because the imposition of irreducible lifelong imprisonment removes all hope and thereby denies the human dignity of the prisoner?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2135.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2145.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is the warehousing of a human being forever until their dying breath inhuman and degrading of itself?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2145.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2157.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court has considered this problem on at least two previous occasions prior to this application, in Kafkaris and in Leger.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2157.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2164.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in neither was it able to reach a definitive resolution for quite incidental reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2164.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2176.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In both, judges in side opinions have powerfully called for the court to declare such sentences inhuman and degrading from their imposition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2176.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2205.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Bratzer in Kafkaris, in a concurring opinion which asserted that the time had come to declare irreducible lifelong imprisonment a violation of Article 3, and Judge Spielman and three others in Leger, who asserted the same, referring to the consensus at European level as to the need to work toward resettlement of even the longest serving prisoners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2205.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2223.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the current case, we adopt the argument of the dissenting opinion of the chamber, which suggested that the majority had based their conclusion primarily upon a misconceived interpretation of Kafkaris by the domestic courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2223.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2249.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that the decision of the majority by the slimmest of margins legitimizes a form of sentence which permanently excludes the individual from society, contrary to the historical position in the United Kingdom, contrary to the current position in Scotland and Northern Ireland, contrary to the settled European penal policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2249.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2264.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it allows for an extreme sentence, which can achieve no penological purpose, which was not already achieved by existing measures which allowed for review after 25 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2264.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2284.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the applicants in the current case were unsuccessful in their attempt to persuade the fourth section that an irreducible whole life prison sentence was a breach of Article 3 ab initio, the judgment was hardly a vindication of irreducible lifelong sentences, or indeed, the UK government's position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2287.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2312.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, the fourth section rightly rejected the government's argument that UK whole life sentences are not irreducible de jure and de facto because of section 30 of the 1997 crime sentences act, the provision which allows for compassionate release, but only where the prisoner is within weeks of death due to terminal illness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2312.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2323.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the chamber implicitly accepted that there could be cases where the penological justification for continued detention might become outweighed by the arguments for release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2323.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2329.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And such a sentence might thereby result in violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2329.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2346.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In essence, it was accepting that the execution of irreducible lifelong sentences, if not their imposition, may result in a violation of Article 3, but rejected the application on the basis that no violation had yet arisen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2346.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2366.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The twofold problem with that approach, as identified by the opinion of the three dissenting judges, is that it fails to address the substantive issue that results from the imposition of such sentences and the procedural issue that arises where a sentence may become in violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2366.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2369.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There must be some sort of review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2369.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2378.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There must be some sort of mechanism in place whereby such violation may be recognized and remedied when it arises.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2378.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2390.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Most fundamentally, therefore, the judgment of the fourth section failed to address or resolve the central question, one which would provide much-needed guidance for all convention states.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2390.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2413.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Does irreducible lifelong imprisonment violate Article 3, both because it fails to respect human dignity ab initio and because the lack of any review mechanism makes it impossible to recognize and remedy a violation when the balance of penological justifications may change and require release?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2413.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2428.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before I develop the argument, I make clear that we do not say that these applicants should necessarily ever be released, just that they should not have all prospects of future release taken away at the outset of their sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2428.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2432.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The serious nature of the conviction of fences is obvious.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2432.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2444.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But to suggest that the seriousness of the offending negates all penological considerations except punishment and retribution is an emotional and not a rational response.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2444.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2458.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the court finds that irreducible lifelong terms are incompatible with Article 3 per se, it would, of course, be for the United Kingdom to determine how to amend its statutory framework to comply.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2458.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2478.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as an illustration of how simple the resolution of this issue really would be, the UK could amend the law to revert to the position pre-2003 and reintroduce 25-year reviews or require minimum terms or tariffs in every case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2478.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2487.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A review of a whole life tariff would necessarily involve a reconsideration of all the penological justifications of the sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2487.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2499.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This would involve reweighing the original requirements for retribution against the extent to which the offender has been rehabilitated and the extent to which his or her risk is diminished.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2499.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2507.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There can be no doubt that after the lapse of many years, the relative weight of these justifications may change.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2507.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2522.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Basic respect for human dignity requires some such re-evaluation to give a prisoner a prospect of release and the hope of life in a free society, however remote that prospect might be in fact.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2522.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2528.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I move now to consider a summary of the position of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2528.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2539.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fourth section drew a distinction between life terms with a fixed minimum term and discretionary life terms and mandatory life terms without prospect of release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2539.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2548.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit a life term is not of itself a violation of any aspects of the convention if it is subject to periodic review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2548.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2564.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do not contend that those serving life terms must necessarily ever be released because the penological justifications for their continuing detention may remain and may outweigh other considerations until death.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2564.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2576.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A clear example of this is where a prisoner on periodic review on assessment is adjudged to remain too dangerous to be released into the general community.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2576.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2583.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The key point is whether the sentence is reducible, not whether it is in fact reduced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2583.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2595.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The distinction between discretionary and mandatory lifelong irreducible terms appears to have first arisen in the domestic case of Bieber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2595.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2598.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say in fact it is something of a distraction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2598.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2609.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Certainly the mandatory imposition of a whole life sentence is more likely to be disproportionate to the offending than one which is imposed after judicial deliberation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2609.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2613.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But both result in an irreducible lifelong sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2613.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2618.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is that fact which is relevant to the issue in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2618.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2629.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is an essential difference between an irreducible life sentence and an ordinary life sentence where the prisoner in fact remains in detention after review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2629.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2635.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the former, the state declares the prisoner socially ineligible evermore.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2635.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2647.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the latter, it is the personal characteristics of the prisoner and perhaps his inclination which require his or her indefinite but not permanent exclusion from society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2647.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2652.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is this difference that is at the heart of these applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2652.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2661.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants argue that in the sentencing context, a violation of Article 3 arises in at least three circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2661.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2666.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, where the length of the sentence is grossly disproportionate to the offending.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2666.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2671.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, where the effect of its imposition is to destroy human dignity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2671.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2680.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And thirdly, where the lack of any procedural mechanism to identify a breach, if it occurs, may lead to violation without remedy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2680.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2687.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the first case, a sentence, fixed term or indeterminate, may be manifestly disproportionate to the offending.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2687.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2691.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, a 30-year sentence for stealing a loaf of bread.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2691.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2695.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do not put the applicants in this category.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2695.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2703.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have acknowledged that the imposition of a life sentence does not ordinarily violate Article 3, even if de facto it lasts until death.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2703.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2708.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, where the offender remains a danger to society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2708.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2719.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The problem identified in these applications arises not because the applicants have life sentences, not even that they have lifelong sentences, but because they have no prospect of release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2719.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2734.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is this which raises the second issue, the imposition of whole life sentence is precious human dignity from the outset, ab initio, as it removes any chance and therefore any hope of release in the future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2734.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2742.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The individual is left in a position of hopelessness, whereby he cannot progress whatever occurs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2742.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2749.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In excluding the prisoner from society on a permanent basis, it renders a human life devoid of meaning and hope.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2749.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2753.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the sentence thereby becomes inhuman and degrading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2753.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2757.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, it becomes pointless for society as well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2757.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2768.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In respect of this point, we note and refer to the unchallenged evidence of psychologists relating to the first and second applicants, which the court has.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2768.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2785.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We cannot better the words of the minority dissenting opinion in the current case, and I quote, the Article 3 problem does not consist merely in keeping the prisoner in detention longer than would be justified, as suggested in the domestic judgments that we have cited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2785.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2796.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kafka shows that it consists, equally importantly, of depriving him of any hope for the future, however tenuous that hope may be, unquote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2796.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2807.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, the imposition of such a sentence of hopelessness removes any incentive or reason for the prisoner to conform, to behave, to address his or her criminal behavior.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2807.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2814.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also removes any reason for the state to provide treatment or courses by which the prisoner can progress.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2814.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2819.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such prisoners will inevitably spend decades in the highest security conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2819.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2829.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They will be a danger to other inmates and prison staff, and will form a cohort of outcasts within the system, corroding its rehabilitative purpose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2829.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2844.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third category where Article 3 may arise is in the execution of the sentence, where continuing detention until death may become disproportionate to the penological justifications for its imposition, because of countervailing justifications for release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2844.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2851.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the category implicitly recognized by the judgment of the fourth section of paragraph 92.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2851.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2858.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Without any mechanism for review, a violation will result in at least some cases at some indeterminate point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2858.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2865.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Without any domestic procedure for review, how could such a violation ever be assessed or remedied?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2865.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2871.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have noted that the second category, the effect of imposition of such sentences, is substantive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2871.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2873.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third is procedural.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2873.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2878.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both in our submission result in violation of Article 3 at the present time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2878.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2882.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the purpose or utility of whole life terms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2882.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2887.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What penological justification there is for a sentence of permanent exclusion from society?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2887.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2896.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The four key justifications for sentences of imprisonment are often said to be punishment, deterrence, public protection, and rehabilitation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2896.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2905.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In essence, the only one of those that applies here, the real penological justification for whole life imprisonment, is punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2905.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2913.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Deterrence and public protection are dealt with by the imposition of the life sentence itself, perhaps with a long minimum term.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2913.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2916.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The lack of a review is unlikely to touch on either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2916.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2918.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Rehabilitation clearly does not arise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2921.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2927.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Punishment, retribution, therefore, appears to be the only applicable justification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2927.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2939.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government argues that there are some types of offending that are so serious, so extreme, that it is entitled to determine that lifelong imprisonment should have followed for punishment and retribution alone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2939.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2944.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On an arithmetic level, there may be some logic to that approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2944.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2948.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The taking of one life should incur a tariff of, say, 15 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2948.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2952.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Might not a multiple killer justify a whole life sentence?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2952.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2962.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the answer to that must be that sentencing cannot be merely reduced to mathematics and must take account of other penological reasons which may justify release in the future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2962.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2971.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can it really be maintained that a person cannot reform, cannot atone, after several decades of incarceration?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2971.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2981.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And even if it be correct in principle that some crimes are so serious that lifelong punishment could be justified, why must such sentence be irreducible?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2981.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2988.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the UK, the irreducible lifelong sentence is a very recent invention indeed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2988.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2992.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The history of whole life tariffs was traced in the domestic case of Hindley.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2992.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2997.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The United Kingdom has only had whole life sentences since 1988.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2997.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3008.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And until the 2003 Criminal Justice Act, such sentences were de facto reducible because of the policy of review of such sentences after 25 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3008.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3015.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government asserts that it is for member states, including the UK, to determine their own penal policies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3015.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3017.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We agree.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3017.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3023.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But they must do so in compliance with their international obligations, including the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3023.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3032.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is no answer to those obligations simply to say that there are some offenses which are so serious as to merit irreducible lifelong incarceration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3032.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3039.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Without review, the policy considers only one penological issue, punishment, to the exclusion of all others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3039.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3053.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that this is not a position that reflects settled or longstanding domestic penological opinion, but is a recent departure from previously recognized domestic and international policy, certainly within Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3053.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3063.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The golden thread of such policy has been the moving away from capital and corporal punishments to rehabilitation and resocialization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3063.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3074.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The longstanding approach to punishment in English law, the nature and purpose of imprisonment for the last century, was set in the oft-quoted speech of Winston Churchill, Home Secretary in 1910.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3074.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3108.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I quote, a calm and dispassionate recognition of the rights of the accused against the state, and even of convicted criminals against the state, a constant heart-searching by all charged with the duty of punishment, a desire and eagerness to rehabilitate in the world of industry, all those who have paid their dues in the hard coinage of punishment, tireless efforts towards the discovery of curative and regenerating processes, and an unfaltering faith that there is a treasure, if only you can find it, in the heart of every man.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3108.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3121.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These are the symbols which, in the treatment of crime and criminals, mark and measure the stored-up strength of a nation, and are the signs and proof of the living virtue in it, unquote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3121.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3125.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We note the position before the International Criminal Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3125.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3137.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Rome Statute recognizes that there are offenses for which prisoners can be sentenced to life imprisonment, often for the most serious of offenses, war crimes and genocide amongst them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3137.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3142.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But under the statute, these are automatically subject to review after 25 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3142.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3148.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is difficult to understand why, in 2003, the UK ceased the same practice of 25-year review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3148.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3155.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Certainly, little explanation has been forthcoming from the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3155.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3166.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Parliament, the question arose earlier this year when an amendment to the law to reintroduce a review in such cases was proposed by Lord Lloyd, an ex-lawlord.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3166.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3174.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the course of the debate, the noted jurist, Lord Panick, said, and I quote, The argument for the amendment is very simple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3174.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3187.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is simply wrong in principle for anyone, however wicked, to be told that they must spend the whole of their life in prison with no possibility of review, however long it's going to elapse, and whatever progress they make.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3187.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3196.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is unlikely that a murderer who's committed such grave crimes that he has received a whole life tariff will ever make the progress that would make release appropriate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3196.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3210.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the point surely is that basic humanity demands that the offender has a chance, however remote, to prove to others and himself that he can live a worthwhile life, end quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3210.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3221.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither have we had much more of an explanation in the course of these proceedings as to why the 25-year review was abolished in 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3221.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3242.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, it is of note that the second applicant was sent a letter dated the 15th of December, 1994, which the court has, which promised a review at the 10 and 25-year stage of his whole life sentence, and where appropriate, every five years thereafter, a promise which has not been kept due to the abolition of the policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3242.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3247.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before I leave this part of the argument, I have been referring advisedly to the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3247.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3264.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I remind the court, however, that in Scotland, since the 2001 Convention Rights Compliance Scotland Act, minimum terms which determine when the review of a life sentence will take place have to be set in every case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3264.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3267.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There can be no whole life tariff in Scotland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3267.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3275.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Northern Ireland, there is provision for whole life tariffs, but subject to review at any time by the Secretary of State.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3275.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3283.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As already noted from Les Gers, it is undeniable that pan-European penal policy is against irreducible lifelong sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3283.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3306.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Resolutions and recommendations of the Committee of Ministers and the European prison rules have all expressly stated that rehabilitation and resocialization should be a part of all prison sentences, and no prisoner should be left without hope, without possibility of redemption, as we've demonstrated with a detailed analysis of such documents in our written submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3306.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3324.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As long ago as 1976, the general report of the subcommittee, which drafted Resolution 76-2 to the Committee of Ministers relating to long-term prisoners, starkly asserted it is inhuman to imprison a person for life without any hope of release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3324.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3335.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Further recommendations and the European prison rules have made clear that resocialization and rehabilitation are required components of all prison sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3335.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3345.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The CPT, too, has indicated that conditional release, and I note distinguishing such from compassionate release, is a requirement of all prison sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3345.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3365.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Recently, the CPT, in a report relating to Switzerland that we've submitted to the court, at paragraph 118, unequivocally asserted, and I quote, the CPT considers that it is inhuman to imprison a person for life with no real hope of release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3365.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3379.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has been quite unable to identify any pan-European policy or document, which even accepts the proposition that any prison sentence can be designed to last until death and be irreducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3379.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3386.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The very notion of an irreducible lifelong sentence is contrary to the prevailing direction of European penal policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3386.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3395.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An irreducible lifelong sentence is a sentence of permanent social exclusion, the only such sentence available since the abolition of the death penalty.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3395.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3412.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whereas it is undoubtedly for national systems to determine their own penal policies and to determine their own sentencing ranges, they must do so not only within the law, but also within their international obligations, which include compliance with the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3412.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3420.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It must be recognized that the UK is very significantly out of step in its policies towards long-term prisoners generally.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3420.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3433.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It currently has more indeterminate sentenced prisoners, life sentence prisoners, than all of the other Council of Europe states put together, more than 13,000 in England and Wales alone.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3433.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3444.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Comparative studies referred to in our written submissions, particularly by Professor Vanzil-Schmidt, note that the UK is almost alone in Europe in having irreducible lifelong sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3444.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3452.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And a few exceptions seem to have developed systems where, by the terms, can be commuted or be subject to pardon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3452.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3454.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is not the case in the UK.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3454.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3462.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this has not been suggested to be a case by the government at any stage of these proceedings or elsewhere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3462.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3473.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Whereas the prevailing pan-European policy does not bind this court, it is plainly of strong persuasive effect in interpreting the living instrument that is the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3473.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3475.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3475.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3487.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I've already noted that the dissenting opinion argued that the majority had adopted a flawed analysis of the Kafkaris case by the Court of Appeal in Biba.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3487.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3492.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This flawed analysis had been accepted by the House of Lords in Wellington.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3492.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3501.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the words of the majority in this case were repeated in the recent extradition cases, Harkins and Baba Ahmed, as already referred to.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3501.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3506.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We respectfully agree with the analysis of the dissenting judges for reasons which I will develop.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3506.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3518.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But before I do, it is a matter of note that neither Biba nor Wellington nor the extradition cases were ultimately held to involve irreducible lifelong sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3518.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3526.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A proper and careful analysis of Kafkaris is therefore vital to the proper resolution of these applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3526.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3537.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, it is clear that the government of Cyprus conducted Kafkaris on the basis that an irreducible lifelong sentence was indeed incompatible with Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3537.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3550.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such is clear from paragraphs 86 and 89, where the government cited the proper test as, and I quote, whether an applicant had been deprived of all hope of obtaining an adjustment to his sentence, unquote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3550.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3553.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The position could not be much clearer than that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3553.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3560.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And nothing said in the court's assessment from 95 in any way disputed that test.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3560.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3566.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that the court did not expressly state that an irreducible life term was incompatible with Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3566.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3572.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this was because the sentence under consideration was found by the majority to be reducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3572.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3578.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is that fact that led to the guarded language used at 98 of the judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3578.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3590.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If there were any doubt that the court would have held an irreducible sentence incompatible, one only has to look at the next section of the judgment headed application of the above principles to the instant case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3590.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3593.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment continued at 100.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3593.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3604.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the instant case, the court must determine whether the sentence of life imprisonment imposed on the applicant in the particular circumstances has removed any prospect of release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3604.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3609.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was no suggestion that if so, the court had then to look at any other factor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3609.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3620.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court determined at 107 that given there were some prospects for release, the indeterminate nature of the sentence was not incompatible with Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3620.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3627.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is important, too, to remember that seven of the judges found a breach of Article 3 on the facts in Kafkaris.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3627.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3635.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And one of the majority made plain in his concurring opinion that he would have found a violation had the sentence been irreducible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3635.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3640.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does not follow that the remaining nine judges believed otherwise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3640.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3650.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So returning to the domestic authorities in cases which did not ultimately involve irreducible sentences, we respectfully agree with the minority opinion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3650.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3665.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the current case, the Court of Appeal and House of Lords misinterpreted the guarded language used in Kafkaris as indicating that irreducible life terms would not necessarily violate Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3665.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3670.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We note what has already been said about Lord Bingham, and we'll return to that perhaps in reply.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3670.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3693.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in the Privy Council case of de Boucherville versus Mauritius, he took a similar view to that of the minority in this case, that Kafkaris, decided as it was on the irreducibility point, would have determined irreducible life sentences violated Article 3 per se if it had fallen for determination.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3693.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3701.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Properly interpreted, Kafkaris gives no vindication to irreducible life sentences whatsoever, quite the opposite.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3701.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3715.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, we note the domestic courts decided that UK whole life tariffs did not constitute irreducible terms because of Section 30, which allows for compassionate release where the prisoner has but a few weeks to live.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3715.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3721.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This argument was rightly rejected by six of the seven judges in the fourth section of the present applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3721.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3734.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a matter of domestic law, release from any life sentence can only be directed by the parole board, which simply cannot happen in a whole life case because there's no review, or by Section 30.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3734.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3745.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although the government have tried to reassert this argument, we respectfully say that the fourth section was correct on this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3745.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3754.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Release only available on medical prognosis that the prisoner has weeks to live cannot make an otherwise lifelong sentence reducible in any meaningful way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3754.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3763.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The suggestion that this power could be stretched to accommodate Article 3, we say, is misconceived because that would plainly be ultra varies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3763.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3774.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has not been suggested by the domestic courts or by the government in these proceedings that any other prerogative power allows for early release of UK whole life prisoners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3774.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3782.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We note there has not been a single compassionate release of a whole life tariff prisoner in the history of such sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3785.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3788.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can I make one further point about the domestic cases?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3788.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3806.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The domestic cases suggest that irreducible lifelong terms do not contravene Article 3 because lifelong detention is justified for punishment and retribution alone by the seriousness of the offending in these cases, which does not recede over time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3806.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3814.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If this were so, how could it be the case that Article 3 issues might arise for determination in the future?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3814.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3819.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is a situation which we say belongs in a work by Franz Kafka.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3819.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3839.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit that however seriously offending, there will always be a need for a review at some point, a mechanism by which the balance of penological reasons for continued detention or release can be resolved and that retribution cannot simply override of the penological justifications evermore.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3839.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3843.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In conclusion, may I make the following points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3843.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3854.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, we note that respect for human dignity has been recognized as fundamental to the protection of human rights in most of the basic documents.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3854.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3871.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The cases that we've cited link human dignity to the issue of irreducible lifelong sentences as being inherently inhuman and degrading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3871.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3878.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, pan-European penal policy is unequivocally against irreducible lifelong sentences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3878.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3886.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, the majority appear to have based their decision on the misconceived analysis of Kafkaris by the domestic courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3886.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3904.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When viewed in that context, we say that the United Kingdom government position is untenable, and we urge this court to say that the time has come to state unequivocally that irreducible lifelong detention is a violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3904.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3904.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3907.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3910.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Weatherby.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3910.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3914.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the judges and ask if there are questions. Judge Sicilianos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3919.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3921.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3921.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3923.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3923.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3927.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first is for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3927.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3929.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Perry, if I got it correctly,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3929.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3939.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>you have said that, and I quote, long-life incarceration is imposed for the purposes of pure punishment, end of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3939.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3947.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I ask you whether you conceive punishment as the only purpose of a life sentence?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3947.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3952.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question goes to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3952.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3955.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Weatherby, you allege that in this case,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3955.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3958.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>there would be a violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3958.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3971.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If I understood correctly, your written submissions, as well as your pleadings this morning, you seem to suggest that such a violation would be both procedural and substantive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3971.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3980.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Could you please analyze a bit more the nature of the violation you invoke, taking into account the case law of the court in this respect?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3980.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3980.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3982.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3982.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3982.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3985.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Mahoney, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paul Mahoney</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3988.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3991.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3991.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3998.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should like to put a question to the United Kingdom government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3998.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4060.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should like to know whether the government have given consideration to redrafting the relevant prison service order so as to bring it into line with the explanations that the government themselves have given to the three applicants and to the court in the present proceedings in relation to the applicable law governing the exercise by the Secretary of State of his discretionary power to release under Section 30 of the 1997 Act, and in particular, in relation to the duty incumbent on the Secretary of State by virtue of the Human Rights Act 1998 to take into account considerations relating to Article III of the Convention, as well as terminal illness and physical incapacity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4060.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4060.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4061.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4062.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4062.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4065.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4075.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4076.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4076.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4093.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to know if the government can give a single example where the Secretary of State exercised his power of release under the 1997 Act for penalogical grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4093.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4095.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A single example.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4095.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4095.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4097.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4098.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge lemmens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4102.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4128.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Could I simply extend that question and ask the government not only for examples where, in fact, the Secretary of State exercised his power to release prisoners serving a life sentence, but could you give examples of situations where it could be imagined that after some time, the continued detention becomes unjustified?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4128.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4135.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So not necessarily situations that have actually occurred, but which, according to the government, might justify a release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4138.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4141.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, no other questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4141.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4149.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now we will have a break now and we will resume our hearing at 10.45.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4223.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4226.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated. The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4226.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4230.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Perry, please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4232.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4241.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, members of the court, may I make, first of all, six short points in response</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4241.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4244.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to the submissions advanced on behalf of the applicants?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4244.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4252.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if it pleases the court, may I then move on to address the questions that have been put to the government?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4252.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4259.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the six short points that we would make in response to the applicants'</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4259.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4261.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>arguments are these.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4261.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4284.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, insofar as reliance is placed on the opinions and reasoning of Judge Bratzer in Kafkaris, we simply note that he was part of the majority in the instant cases and adopted the analysis which had been adopted by the domestic courts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4284.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4287.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's the first point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4287.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4297.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second point that the government would wish to make concerns Section 30 of the Crime Sentences Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4297.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4322.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the point that we would make in relation to that at this stage is that in Bieber, Lord Phillips made it clear that Section 30 would have to be interpreted in such a way so as to permit release if continued detention amounted to inhuman or degrading treatment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4322.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4326.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>See Lord Phillips at paragraph 48.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4326.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4348.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, and this is perhaps of some significance given the issues before the court, the court will recall that in the second applicant's case, his sentence was reviewed by the High Court in 2008 and he appealed to the Court of Appeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4348.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4367.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Lord Judge presiding over the Court of Appeal also said that if the time were to arise when his continued detention was inhuman or degrading, then the Secretary of State would be required to exercise his powers under Section 30.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4367.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4371.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if he did not do so, he would be subject to supervision by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4371.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4383.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I just give the court the reference to remind the court, it's at paragraph 34 of the second applicant's case before the Court of Appeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4383.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4385.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The third point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4385.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4396.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On behalf of the applicants, it has been submitted that the government could easily revert to the pre-2003 position.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4396.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4402.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I just explain the government's position in relation to this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4402.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4409.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the pre-2003 position was a process involving the executive.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4409.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4430.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The whole point of the reforms enacted in 2003 was to judicialize the process and ensure that the independent and impartial judiciary were responsible for setting tariffs and, in appropriate cases, setting whole life terms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4430.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4443.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, both the second and third applicants in this case have had their cases considered by the High Court because they were transitional cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4443.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4458.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second applicant in May 2008 and the third applicant in June 2008 and, of course, the first applicant was sentenced for offenses committed after the new scheme had come into effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4458.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4471.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do wish to emphasize that a review would involve a radical change, given that the sentence originally imposed is imposed by a judicial officer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4471.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4479.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, if the applicant's argument is correct, it is difficult to see where it would stop.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4479.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4487.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why is not every sentence, every determinate sentence, subject to a review to ensure that there are good penological reasons for its continuation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4487.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4490.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any determinate or indeterminate sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4490.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4500.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we submit that the judicialization of the process is the important point to note in relation to the review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4500.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4515.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fourth point is that an amendment, a proposed amendment to the legislation, has been rejected by the House of Lords in Parliament.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4515.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4528.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the very point that is advanced by the applicant has been rejected by Parliament, at least the upper chamber in the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4528.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4536.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we submit that it would not be appropriate for it to be achieved by judicial fiat.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4536.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4549.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fifth point, we do not accept that there is a settled consensus in sentencing policy in this area, as the court noted in Kafkaris.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4549.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4574.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also rely on the pan-European document or pan-European Union document, the European arrest warrant, to which we've already made reference, which makes it clear that there is no mandatory prohibition on the surrender between Union states of those who've been sentenced to imprisonment for more than 20 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4574.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4588.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the sixth and final point in response to the applicant's arguments, the government do not accept that its position is either irrational or emotional.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4588.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4593.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has been supported by successive Lords Chief Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4593.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4598.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has been supported by the House of Lords in its judicial capacity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4598.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4608.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it has been supported most recently by the Court of Appeal, specially convened to consider this very issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4608.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4611.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So Mr. President, members of the court, those are the points that we make in reply.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4611.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4619.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I then turn to answer the questions posed by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4619.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4633.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the first question is whether pure punishment is the only purpose of the whole life tariff.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4633.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4636.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I just make this point first of all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4636.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4647.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Criminal Justice Act 2003 contains statutory guidance on the purposes of punishment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4647.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4662.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they include punishment, the reduction of crime and deterrence, public protection, reform and rehabilitation, and the making of reparations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4662.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4684.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However the minimum term, whether it be a term of finite years or the whole life term, which is equivalent to the tariff period, what's sometimes called the tariff period, is imposed for the purposes of punishment and deterrence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4684.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4695.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So whether it's the minimum term of 30 years, the 30 year period is concerned with punishment and deterrence, as is the whole life term.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4695.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4710.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is explained by the Court of Appeal in the recent judgment, Lord Judge presiding, in the four cases where these matters were considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4710.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4712.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those are the government's response to the first question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4712.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4716.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope we've addressed those points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4716.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4734.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second question, has there been any redrafting of the relevant prison service order to reflect the government's position and the domestic court's analysis of Section 30?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4734.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4738.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The short answer to the question is no.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4738.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4743.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we would submit it doesn't matter for these reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4743.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4751.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, Section 30 is a provision contained in primary legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4751.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4777.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the Human Rights Act 1998 ensures that any public authority of which the Secretary of State is one must act compatibly with convention rights, and primary legislation must be interpreted compatibly with convention rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4777.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4803.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That Section 30 could be deployed and would be deployed in the manner for which the government contend is clear from the decision of the Court of Appeal in Beaver, to which reference has already been made, and the decision of the Court of Appeal in the second applicant's case, where express reference was made to Section 30.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4803.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4817.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Release would not be ultraviaries because the Minister or the Secretary of State would be required to order release if continued detention were inhuman or degrading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4817.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4829.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would be mandated by the Minister's obligation to act in accordance with the human rights contained in the first schedule to the Human Rights Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4829.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4834.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I hope the government have responded to that question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4834.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4847.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The next question, we were asked if we could provide a single example of a whole life order prisoner being released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4847.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4871.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I, for these purposes, say that we dealt with this in our original observations in April 2011, and the short answer is no prisoner serving a whole life term has ever been released on compassionate grounds under Section 30.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4871.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4879.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, we made two points, having set out the position we made two points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4879.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4884.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, it's unsurprising that no one has been released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4884.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4893.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are only 42 prisoners, there were 41 at that time, there are now 42 prisoners serving such a term.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4893.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4918.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, those who are serving lifelong terms have, by definition, committed the most heinous crimes known to English law, and there has been a judicial determination that a whole life term is necessary for the purposes of punishment and deterrence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4918.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4942.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the judicial nature of the sentence, it's hardly surprising that it would only be in exceptional circumstances that the executive should have the power to mitigate the sentence, and when exercising his powers under Section 30, the Secretary of State is certainly not acting as a second court of appeal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4942.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4949.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But he would be required to consider whether continued detention was inhuman or degrading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4949.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4956.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, may I finally, on this aspect, also invite the Court's attention to certain</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4956.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4979.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>observations made by Lord Hoffman in the Wellington case, where this point was being made, as it was being made in the observations made to this Court in the extradition cases involving the United States, that no one has been released, either under the governor-released provisions in the United States or otherwise.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4979.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4985.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And Lord Hoffman stated that the argument on analysis created a paradox.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4985.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4990.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The more horrendous the crime, the less likely was release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4990.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5007.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But on the argument that because there had been no release, that meant there was a breach of some right, it meant that the more horrendous the crime, the stronger the claim would be not to be extradited.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5007.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5018.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Transposed to the domestic context, the short point is the whole life term has been imposed by an independent and impartial tribunal to reflect the seriousness of the offending.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5018.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5030.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it would be paradoxical to conclude that because there's been no order for release by the executive, the sentence was irreducible or that there'd been otherwise a violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5030.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5050.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, the government were asked to, if it could conceive of circumstances in which a case might arise where someone would be released.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5050.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5056.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On behalf of the government, we submit it's difficult to conceive of such a case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5056.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5068.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We submit the fact that it's difficult to conceive of such a case suggests that the position is more theoretical, or the hypothesis is more theoretical than real.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5068.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5084.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to say at the outset there should be a review to deal with the unlikely hypothesis, we submit should not mean the difference between a violation and non-violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5084.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5105.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We do, however, rely on the Section 30 mechanism, and we do invite the court to consider, as of course the court has repeatedly stated it does, the facts of the instant cases where it is not suggested that continued detention does not serve any penological purpose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5105.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5110.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, Mr. President, those are the government's response to the questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5110.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5115.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unless the government can assist the court further, those are our submissions today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5119.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5122.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Mr. Perry. Mr. Weatherby, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5127.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5145.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Sicilianos asked us to clarify our submissions in relation to substantive and procedural violations, and I will seek to do so in short order.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5145.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5159.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say that the substantive violation is the effect at imposition, the effect now, on a prisoner serving an irreducible lifelong term.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5159.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5171.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It puts a prisoner who conceivably might be 25 years old in a position of abject hopelessness.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5171.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5182.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is not a matter of sympathy for the prisoner who will necessarily have committed heinous crimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5182.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5190.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a matter of the humanity that the state should be required to show.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5190.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5209.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government have made it clear that their position is, in light of the Chamber's judgment and other authorities, that in effect there is no necessity for any kind of review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5209.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5220.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, there appears to be a concession that there is a possibility of an Article 3 issue arising in the future.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5220.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5248.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is what I earlier described as Kafkaesque, because the government assert that it is perfectly lawful under the Convention to have a system which declares the permanent exclusion of the prisoner from society, but where there may be a violation in the future, but with no available process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5248.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5262.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we say that the imposition of a lifelong irreducible sentence puts the prisoner in a position of hopelessness, and that is a substantive breach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5262.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5273.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In terms of a procedural violation, we take the argument of the dissenting opinion in the Chamber's judgments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5273.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5299.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, in effect, that there must be a possibility of an Article 3 issue arising in the future, and therefore there must be a review mechanism now, so that the prisoner and everybody else is in the position of knowing what the future holds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5299.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5313.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me say that we accept that what we describe as the substantive and the procedural arguments may in fact be very much two sides to the same argument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5313.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5328.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In respect of the case law, we say that the domestic authorities and those of this Court acknowledge that an Article 3 issue may arise at some point in these cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5328.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5355.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say that the Court may gain some assistance from the case law that we have cited in our written submissions, and in particular from the 1986 German war crimes case, which asserted that even the most heinous of offending should not lead to the absence of a review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5355.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5376.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It must not preclude a review, because the balance of penological justifications, even where there is very serious offending indeed, is prone to change over time, particularly with maturity and age.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5376.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5387.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I trespass a little on the questions that were asked to the Government, if very swiftly?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5387.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5412.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would say in respect of the first question that whole life tariffs under the statutory guidance that has been cited to you do in fact deal with punishment and deterrence only, and therefore do not deal with and do not accommodate the other penological justifications going forward.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5412.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5426.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Can I address the issue of the Secretary of State's policy regarding Section 30, and whether it could in fact be changed to accommodate Article 3?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5426.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5455.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Human Rights Act in the UK requires the Executive and allows the Courts to read down legislation to make such provisions compatible with Convention rights, but it can only do so if such can be accommodated within the nature and purpose of that primary legislation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5455.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5466.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise the domestic provisions under the Human Rights Act are simply a declaration that the legislation is incompatible with the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5466.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5490.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is that point which leads to our suggestion that any attempt to accommodate Article 3 within Section 30 would be outside of the plain statutory purpose of that provision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5490.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5499.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Section 30 expressly refers to compassionate release and not conditional release.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5499.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5511.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I remind the Court of the submissions I made earlier about the clear distinction made between the two, in particular by the CPT.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5511.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5525.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If Section 30 was expressed in such a way as other penological justifications could be considered, then the position might be different.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5525.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5538.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in common with six of the seven judges in the Chamber's cases, we respectfully agree that Section 30 does not provide an answer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5538.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5563.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me also say that the recent Court of Appeal case of Oakes, which my friend has referred to, is a restatement of the domestic position, but it makes no suggestion that the Chamber's judgment on this point, the Section 30 point, was wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5563.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5572.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now briefly reply to a few of the points made by the Government today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5572.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5578.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Staying with the recent case of Oakes in the Court of Appeal, which, as my hon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5578.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5597.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Friend has indicated, delivered a judgment a week before this hearing, the reason that we did not address it in detail in our submissions earlier is that it plainly does not take these matters any further.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5597.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5610.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It simply restates the Bieber position without the Section 30 issue, to which I have already spoken.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5610.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5627.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will say before I leave the Oakes case that the Government earlier said that Lord Bingham upheld the legality of whole life tariffs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5627.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5632.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is correct so far as that statement goes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5632.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5640.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the case of Hindley, he ruled that whole life tariffs were lawful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5640.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5651.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, that was in the context of the previous regime, where there was the express 25-year review.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5651.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5667.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have already indicated that a proper analysis of the Debucheville case versus Mauritius would indicate that Lord Bingham would have taken a very different view of the current regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5667.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5690.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I refer to the House of Lords judgments in Hindley, in particular to a passage by Lord Steyn, which upheld Lord Bingham's position on whole life tariffs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5690.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5708.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On instructions, counsel for the Secretary of State volunteered and gave assurances to the House that this statement means that the Secretary of State is prepared to reconsider and review any whole life tariff decision from time to time, even in the absence of exceptional progress.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5708.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5727.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In these circumstances, counsel for the Secretary of State submitted that the policy of imposing a whole life tariff merely involves the expression of the current view of the Secretary of State that the requirements of retribution and deterrence make it inappropriate to release such a prisoner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5727.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5730.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It does not rule out reconsideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5730.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5748.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The views of Lord Bingham and the House of Lords in Hindley were to uphold not the current whole life system in the United Kingdom, but the previous one, which had a 25-year review mechanism built in.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5748.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5761.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Government say that the problem with the 25-year review is that the life sentence process was judicialised.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5761.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5776.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The discretion that the Executive had in a number of different respects was transferred to the judiciary, and therefore that is why the 25-year review went.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5776.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5800.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The simple answer to that submission, we say, is that such a review could easily be judicialised itself in that a review could be undertaken by the quasi-judicial body which considers other life sentence issues, the Parole Board for England and Wales.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5800.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5809.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So we say that there is no real difficulty in changing the system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5809.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5831.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In respect of the Government's position regarding a review, the Government put forward as a suggestion as to why there is no review, is that the chances of an Article 3 issue arising are tenuous?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5831.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5844.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We disagree with that submission for the reasons spelt out, and in particular we again make reference to the German jurisprudence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5844.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5870.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We say that where there is a possibility of a need to rebalance the penological justifications perhaps after 20 or 40 or even 60 years, as we say surely there must be, then there is a clear need for a review, and without such a review there is a substantive and procedural breach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5870.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5891.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally in respect of the extradition directive, we simply say that that directive was dealing with other issues and simply did not trespass into the realm within which this argument has been dealt.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5891.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5891.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unless I can be of assistance to the Court, those are our submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5896.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5899.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Weatherby.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5899.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5902.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5902.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5909.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5909.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5913.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5913.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5917.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5917.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5922.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5922.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5925.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
