<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>669718_10062020</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Good morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>10.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Good morning to all participants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>10.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>10.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>13.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>30.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome all participants to this first ever public hearing organized by the European Court of Human Rights with the use of video conferencing technology, which has been made necessary due to the COVID-19 health crisis.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>30.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>49.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Allow me to begin by thanking the applicant, the respondent government, and the third party intervenors for their cooperation in preparing this hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case of M.A. versus Denmark, which I now declare open.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>49.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>60.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should note before proceeding that this hearing is being recorded in its entirety and will be webcast in order to ensure its public character.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>60.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>68.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It will be available to the public on the court's website tomorrow, Thursday, June 11.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>68.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>81.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application in this case was lodged with the court on 30 January 2018 under Article 34 of the convention by a Syrian national, Mr. M.A.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>81.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>89.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was allocated to the fourth section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the rules of court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>89.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>96.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was communicated to the respondent government on 7 September 2018.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>96.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>106.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 19 November 2019, the chamber decided to relinquish jurisdiction in favor of the grand chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>106.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>121.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The commissioner for human rights of the Council of Europe has exercised her right under Article 36, paragraph 3 of the convention, to intervene in the proceedings before the grand chamber and submitted written observations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>121.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>142.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Leave to intervene under Article 36, paragraph 2 of the convention, and Rule 44, paragraph 3 of the rules of court was granted to the governments of Norway and Switzerland, the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, and the Danish Institute for Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>142.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>148.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At this hearing, the respondent government are represented by their agent, Mr. Michael Braad,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>148.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>152.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and their co-agent, Ms. Nina Holst-Christensen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>152.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>156.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are assisted by Ms. Lone  Zeuner, Ms. Moya-Louise Lindsay-Poulsen, Ms. Anna-Sophie Saugmann-Jensen, Mr. Øzlem Akar,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>163.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>169.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Christian Wegener, Mr. Niels Rune Brandt, Ms. Sarah Larsen Vaabengaard, and Ms. Sofie Bach Andersen, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>174.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>179.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mr. Christian Dahlager, lawyer,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>179.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>183.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and by Ms. Dorthe Kynde Nielsen, counsel.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>183.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>190.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Commissioner for Human Rights of the Council of Europe, Ms. Dunja Mijatović, will also participate in this hearing,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>190.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>197.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>pursuant to her right to intervene as a third party under Article 36, paragraph 3 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>197.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>202.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She is assisted by Ms. Anne Weber, advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>202.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>211.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the government of Switzerland were granted leave to participate in this hearing under Article 36, paragraph 2 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>211.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>214.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are represented by their agent, Mr. Alain Chablais,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>214.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>217.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>assisted by Ms. Dominique Steiger Leuba,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>217.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>221.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and Ms. Karen Mareike Hamann, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>221.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>226.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>226.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>237.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant and the representative of the third parties, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>237.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>239.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Braad for the government will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>239.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>242.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mr. Dahlager for the applicant,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>242.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>247.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and finally Ms. Mijatović and Mr. Chablais, third parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>247.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>249.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Braad.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>249.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>249.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>252.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>263.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Distinguished members of the court, it's an honor to appear before you on behalf of the Danish government, in particular on a day like today, a historic day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>263.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>268.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And despite the initial difficulties here, I hope that things will be working well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>268.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>273.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have had indications that, yeah, the technical side of things will be working well.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>273.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>275.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I hope that will be the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>275.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>278.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, please mark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>278.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>287.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case today concerns Article 8 of the European Convention on Human Rights, as well as Article 14, taken in conjunction with Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>287.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>301.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The issue at hand is the postponement of family reunification for persons granted temporary subsidiary protection based on the general situation in the home country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>301.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>312.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the government's opinion, the heart of the matter, when assessing the compatibility of the convention with the contested Danish rules, is the following question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>312.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>330.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Do beneficiaries of subsidiary protection who have fled a general situation in their home country, do they enjoy the same favorable family reunification rights as refugees under the 1951 Refugee Convention?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>330.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>336.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's a fundamental question, obviously of great importance to the individuals involved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>336.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>352.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's also a very important question for countries around Europe and their efforts to manage and to absorb recent years' rising influx from regions of conflict, and to do so in a responsible and balanced way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>352.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>364.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The answer to that question may have quite far-reaching consequences for the immigration policies of a number of European countries, including my own.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>364.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>378.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will begin my intervention with a few words on the facts of the case, and I will then turn to the specific Danish three-year rule, including an outline of its background, and I will address the question of its compatibility with Article 8 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>378.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>386.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will then conclude with a question of Article 14, taken in conjunction with Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>386.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>389.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the present case concerns a refusal</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>389.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>411.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to grant family reunification to the applicant's wife on the grounds that the applicant had not held his residence permit under Section 7, Paragraph 3 of the Danish Aliens Act for the preceding three years, and because no exceptional circumstances warranted reunification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>411.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>426.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, this refusal has been upheld by the Independent Immigration Appeals Board in Denmark, by the High Court in Denmark, and also by the Supreme Court of Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>426.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>437.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should mention that the applicant and the applicant's wife have since then been reunited in Denmark in September 2019.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>437.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>440.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I will now focus on Article 8 of the convention</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>440.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>447.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and the statutory postponement of the access to family reunification for three years under Danish law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>447.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>471.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This three-year rule, or waiting period, as it has been referred to, reflects how the Danish legislature has interpreted the positive obligations flowing from Article 8 of the convention in cases concerning family reunification with beneficiaries of temporary protection status who have fled a general situation in their home country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>471.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>486.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The rule reflects the basic view that this group does not generally have a right to family reunification under Article 8 within the first three years of a stay in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>486.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>495.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, this is due to the generally more uncertain and temporary nature of this group's need for protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>495.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>507.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, if exceptional circumstances apply, within the first three years of stay in Denmark, also persons in this group are entitled to family reunification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>507.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>527.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Perhaps I should add here that in the period from mid-February 2015 to the end of July 2017, exemptions were made in 79 cases concerning spouses and children out of a total of 309 decided applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>527.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>536.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that equals exemptions in approximately 25% of the cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>536.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>539.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the court has not yet dealt with the question</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>539.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>550.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>whether beneficiaries of subsidiary protection enjoy a similarly favorable family reunification right as refugees covered by the 1951 convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>550.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>559.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The existing case law on refugees' right to family reunification, including, for instance, the court's rulings in Tandem-O-Sinka v. France case,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>559.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>569.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>concerns refugees covered by the 1951 convention and not other groups of beneficiaries of international protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>569.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>589.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for the first time, the court has now presented with the question a person who is not a refugee under the 1951 refugee convention but who is a beneficiary of subsidiary protection and who has fled a general situation in the home country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>589.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>603.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Does this person have a right to the same favorable family reunification procedure as refugees covered by the 1951 convention?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>603.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>610.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My government's answer to that question is no.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>610.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>627.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before I elaborate on the reasons why we find that the Danish three-year rule is compatible with the convention, I will briefly outline the specific Danish asylum and family reunification legislation and its background.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>627.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>639.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Traditionally, and until the 2015 amendment to the Aliens Act, Danish asylum law operated with only two categories of persons granted international protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>639.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>655.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first category being persons granted so-called convention status, referring to persons covered by the 1951 refugee convention and given residence permit pursuant to section 7, paragraph 1 of the Danish Aliens Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>655.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>666.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second category being persons granted subsidiary protection status and given residence permit due to personal grounds pursuant to section 7, paragraph 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>666.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>682.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is granted when the person due to personal grounds and not due to the general situation in a country risks the death penalty, torture, inhumane or degrading treatment in the country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>682.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>692.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In essence, no distinction was made between these two categories, access to family reunification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>692.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>704.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both categories were and still are eligible for family reunification from the time they are granted asylum in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>704.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>708.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, Mr. President, why did Denmark amend its legislation</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>708.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>716.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and introduce a new temporary protection status for persons fleeing from the general situation in their country?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>716.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>729.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And why did Denmark generally postpone the right to family reunification for this new group, initially for one year and later for three years?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>729.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>739.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think to better understand this, it's necessary to take a look at the factual developments in Denmark from 2012 and onwards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>739.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>757.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From 2012 and onwards, Denmark saw a very significant increase in the number of asylum applicants and a subsequent increase in recognised asylum claims, in particular stemming from the conflict in Syria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>757.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>761.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Numbers more than doubled over the course of a few years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>761.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>772.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can refer you to Table 1 and 2 of the statistics in Annex 6 to our memorial of 27 January this year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>772.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>783.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the spring of 2015, Denmark was per capita the fifth largest EU destination for asylum seekers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>783.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>801.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also in the period from 2013 to 2017, Syrian nationals represented the highest number of asylum applicants in Denmark, and in 2014 alone amounted to half of all asylum applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>801.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>817.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The percentage of successful asylum claims from Syrian nationals decided by the Danish Immigration Service has been at a steady level, between 96 and 99 per cent from 2013 and on.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>817.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>845.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr President, also another development should be mentioned as part of the overall background, the court's judgement in June 2011 in the Sufi and Elmi case, applying for the first time the principle for Somali nationals that everyone present in Mogadishu City would be considered at a real risk of treatment prohibited by Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>845.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>863.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This led to a sudden spike in the percentage of successful asylum claims from Somali nationals decided by the Danish Immigration Service, rising from 22 per cent in 2011 to 93 per cent in 2012.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>863.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>874.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Many of the Somali nationals were granted subsidiary protection pursuant to Section 7, Paragraph 2 of the Danish Aliens Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>874.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>894.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not because they, due to individual circumstances, risked treatment prohibited by Article 3 of the Convention, but rather they were found to be covered by the principles set out in the Sufi and Elmi case due to the general situation in South and Central Somalia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>894.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>906.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, after two years, the court took to a re-evaluation of the situation in the case of KAB v. Sweden in September 2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>906.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>922.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Here the court concluded that the situation in Mogadishu was no longer of such a nature as to place everyone present in the city at a real risk of treatment contrary to Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>922.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>929.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Reading those two rulings from the court in conjunction made one thing very clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>929.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>946.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When a situation in a country or a specific area is so severe that one's life and human dignity is at risk solely from the very presence in that area, the situation is often very volatile.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>946.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>952.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It may change rather quickly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>952.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>955.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, Mr. President, it's on this overall background</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>955.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>966.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that the introduction in 2015 of Section 7, Paragraph 3 of the Danish Aliens Act, the temporary protection status should be considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>966.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>986.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 2015, given the sheer number of incoming asylum applicants, it became clear at political level that something had to be done to maintain control of the influx and to safeguard and maintain the cohesion of the Danish society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>986.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>994.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is a point that I wish to emphasize because we believe it's a crucial element in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>994.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1007.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Faced with an extraordinary and potentially overwhelming influx, governments across Europe found themselves compelled to react.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1007.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1012.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They did so not for short political gain.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1012.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1019.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They did so to maintain control and to safeguard cohesion of their societies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1019.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1028.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, something clearly had to be done, a response was called for.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1028.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1043.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the Danish legislator decided to subdivide the beneficiaries of subsidiary protection into two separate categories based on the type of protection needed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1043.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1046.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, a new distinction was introduced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1046.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1063.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was protection needed based on individual circumstance or was it called for merely based on the general situation in the home country, a situation foreseen to be of a more temporary nature?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1063.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1072.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the first category where protection needs were based on individual circumstances was entitled to subsidiary protection status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1072.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1082.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second group where protection needs were based on general situation was entitled to the new temporary protection status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1082.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1089.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to illustrate those distinctions, it may be helpful with an example.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1089.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1114.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A male Syrian asylum seeker liable for military service who refuses to serve the Syrian government will generally be considered to have a well-founded fear of persecution and will, as a main rule, be granted protection under section 7 paragraph 1 of the Danish Aliens Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1114.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1133.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But a male Syrian asylum seeker not liable for military service but who has fled the general situation in Syria will generally be granted protection under section 7 paragraph 3 of the Danish Aliens Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1133.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1141.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the reasoning behind the Danish legislator's 2015 amendment was twofold.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1141.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1145.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, it was to offer protection to asylum seekers for as long as needed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1145.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1158.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, and at the same time, seeking some assurance that when the protection was no longer needed, the persons could be returned to their home country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1158.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1169.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And allowing this context, perhaps to briefly quote from the preparatory works of the 2015 amending act also contained in annex 3 to our memorial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1169.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1186.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I quote, the government takes a humane approach to asylum policy and is fundamentally of the view that Denmark should take a share of the responsibility for the world's refugees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1186.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1201.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, it is necessary to acknowledge that Denmark cannot offer residency to all those who need help.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1201.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1219.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then it goes on to say about the specific new category, and I quote again, this group's need for protection is generally of a more temporary nature as the need for protection is based on a general situation which may change.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1219.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1236.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, a particularly serious situation of armed conflict creating a surge in asylum seekers for a period could change and make it possible for a large or small part of such asylum seekers to return to their country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1236.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1252.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With the bill, it is proposed to introduce a temporary protection status tailored to the need for protection of aliens who obtain asylum because of a particularly serious situation in their country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1252.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1255.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>End of quote.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1255.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1275.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it was then further proposed to give this new group with temporary protection status a more limited access to family reunification than beneficiaries of international protection, including refugees under the 51 convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1275.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1289.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was based on the fact that the nature of the stay of persons granted temporary protection is generally more uncertain and foreseen to be of a more limited duration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1289.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1304.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it was decided in 2015 that this new category would not generally be eligible for family reunification unless their residence permit was extended after one year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1304.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1327.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This waiting period was considered necessary in the interest of inter alia and effective immigration control as a continued access to family reunification from day one for this group would add to the immigration pressure and would add to the potential risk to the cohesion of the Danish society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1327.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1345.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The scheme put into force postponing family reunification for this group for one year was an attempt to find a measured approach to the increasing influx and to try and strike a fair balance between competing interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1345.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1360.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So a balance of on the one hand, the individual's interest in family reunification and on the other hand, the state's interest in maintaining an effective immigration control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1360.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1368.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When balancing these interests, the following factors in particular were taken into account.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1368.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1373.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the temporary stay of less than one year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1373.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1378.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, the limited ties with Denmark at this point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1378.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1401.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Third, the fact that the rules did not exclude but only generally postpone the access to family reunification and that family reunification would be possible even within the first year if special circumstances applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1401.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1405.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So Mr. President, turning now to the Danish amendment in 2016</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1405.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1414.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>whereby the postponement was extended from one year to three years, this was based on similar considerations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1414.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1419.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So why this further postponement of the access to family reunification, you may ask.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1419.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1430.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, between the 2015 amendment and the 2016 amendment, the asylum pressure on Europe rose to an unprecedented and quite overwhelming level.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1430.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1434.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In many ways, it came out of the government's control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1434.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1451.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'm sure we all recall the tragic media newscasts showing huge waves of desperate asylum seekers, men, women, and children moving north from Southern Europe to Germany and many of them trying to reach Denmark and Sweden by foot.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1451.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1475.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ID checks and the reintroduction of border control in Sweden led to a serious risk to public order and public security because in the Copenhagen area, within a short period of time, a very large number of illegal migrants in effect became stranded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1475.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1485.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This development was obviously part of the broader European migration crisis and it made it apparent for Denmark that the measures already taken were not sufficient.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1485.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1496.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Danish legislature therefore found it necessary to take further steps and one of them was the extension of the waiting period from one to three years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1496.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1508.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The legislature concluded that a large number of new arrivals could potentially jeopardise the successful integration efforts in Denmark, a country with a high redistribution of wealth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1508.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1529.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was considered necessary to further postpone the right to family reunification in order to manage the immigration pressure and to ensure sufficient capacity to integrate the large number of newly arrived individuals and secure the social cohesion of the Danish society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1529.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1548.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me also in this context draw your attention to the fact that the municipalities in Denmark are obligated to offer, for instance, housing, language training, employment initiatives for all persons granted international protection in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1548.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1556.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it's in light of all of this that the extension of the waiting period from one to three years shall be seen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1556.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1567.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The waiting period remains limited in time with a predictable and near certain path to family reunification after three years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1567.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1587.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It also includes an individual assessment in all cases of whether extraordinary circumstances apply so that an exemption may be granted and exceptions are in fact granted in a substantial number of cases, as I mentioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1587.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1591.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, the government obviously recognises that the number</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1591.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1597.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of asylum seekers arriving over the past years has decreased.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1597.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1606.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But that does not automatically mean that the logical response is to revert to the legislation of the past.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1606.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1618.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An extraordinary situation with significant potential risks of new overwhelming movements of refugees sadly still remains.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1618.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1625.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The refugee situation in and outside the EU is still complex and it's still volatile.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1625.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1645.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The complexity is characterised by a high degree of uncertainty and interchangeability as a result of inter-alia pressure on the external EU borders, accumulation of refugees and migrants in neighbouring regions and the risk of secondary movements within the EU.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1645.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1655.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The volatility of the situation was once again underlined in the beginning of this year at Greece's external EU borders with Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1655.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1670.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Statements from the Turkish President and the withdrawal of the Turkish Coast and Border Guard suddenly threatened to send the EU back to 2016 under substantial migratory pressure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1670.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1680.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It should be recalled that right at the external border of the EU, Turkey still hosts more than 3.5 million Syrians with protection status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1680.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1683.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>3.5 million Syrians.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1683.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1688.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This unfortunately has not changed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1688.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1703.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, we see large secondary movement within the EU and we have a Dublin regulation not functioning or in the case of transfers to Greece, not working at all for the past nine years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1703.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1720.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So despite the currently reduced numbers, the situation cannot be considered stable and we cannot predict the number of asylum seekers in Denmark or in the EU in the coming weeks, in the coming months or in the coming years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1720.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1732.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For as we have experienced in this extraordinary situation, developments may very rapidly change.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1732.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1746.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to UNHCR, at the end of 2018, Syrian nationals still made up the largest forcibly displaced population with 13 million people living in displacement, including 6.7 million refugees,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1746.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1748.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>6.2 million internally displaced</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1748.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1754.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and 140,000 asylum seekers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1754.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1757.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, I will just end this part of my argument</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1757.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1779.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>by just directing the court's attention to the very careful and elaborate considerations regarding the compatibility of the Danish rules with the Convention and the court's case law, both in the travaux préparatoire of the Danish legislation and in the Supreme Court's very carefully reasoned judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1779.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1783.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>All of this is annexed to the memorial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1783.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1785.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, there's no consensus at the European level</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1785.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1796.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on whether beneficiaries of subsidiary protection should enjoy a similarly favourable family reunification procedure as refugees covered by the 51 Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1796.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1802.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is also further elaborated in our memorial in pages 27 to 29.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1802.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1814.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, it's important to note that a number of European countries have introduced various restrictions on the access to family reunification for refugees who are not covered by the 1951 Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1814.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1817.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And let me give you a few examples.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1817.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1832.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Sweden, a new temporary statute entered into force in July 2016, which suspended the right to family reunification for subsidiary protection beneficiaries for a period of three years altogether.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1832.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1842.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The statute applies to those who have applied for asylum after 24 November 2015 and remained in force until July 2019.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1842.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1852.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In June 19, the suspension was extended until July 21, so it entails altogether a period of five years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1852.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1861.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Germany, the right to family reunification for persons granted subsidiary protection was postponed by two years in March 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1861.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1881.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As of 1 August 2018, the two-year waiting period was replaced by new legislation under which family reunification to beneficiaries of subsidiary protection was made possible again, albeit with a quantitative limitation to a quota of up to 1,000 persons per month.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1881.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1886.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The authorities will decide on humanitarian grounds whom to grant a residence permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1886.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1897.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Switzerland, individuals with a status similar to subsidiary protection are subject to a waiting period of three years as from recognition to reunification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1897.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1914.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides the countries that I have mentioned, also Austria, Latvia, Finland, Czech Republic, Hungary, Slovakia, Cyprus, Malta and Greece have introduced restrictions on the access to family reunification or other distinctions for refugees not covered by the 51 Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1914.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1917.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And again, I refer you to our memorial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1917.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1928.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So a number of countries have introduced legislation granting different family reunification rights to refugees under the 51 Convention and to beneficiaries of subsidiary protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1928.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1940.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In all of these countries, this has been considered a necessary response to the overwhelming increase in the number of asylum seekers from 2012 and onwards.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1940.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1942.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the court,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1942.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1945.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>let me now focus on the specific case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1945.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1955.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In June 15, the applicant, at that time 55 years old, was found entitled to international protection due to the general situation in Syria at the time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1955.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1957.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was therefore granted temporary protection status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1957.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1974.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The subsequent application for family reunification with his wife was rejected in July 16 with reference to the three-year postponement and also with reference to the fact that the authorities, after a careful individual examination, found no grounds for exempting the applicant from the three-year rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1974.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1984.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government submits that a fair balance was struck when the authorities back in 2016 refused family reunification between the applicant and his wife.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1984.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1997.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The essence is that the nature of the applicant's stay in Denmark was uncertain and expected to be of a limited duration, as his protection need was the result of a general situation in his home country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1997.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1999.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the situation could change rather quickly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1999.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2006.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should an improvement in Syria occur within the three-year period, he would be able to return to his wife in Syria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2006.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2013.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if no improvements, he would be eligible for family reunification in Denmark after the three-year period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2013.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2028.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Under these circumstances, the Danish society's interest in managing the immigration pressure and thereby securing the capacity to integrate the large number of newly arrived persons outweighed, in the opinion of the Danish authorities, the applicant's interest in family reunification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2028.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2031.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me recall paragraph 22 of the government's memorial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2031.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2052.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It states that in mid-2019, approximately three and a half years after the three-year waiting period came into force, the Danish Refugee Appeals Board found that the situation in the Damascus area in Syria had improved in such a way that a person originating from that area is no longer entitled to temporary protection, that is, by default.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2052.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2063.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's correct that the applicant has stated in his subsequent letter to the court from 11 March this year that at the moment, there are no forced returns to Syria due to foreign policy reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2063.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2069.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is based on an analysis and a policy which we share with our close allies in Europe and the USA.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2069.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2084.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Among other things, Denmark, along with some of the most important allies, including France, Germany, and UK, maintains that countries should refrain from actions that may be interpreted as normalization relations with the Syrian regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2084.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2093.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In light of all the aspects just mentioned, it is the view of the Danish government that a fair balance was struck between competing interests and within the state's margin of appreciation in the applicant's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2093.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2103.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, the government of Denmark respectfully submits to the court that no violation of Article 8 of the Convention has taken place in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2103.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2108.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now, finally, a few brief remarks on Article 14.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2108.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2138.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, the government's opinion is that the alleged violation of Article 14 should be rejected for the very reason that the applicant is neither in an unlawful nor a relevantly similar situation to refugees under the 1951 Convention or beneficiaries of subsidiary protection due to personal grounds granted residence permits pursuant to Section 7, Paragraph 1, or Paragraph 2 of the Aliens Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2138.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2151.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As mentioned earlier, those granted temporary protection status under Section 7, Paragraph 3, have been found to face no individual persecution but have fled the general conditions in their country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2151.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2160.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As has already been said, the situation in the home country is volatile and may change rather quickly and become more peaceful.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2160.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2170.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In general, this group, therefore, is expected to have a different and more temporary need of protection than those subjected to individual persecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2170.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2181.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for this reason, the government submits that the applicant was neither in an unlawful nor a relevantly similar situation with persons granted protection due to individual persecution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2181.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2184.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, should the Court conclude otherwise</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2184.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2195.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and find a difference in treatment, it is the government's opinion that such a difference is not discriminatory as it has an objective and reasonable justification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2195.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2208.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As mentioned before, the difference is based on the fact that the applicant is not individually perpetrated but has fled the general situation in the home country and that the general situation in the home country may change rather quickly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2208.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2216.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a consequence, the applicant's separation from his wife was likewise expected to be of a temporary duration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2216.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2223.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The assumptions find some support in the fact that Syrians, like the applicant, are now beginning to return to Syria voluntarily.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2223.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2231.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As mentioned, the Danish Refugee Appeals Board has found that an improvement over a longer period in the Damascus area has taken place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2231.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2245.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For instance, the UNHCR has reported that the numbers of voluntary repenise to Syria from the region have doubled from 16 to 18, and I refer the Court to paragraph 70 of our memorial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2245.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2266.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government submits that the postponement of the access to family reunification for three years pursues a legitimate aim of protecting the economic well-being of the Danish society, as it is a fact that an extraordinarily large number of new arrivals may significantly affect and challenge the successful integration and social cohesion in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2266.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2279.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On this basis, the government of Denmark respectfully submits that the Court should find that there has been no violation of Article 14 in conjunction with Article 8 of the Convention of the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2279.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2283.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, in closing, I would just like to say</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2283.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2288.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>that at the end of 2015, the European migrant crisis was at its peak.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2288.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2293.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The tragic flow of new asylum seekers reaching European shores was relentless.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2293.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2295.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It showed no prospect of weakening.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2295.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2304.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that time, Denmark was among the top five EU member states who received the largest number of asylum seekers per capita.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2304.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2319.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the backdrop against which the Danish legislature decided to postpone family reunification for beneficiaries of subsidiary protection, having fled the general situation in the home country, a situation foreseen to be of a more temporary nature than for those having fled to individual circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2319.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2331.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the view of my government, this measure, which corresponds to similar measures in a number of other European countries, was justified under the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2331.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2336.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was a necessary step to protect fundamental interests of the Danish society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2336.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2344.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was a carefully considered step, and it struck a fair balance between the competing interests and within states' margin of appreciation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2344.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2344.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2347.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2350.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Mr. Braad.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2350.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2355.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just to confirm, both your audio and video was clear throughout.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2355.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2356.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2356.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2360.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the applicant, Mr. Dahlager.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2360.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2360.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2362.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2368.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. President, members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2368.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2376.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant fled Syria in 2014.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2376.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2393.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some months later, in January 2015, he had entered into Denmark and was granted protection in June based on the war and violence in Syria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2393.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2400.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In November 2015, he and his wife applied for family reunification in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2400.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2415.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This application was denied ten months later, in September 2016, by the Immigration Board with reference to the discussed three-year waiting periods here today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2415.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2425.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That waiting period had come into force some three months after he applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2425.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2444.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today the government's argument is that the Immigration Board's decision was necessary and justified in particular in light of the high number of refugees facing Europe in 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2444.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2474.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to say here at the outset that the applicant and myself of course appreciate the challenges that Denmark and other European countries, in particular Germany and Sweden, was facing in 2015, but I would also like to stress a few facts regarding the particular situation in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2474.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2499.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first, as also today indicated by the government, is that when the Immigration Board made its decision in September 2016, Denmark was not facing the same number of refugees that the government thought initially could justify the waiting period when it was adopted in February 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2499.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2522.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, the number had fallen to a very manageable figure of about 300 asylum seekers in September, which was a number that is pretty close to what was the normal situation before the perceived refugee crisis in 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2522.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2538.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this connection, the Court will also recall that several other measures were put in place in 2015 on a national and international level to deal with the refugee matter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2538.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2556.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>By far, the most significant was that the European Council and Turkey already in November 2015 entered into an agreement to allocate refugees in Turkey.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2556.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2574.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As a matter of fact, very few Syrians have entered into the European Union after that agreement and that they are now placed primarily in Turkey and in Lebanon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2574.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2586.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second point is that the three-year waiting period came into force in the wake of the general election in Denmark in 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2586.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2603.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the election process, there was a very strong call from the majority to limit the rights of foreign nationals, especially the protection standards for refugees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2603.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2611.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was a concern for several European bodies dealing with human rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2611.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2621.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is also explained in the submissions by the Commissioner on Human Rights and the UN Refugee Agency.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2621.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2646.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It came actually that far that written recommendations were made to the new government to revise the proposed restrictions and limitations, and a particular recommendation was made to the government to reduce the proposed three-year waiting period to conform with international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2646.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2664.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But not only was international bodies concerned, also the government in Denmark had its concern on whether the waiting period was legally consistent with Article 8 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2664.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2685.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course, it was a delicate matter, considering the political environment and the government's political base, and this also appears from the preparatory work, because this concern is phrased rather carefully in that preparatory work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2685.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2690.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will quote a relevant part from it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2690.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2712.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What the government says is, there is a certain risk when reviewing a specific case that the European Court may decide that Denmark cannot generally make it a condition for family reunification that aliens have resided for three years in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2712.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2733.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nevertheless, the Act was adopted, and my point is that I believe it is important for the court to recall in this case that there has been a substantial influence when adopting the Act from political consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2733.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2750.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The justification of that three-year waiting period has primarily been rooted in political consideration rather than a careful assessment of international law and a careful assessment of relevant facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2750.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2755.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will revert to the significance of this later in my submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2755.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2767.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The final point regarding the facts is that the immigration authorities' processing time is in addition to the three-year waiting period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2767.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2773.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The de facto separation is therefore considerable longer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2773.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2781.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present matter, it meant that my client was separated from his wife for more than four and a half years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2781.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2799.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to clarify a new point that came up in the government's submission, the latest submission in January 2020 this year, that the government is alleging that it took my client eight months to apply in the second round.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2799.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2802.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is definitely not true.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2802.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2814.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He applied on April 26, 2015, and I have the application here in front of me if the government is still in doubt regarding this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2814.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2831.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So turning to the legal issues, my submission is that the Immigration Board's decision was unjustified when considering the particular circumstances in my client's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2831.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2861.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, I submit that a three-year waiting period for some in need of protection and not applying for others in need of protection is at any rate excessive and a different treatment that violates Article 8 and Article 14 of the Convention on Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2861.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2877.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding this, the starting point should be that the court has stated in its rulings in Tanda-Muxinka v. France and in Tanda v. France that there is a consensus at international</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2877.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2891.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and European level on the need for refugees to benefit from a unification procedure that is more favorable than for other aliens.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2891.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2904.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Precisely the same is expressed in the submissions by the UN Refugee Agency and the Commissioner on Human Rights to this court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2904.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2911.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are several reasons behind this overriding principle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2911.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2915.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first or the most important are two, actually.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2915.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2936.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first is that family reunification in cases of refugees is a result of their flight and the second is that they are not able to resume family life in the home country because of the risk of serious ill-treatment in that country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2936.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2953.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the clear consensus, the firm consensus in international law is that the only way to resume family life is in the host country that has granted protection to the individual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2953.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2958.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I also think this was indicated by the government today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2958.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2966.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a fact that this basic principle still is recognized under Danish law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2966.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2975.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The waiting period is not intended to cause the right to family reunification or to cancel the right to family reunification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2975.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2991.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What it does is it seeks to suspend reunification rights for a period of three years in a general manner for all individuals who are in need of general protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2991.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3011.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the first trouble with this waiting period is that it does not leave the authorities sufficient room to consider the particular circumstances in each case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3011.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3017.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was exactly the same concern that the government had when the law was adopted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3017.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3035.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would say rightfully so because it is a fundamental right also in Danish law that a thorough individual assessment of a matter must be afforded to the individual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3035.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3056.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court has also ruled on this in Kulcin versus Russia and has especially stated that it is an aggravating circumstance if national law does not make room for individual assessments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3056.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3064.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In spite of these very clear red flags, no thorough assessment has been made in my client's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3064.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3086.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this has, as a matter of fact, adversely affected the protection of my client's rights because, when considering the court's extensive case law on family reunification, he was actually – or there were actually – several factors in favor of my client.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3086.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3100.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, the Immigration Board did not consider what is otherwise a decisive factor that marriage was entered into before flight.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3100.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3115.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, did they consider that there were particular strong bounds between the couple based on more than 25 years of marriage and the couple's two adult children.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3115.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3130.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also of critical importance in favor of my client is that the number of refugees has decreased to a very manageable number at the material time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3130.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3147.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And finally, no thoughts were given to the fact that the applicant – or when the applicant arrived in Denmark, the three-year waiting period was not enforced, nor was it enforced when he applied in November 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3147.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3161.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, it could have been reasonable to weigh in that he had actually legitimate legal expectations that a timely reunification would be granted to him.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3161.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3170.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Against all of this, the government has afforded only one single argument.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3170.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3184.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is that in September 2016, it could be rightfully assumed by the Immigration Board that the violence in Syria would cease rather quickly.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3184.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3207.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore there was no need for a thorough assessment of my client's case, nor was it necessary to grant him reunification at that time, because it could safely be assumed that he soon would be able to return to Syria and enjoy family life there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3207.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3215.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now Mr. President, the Court has held in Bayer v. Denmark that limitations and restrictions</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3215.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3233.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on human rights cannot be deemed sufficiently justified if they are not based on a careful and objective assessment of facts by the contracting state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3233.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3245.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this present matter, likewise, the Danish government has refrained from the same as they did in the Bayer case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3245.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3269.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government has not in its remission put forward any facts nor evidence to support the Immigration Board's assumption that my client would be able to return to Syria, implying that the violence in Syria would cease within a short time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3269.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3296.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in addition to this, I would submit respectfully that the government most likely will find it very difficult to establish such convincing facts, because the waiting period was first and foremost justified by political considerations rather than a proper and objective assessment of relevant facts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3296.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3326.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So in conclusion to this part of my submission, I will respectfully submit that the lack of evidence, the lack of a sufficient assessment of my client's case, must lead to that any doubts on the merits of this case should be resolved in favor of my client rather than in favor of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3326.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3339.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will hereafter address the other part of my submission, namely that a minimum three-year waiting period is inconsistent with Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3339.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3353.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Beyond this, the Commissioner has made it crystal clear in her submission to the Court that waiting periods of more than one year should be considered inappropriate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3353.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3382.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, in Tandem with Senga versus France, this Court has ruled that the fact it took France almost three years, three and a half years, to process an application for family reunification submitted by a refugee was clearly excessive, and the Court found a violation of Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3382.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3392.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think it's fair to say at this point that there is really nothing to support the government's assumptions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3392.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3406.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's nothing in expert recommendations nor in the Court's case law that supports that a three-year waiting period is consistent with Article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3406.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3431.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another route to address this, and I think perhaps the most critical, is to consider whether it is fair that one class of individuals in need of protection is treated differently and with considerably lower protection standards than other individuals in need of protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3431.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3458.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The UN Refugee Agency has in particular addressed this issue in its submission to the Court and has stated that there is no objective reason to distinguish between refugees who seek individual protection and those who seek protection due to war and general violence in their home country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3458.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3468.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Precisely the same is also set forth by the Commissioner in her submission to the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3468.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3477.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This Court has also, in two rulings, said I would submit rather the same.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3477.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3487.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first is in Tukwabe-Czechly v. Netherlands, where the Court said it was questionable to</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3487.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3507.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>maintain as the Dutch government did, that the applicant could be said to have left her family at free will, bearing in mind that she had fled her home country in the course of a civil war.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3507.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3521.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I submit that this rather clearly indicates that she was entitled to be treated in the same preferential manner as refugees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3521.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3529.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the next case, and this is the Court's leading decision in Hode and Abdi v. the United</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3529.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3537.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kingdom, the Court ruled that the applicant, Mr. Hode, who was granted protection in the</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3537.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3560.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>United Kingdom, was not only in the same position as other refugees, but the Court went actually a step further and said that he could compare himself to immigrant workers and exchange students for the purpose of family reunification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3560.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3578.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The overriding decisive factor for the Court was that the individuals in question equally only were granted a limited period of residence in the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3578.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3587.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I respectfully say that if Mr. Hode could compare himself to not only refugees, but</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3587.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3611.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>also to migrant workers and students, then the Court must surely also say that my client may compare himself to those individuals in need of protection for individual reasons because they are in the same similar situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3611.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3630.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the particular reasons for this is that likewise in the Hode and Abdi ruling, all individuals in need of protection, whether for general or individual reasons, equally are subject to a limited residence permit in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3630.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3655.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And secondly of importance is that individuals in need of protection basically have the same protection needs and probably most important, none of them are able to resume family life at their home country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3655.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3668.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will also submit that this is not a controversial standpoint because it falls in line with essential European values of equal rights and equal protections.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3668.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3684.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And further, this standpoint is in line with the recommendations by the Commissioner for Human Rights and the UN Refugee Agency that is made to this Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3684.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3706.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The final question is hereafter whether the high numbers of refugees in 2015 should allow Denmark with a wider room to limit family reunification than what is otherwise allowed under the Convention and in the Court's case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3706.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3718.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have dealt with this question in extension in my written submission and will therefore limit myself to two essential points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3718.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3746.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first goes to the government's general claim that the Grand Chamber's ruling must be structured in such a manner that the Court takes a cautious approach and in principle leaves it to the Danish government and other European governments to decide on its own immigration politics.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3746.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3755.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I submit that the government's claim is wrong and I submit that it is behind, beside the point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3755.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3792.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason for this is that when it comes to those fundamental rights, differentiated treatment, the treatment of vulnerable groups, the essential rights to family life, the Court has firmly held that it will carry out an intensive review of the contracting state's claim that there was a public emergency need to limit the rights otherwise afforded under the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3792.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3819.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would say that this is particularly so if the government's claim, likewise in the present matter, is not supported truly by evidence and objective assessment of relevant facts, but rather on speculative policy decisions in the wake of a general election.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3819.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3828.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second point goes to the government's margin of appreciation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3828.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3844.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When considering this, I submit that the Grand Chamber must acknowledge that the three-year waiting period surely is at the outer edge of the human rights limitations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3844.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3871.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the same direction points, and perhaps even more critical, that the Court has held firmly in its present case law, when it comes to differentiated treatment based on a status that is beyond the individual's control, the contracting state's margin of appreciation is very narrow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3871.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3906.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So for instance, when differentiated treatment is based on gender or on race, the Court has ruled that the status, sorry, has ruled that there's no margin of appreciation because the status is inherent and because the individual do not have an ability to change that status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3906.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3914.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is a very good reason to apply this restriction on state discretion in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3914.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3931.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason is that the differentiated treatment by the Danish government is based on one single determining factor, namely that my client has fled the violence in Syria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3931.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3946.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This violence is indisputable a fact or status that is utterly and hopelessly beyond my client's control.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3946.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3961.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This overriding fact that the situation is unchangeable for my client and for other Syrian refugees is the crux of the matter as I see it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3961.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3995.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if the Grand Chamber confers to this, I will respectfully submit that the Court then must afford the government with a narrow margin of appreciation and that a differentiated reunification practice in times where things are difficult should center around a maximum one-year waiting period as also set forth by the Commissioner for Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3995.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3997.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this will end my oral submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3997.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4001.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So thank you, Mr. President, members of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4004.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4007.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Mr. Dahlager.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4007.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4014.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can also confirm that your presentation was met with clear audio and video.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4014.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4020.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I now turn to the Council of Europe Human Rights Commissioner, Mrs. Mijatović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4020.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4021.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor for ten minutes, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>ThirdParty</Role>
		<Name>TP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4024.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4029.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, distinguished members of the Court, ladies and gentlemen,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4030.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4045.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have decided to intervene in this case because the issue of family reunification is key to the lives of many people receiving international protection in Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4047.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4064.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is no exaggeration to say that once their basic safety and immediate humanitarian needs are met, ensuring that families can be brought back together again is one of the central preoccupations of many of them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4065.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4085.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, there is ample research showing that devastating effects of concerns about the situation of family members who are left behind, showing the mental well-being of recipients of international protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4086.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4097.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such concerns have been found to get in the way of language learning, job market orientation and other actions necessary for integration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4099.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4108.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this way, family separation may both negatively affect recipients of international protection and their host societies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4109.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4123.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, delays in family reunification may leave family members in a vulnerable situation in the country of origin or in the countries in the region to which they have fled.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4123.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4139.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When family reunification is unduly restricted, this eliminates an important safe and legal route to Council of Europe member states which may let family members to seek dangerous and irregular routes to Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4141.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4154.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From this perspective, it is of particular concern when member states introduce restrictions on the access to and enjoyment of family reunification for beneficiaries of international protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4155.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4173.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of the ways in which access to family reunification has been limited has been to introduce long waiting times before a recipient of international protection can file an application for reunification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4173.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4187.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, I have been particularly concerned by situations in which different family reunification regimes were introduced for different protection statuses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4187.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4207.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>While those recognized under the 1951 Refugee Convention are usually exempt from such long waiting times, although they may also face restrictions, they have been increasingly applied to persons with either subsidiary or temporary protection status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4207.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4229.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Denmark, the restrictions on family reunification at issue in the present case is a three-year waiting period applied to persons at risk of death penalty or torture or inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment when this is based on generalized situation in the country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4230.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4245.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This same restriction is not applied to those recognized as 1951 Convention refugees or to those for whom risks upon return are not based on a generalized situation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4246.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4270.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This court, with regard to 1951 Convention refugees, have found that family unity is an essential right and that family reunion is an essential element in enabling persons who have fled persecution to resume a normal life to be able to return to their country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4271.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4278.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Certain elements have played a central role in this court's considerations when reaching that conclusion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4279.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4288.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, refugees cannot be returned and as such they cannot be expected to reestablish family life in their country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4288.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4306.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the conferral of refugee status confirms that a person has not made a conscious or voluntary decision to leave family members behind and should therefore not be held responsible for the interruption of family life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4306.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4315.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And thirdly, refugee status constitutes evidence of vulnerability which should be taken into account in family reunification cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4316.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4327.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In my view, each of the elements I mentioned should apply in the same way to 1951 Convention refugees as they do to persons provided with international protection on other grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4328.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4349.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When a protection status is granted because a person would face serious human rights violations in his or her country of origin, this clearly marks an individual out as being unreturnable and therefore unable to reestablish family life in the country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4349.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4364.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, such a protection status clearly acknowledges the threats faced by the person which would mean they cannot be considered as having voluntarily left their country of origin, consciously leaving family members behind.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4365.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4374.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, as this court has acknowledged, a person's status as an asylum seeker may be evidence of his or her vulnerability.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4374.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4386.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If this is the case for asylum seekers, this would surely be the case for a person who, having undergone asylum procedure, is recognized as being in need of international protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4387.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4404.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The main justification for the differences in family reunification rights between different status holders is that the need for protection of some of them is supposedly more temporary than for others, such as 1951 Convention of Refugees.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4404.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4415.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this light, I have already submitted that a status that is formally more temporary, such as one-year residence permit, invariably leaves open the possibility for renewal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4416.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4428.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that a person with such a status may be in need of protection for a significantly longer period than covered by the initial permit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4428.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4441.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, it is noteworthy that certain national groups are disproportionately affected by the introduction of new temporary statuses and the subsequent waiting periods for family reunification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4442.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4445.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is specifically the case for Syrian nationals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4446.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4457.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As I have underlined, the impact that these new rules have on certain groups is visible from statistics in various Council of Europe member states, including Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4459.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4476.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is so despite the fact that even at a time when many of these restrictions were introduced in 2015 and 2016, the conflict in Syria and the widely recognized impossibility of return in the vast majority of cases had already been protected.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4476.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4490.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the security situation at that time, it is in my view questionable that it could have been reasonably presumed that the protection status of Syrians could be ended after a one-year period or even in the years following that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4491.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4503.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I note that even now, several years after this shift in legislation, the overwhelming majority of Syrians who apply for asylum in EU member states are still granted international protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4503.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4522.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In many cases, restrictions on family reunification in Council of Europe member states have been introduced in the context of increasing arrivals in 2015 and 2016 and associated concerns about pressures on their integration and welfare systems.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4522.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4531.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this context, I again express my concern that specific national groups are particularly affected by such restrictions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4531.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4538.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also note that the fact that prolonging family separation is ultimately detrimental to integration efforts.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4538.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4546.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, in many cases, restrictions have been maintained even after the pressures that led to their introduction have eased.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4547.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4555.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would also like to share with the Court my concern over the length of the delays in family reunification.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4555.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4582.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Considering the severe consequences of family reunification and the severe consequences of family separation for beneficiaries of international protections and their family members, the issue paper that my office published in 2017 to address the increasing restrictions on family reunification recommended that member states consider waiting times of more than one year inappropriate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4582.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4595.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I further note that the Danish law's waiting period of three years is comparable to the length of time that the Court previously found to be excessive, particularly in the case already mentioned of Tandem Muzinga v. France.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4596.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4605.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also note that the period of family separation will likely be much longer than just the three-year waiting period established by Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4606.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4616.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Family separation will have already occurred from the moment of flight and endures during the procedure to confer a protection status of the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4616.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4628.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Once an application for family reunification can be submitted, its processing and the making of subsequent arrangements for the de facto reunification will take additional time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4629.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4634.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any situation, therefore, family reunification typically takes a long time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4635.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4652.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Adding to this three-year waiting period before an application can be made in the first place will therefore significantly prolong family separation and hardship faced both by the beneficiary of international protection and any family members left behind.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4653.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4673.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To conclude, let me reiterate the importance of the ability of all those granted international protection, regardless of whether this is as a 1951 Convention refugee or under another status, to reunite with family members left behind.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4673.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4703.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In light of the similar situation of persons with such other statuses to 1951 Convention refugees and the fact that their need for protection is in practice almost never temporary, I believe differential treatment with regards to family reunification and in particular subjecting them to a waiting period cannot be objectively and reasonably justified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4704.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4708.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope my comment will be helpful to the Court and I thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4712.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4715.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Madam Commissioner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4715.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4722.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before I give the floor to the Swiss government, may I remind the parties that Mr. Chablais will speak in French,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4722.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4727.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>so you may wish to switch to the interpretation provided to you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4727.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4731.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Alors, je me tourne vers le gouvernement suisse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4731.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4733.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Chablais, vous avez la parole.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4733.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4743.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Chablais.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>ThirdParty</Role>
		<Name>TP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4749.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4749.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Voilà, vous m'entendez?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4750.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4751.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Très bien, merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>ThirdParty</Role>
		<Name>TP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4753.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4765.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les Juges, l'affaire dont il est question aujourd'hui nous rappelle, à travers le destin du requérant, le drame du conflit syrien et le lot de souffrance qu'il entraîne.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4765.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4777.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'affaire illustre aussi le fait que les déplacements de population et les vagues migratoires concernent de nombreux pays européens, y compris ceux qui sont géographiquement éloignés des foyers de tension.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4777.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4780.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Avec d'autres, la Suisse en fait partie.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4780.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4790.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il faut cependant garder à l'esprit que la question qui se pose ici n'est pas celle de la protection à accorder aux personnes qui fuient les persécutions dans leur pays.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4790.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4795.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La nécessité de cette protection est largement reconnue et admise par nos gouvernements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4795.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4807.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il faut ainsi se réjouir que le requérant ait obtenu, quelques mois seulement après son arrivée au Danemark, une protection temporaire sur la base de la législation relative aux étrangers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4807.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4825.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La question qui vous occupe aujourd'hui concerne la façon dont nos États sont tenus de permettre aux personnes bénéficiant d'une protection internationale de mener leur vie familiale, plus particulièrement quant à la possibilité de faire venir leurs conjoints pour les rejoindre.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4825.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4827.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cette question dépasse le sort du cas d'espèce.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4827.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4836.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Potentiellement, ce sont de très nombreuses personnes qui pourraient être concernées par l'issue de cette affaire, et ce, dans plusieurs États membres du Conseil de l'Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4836.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4851.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Un arrêt de votre cours, qui étendrait les possibilités de bénéficier d'un regroupement familial pour des personnes n'ayant pas obtenu le statut de réfugié, pourrait donc avoir, en Suisse également, des répercussions considérables.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4851.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4877.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En ce qui concerne le grief de violation de l'article 8, votre cours rappelle régulièrement que les États ont, en vertu d'un principe de droite internationale bien établi, le droit de contrôler l'entrée des non-nationaux sur leur sol, et que la Convention ne garantit pas le droit pour un étranger d'entrer ou de résider dans un pays particulier, voire par exemple une aire contre Pays-Bas, paragraphe 54.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4877.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4886.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il s'agit là d'une prérogative essentielle qui appartient aux États, qui doivent pouvoir réagir aux défis posés par les mouvements migratoires transfrontaliers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4886.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4892.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, ces défis évoluent en fonction de la situation internationale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4892.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4902.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ces dernières années, plusieurs États, dont la Suisse, ont ainsi révisé leurs législations en la matière, y compris quant aux conditions relatives au regroupement familial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4902.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4909.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>De telles adaptations législatives ont par exemple été introduites suite à la crise des réfugiés en 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4909.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4915.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il est donc important qu'à l'avenir, les États puissent continuer à répondre aux situations migratoires nouvelles.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4915.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4924.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les décisions de leur Parlement constituent l'expression démocratique de choix politiques qu'il convient de respecter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4924.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4938.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il faut ensuite rappeler que la Cour souligne, de façon constante, que ni la Convention ni ses protocoles ne consacrent le droit à l'asile politique, voire par exemple Ville-Varaja et autres contre le Royaume-Uni, paragraphe 102.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4938.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4945.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>De la même façon, la Convention de Genève relative au statut des réfugiés ne crée pas de droit à l'asile.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4945.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4950.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Elle ne fonde aucun droit d'entrée individuelle sur le territoire d'un État particulier.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4950.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4960.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Convention de Genève ne contient pas non plus de dispositions relatives au regroupement familial des réfugiés, de sorte qu'on ne peut en déduire aucun droit en la matière.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4960.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4973.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La seule trace d'une référence au regroupement familial se trouve dans l'acte final de 1951 de la Conférence holluzienne des plénipotentiaires sur le statut des réfugiés et des apatrides.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4973.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4984.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, ce document ne contient qu'une recommandation non contraignante qui invite les gouvernements à, je cite, « prendre les mesures nécessaires pour la protection de la famille des réfugiés ».</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4984.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4986.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Une citation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4986.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4992.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cette recommandation les enjoint à faire en sorte que l'unité de la famille soit, je cite, « maintenue ».</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4992.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5008.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il n'est donc pas question d'inviter les gouvernements à permettre la création d'une unité familiale qui n'a jamais existé auparavant, ni même de recréer une unité de la famille lorsque celle-ci a fait délibérément l'objet d'une séparation avant la fuite du pays d'origine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5008.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5028.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cela étant, dans l'affaire Mugenzi contre France, paragraphe 54, la Cour a souligné à juste titre que l'unité de la famille est un droit essentiel du réfugié, que le regroupement familial est un élément fondamental pour permettre à des personnes qui ont fui des persécutions de reprendre une vie normale.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5028.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5043.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cette mise en perspective du droit des réfugiés, en particulier sur la question du regroupement familial, nous paraît essentielle, car votre Cour interprète à juste titre les dispositions de la Convention à la lumière des règles du droit international.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5043.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5058.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, lorsqu'il est question d'examiner, sous l'angle de l'article 8, le souhait d'un demandeur d'asile de pouvoir bénéficier du regroupement familial, il faut s'interroger sur ce que le régime de la Convention de Genève prévoit en la matière.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5058.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5061.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et la réponse, nous l'avons vue, est assez claire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5061.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5078.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Convention de Genève ne saurait donc justifier que la Cour étende davantage, au titre de l'article 8, le champ des obligations de l'État en matière de regroupement familial des personnes au bénéfice d'une protection internationale qui n'ont pas obtenu la qualité de réfugié.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5078.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5084.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pour ces personnes, c'est le principe 23 répété par la Cour en matière d'immigration qui doit servir de référence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5084.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5105.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, selon ce principe, l'article 8 ne saurait s'interpréter comme comportant pour un État l'obligation générale de respecter le choix par des couples mariés de leur résidence commune et de permettre le regroupement familial sur son territoire, voire par exemple à Régule, paragraphe 38, ou encore à Régionnesse, paragraphe 107.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5105.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5116.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il convient maintenant de s'arrêter sur la seconde question posée au gouvernement danois, soit celle d'une éventuelle violation de l'article 14 en lien avec l'article 8.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5116.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5131.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour ne considère une différence comme discriminatoire que si elle ne repose pas sur une justification objective et raisonnable, c'est-à-dire si elle ne poursuit pas un but légitime ou s'il n'y a pas un rapport raisonnable de proportionnalité entre les moyens employés et le but visé.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5131.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5137.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cependant, toute différence de traitement n'emporte pas automatiquement violation de l'article 14.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5137.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5149.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il faut en effet démontrer que des personnes placées dans des situations analogues ou comparables jouissent d'un traitement préférentiel et que cette distinction est discriminatoire.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5149.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5174.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dans le cas d'espèces, il est question d'une différence de traitement entre d'un côté un individu n'ayant obtenu qu'une protection subsidiaire de nature temporaire, puisqu'il affluit une situation générale de violence, et de l'autre côté, deux autres catégories d'individus bénéficiant d'une protection plus durable, puisqu'ils sont personnellement exposés à un risque de persécution dans leur pays d'origine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5174.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5183.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le gouvernement suisse soutient que ces différentes catégories d'individus ne sont en réalité pas placées dans une situation analogue ou comparable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5183.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5191.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>À supposer qu'ils le soient, alors faudrait-il considérer la différence entre eux comme objective et poursuivant un but légitime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5191.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5208.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En effet, un risque avéré de persécution individuelle peut justifier une protection plus forte, partant l'octroi d'un statut plus durable qu'un risque de violence généralisée touchant une population ou un groupe de population dans son ensemble.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5208.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5218.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le droit suisse de l'asile et des étrangers connaît lui aussi, à l'instar de plusieurs autres pays européens, des distinctions comparables, y compris pour différencier certaines catégories de réfugiés.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5218.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5234.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il protège ainsi davantage les individus qui obtiennent l'asile de ceux qui voient leur demande d'asile rejetée et ne sont admis en Suisse qu'à titre provisoire, en raison du fait que leur renvoi est temporairement impossible, illicite ou inexigible.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5234.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5244.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La nature du séjour des personnes admises provisoirement est par définition beaucoup plus précaire, puisque ces personnes n'ont pas vocation à s'établir durablement dans le pays d'accueil.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5244.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5249.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il est donc logique que le regroupement familial de ces personnes puisse être différé.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5249.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5258.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Cela n'empêche pas que le principe du non-refoulement s'applique à tous ces individus, quelle que soit la catégorie dont ils relèvent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5258.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5270.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Bien entendu, si une différence de traitement poursuit un objectif légitime et se fonde sur des critères objectifs, encore faut-il qu'elle ne soit pas manifestement déraisonnable dans ses effets pour les personnes concernées.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5270.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5293.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sur ce point, le gouvernement suisse estime qu'un délai de carence de trois ans avant que l'intéressé puisse faire valoir une demande de regroupement familial est raisonnable au regard de l'objectif visé, à savoir une maîtrise de l'immigration et un maintien du bien-être économique de l'État, y compris en assurant une bonne intégration des nouveaux arrivants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5293.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5307.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il est vrai que votre cour, dans son arrêt de tente d'abusing à contre France, a constaté une violation de l'article 8 dans la situation du requérant dont le regroupement familial n'a pu se réaliser que trois ans et demi après le dépôt de sa demande.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5307.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5312.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Les circonstances étaient cependant bien différentes de l'affaire qui vous occupe aujourd'hui.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5312.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5319.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En effet, le requérant Tanda Muzinga disposait d'une attestation de réfugié du HDR, tout comme son épouse.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5319.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5329.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sa vie familiale n'avait été interrompue qu'en raison de sa fuite, par crainte sérieuse de persécution en France de la Convention de Genève, et cela ne lui était donc pas imputable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5329.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5338.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Enfin et surtout, c'est bien le temps excessif pris par les autorités pour accorder les visas d'entrée à sa famille qui était en jeu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5338.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5347.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il serait dès lors erroné de vouloir tirer de cet arrêt une quelconque conclusion sur la durée généralement admissible d'un délai de carence figurant dans la loi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5347.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5351.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pour conclure, permettez-moi encore, M. le Président,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5351.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5359.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>d'ajouter quelques remarques sur la question de l'admissibilité des conditions légales, encadrant le droit au regroupement familial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5359.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5361.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ces conditions sont assez variées.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5361.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5374.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Il s'agisse de délais de carence, de délais maximum, de critères d'intégration, ou encore d'exigences relatives à un revenu minimum ou à une absence de dépendance à l'aide sociale, par exemple.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5374.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5377.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Votre Cour a déjà eu l'occasion d'examiner de telles conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5377.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5390.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Elle ne les a, à juste titre, pas considérées comme irréconciliables avec la Convention, voire par exemple l'arrêt Konstantinov contre Pays-Bas par agrafe 50, ou encore l'arrêt Kazanbansic contre Suisse par agrafe 59.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5390.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5399.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Lorsque de telles conditions sont inscrites dans la loi, il est important que le législateur ménage la possibilité d'admettre des exceptions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5399.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5415.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>En d'autres termes, l'autorité doit pouvoir garder un pouvoir d'appréciation pour tenir compte des situations individuelles particulières, en prévoyant expressément la possibilité de prendre en compte des raisons spéciales, notamment au titre de la nécessité de maintenir l'unité de la famille.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5415.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5420.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le législateur danois a précisément ménagé un tel pouvoir d'appréciation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5420.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5432.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or, nous l'avons vu, en pratique, de nombreuses exceptions ont été accordées, comme nous l'ont indiqué les représentants danois, aux demandeurs d'une autorisation de regroupement familial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5432.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5443.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>De la même manière, le droit suisse préserve expressément le pouvoir d'appréciation des autorités compétentes, qui doivent tenir compte des intérêts publics, de la situation personnelle de l'intéressé, ainsi que de son intégration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5443.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5461.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ce pouvoir d'appréciation des autorités, à condition qu'il soit prévu dans la loi et que les autorités en fassent bon usage, permet de garantir une application du droit national qui se concilie avec les exigences de la Convention, en particulier celle de l'article 8, paragraphe 2.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5461.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5473.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Voilà, Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les juges, les raisons pour lesquelles le gouvernement suisse invite la Grande Chambre à rejeter la requête dont elle est saisie dans l'affaire M1 contre Danemark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5473.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5474.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Je vous remercie de votre attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5476.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5478.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci, Merci beaucoup Mr. Chablais, votre audio et video etaient clair.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5478.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5491.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Okey, now we turn to, and I invite the Judges who wish to pose questions to raise their hands, Judge Serghides.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Georgios A. Serghides</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5493.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5496.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5496.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5501.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is addressed to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5501.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5525.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it appears from your pleadings, it is a common ground that originally a request for family reunification was made on 4th November 2015, which was refused first by the Danish Immigration Office and finally by the Immigration Appeals Board in September 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5525.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5540.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As it appears also from your pleadings, it is a common ground that family reunification was granted on 24th June 2019.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5540.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5577.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant argues that he applied again for family reunification on 26th April 2018, that the government rejected his application on 22 October 2018 and requested additional information in particular pertaining to the authenticity of his marriage, which the applicant subsequently provided and the family reunification was granted on 24th June 2019.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5577.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5593.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other hand, the government argues at paragraph 12 of their memorial that the applicant applied for family reunification on 12 February 2019 and that on 24 June 2019 the request was approved.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5593.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5613.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is how many times the applicant applied for family reunification, in particular when the applicant's second request was rejected and was requested to provide additional information pertaining to the authenticity of his marriage, as the applicant argues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5613.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5625.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Was this submission of additional information made in the context of a third request or as a part of the second request?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5625.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5627.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another question to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5627.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5649.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What was the reason of the delay for examining the last request for reunification and why eventually the applicant had to stay four years and a half in Denmark from January 2015 up to 24 June 2019 to be permitted to have family reunification?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5649.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5649.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5649.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5651.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Schukking.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Jolien Schukking</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5659.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5665.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, I would like to thank the parties and all the interveners for their very clear statements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5665.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5676.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a question to the representative of the government, but of course also the representative of the applicant is invited to reply.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5676.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5696.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The question relates to the application of section 9c paragraph 1 of the Danish Aliens Act, the provision that provides for granting residence permits to family members within the three years waiting period in exceptional situations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5696.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5710.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the explanatory report to the law that introduced this waiting period, I got the impression that such an exceptional situation would only be accepted in a very few circumstances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5710.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5720.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, in your introductory remarks, you mentioned that in a substantial number of cases, this provision has been applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5720.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5736.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is, could you please, in the second round, repeat the numbers you mentioned, and could you please provide us with a number of concrete situations in which this exceptional situation has been accepted? Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5738.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5741.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Le juge Pastor Vilanova, he will ask in French.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Pere Pastor Vilanova</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5745.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5747.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci beaucoup, M. le président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5747.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5758.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'ai une question, donc, deux questions qui sont adressées au requérant, mais rien n'empêche, bien entendu, le gouvernement d'apporter des éléments si nécessaires.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5759.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5761.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La première question est la suivante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5762.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5768.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pourquoi l'épouse du requérant, c'est-à-dire Mme Jen, n'a jamais demandé l'asile au Danemark?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5770.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5773.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Et ma deuxième question est la suivante.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5773.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5777.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quelle était la situation, donc, de cette dame, de Mme Jen?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5777.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5784.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Donc, quelle était sa situation en Syrie pendant que son mari résidait seul au Danemark?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5784.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5787.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Elle avait un travail stable, par exemple?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5787.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5789.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Par exemple? Je vous remercie, M. le président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5790.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5792.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. Judge Elósegui.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5792.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5804.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A minute.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5804.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5805.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Microphone for Judge Elósegui, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>María Elósegui</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5805.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5806.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5806.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5807.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Perfect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5807.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5810.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, thank you to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5810.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5818.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have two questions, one for the government and another for the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5818.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5833.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the government, a very concrete one related to the differences between the application of the Article Section 7.3, 7.2, or 7.1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5833.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5868.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then, could you explain the differences in the procedure dealing with a request for protection in order to substantiate in the interviews the real and personal risk of a treatment contrary to Article 3 due to the individual circumstances that upon return she or he can suffer?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5868.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5883.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then my question is about these interviews and the assessment to classify these asylum seekers in one of these three situations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5883.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5890.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My other question for the applicant is very short.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5890.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5915.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have said in your observations, well, then I want to ask in which arguments do you support your statement that in your case to say that the need for protection was only temporary was a pure speculation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5915.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5920.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Why you say that it was a pure speculation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5920.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5921.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And nothing else.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5921.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5921.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5923.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5924.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Lemmens</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5929.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5932.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5932.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5942.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to ask a question relating to Article 14, and it is a little bit prompted by what Mr. Chablais said at the end.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5942.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5963.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Assuming that there are here comparable situations, assuming that there is a legitimate aim for the difference in treatment, the question arises whether the means to create this difference in treatment are relevant for the aims pursued.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5963.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5970.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Braad said that the reasons for the 2015 amendments</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5970.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5983.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>were, on the one hand, to offer protection as long as needed, and on the other hand, to ensure that the return is possible when there is no longer a need for protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5983.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5998.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So then my question comes, to what extent is this specific difference in treatment based on the waiting period for the right to family reunification?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5998.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6003.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To what extent is it relevant for the aims pursued?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6003.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6003.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6005.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6007.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Kjølbro.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Jon Fridrik Kjølbro</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6011.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6012.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6012.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6021.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have one question, and it is directed to the government, and it concerns the choice for the duration of the waiting period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6021.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6030.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I understand the pleadings of the applicant to be that the applicant is not, as such, calling into question the legitimacy of introducing a waiting period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6030.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6039.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And in his observations, a waiting period of one year would have been reasonable, but he's challenging the three-year waiting period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6039.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6044.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is, when it was introduced in 2015, it was one year.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6044.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6049.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When it was amended in 2016, it became three years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6049.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6056.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I assume that the government has been must have reflected on whether it should be one year, two years, three years, or four years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6056.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6061.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And therefore, my question is, why did the government opt for three years?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6061.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6064.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One year would have been the recommendation of the Commissioner of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6064.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6071.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Two years would have been the EU Family Reunification Directive from 2003.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6071.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6075.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Three years seems to be the legislation in Sweden and other places.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6075.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6089.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But could you shed some light on why the government opted for three years, or to ask in a more direct way, was it to have as long a period as possible, which was still compatible with international obligations?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6089.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6089.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6092.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6092.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Turković.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6096.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6097.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6097.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6098.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Just two questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6098.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6106.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't know whether I understood properly, but now apparently there is the law that applies three years to all the groups.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6106.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6111.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So could you explain what was the reason to extend to all the groups?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6111.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6113.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second question, am I wrong?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6113.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6113.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't know.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6113.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6116.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Maybe I'm wrong.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6116.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6124.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then the second question is, we heard today a couple of times that different groups are affected differently.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6124.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6134.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would be interested whether you have data whether such legislation affects women comparatively much more than men.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6134.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6135.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6138.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6140.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6140.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6146.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I do not see any other requests for posing questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6146.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6154.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now the court will withdraw until 10 minutes past 12, 25 minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6154.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6167.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing will resume, again, I say, 10 minutes past 12, upon which the parties can reply to the judges' questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6167.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6168.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is suspended.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6186.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6188.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6188.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6190.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Braad for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6190.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6190.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6192.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6198.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President, thank you to you and the distinguished members of the court for the many pertinent questions asked.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6198.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6203.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will try to respond to them in the manner they were or in the order they were presented to us.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6203.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6213.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, I will try and respond to Judge Saki's question about the different applications and about the yes, the processing times.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6213.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6217.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I admit it is a bit confusing, I think, to all of us.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6217.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6228.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I will try to see if I can clarify. Perhaps I should start out by referring to the case law, the McKenzie v. France and Santa Mocinga v. France cases,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6228.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6237.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>where the court found that processing times of respectively five years and three and a half years were excessive, as we have also heard today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6237.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6250.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The French cases concerned the processing time from the point in time where when the applicants had the right to family reunification, recognized in principle under French law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6250.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6264.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the government and the applicant in this case, I think, differentiate on the question as to what point in time from which the processing time in the family reunification case should be counted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6264.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6278.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I think the question is, should it be counted from the application back in April 2018 for reopening of the previously submitted application?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6278.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6289.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or should it be counted from the submission in February 19 of the new application to the first instance after expiry of the three year period?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6289.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6295.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I have to say the procedure in this case, specific case, has been somewhat unfortunate and unusual.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6295.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6304.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think it's fair to say that misunderstandings have been have been on both sides of this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6304.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6317.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But what I what I will say, I think, be that as it may, leaving all that aside, I think that in the applicant's case, the three year waiting period expired in June 2018.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6317.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6327.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I think that's a key point. So it is from this point in time that the processing time should be counted at its earliest, in our opinion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6327.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6339.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So and even counting from this earliest possible point in time, the processing took approximately one year and two weeks before the family reunification was granted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6339.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6348.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the opinion of the government, that is not excessive and it's not a violation of the procedural aspects of Article eight of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6348.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6362.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Let me also add that the average Danish processing time is approximately three months and in 2018 and six months in 2019.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6362.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6372.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, I hope that answers the question from Mr. Sarkis, and I will now turn to to judge Shikins Shukins questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6372.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6387.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a question about the the number of exemptions made and also a question about some examples of the exceptions made to the to this three year waiting period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6387.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6396.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So let me try and respond to that. I can repeat as what I said in the the initial submission that in every case,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6396.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6404.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the authorities assess whether family reunification must be granted before the expiry of the waiting period of three years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6404.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6409.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Reunification is always granted when so required by Denmark's international obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6409.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6426.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as an example of this, if the family member in Denmark has been taking care of a disabled spouse in the home country or if the family member, for example, has severely ill minor children in the home country, this is something that will be taken into consideration.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6426.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6437.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another example could be if the family member in Denmark is a minor child and the best interest of the child would be to to grant its its its parents family reunification in in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6437.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6447.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it is actually a significant number of of cases where this exemption is made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6447.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6453.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I mentioned the number 25, approximately 25 percent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6453.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6467.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is and that is a valid that's a valid number. Turning then to the the question from Judge Losekey,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6467.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6480.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>on the legal differences between the the the categories in Section seven, paragraph one to three.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6480.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6488.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also there was a question about the practices concerning how to distinguish between the different categories.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6488.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6491.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What kind of practices concerning interviews do we have and so on?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6491.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6503.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'll try to respond to that as as well, perhaps first clarifying the different the different scopes of the of the different paragraphs of Section seven in the Danish law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6503.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6514.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if I start by Section seven, one of the Danish Aliens Act, I'll say that refugees covered by the 51 Refugee Convention are granted residence pursuant to this paragraph.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6514.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6529.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is when a person, obviously, is is found to have well-founded fear of being persecuted for reasons of, for example, race, religion, nationality, membership of a particular social group or political union opinion.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6529.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6536.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So these refugees are given convention status according to Section seven, one of the Aliens Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6536.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6550.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If we then move on to Section seven, paragraph two, this is referring to persons in risk of treatment contrary to Article three of the convention due to personal grounds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6550.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6556.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are granted residence pursuant to Section seven, paragraph two of our Aliens Act.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6556.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6565.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that includes, for example, risk of death penalty, being subjected to torture or inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment, as I mentioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6565.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6576.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the person must face individual persecution, for instance, because of a specific conflict with the persons or with the persons in their home country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6576.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6579.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So these persons are given subsidiary protection status.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6579.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6595.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, so I hope that clarifies at least to some extent the the Section seven, paragraph one and paragraph two.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6595.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6601.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I already dealt with the new the new category in the in Section seven, paragraph three.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6601.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6615.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then to the question of of the of the interview practices, how how do we how do we go about to make the distinctions when applying for for asylum in Denmark?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6615.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6622.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The person is requested to fill out a form and afterwards the subject to take part in an interview.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6622.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6626.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's held with the Danish Immigration Service with an interpreter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6626.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6629.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The length of the interview can vary quite a quite a bit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6629.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6631.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some will take a few hours.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6631.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6640.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Others will will take up to a couple of days and also further further interviews may be held if needed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6640.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6656.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the person disagrees with the asylum status that is granted, the person may appeal to the Refugee Appeals Board in Denmark and the person will then be afforded legal service without charge.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6656.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6675.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the protection status of the person in question will be determined after what we consider a very careful assessment examination of of the person's background in this in the way that I have in the way that I have described.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6675.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6690.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope that responds to George Lusiky's question and I now turn then to to the questions posed by George Lemons concerning Article 14.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6690.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6705.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So assuming that there is a legitimate ground to differentiate persons under Section 7.3 compared to the persons under Section 7.2 and 7.1.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6705.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6730.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I say I'd argue that it has been the view of the Danish Parliament, the Danish governments that the the waiting period in the in case here was needed and was a proportionate means to to meet the number of legitimate aims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6730.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6743.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It has to do with the number of new arrivals that has great significance as I as I as I explained during my initial submission has significance for the social cohesion of Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6743.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6755.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the view has been that this is a measure that would help us accomplish this aim of maintaining social cohesion of our society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6755.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6768.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should also mention in this regard as I alluded to in my initial statement that Denmark has a very elaborate welfare system is a very high degree of redistribution of wealth in the Danish society.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6768.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6774.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So also that is is is is part of the the background.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6774.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6789.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the the conditions for foreigners with a recognized need of protection are in most aspects the same as for other people residing in in Denmark.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6789.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6799.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There's access to free public health care access to permanent residents housing language training as I mentioned.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6799.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6810.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So all of this is is included. It was in what is being offered to to to persons recognized who has a recognized need for protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6810.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6825.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, I hope that responded to just limits questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6825.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6841.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, you are free to to to to to return to judge Kupfer who posed a question about the choice that the legislature in Denmark made between the one year postponement or three year postponement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6841.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6845.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What what was the what was the deliberations behind this choice?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6845.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6853.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What was the reflections? And and I think Judge Kirby already himself indicated this when he posed the answer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6853.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6871.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was a it was an attempt to try to balance two things at one time to try to find a balancing point between a political desire in Denmark to to respond to the situation and urgent call to try to respond to the extraordinary situation on the one hand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6871.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6885.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And on the other hand, a wish to to to stay within the framework of the convention to to to to to identify a way forward that would be in compliance with the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6885.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6902.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So those two factors were the determining in in identifying this this rule. And and as just Cuba indicated, some countries have had a more extensive period of waiting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6902.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6914.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Others have resorted to to to to other more minimalistic approaches. The Danish government tried to find a middle way in this and try to find a proportionate and a measured response.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6914.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6927.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the three waiting period was the result of these deliberations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6927.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6943.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Perhaps in this context, I could just briefly take a moment to to comment on the on the on the the indication from from applicants council that that that maybe in some way the court has already taken a position on this issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6943.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6949.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would I would like to to counter argue that that comment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6949.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6967.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think it's correct that that that in the Danish travel, perhaps one or I know it's correct that there is a mentioning that there's a certain risk of process if one extends the waiting period from one year to three years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6967.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6983.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is due to the to the fact, of course, that that neither this court nor the European Court in Luxembourg has had an opportunity to to take specific position on this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6983.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6995.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So just to make that point, just to make that point clear, this is, in our opinion, the first time the court has had an opportunity to take a position on this on this question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6995.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7001.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then finally to judge took of it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7001.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7018.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A question about. Yeah, the the also also a question about the different categories, I think the Danish section paragraph one to two to three, I hope also in the light of time is now expiring.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7018.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7026.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I hope I have I did respond to that earlier on in some of the other questions, so maybe I do not need to go into too much detail.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7026.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7041.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I'll just in closing. Say a few words, very brief words on the potential consequences of the court's decision in this case, as mentioned also in what I said earlier this morning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7041.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7050.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case does have quite far reaching consequences for many European countries. And if the courts should conclude the beneficiaries of subsidiary protection,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7050.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7060.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>if they enjoy the same favorable family unification rights as refugees under the 51 convention, this will have very far reaching consequences.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7060.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7071.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We believe we believe it would affect the room for maneuver of European countries to secure a humane and a balanced response to present day challenges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7071.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7077.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to respond to to the potential for a new, overwhelming influx.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7077.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7096.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So turning to the present case, if the court should conclude that beneficiaries of subsidiary protection who have fled a general situation in their home country should be treated the same way as beneficiaries of subsidiary protection who have fled due to personal grounds, the Danish legislator would be in a very difficult position. I have to say that.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7096.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7104.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And and to comply with the court's conclusion, the Danish legislator would basically have to choose between two options.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7104.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7108.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first option would be to abolish the waiting period altogether.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7108.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7125.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the second logical position or option would be perhaps more likely option would be to to restrict the access to family reunification in a similar way for all beneficiaries of subsidiary protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7125.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7134.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is, of course, assuming that the convention allows for a distinction between refugees under the 51 convention and beneficiaries of subsidiary protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7134.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7149.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But as indicated, the second option would probably be the choice to secure that recent years, rising influx of asylum seekers from regions of conflict is managed and absorbed in a responsible and in a balanced way.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7149.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7166.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this way, what may today be perceived as a victory for the applicant may in fact, depending on the resulting choices of our legislator, but may in the in the end turn out to be to the detriment of others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7166.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7166.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And with that, I would like to conclude. Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7170.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7173.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Mr. Braad.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7173.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7176.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call now Mr. Dahlager for the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7178.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7180.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7180.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7189.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will try to respond to the questions in the order that they have been posed to us.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7189.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7198.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, Judge Schurges, who asked how many times did my client apply, and why did it take so long?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7198.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7221.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, as mentioned by the judge, he applied in November 2015, and that application was flatly denied on basis of the three-year rules without any consideration whatsoever on the particular matters in pertaining to my client's case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7221.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7228.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In April 26, 2018, he applied again.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7228.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7233.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And why did he apply in April 2018?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7233.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7239.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because he was granted protection in June 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7239.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7244.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So was he able, actually, to apply a couple of months before the three-year period?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7244.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7263.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Yes, he was, because under the law, there is a possibility or a requirement, I think, also, as the government has mentioned, that you are able to apply two years and 10 months after initially granted protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7263.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7267.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So April corresponds to exactly two years and 10 months.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7267.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7273.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's why he applied then.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7273.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7281.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then it has been sort of indicated by the government that he applied again in January 2019.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7281.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7304.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is what I said under my submission, definitely wrong, because what he did on January 2019, that was merely a letter or a follow-up from our offices providing additional information to the authorities, in particular, because they contested that he has been married to his wife.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7304.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7313.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So they required a marriage license from Syria, which was very difficult to obtain in the course of the civil war in Syria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7313.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7317.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that also indicates why it took so long.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7317.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7332.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The reason was that there was a requirement for the marriage license, and also because it is, as a matter of fact, very difficult to get in touch with the immigration authorities pertaining to these matters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7332.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7338.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we used, in our office, considerable time upon this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7338.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7349.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then turning to the question asked by Judge Schulich, regarding the possible exemptions under 9C.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7354.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7370.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>From the preparatory work, and I have actually quoted that in my last submission in January on page six, it is very clearly stated when an exception may be made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7370.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7386.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because what it says is, and that's at the bottom of page six, is that, as previously, family reunification must be granted also within the first three years of residence in Denmark if dictated by Denmark's international obligations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7386.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7389.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that sounds very assuring.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7389.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7414.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in the next sentence, it says, this applies, for example, if the alien resident in Denmark cared for a disabled spouse in the country of origin before leaving that country of origin, or if the alien resident in Denmark has seriously ill minor children in the country of origin.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7414.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7421.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So, exemptions are limited to very, very few instances.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7421.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7440.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And replying to the sort of pointed way to put it, that 25% of applications was given, is sort of not at the point.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7440.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7449.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because that only goes to those applications that are submitted before the three years waiting period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7449.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7457.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So out of those that are submitted, I think it was 79, 25% are accepted, which is actually a very low number.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7457.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7470.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But if you want to compare, then of course what is relevant is to see the overall amount of applications, also including those applications that has been forwarded after the three years waiting period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7470.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7488.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is sort of the relevant figure, and not saying 25% of those few applications filed before they actually was allowed to file because of the three year waiting period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7488.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7491.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Judge Villanova asked,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7491.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7500.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>why did my client not apply for asylum?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7500.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7507.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, I can only refer what my client has told me.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7507.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7514.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And he has said that it was not possible for them to flee together from Syria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7514.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7518.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They thought it was too dangerous.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7518.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7521.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They thought it would be too troublesome for her to follow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7521.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7523.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She is also at old age.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7523.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7536.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I also think, he's a proud man, that he indicates that they financially didn't have the means.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7536.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7563.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think this way of doing it is not far from what is the ordinary way, and what we have seen from historical point that the normal is that the stronger person goes first, and then relying on family reunification with spouses, and this is normally provided under international law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7563.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7568.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think also I was asked, how did she manage in Syria?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7568.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7574.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't know for sure, because she finds it difficult to speak about it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7574.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7579.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I can only say, to the other question that was asked, did she have any employment in Syria?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7579.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7588.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No, she did not have any employment in Syria in that period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7588.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7608.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then, Josh Edisquas has asked, I think I said it was pure speculation, and I apologize, I think I got a little bit carried away when I was submitting my oral, orally submitting.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7608.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7626.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a little bit strong wording, but I would maintain that the justification for the three-year rule is based on merely presumptions, and assumptions, and political considerations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7626.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7657.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think this is pretty much clear, if again going back to the preparatory work, and page 5 of my written submission, what the government says there, and the majority of politicians says to justify the rule is, and I'm quoting, this group's need for protection is generally of a more temporary nature, as the need for protection is based on a general situation which may change.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7657.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7660.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And actually the same has been said by the government today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7660.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7663.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is just a statement, a three-line statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7663.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7673.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There is no data, there is no evidence, there is no considerations regarding the specific nature of the war in Syria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7673.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7687.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The international consideration in 2015, was it likely that the war in Syria that had been going on for years should end suddenly, enabling my client to go back home in 2016.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7687.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7709.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I don't think this is sufficient to support a heavy and strong limitation of ordinary family rights for people in need of protection.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7709.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7732.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think that was the questions asked to me, and maybe I will just make one final comment, and which is that I think the government has said today that there is a consensus in Europe on waiting periods.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7732.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7764.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a rather pointed argument, and it is not in accordance with what the government has submitted in its written submission, because from the written submission it appears that actually a very few numbers, a few countries in Europe, probably four, at the very best five, has measures that are comparable to the Danish three-year rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7764.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7782.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So thinking and alleging that there is a European concession on this is not true, and in particular there is no concession among those, I think it's 47 contracting parties, that certainly do not have similar rules.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7782.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7785.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is my final word today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7785.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7787.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7787.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7787.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, members of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Robert Spano</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7790.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7793.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much indeed, Mr. Dahlager.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7793.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7797.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to an end in the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7797.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7817.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I want to again, on behalf of the court, thank all the participants this morning for this unique hearing in the history of the court and for your submissions and your answers to the questions posed by judges.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7817.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7822.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7822.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7829.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered at a later date, and the parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7829.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7833.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is therefore closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>7833.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>7833.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
