<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>7124301_11012012</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>17.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>18.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>73.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>79.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Vistiŋš and Perepjolkins against Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>81.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>93.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The case was lodged with the court on 5 June 2001 under Article 34 of the Convention by two Latvia nationals, Mr. Jānis Vistiņš and Mr. Genādijs Perepjolkins.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>93.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>100.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the third section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>100.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>104.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was declared admissible on 30 November 2006.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>104.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>110.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 8 March 2011, a chamber of the third section delivered its judgment in the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>110.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>117.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 15 September 2011, the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the applicant's request to refer the case to the Grand Chamber of the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>119.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>129.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Mrs. Reine, assisted by Mrs. Kaulina, counsel, and Mrs. Priedīte-Kanceviča, Mrs. Strautmane, and Mr. Bramans, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>129.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>135.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mr. Radziņš, counsel, assisted by Mrs. Kārkliņa, counsel, and Mr. Gromovs, advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>147.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>152.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of the applicants, Mr. Perepjolkins, is also present.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>152.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>156.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome them all in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>156.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>161.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As representative of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>161.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>166.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Radziņš for the applicants will speak first, and then Mrs. Reine for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>166.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>167.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Radziņš.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>172.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>176.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dear Mr. President, honorable judges, ladies and gentlemen,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>176.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>179.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Perepiolkins and Mr. Vistinch,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>179.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>188.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>who are represented by me, submitted their application to the European Court of Human Rights on the 5th of June, 2001.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>188.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>200.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They claimed the violation of their rights in breach of Article 14 of the Convention and Article 1 of Protocol 1, and plead compensation for damages caused to them, totaling approximately 6.7</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>200.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>212.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>million euros due to infringement of their property rights, namely unlawful expropriation of their property, ignoring the law, and discrimination on the grounds of type of property acquisition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>212.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>225.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this regard, I confirm all the facts and foundations as they have been set out in the submissions to the court and in the memorial on the merits of the case of 3rd of November, 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>225.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>228.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I would like to stress the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>228.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>245.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The state, in its observations, mainly pointed out that the disproportionate amount of the compensation paid to the applicants was connected to the fact that expropriation of land took place within the framework of the land reform.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>245.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>254.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is why it is important to understand that the land reform in Latvia has been continued from 1990 until nowadays.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>254.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>261.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And according to the national law on the land reform, it will be finalized by fixing its completion by a separate law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>261.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>272.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But completion of the land reform in certain cities and overall in the state must be distinguished from the completion of the land reform regarding the property of the individuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>272.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>277.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The goal of the land reform was to convert state property to private.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>277.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>286.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And nowhere in the legislation was foreseen the contrary, since it would have been in contradiction to the principles of denationalization.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>286.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>297.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, if the land reform were to mean that property rights obtained as a result of it are unstable and might be repeatedly ignored, it would contradict logic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>297.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>305.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We are convinced that within the framework of any land reform, change of the title may take place no more than once.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>305.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>316.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the land returned to the former owners or privatized by individual persons and legal entities became an object of the civil law-based free circulations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>316.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>328.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only restrictions are connected with the right of municipality to first refusal in case of selling the land, as well as a few restrictions connected with the maximum rent amount.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>328.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>342.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, if the state found that denationalization of the property initial was not conducted in accordance with the legislation, then the state had the right to contest the related decisions before the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>342.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>359.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The state never conducted such actions in relation to those plots of land which Perepyolkins and Vistinch in 1994 received as donations from the persons who received these plots within the framework of the denationalization process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>359.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>365.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 1994, the legislation didn't contain any restrictions regarding the donation of land.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>365.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>378.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, should it have appeared to the state that a different kind of deal was being veiled by a donation, then the state had an obligation and was fully capable of disputing such deal within a 10-year period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>378.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>380.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It doesn't happen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>380.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>387.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The state didn't initiate such dispute in relation to the above-mentioned donations to my clients.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>387.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>410.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Perepyolkins and Vistinch were a wall that they received plots of land were located in the territory of Riga Free Harbor, and that according to the Riga Free Harbor law, the remuneration received by owners of the land from the harbor for the rent might not exceed 5% of the cadastral value of land annually.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>410.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>415.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In such a way, the state protected its as well as public interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>415.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>424.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, the land owners could not receive disproportionate income by utilizing the location of the land plots in the territory of the harbor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>424.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>436.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is the way that the state and society benefits from harbors, which undeniably are an important source of income for Latvia as a transit country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>436.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>454.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For this reason, from 1995 to 1999, Perepyolkins and Vistinch litigated with Riga Free Harbor regarding the rent amount, because the harbor didn't wish to pay the maximum 5% rent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>454.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>457.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court partly satisfied their claim.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>457.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>479.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, the court stated that Perepyolkins and Vistinch were entitled to receive rent for a three-year period amounting to 421,000 lats, which corresponds to approximately 600,000 euros, or about 2% of cadastral value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>479.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>498.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the time of launching litigation between the applicants and Riga Free Harbor, the law on eminent domain provided that in the case if the owners of the land not being satisfied with the amount offered by the state, then the amount of compensation should be determined by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>498.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>507.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were no restrictions that would stipulate that the amount of compensation might depend on the way the property was acquired.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>507.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>518.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is why we are of the opinion that there has been a violation of Article 1 of Protocol 1 of the Convention, which states that expropriation is provided by law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>518.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>526.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Formally, a separate law on expropriation of properties owned by Perepyolkins and Vistinch was adopted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>526.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>546.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But at the same time, it should be considered that this separate law was based on the legislative amendments which were adopted in the law on procedure by which the law on eminent domain takes effect during the course of litigation between my clients versus Riga's Free Harbor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>546.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>566.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These amendments provided that regarding expropriation of the real estate from the persons who have acquired the real estate on the basis of donations from persons who have retrieved their property as a result of land reform, the prices of 1940 shall be applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>566.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>572.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the amount of compensation was not allowed to be determined by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>572.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>582.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And thus, compensation for the expropriated land plots of my clients was only 1,000th of its cadastral value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>582.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>587.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have no objections to the rights of the state to provide expropriation of property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>587.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>606.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, it's unacceptable if the state applies self-advantageous conditions towards an expropriation property which is already an object of civil law-based free circulation by linking the possible amount of compensation with the prices as at 1940.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>606.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>613.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Neither Peripjalkins nor Vistinch nor their relatives had been connected to these properties in 1940.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>613.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>622.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it is unlawful if their rights to just compensation are being restricted due to the status of the former owners of the land.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>622.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>634.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, it's unlawful taking into account that at the time of donations taking legal effect, there were no indications that any restrictions of that kind would be applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>634.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>647.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Had the parties been aware of such provisions of the expropriation law, they, under the Latvian law, would have concluded a purchase agreement, both by naming the price for which the state should have bought out the property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>647.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>660.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition, the amount to be paid by a named purchaser might have been considerably lower since Latvian civil law provides a friendship purchase when the subject matter is sold below its actual value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>660.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>669.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, we believe that even in such case, the state would have also applied the price of 1940 regarding this kind of friendship purchase.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>669.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>677.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Because as I mentioned before, the law was changed after the deals took place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>677.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>701.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Taking into account the above mentioned, we are fully convinced that the only goal of adoption of this law, which prohibited the competence of the court to determine the amount of compensation provided by the general law, was to ensure the expropriation of the land plots owned by Perepiolkins and Vistinj under the above mentioned discriminatory conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>701.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>715.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was confirmed by the fact that the land in the territory of Riga Free Harbor was owned and still is owned by several individuals who have obtained it as a result of land reform.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>715.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>723.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Indeed, they have not been deprived of their land property, which is more inexplicable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>723.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>739.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Riga City municipality has bought out a land plot for the price amounting to 60% of the current cadastral value from the same person from whom Perepiolkins had acquired one of the land plots.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>739.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>748.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Needless to say that this transaction was in no way linked with or restricted in any way by the prices of 1940.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>748.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>763.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to stress that there has been no single other person in Latvia, except for my clients, who had acquired the property by donation and who was later deprived of his property according to the prices of 1940.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>763.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>781.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Unfortunately, there will be nobody else, as on 4th of October, 2010, the new law on the expropriation of the movable property for public interest was adopted, which provides no restrictions with regard to prices of 1940.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>781.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>804.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It follows that the provision of the law that violated the rights of Perepiolkins and Vistinj existed for 13 years, till this litigation lasts, and was applied regarding only two persons in all the country, and which is important, it didn't exist at the time when they acquired their properties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>804.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>821.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, we believe that paragraph 1 of Article 1 of the Convention, which states that expropriation shall be carried out under the conditions provided for by the law, implies a set of provisions which shall be applied to all members of society, not only to particular individuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>821.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>833.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Otherwise, it shall be considered discrimination and violation of the rights of individuals under Article 14 of the Convention, which was conducted by the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>833.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>842.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government, in its submissions, referred numerous times to the specificity of the conditions of a country in transition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>842.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>844.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I could not agree more with this statement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>844.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>861.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to better understand the situation in Latvia at the end of 1990s, when the above mentioned law was adopted, it should be noted that cooperation between political parties and economic groups was a widely accepted practice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>861.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>863.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It took various forms.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>863.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>869.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Among them was the adoption of laws according to the business interests of particular individuals.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>869.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>885.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the most common practice was to adopt seemingly unimportant, minor, and well-hidden in terms of their true goal and impact amendments to the law, which immediately after their adoption were used for the benefit of specific interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>885.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>890.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our state has paid for most of them with its economic downfall.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>890.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>902.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this concrete case, the land plots which were expropriated from my clients, after expropriation, were immediately leased to two limited liability companies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>902.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>913.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These companies have among their owners such prominent persons as, for example, the former head of chancellery of the President of Republic of Latvia, as well as the former Minister of Justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>913.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>922.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Afterwards, the rent for their companies was set at 1.5% of cadastral value of the land.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>922.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>932.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the cadastral value was reduced to approximately 1 5th of the cadastral value on the date of expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>932.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>938.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As land tax is also in amount of 1.5% of cadastral value,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>938.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>947.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>then it means that rent received from these companies is used only to cover the tax expenses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>947.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>953.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It means no income for public needs at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>953.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>961.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only beneficiaries from this expropriation are these two companies paying rent in the amount of tax.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>961.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>963.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Amazing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>963.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>983.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We also consider, as manifestly unfounded, the explanation which was provided by the state in its memorial stating that there had been different legal circumstances regarding expropriation of the land for the needs of building the Latvian National Library for market value prices.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>983.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1000.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Precisely this case involving National Library was the right one in which to discuss the interests of the state and society, but not our case, which involves business activities at the harbor carried out by many different private entities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1000.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1023.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Furthermore, we consider unfounded the explanation of the state that expropriation for the needs of the construction of Latvian National Library was provided outside the framework of the land reform because legal status of land reform in Riga generally is the same as it was when expropriation of land of my clients took place.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1023.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1030.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only difference was the identity of the individuals entitled to receive compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1030.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1042.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is why we claim the violation of our rights and breach of Article 14 of the Convention and Article 1 of Protocol 1 and plead a compensation for damages caused to us.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1042.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1054.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the letter received from Grand Chamber, it was advised to focus also on a few principles established by the court in its case law and applicability of these principles to the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1054.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1057.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like my colleague, Mr. Goromov,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1057.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1057.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>to speak about these questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1063.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1065.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. Radziņš, Mr. Gromovs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1068.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1072.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1072.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1080.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable President, distinguished members of the court, I would like to continue the arguments of our clients and address the following points.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1080.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1084.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, applicability of the land reform concept to the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1084.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1095.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As mentioned before, our clients were in possession of the property which was not subject to the land reform legislation anymore and is object of the civil law-based recirculation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1095.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1107.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If despite the mentioned fact, the court will choose to examine the issues related to the land reform as a statewide discretion in this regard, we would like to stress the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1107.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1124.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its submissions, the government refers to the judgment of the court related to property reforms in other countries, such as the case Jan versus Germany, while describing the wide margin of appreciation which is afforded by the state in the course of the changing state's regime, including the property reform processes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1124.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1134.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Based on this judgment, the government concluded with the argument that the different treatment of applicants, if any, had an objective and reasonable justification in the instant case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1134.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1147.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, it's well recognized in academic literature that Latvia, as well as Lithuania and Estonia, should be deemed as a category in themselves by analyzing the cases of the post-communist regime institution.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1147.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1159.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is because, unlike in the rest of the cases, Germany, Poland, and other countries, the eradication of private property in Latvia took place in the conditions of Soviet occupation of the whole country.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1159.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1172.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, in Germany, the Federal Constitutional Court stated that compensation in institution cases is not based on the right to property, but the extent of principles on fairness, justice, and the social state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1172.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1176.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Consequently, there was no obligation to afford the full compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1176.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1188.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The main principle of compensation in Germany was declared to be equal treatment, but the financial situation of the state and other obligations arising from reunification were to be taken into consideration, too.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1188.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1209.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The joint statement of the two German states regarding solving the property issues, which subsequently was made part of the reunification treaty, spoke about necessity of finding a socially acceptable balance between competing interests, while taking into account the need for legal certainty and clarity in order to protect the right to property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1209.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1218.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Latvian case, the main goal of the restitution system and the property reform legislation was to ensure the reparative justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1218.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1224.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this is rectification of past wrongs without mentioning any related social aims.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1224.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1231.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the reform was conducted by means of the renewal of property rights for the former owners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1231.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1237.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And such interpretative approach was also confirmed by the Latvian Constitutional Court in 1999.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1237.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1252.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we conclude this point by saying that the arguments of government about the situation of our clients and governmental actions as conducted in specific situation of the country in the process of land reform are unsubstantiated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1252.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1261.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the second point, the issues of proportionality, it follows from submissions of the government that the amount of compensation for Mr. Peripertin and Vistinch,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1261.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1266.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>when they were to be paid less than 1,000 of the cadastral value of his possession for Mr. Vistinch</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1266.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1270.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and 1,350 of cadastral value of possession for Mr. Peripertin</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1270.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1273.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>should be considered fair and reasonable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1273.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1278.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, the government referred for numerous times to the land reform in its submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1278.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1301.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One of the main goal of this reform was to restore historic justice in case when in 1940, the people were deprived fully of their property and most frequently on the basis of their status in Latvian society, also using such non-political criteria of their status as their wealth, including the possession of removable property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1301.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1327.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, firstly, we would like to underline that in light of the court judgments in Pinsala and Pins versus Czech Republic, where the compensation amounting to 1 50s of the taken property market value was found unacceptable, the court found that the fair balance is generally achieved where the compensation paid to the person whose property has been taken and reasonably related to the market value, as determined by the time of expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1327.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1342.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Secondly, the amount of compensation for our clients was also justified by the government based on, among other reasons, by the personal and social situation, or in other words, the wealth of our clients.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1342.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1348.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should their wealth plays a decisive role during assessment of amount of compensation for the expropriated property?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1348.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1365.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If you follow directly this logic, the same social injustice is proposed as in 1940, when some of the former owners of the nationalized property were allowed to live in and use their former properties, but already as their tenants who paid the rent to the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1365.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1375.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, certainly, the government's arguments about lack of investments into possessions of our clients are ill-founded and not related to the claims of our clients.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1375.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1390.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Our clients didn't claim that they enhanced the value by means of their commercial operations, because such operations will be restricted by the place and nature of the company on the territory of which the property was located, Riga Free City Harbor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1390.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1402.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any argument put forward by the government that our clients should have invested further in their property means that the investment could only be done within the scope of activities of the mentioned harbor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1402.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1413.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such commercial activity would have been very much restricted to the specificity of work of the harbor, and its linkage to the compensation should not be considered fair and well-founded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1413.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1427.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, firstly, we would like to point out that the amount asked by our clients as a just satisfaction is not even remotely close to the market value at the time, but this is based on the state-approved cadastral value of the land in 1997.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1427.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1435.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At that time, in Riga, as capital of Latvia, such cadastral value as a rule was much lower than any market value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1435.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1445.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Distinguished court, we truly believe that the right for reasonable compensation for expropriated possession should not depend on the amount of income of the landowners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1445.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1457.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As such approach may lead to the situation when it may be declared that the person in issue does not need any financial compensation at all, or that the amount of this compensation should be just symbolic one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1457.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1464.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This would also amount to discriminatory treatment of different categories of persons who enjoy the right to possession.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1464.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1472.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the amount of compensation which was provided by the state to our clients should be deemed as disproportionately and unfairly low.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1472.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1477.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, assert on the lawfulness of the expropriation procedure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1477.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1489.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its submissions, the government went to great lengths, meticulously and repetitiously describing its view on the reason, Latvian legislative procedure, and adopted legislation on expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1489.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1499.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to found their arguments, then the expropriation took place in accordance with the law, and also quoting certain judgments of the Court of Human Rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1499.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1506.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would like to point out that the principle of legality is not limited to the compliance of actions of the government with the national law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1506.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1517.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In Carbonara and Ventura versus Italy, the court stated that the requirement of lawfulness means that rules of domestic law must be sufficiently precise and foreseeable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1517.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1533.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The predictability criteria is clearly missing in the case of our clients, and the legislator adopted the amendments to the law and procedure by which the law on eminent domain takes effect during the course of litigation between our clients and Ringa III Harbor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1533.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1542.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No doubt, such lack of predictability facilitated the whole process of successful expropriation of property from our clients.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1542.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1548.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But at the same time, it damaged greatly the whole concept of lawfulness of this process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1548.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1571.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such approach by the state to the adoption and application of the necessary legislation, which was applicable to our case, could be compared to the situation when the person would be convicted as guilty of crime, but the actions of this person were identified as the criminal ones because the law changing the definition of crime on the issue was adopted during the course of the trial.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1571.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1575.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, lastly, on the other arguments of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1575.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1594.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When assessing the efforts which were made by the government in order to prove the legality of expropriation of our client's property, we find it even more appalling that the government proposed to the court as one of the options for the final decision to reject our application by applying Article 35, Paragraph 3b, and Paragraph 4 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1594.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1606.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The provisions of Article 35, Paragraph 3b, as the government is well aware of, are not applicable to any applications declared admissible before entering the force of the Protocol 14 to the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1606.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1622.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We would like to conclude that our clients truly believe that there was a violation of their rights, of the peaceful enjoyment of possessions, as guaranteed by Article 1 of the Protocol 1 and Article 14 of the convention, and their application is well-founded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1622.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1625.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was also declared admissible by the Grand Chamber.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1625.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1637.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, it's not clear for us why it's suggested to the court by other parties that there is a possibility to breach the legal provisions of convention and to apply non-applicable provisions of conventions to the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1637.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1644.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, we would like to stress that our clients maintain their previous respective claims for just satisfaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1644.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1650.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having said that, I would like to thank the Honorable Court for the possibility to speak and to present the arguments of our clients before you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1655.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1657.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Gromovs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1657.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1661.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then I give the floor to Mrs. Reine on behalf of the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1661.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1661.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mrs. Reine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1663.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1665.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1665.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1668.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. President of the Court, distinguished judges,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1668.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1678.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ladies and gentlemen, the present case has been referred to the Grand Chamber by a decision of the panel of five judges dated 15th September, 2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1678.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1694.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Interestingly enough, this decision and today's hearing comes almost 15 years after the national authorities have adopted the impugnant decision, and almost 11 years after the present application has been lodged with the Strasbourg Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1694.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1705.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In few moments, I will explain the relevance of these dates in the context of the present case and strongly invite the distinguished judges to keep them in mind when examining the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1705.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1715.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present address, I will provide replies to questions posed by the Court insofar as they have not yet been answered in the government's written submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1715.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1723.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In doing so, I may not necessarily follow the order in which the questions were posed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1723.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1733.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will also use the opportunity to provide other relevant information that has not been included in the government's previous submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1733.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1741.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Should the Court deem it necessary, documents supporting my statements will be submitted to the Court after today's hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1741.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1743.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now proceed with our submission.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1743.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1750.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May I recommend the distinguished judges to keep a pen nearby, as you may very well need it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1750.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1772.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 1994, that is almost 18 years ago, less than four years after the restoration of Latvia's independence, and less than three years after the beginning of the land reform in Latvia's cities, the applicants signed a contract of donation for the plots of land located on the Iceland used for harbor purposes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1772.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1776.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Altogether, five plots of land were donated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1776.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1778.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first applicant, Mr. Janis Vistinj,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1778.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1785.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>acquired one plot of land upon which a part of the free port construction was located.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1785.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1788.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second applicant, Mr. Gennadis Perpilkis,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1788.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1794.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>acquired four plots of land upon which a part of free port construction was located.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1794.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1801.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The chamber, in its judgment, has very discreetly described the events surrounding the donation contracts concluded by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1801.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1811.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will allow myself to be more straightforward in describing these events, which provide good contextual background for the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1811.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1824.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the chamber, in its judgment, described the deal as donations made in return for certain personal services that the applicants had rendered to the donors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1824.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1830.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One may only guess as to the true nature of services rendered by the applicants to the donors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1830.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1837.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, I will mention only well-known objective facts that may not be challenged.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1837.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1847.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The territory of the Kunzinsala, Iceland started to be developed for the harbor purposes by the Soviet regime in the late 1970s.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1847.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1853.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before that time, there was absolutely nothing on the land plots later acquired by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1853.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1856.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Only wheat grew.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1856.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1879.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The exact place for the harbor was chosen, amongst other factors, given the depth of the Daugava River in the area and the Iceland's convenient location closely to the Daugava River mouth, the Riga city, and the Riga shipyard located in the Sarkan Daugava district, which is exactly behind the Kunzinsala, Iceland.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1879.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1890.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Development of the harbor included, amongst other, construction of a wharf, installing ship loaders, and developing transport infrastructure system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1890.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1895.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The history remains silent as to the exact amount of investment made.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1895.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1915.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is known, however, is that between the moment of restoration of Latvia's independence and the expropriation of the plots of land belonging to the applicants, that is during the period of a bit over six years, national authorities invested in the harbor more than 9.5 million euros,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1915.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1922.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>which for the then economic and budget situation was an enormous amount of money.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1922.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1945.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Shortly following the restoration of Latvia's independence in 1991, the Seima adopted the law on land reform in the cities of the Republic of Latvia, which unfortunately, and due to the obvious error by the legislator, did not contain any limitations to restoration of property rights to strategically important objects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1945.27</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1963.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hence, using the loophole contained in the law, former owners and their heirs, who have not made a single broken cent of investment in the harbor, have restored their property rights to the now very valuable and strategically important land.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1963.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1991.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But for whatever reason, those former owners obviously did not have the intention of keeping or using these plots of land, as depending on the plot of land at issue, between a couple of days and a couple of months, after registering their title in the land books, they have donated these plots of land to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1991.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2009.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I invite the court to reflect for a second, who in his or her right mind, after having such a good luck of restoring property rights over strategically important plots of land, having an endless potential of bringing profit, would want to give them away.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2009.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2018.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, by means of donation, what kind of service one would need to render in return?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2018.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2021.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We may only guess.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2021.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2034.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Perhaps the applicants had very far reaching business plans to develop the harbor that convinced the owners of the need to providing a solid platform for the just developing private sector.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2034.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2037.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, let's see.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2037.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2050.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I should have mentioned that by the time the applicant concluded the contracts of donation, the national authorities had already realized that there had been a great loophole in the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2050.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2060.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The situation with the harbor land could have been fixed had the original owners or their heirs wished to sell the land.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2060.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2070.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As in case of commercial transaction, such as purchase, the state or municipality would have the right of the first hand.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2070.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2076.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But this rule did not extend to the contracts of donation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2076.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2080.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the hands of the national authorities were tied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2080.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2084.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They could only watch from a distance.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2084.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2097.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another important aspect of the contract of donation is that the parties had to indicate provisional value of the land plot for the purpose of calculating the transaction fee.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2097.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2109.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants valued four plots of land at around 700 euros each, and the fifth plot of land at around 1,400 euros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2109.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2126.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the total investment of the first applicant for acquiring one plot of land, having total surface area of 17,998 square meters, was 119 euros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2126.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2141.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second applicant invested 164 euros and 87 cents for acquiring four plots of land, having total surface area of 47,740 square meters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2141.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2147.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those investments were composed of fees for registering the deal in the land books.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2147.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2158.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not a single broken penny was invested by the applicant into the contested plots of land before or after the donation agreements were concluded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2158.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2171.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In fact, it is crystal clear from the facts of the present case, as has just been confirmed by the applicant, that development of the harbor has never been the applicant's purpose.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2171.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2177.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it is reasonable to ask, what was the applicant's goal?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2177.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2185.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They expected that the national authorities will sooner or later buy back their plots of land.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2185.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2199.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Meanwhile, the applicants, by means of rather ultimate language, demanded rent payments, going as far as giving notice to the Freeport management to vacate the territory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2199.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2222.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants' appetite grew so big that their demand in rent payments varied between 37% of the Freeport's annual profit in 1994, 46% of the Freeport profit in 1995, and almost four times more than the Freeport's annual profit in 1996.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2222.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2231.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition to the rent payments, Freeport had to pay land tax for the land plots belonging to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2231.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2237.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What options were available to the national authorities to deal with this situation?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2237.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2240.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To move the harbor to another place?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2240.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2244.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To satisfy the applicant's appetite in rent?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2244.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2247.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or to acquire back the property?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2247.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2259.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Casadevall, in his dissenting opinion, annexed to the chamber's judgment, makes specific emphasis on the need to reach a friendly settlement between the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2259.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2270.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What obviously skipped the respective judge's attention is that the national authorities, in fact, offered the applicants a friendly agreement to purchase back the plots of land.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2270.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2276.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the applicants expressly refused to enter into any negotiations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2276.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2284.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, all options offered by the national law at the time concerned were exhausted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2284.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2297.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The national authorities had to set the legislative framework that would allow to deal with this situation and other similar situations to achieve social justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2297.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2306.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I must know that the real politic of lawmaking not always follows the rule that the law comes before the concrete situation arises.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2306.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2312.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Sometimes the real situation drives the lawmaker to create a legal rule.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2312.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2317.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Both approaches are equally constitutional.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2317.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2325.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the issue of legal certainty, one would need to define legal certainty in the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2325.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2333.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>National authorities were confronted by a situation which was not yet governed by the law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2333.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2341.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, it was rather a situation of legal uncertainty for which a legal rule had to be created.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2341.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2352.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the legislator was driven by the need to fix several legislative loopholes that were uncovered in the course of the land reform process.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2352.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2363.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First, it had to prevent further restoration of property rights to former owners and their heirs to strategically important objects.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2363.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2378.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Second, it had to establish a procedure whereby a state could restore a title over a strategically important object for which property title had been erroneously restored.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2378.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2389.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thirdly, it had to review the compensation rules to ensure that compensation paid in the mentioned cases achieves the aim of social justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2389.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2401.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, both processes should be viewed together as a part of the ongoing land reform, as correctly noted by the chamber in its judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2401.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2407.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Another important aspect to be kept in mind is that no legal rule is permanent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2407.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2414.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any law may be changed at any point of time, even with retroactive effect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2414.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2427.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is important is whether the adoption of legal rule followed the constitutional procedure and whether it was driven by an objective need in the public interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2427.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2439.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this respect, it is important to keep in mind that the applicants never had any legal expectation that they would remain proprietors of the disputed land.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2439.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2448.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their legal expectation referred to the amount of compensation that they could expect in case of expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2448.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2494.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The 19 December 1996 amendments to the Supreme Council's decision of 15 September 1992 on the conditions of the entry into force of the Expropriation Act, which in other words, were adopted more than six months before the applicant's property was expropriated, established a very clear rule that if an owner acquired from the original owner or his or her by means of donation agreement a plot of land that is subject to expropriation for public needs, the amount of compensation to be paid to the owner shall not exceed the property's value as existed in 1940.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2494.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2507.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, the amendments established an additional mechanism whereby owners could be compensated for any investments made in developing of the land at issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2507.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2518.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, as of the date the amendments were adopted, the applicants could no longer rely on their previous legitimate expectation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2518.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2523.77</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In their submissions to the court, the applicants are explicitly clear.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2523.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2530.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are not concerned about the procedure whereby the law on expropriating their land plots was adopted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2530.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2537.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The substance of the applicant's complaint refers to the amount of compensation they received.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2537.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2543.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Or to be more precise, the wish to receive an exorbitant amount in compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2543.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2552.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would invite the court to think how far these expectations meet the conditions of legitimacy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2552.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2558.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will now turn to the issue of excessive burden put on the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2558.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2572.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In this context, I would like to reiterate the well-established principle that the right to receive compensation proportional to the real value of the expropriated property is subject to many exceptions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2572.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2598.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Moreover, and referring specifically to the Yarn case, given its specific relevance to the present case, I would like to recall the court's conclusion that in case of objective necessity and in the context of transitional economy, the state's margin of appreciation goes as far as allowing expropriation for public needs without any compensation at all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2598.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2609.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To sum up what has been said above, the government would strongly invite the court to keep in mind the following issues when re-examining the present case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2609.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2623.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>May individuals as the applicants in the present case assume that they enjoy true legitimate property rights and claim protection provided by Article 1 of Protocol Number 1 to the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2623.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2633.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How far goals that they pursue comply with the requirement of Article 17 of the Convention that prohibits abuse of rights?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2633.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2660.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Looking back at events that took place almost 15 years ago, what added value may the future court's judgment bring in respect of the situation that largely took place before ratification of the Convention and in respect of the quality of the law that is no longer in force if the situation as such did not create a significant disadvantage to the applicants?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2660.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2679.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I remind that amendments of 19 December, 96 to the Supreme Council decision of 15 September, 92, as well as preceding amendments to the law reform laws were adopted and entered into force before Latvia ratified the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2679.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2700.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only act directly pertaining to the present case that was adopted less than two months following the entry into force of the Convention with respect to Latvia was the regulation of 5 August, 97, and the subsequent law adopted by the SIEMA.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2700.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2723.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given the lapse of time that have passed between the examination of the case by the national authorities and today's hearing, I may only urge the court to follow the principle established in the case SH and others versus Austria, that is to put itself in the shoes of the national authorities as they were back in 1997.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2723.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2733.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When examining whether the applicants bore an excessive burden, one needs to carefully choose the point of departure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2733.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2747.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would not be fair or reasonable to choose as a point of departure the commercial or cadastral value of the land if the applicants have never contributed a single cent to raising its value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2747.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2763.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In situations as the present one, the departing point should rather be the applicant's contribution to the development of the property in question, both in terms of time and in terms of financial investment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2763.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2781.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the present case, the first applicant invested 119 euros for which he received 780 euros and 10 cents in compensation and 75,500 euros in rent payments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2781.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2791.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, his investment brought 641% profit over the period of three years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2791.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2811.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second applicant invested 164 euros 87 cents for which he received 12,260 euros 77 cents in compensation and 524,000 euros in rent payments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2811.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2819.27</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, his investment brought 3,253% of profit over the period of three years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2823.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2828.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The national authorities may not have acted perfectly by the books.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2828.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2832.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the proverbs say, no one is perfect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2832.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2849.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Still, the legal perfectionism should not be exaggerated to the extent that would not allow the national authorities to take a swift action in response to an emerging situation that endangers important public interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2849.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2868.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Speaking of the alleged violation of Article 14 of the Convention, the government fully aligns itself with the conclusions made by the chamber in its judgment that the applicant's situation may not be considered comparable to that of other property owners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2868.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2875.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, there is no basis to speak of a different treatment of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2875.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2888.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, when commenting the outcome of the impugned measures for the applicant, another famous proverb comes into mind, look not a gift horse in the mouth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2888.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2897.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For the reasons given above, the government believes that the chamber's judgment is well-founded and well-balanced.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2897.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2907.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Not only it confirms the assessment made by the national authorities, but also fully complies with the well-established case law of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2907.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2917.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government believes that the applicants have not suffered a significant disadvantage meriting examination of the present case by the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2917.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2926.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any event, the government believes that there is no reason for the grand chamber to depart from conclusions made by the chamber in its judgment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2926.37</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2926.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2928.77</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2931.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mrs Reine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2931.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2934.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That then concludes the first round of addresses.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2934.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2940.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like now to ask if any of the judges wish to put questions to the parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2940.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2940.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First Judge Fura and then Judge Garlicki.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Elisabet Fura</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2944.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2945.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2945.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2951.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have a couple or three questions to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2951.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2958.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If I read the case file correctly, no VAT was levied on the transaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2958.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2962.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I guess this was because it was a donation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2962.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2972.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I would like you to confirm that it would have been different if it had been a commercial transaction and not a donation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2972.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2977.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My second question is rather a hypothetical one.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2977.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2981.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I'd like to put it to you all the same.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2981.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3010.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the hypothetical event of a sale of the property by the applicants at a higher price than the original acquisition price, since it was a donation, the acquisition price was zero, or the initial valuation, would there be a tax levied on the benefit that they made in selling these properties?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3010.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3026.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the third question, and this is rather a technical detail, I'm afraid, but just for me to understand completely, there is a notarial fee paid.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3026.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3032.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And as far as I understand, the fee was zero or equal to 0.35</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3032.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3034.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>euros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3034.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3038.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is referred to in the government submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3038.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3045.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Is this the global fee paid, or is it for each donation contract?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3045.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3047.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that were all my questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3047.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3047.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3048.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3050.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Garlicki.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Lech Garlicki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3054.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3061.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. I have two questions which may be addressed to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3062.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3082.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first is whether we could be given a more detailed description of the plots in question as in 1994, namely as in the moment of acquisition by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3082.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3099.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In particular, have there been already any hardware installation, any technical infrastructure like cranes, embankments? The government observations mention warehouse containers,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3099.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3107.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>stack uncovered cargo sites. But what I would like to have is a clear information</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3107.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3113.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>of what already was on this land in the moment of acquisition.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3113.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3138.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then my second question is we know that the market value of the plots in January 1996 was respectively 9,000 euros and 5 millions. Do we have any estimate what was approximately</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3138.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3149.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the market value of these plots when acquired in 1994? In other words, have there been some</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3149.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3159.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>dramatic jump in the market value within these two years or the market value already in 1994 was at least significant? Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3164.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3165.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3165.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3166.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Šikuta.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Ján Šikuta</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3168.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3176.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you. I have a question to the government and the question relates to tax reassessment</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3176.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3183.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>proceedings. In spite of the fact that at the end the courts rejected the claims of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3183.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3217.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the finance department of the Municipal Council of Riga, but my question is that the finance department asked the applicant to pay for one year, 1997, tax in sum of 18,891 and 78,382 Latvian. Now I don't know what it is in Latvian. So my question is from which value or how</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3217.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3223.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>come the finance department to this very high tax for one year? Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3225.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3227.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Sajó.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3229.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3236.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you Mr. President. My question is a follow-up to the question raised by Judge</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3236.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3246.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Garlicki and it is going to both parties. If you could elaborate on the use of these</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3246.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3257.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>plots specifically in 1997 and today. What are these plots good for the operation of</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3257.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3297.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the harbor and whether they were considered in Soviet times to be part of the harbor because in the statement of facts there are allegations that only when the decision concerning the establishment of the free port of Riga was taken, it was at that point that these plots were prospectively, and I emphasize prospectively, taken into consideration. So I just have difficulties</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3297.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3310.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>understanding how these plots were in the Soviet times, in 1994 and today, related to harbor operations physically and legally. Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3312.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3314.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Potocki.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>André Potocki</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3319.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3321.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci, Monsieur le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3321.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3326.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>J'ai une question pour le gouvernement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3326.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3343.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>L'article 2, tel que modifié par la loi du 19 décembre 1996, comporte un dernier alinéa qui vise les bénéficiaires de donations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3343.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3353.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce que le gouvernement peut indiquer à la Cour si ce dernier alinéa a été appliqué à d'autres personnes que aux requérants?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3357.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3359.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Judge Sicilianos.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3364.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3366.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci, M. le Président.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3366.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3368.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>C'est une question pour les requérants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3369.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3389.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Selon les faits tels qu'ils sont rapportés dans le dossier de l'affaire, la valeur indicative des biens mentionnés dans les contrats de donation au fin du calcul de la taxe foncière s'élevait à 500 ou 1 000 latis par terrain, soit environ 705 et 1410 euros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3389.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3397.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Apparemment, il s'agissait là de la valeur qui a été déclarée et acceptée par les requérants comme la valeur foncière à l'époque de la donation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3398.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3401.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Est-ce que vous pouvez élaborer un tout petit peu sur ces données?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3401.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3401.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Merci.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3404.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3409.61</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. Are there any other questions from the judges?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3409.61</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3414.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That doesn't seem to be the case. That being so, I propose that we</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3414.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3423.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>have a break of twenty minutes and with a view to allowing the parties to consider their answers to the questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3423.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3426.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the hearing is suspended for twenty minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4845.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4845.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4893.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4898.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is resumed and I give the floor to the applicants' representatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4898.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4900.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Radziņš, is it you who will speak?</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4903.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4904.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4904.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4914.51</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dear Mr. President, Honorable Judges, I will try to answer to questions asked by the Court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4914.51</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4945.87</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At first, regarding taxes, nor VAT, nor income tax was applied to agreements, nor donation agreements, nor purchase agreements on real estate between physical persons in 1994 or in 1996 either.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4945.87</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4977.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These taxes started to apply only about three years ago when we were in deep economic crisis and it was connected with real estate market and only then state provides the law, adopted the law, which stated that income tax will be applied to the deals with real estate between physical persons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4977.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4980.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What about VAT?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4980.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4986.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, VAT today is not applied to all agreements with real estate.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4986.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4994.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It applied only to agreements between legal entities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4994.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4998.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What about notary fees which were paid?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4998.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5014.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then yes, 0.35 euros as state fee for notary approval was paid for each of the agreements</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5014.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5034.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>because this fee in such amount was stated by legal law regulations and this fee didn't depend on the amount of the deal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5034.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5049.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such the sum connected with the donation agreement also was not necessary to show in the agreements.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5049.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5089.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The sum was necessary to show the sum of the purchase agreement, the amount of purchase agreement, but in donations agreement according to civil law such request didn't exist and only at the end of 90s it was stated that if there is not a fixed donation price in the agreement, the amount of donation in the agreement, then it corresponds to the cadastral value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5089.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5097.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And so it is still today.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5097.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5103.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What about market price?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5103.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5121.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In 1994, land market was at the same beginning and there were no even cadastral values.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5121.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5146.75</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that cadastral value which was stated in 1996, for our understanding, more or less corresponded to the market value because there were law and regulations of government how cadastral value is estimated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5146.75</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5154.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And this estimation was and it is connected with market price.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5154.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5164.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's usually estimated according to the market price taking into account the deals during the previous two years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5164.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5182.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that if we are speaking about market price, then in 1994, for our understanding, it was mainly the same as it was in 1996.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5182.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5221.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>About investments, as it is mentioned in our memorial on the merits, and also in our application, when at all there were five plots of land expropriated, and on the moment of expropriation, only three of them were covered with concrete.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5221.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5231.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were no any buildings, no any technical equipments on it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5231.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5246.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As we know, this concrete were put on the land somewhere in the middle of 80s, we can say, during Soviet period.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5246.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5258.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But at the same time, we presented to the court inventorization plans where is mentioned the price of this concrete.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5258.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5265.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is 5.28 lats per square meter.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5265.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5297.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And if we are multiplying square meters with this amount of one square meter, then it corresponds to 214,315 lats, or approximately the price, the amount of this concrete was 305,000 euros.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5297.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5326.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I want to mention that if we are speaking about denationalization in Latvia, then it was provided on very liberal, very simplified and very liberally, because nationalization took place in 1940.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5326.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5343.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In that time in Latvia, there were free market, free real estate market, normal society, and many of, very many of real estate, especially in the center of the city, were mortgaged.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5343.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5354.23</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>When denationalization took place in 1990s, then properties were returned to the former owners without any mortgages.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5354.23</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5367.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it happens that someone bought in 1940 with a loan from the bank property and his heirs received this property back as a gift from the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5367.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5370.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such was denationalization process in Latvia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5370.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5371.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So it was.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5371.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5379.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And also it happened regarding the land in the territories of harbor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5379.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5393.11</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is why in harbors, state adopted the law where stated that yes, it's possible that private persons owns the land in harbor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5393.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5403.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in such cases, the rent received by these persons can't exceed 5% from cadastral value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5403.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5411.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In such way, state protected harbor's interests and also society's interests.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5411.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5417.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And we can't understand why this regulation couldn't be applied to applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5417.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5431.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only reason was that yes, we started to litigate with the state because they wanted 5% and court decided 2% from cadastral value of this rent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5431.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5441.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But state calculated that also such amount is too high and they adopted these laws about what we are speaking here.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5441.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5446.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What about profit of harbor?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5446.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5455.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then honorable judges, you understand that profit of legal entity depends on very many reasons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5455.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5460.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For many, many reasons from business activities, from investment policy.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5460.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5467.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There can be company and harbors with billion turnover without any profit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5467.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5478.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Profit we can't use as something why it's not necessary to pay rent or why it's necessary to expropriate property from landowners.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5478.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5493.67</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If we are speaking about possible investments from landowners in harbor territories, then of course there can't be any investment policy if they are not founding their companies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5493.67</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5516.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The only possibility to invest in harbor from persons who owns properties, who owns land in harbors is to connect their business with harbor land from owner's side, equipment from harbor side, and then business runs.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5516.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5532.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally if we are speaking also about this profit of harbor, then how can we speak about any profit if till this time they are leasing these plots of land for zero?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5532.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5539.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They are leasing plots of land for 1.5% from cadastral value and paying the sum as state,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5543.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5545.71</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>the state as land tax.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5545.71</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5556.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Of course there's no profit, but who's responsible for such agreements which are signed till 2050 years?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5556.55</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5563.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These are mainly my answers to the questions and my comments on state arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5571.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5573.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Radziņš.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5573.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5574.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then I give the floor to Mrs. Reine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5579.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5581.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5581.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5590.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will first provide answers to the judges' questions, and then I will reply to some of the applicants' arguments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5590.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5598.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I may combine some of the questions, so please excuse me, but that's for the reasons of time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5598.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5606.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First question was related to the taxes or levies that had to be paid on transaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5606.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5617.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The key reply to this question is not the amount of tax, but the restrictions that could be applied on the concrete transaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5617.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5619.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was very little difference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5619.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5624.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was 2% and 3% in case of donation agreement, and 3% in case of purchase agreement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5624.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5639.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the key difference between two transactions, between the donation agreement and the purchase agreement, that in case of a purchase agreement, the state or municipality would have the first-hand right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5640.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5642.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That is the key difference.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5642.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5648.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In case of donation, the state could not interfere with the transaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5648.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5662.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A minor point, it was 35 euro cents for each of the land plot, but I think if it's three euros or 35 cents in this particular case, that's very little difference, I must be honest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5662.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5671.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a question about more detailed description of the land plots and the use of lands and the constructions that could be found upon them.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5671.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5682.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first reference that we could find in the archives concerning the exact land plots, it goes back to the end of 1970s.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5682.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5688.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's the time where that particular area started to develop.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5688.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5711.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first document that determined somehow the area of the harbor was, after the restoration of Latvia's independence, was the 1992 Riga Council decision, that was decision number 28, that determined boundaries of the harbor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5711.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5721.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So indeed there are some maybe impreciseness in the Chamber's judgment, but personally I do not find them so dramatic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5721.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5732.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are different documents referring to different periods of time, but the first attempt to define the boundaries, the formal boundaries of the harbor was the 92 decision.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5732.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5743.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then the reference to those particular land plots as belonging to the harbor area is found in the donation contract concluded by the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5743.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5750.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the applicants themselves, in concluding donation contracts, referred to the plots of land as belonging to the harbor area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5750.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5753.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So they were very well aware what they are receiving.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5755.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5766.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That particular area was practically used, as I have already mentioned, for the purposes of the free port since the late 1970s.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5767.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5774.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I must admit it would be difficult today to provide a very, very detailed description of what kind of structures there were built.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5774.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5784.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What we know, that this area was directly linked to the wharf, you could see it in the cadastral map that we have provided the court with.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5784.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5789.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was directly linked to the wharf, so it could not be bypassed, it's obvious.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5789.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5794.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You can't bypass that area when you deal with freight containers.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5794.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5800.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was a closed freight container, there was an open freight container, but the purpose of both parts was the same.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5800.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5805.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You had to move freight somehow, you couldn't go elsewhere.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5805.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5812.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, I could give you some details on the particular freight percentage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5815.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5842.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What we could see in 1996, the turnover of freight in the free trade port, that's the area where the applicants' plots of land were located, was 24% of the overall freight container turnover in Latvia, and it was 47% of the freight container turnover in the Riga area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5843.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5845.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that's a very significant percentage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5850.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5854.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Then I have, let me see, let's do a translation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5858.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5866.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then the Riga Free Trade Port, moreover, had a specialized freight container.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5866.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5885.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was adjusted to receive some kind of specific freight containers, and the turnover of that specific freight containers that were subject to some specific rules were 89% of the turnover of those specific freights in Latvia, 89%.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5885.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5887.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's, well, I think it says it all.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5891.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5910.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That was, it was a question concerning market value of the related property, and again, I would like to turn your attention to the fact that it's extremely difficult to tell the market value of that land since it was not subject to private transactions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5910.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5920.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You can tell the cadastral value, but this area is not open for private transactions, private law transactions, so it's difficult to say the, to tell the market value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5920.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5932.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But when it comes to cadastral value, and it's also related to the question on the tax reassessment attempted by the Riga Council, the tax reassessment was based on the cadastral value.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5932.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5937.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In its turn, the cadastral value is, again, a very relative term.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5937.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5947.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There were, the chamber judgment, if I'm not mistaken, refers to three sets of proceedings determining cadastral value of the land.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5947.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5949.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It mislooks one more.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5949.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>5998.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was the fourth cadastral value proceedings, the expert opinion concerning cadastral value of the free port that was conducted in 1999 that basically recognized that all previous assessments was very relative, and the method, the methodology applied for determining the cadastral value was quite erroneous, because to determine cadastral value of a free port, of a harbor, based on the proximity to the city is basically wrong, because it's not the proximity to the city that determines the cadastral value of that land in question, but it had to be relative to other similar harbors in the area to the turnover of the port, and to many other factors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>5998.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6000.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to many other factors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6000.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6013.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So that assessment was quite different, and much in the end, the price suggested as a cadastral value was much lower than the one suggested originally, because of the erroneous methodology applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6013.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6027.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But in any event, that's, again, a very relative term that may not have decisive effect on the current proceedings as we see it, and I will explain in a few moments why.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6027.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6060.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Regarding Judge Potocki's question on the amendments to the 1992 decision, the applicant's situation, indeed, was the only situation where the concrete amendments have been practically applied, but I must, again, underline that the purpose, the absolute, the ultimate purpose of the mentioned amendments was to prevent similar situations from occurring.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6062.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6073.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And that is one of the reasons why, most probably, the state never needed to apply it again, because the loophole contained in the law had been closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6074.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6076.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And I can only say prevention is better than the cure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6076.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6078.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is what the state has done.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6082.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6085.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was a very interesting question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6085.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6101.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although it was posed to the applicants, I would like to draw your attention to the evaluation of the land plots concerned when it was acquired by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6101.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6105.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It was 500 lots and 1,000 lots, respectively.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6105.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6113.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What is interesting in this concrete case is when the applicant received property, they valued it very low.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6114.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6127.08</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But when they wanted to sell it, or when the property was expropriated from them, they wanted an extreme amount of money based on completely different criteria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6127.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6139.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But we're not speaking of a situation where they would have very specific business plans, they have themselves confirmed they never had any business plan, they were not interested in developing the free port area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6139.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6142.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But then they wanted to have a large amount of money.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6142.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6144.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the reason is, my question is, why?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6144.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6158.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We're speaking about a period of a couple of years, but it was clear from the very moment they received that port, that these plots of land, they would never use it, they don't need it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6158.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6161.06</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They want to sell it and they want to rent it.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6161.06</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6173.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But when they want to rent it, they don't base their assessment on the value of the land as they themselves suggested when acquiring that land, but base it on a totally different criteria.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6174.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6179.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then they claim that they have been discriminated against.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6180.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6182.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think this argument is deprived of logic.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6187.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6192.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will turn to some of the applicant's arguments, if I may.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6192.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6219.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think I have a few minutes left.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6219.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6226.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant suggested that completion of the land reform might consist of one by one transaction.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6226.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6233.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if you take away individual transactions, what's left of the land reform?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6233.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6234.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nothing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6234.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6237.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mean, the land reform has to be somehow completed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6237.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6247.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And to say that if there has been one transaction, there can be no other transaction, I think life dictates different approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6247.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6250.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's the basic reply to this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6250.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6257.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Applicants refer to the fact that the law did not prohibit deals as the one they have concluded, but that was exactly the problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6257.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6261.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If the law does not prohibit something, it doesn't mean that what is done is just and right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6264.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6270.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it doesn't mean that the situation does not need to be rectified.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6270.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6276.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants refer to the 2010 law, which no longer provides restrictions on the amount of compensation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6276.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6281.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I'm sorry, you can't compare the situations which has a distance of almost 20 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6281.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6282.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's incomparable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6282.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6286.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And it's the same as referring to the situation of the National Library.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6286.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6298.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The expropriation of property for the purpose of National Library took place in 2005, that is seven years, no, eight years after the expropriation of the applicant's property.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6298.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6300.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You can't compare those two situations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6300.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6307.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You may compare the situation that is, where you have some proximity between the events and some other comparison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6307.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6312.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the purpose of the National Library project is totally different, is absolutely different.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6318.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6323.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicants again referred to the investments and profits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6323.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6327.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Well, it's very interesting, very interesting approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6327.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6332.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>First of all, again, we need to compare the two situations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6332.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6345.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What the applicants suggest is, the state should have endlessly invested in the area, and then paid for its own investment to the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6348.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6357.3</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And they say that it's discriminatory that the state adopts another approach, whereby it imposes lower rents on private companies.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6357.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6364.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So private companies invest in the land belonging to the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6364.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6375.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the state does not need to spend its own budgetary resources to promote imports and exports, and development of the harbor area.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6375.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6381.66</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I think this approach goes against the very logics of the economic policy of the state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6381.66</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6385.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although I understand the applicant's financial interest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6385.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6387.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will not comment any other suggestions made by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6387.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6394.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If they have any suggestions as to possible corruption, they could go to the law enforcement authorities and submit their applications.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6394.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6421.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's all I may suggest.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6421.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6427.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In case of Latvia, Estonia, and Lithuania, we speak of full reparation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6427.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6430.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To some extent, it is right.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6430.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6439.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The purpose of the land reform is to repair the former owners whose property was nationalized by the occupying regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6439.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6444.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And for that, they have suffered financial and non-pecuniary damage.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6444.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6447.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They could not have used their property, gained profit.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6447.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6455.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But it does not mean in any way that the outcome of the land reform should not be achieving social justice.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6455.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6458.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Those two purposes are simultaneous.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6458.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6460.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They go together.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6460.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6466.58</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And one does not deprive the other of a meaning.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6466.58</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6476.46</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, then the applicants compare their situation to the situation of original owners to some extent.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6476.46</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6488.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I find it difficult to agree with this because again, as I have just mentioned, the original owners suffered as a minimum, even if they have not invested anything in the land plot concern.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6488.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6496.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have suffered non-pecuniary damage because their property has been deprived by the occupying regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6496.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6500.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This, by all means, is not the case of the applicants.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6500.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6508.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They have not been deprived of possessing their property for the period over 50 years.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6508.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6514.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition to what, that they have not invested a single cent in the property concern.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6514.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6523.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then on the other hand, they compare the expropriation of their land to the nationalization in 1940.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6523.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6527.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Again, that's way out of line.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6527.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6532.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They did not suffer any personal damage in the course of expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6532.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6539.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The circumstances were different, and the purpose was absolutely different.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6539.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6541.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I will come in a few minutes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6541.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6544.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I have not used my time for this speech, so I'd like to use it now.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6548.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6563.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No, one last thing that I would like to say is the applicants specifically referred that expropriation of their property took place and amendments to the law were adopted in the context of ongoing litigation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6563.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6567.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a manifestly wrong assumption.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6567.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6574.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The litigation that the applicants referred to were litigation concerning rent payments.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6574.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6579.0</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They had no relation whatsoever to the fact of expropriation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6579.0</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6582.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That decision took many months later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6582.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6583.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>That's all I have to say.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6583.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6583.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Nicolas Bratza</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6588.3</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6590.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mrs. Reine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6590.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6594.42</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now then come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6594.42</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6600.9</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would like to thank the parties for their interventions and their answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6600.9</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6604.38</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6604.38</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6611.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later and the parties will of course be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>6611.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>6611.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
