<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Transcript>
	<WebcastID>733413_06012016</WebcastID>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>11.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>11.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>56.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>57.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please be seated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>64.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>71.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Music versus Croatia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>71.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>84.92</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was lodged with the court on 17 December 2012 under Article 34 of the convention by a Croatian national, Mr. Christian Music.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>84.92</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>94.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The application was allocated to the first section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>94.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>115.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 12 March 2015, a chamber of that section delivered a judgment in which it declared the applicant's complaint under Article 3 of the convention admissible and the remainder of the application inadmissible and held that there had been no violation of Article 3 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>115.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>126.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 10 June 2015, the applicant requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>126.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>133.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on 6 July 2015.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>133.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>165.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On 6 and 16 October 2015, respectively, the president of the Grand Chamber granted leave to the International Observatory of Prisons, French section, the Human Rights League, Belgium, the European Prison Litigation Network, and to the Documentation Center, L'Altro Diritto, to submit written comments as third parties by virtue of Rule 44, Paragraph 3 of the rules of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>165.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>178.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government are represented by their agent, Mrs. Štefica Stažnik, assisted by Mr. Alan Mostovac, Mrs. Marijana  Konforta, and Mrs. Martina  Barić, advisors.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>178.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>187.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant is represented by Mr. Zoran Vidović, counsel, assisted by Mrs. Aleksandra Vidović, advisor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>187.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>191.4</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>191.4</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>200.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I also welcome a delegation of judges, lawyers, and university professors from Italy who are on a study visit to the court.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>200.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>208.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>208.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>211.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mr. Vidović for the applicant will speak first,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>211.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>214.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>and then Mrs. Stažnik for the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>214.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>227.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting from Croatian has been authorized for the benefit of the applicant's representatives.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>227.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>236.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although that interpreting is arranged by the court, no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>236.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>237.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call Mr. Vidović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>237.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>237.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>You have the floor, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>242.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>245.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ja ću na hrvatskom, kakvom je i dopušteno.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>245.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>257.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pod 1. Prvo pozdravljam i zahvaljam se na mogućnosti da ponovno ovom predmetu</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>257.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>267.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>se pozovemo na određene činjenice, odnosno damo dodatno objašnjenje u ovom predmetu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>267.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>277.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Pod 1. U pogledu dopustivosti zahtjeva, podnositelj zahtjeva je pred Ustavnim sudom Republike Hrvatske</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>277.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>292.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>prigovorio utvrđenim zakonskim uvjetima i u biti je ukazao na povrede zbog nedostatka osobnog prostora i nemogućnosti rada u zatvoru u kojem je boravio u Bjelovaru.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>292.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>309.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>S toga smatramo da je iznošenjem svojih prigovora pred Ustavnim sudom Republike Hrvatske podnositelj zahtjeva istrpio sva domaća pravna sredstva na temelju čega je mogao pristupiti i na ovaj sud.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>309.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>331.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Navedeno proizlazi iz prvenstvenog sadržaja Ustavne tužbe i pozivanjem na povredu odredbe Zakona o izvršenju kazne zatvora koje odredbe i odgovaraju člancima 23 i 25 ustava Republike Hrvatske odnosno članku 3 konvencije o zaštiti ljudskih prava i temeljnih sloboda.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>331.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>417.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Ustavni sud je doduše odbacio tužbu smatrajući da ne postoje ustavotvorne bit stvari o kojoj Ustavni sud raspravlja što smo smatrali pogrešnim stajalištem obzirom se podnositelj zahtjeva u svojoj tužbi poziva na neadekvatnu sudsku zaštitu i diskriminirajući položaj zatvorenika temeljem članka 74 ustavak 3 Zakona o izvršenju kazne zatvora koji izričito propisuje da za svakog zatvorenika u spalovnici mora biti najmanje 4 m2 i 10 m3 prostora dok je sud na vedenu odluku tumačio da isto predstavlja samo preporučeni minimalni standard koji može biti objektivno ograničen zavisno od stvarnog građevnog stanja zatvorskog objekta što je naravno suprotno citiranom članku koji izričito i decidirano određuje u prisimnoj i obligatornoj normi riječju mora što je bio dovoljan razlog i osnov za postupanje u ovom predmetu kako pred Ustavnim sudom tim više što je u nekim slučajima i u sličnim predmetima zauzeto potpuno drugo stajalište na koje se poziva i vlada Republike Hrvatske tokom ovog postupa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>417.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>456.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dalje smatramo da je Ustavni sud trebao utvrđivati povredu na kojoj mu je ukazano temenjem cijelokupnog predmeta obzirom se Ustavna tužba podnosi kao pojedinačni akt tijela državne vlasti kojim je odlučeno o pravima i obvezama, a povrijeđeno ljudsko pravo ili temena sloboda zajamčena Ustavom temenjem Ustavnog zakona Republike Hrvatske izvudeći iz toga da je nepotrebno Ustavnu tužbu opterećivati posebno detaljima i dodatnim obrazloženjima. U odnosu na Ustavnu tužbu</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>456.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>477.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>kao pravno sredstvo kojom se strklju domaće pravna sredstva, smatramo da je bitno napomenuti da su donijete i predsude ovog suda, na primjer u predmetu Pilić kontra Hrvatska, broj 33138 od 2006. u kojoj sud ocjenjuje nebitnim pitanje da li podnosite iz zahtije uopće</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>477.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>507.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>je podniju Ustavnu tužbu obzirom je utvrđena praksa Ustavnog suda da otvrdi kako su Ustavne tužbe koje se tiču osnovalnosti određenog predmeta nedopuštene ili presudu u slučaju Longin također protiv Hrvatske 49268 kroz 10 premo koji je zahtjev pred Evropskim sudom smatran dopuštenim iako postupak po Ustavnoj tužbi još uvijek je bio u tijeku za vrijeme podnošenja zahtjeva ovom sudu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>507.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>530.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Stoga smatramo da zadovoljenje članka 35 stavka 1 konvencije o ispravnom iscrpjenju domaćih pravnih sredstava utvrđuje i ovaj sud u samoj presudi, tako da u tom smislu ne bi detaljnije elaborirali, nego ostajemo kod podnjetog zahtjeva odnosno prijedloga da isti stav zadrži i ovo veliko viječe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>530.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>540.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Drugo, sam osnov zahtjeva. Tokom cijelokog postupa vlada Republike Hrvatske,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>540.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>568.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>pa tako i u posljednjem svojem očitovanju ovom velikom viječu, općenito idealizira stanje i uvjete u kaznjonicama i zatvorima u Republici Hrvatskoj, osobito u ovom konkretnom zatvoru u Bjelovaru, a koji se nalazi u sklopu starog kompleksa zgrada izgrađenog još u početku XIX. stoljeća u vrijeme Austro-Hungarske monarhije,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>568.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>578.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>doduše djelomično adaptirane, ali bez bitno izmijenjenih i poboljšenih uvjeta za same zatvorenike.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>578.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>591.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Posobno je da su na same zgradi djelomično neki uvjeti promijenjeni, odnosno poboljšani, ali prvenstveno za potrebe suda, dok u zatvorskom dijelu je ostalo gotovo neizmijenjeno.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>591.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>622.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nažalost, zgrada puna vlage s neadekvatnim prostorom za kraće boravljenja pritvorenika, što je prvenstveno bila i namjena, a posebno za njihovo duže boravljenje, koje izvješća same vlade kako se gotovo svake godine prostori obnavljuju uređenjem i bojanjem zidova, što pokazuje da je prostor neadekvatan i vlažan, sa kojeg otpada boja i žbuka, jer u protivnom to ne bi trebalo činiti svake godine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>622.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>641.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Tijekom celog ovog postupka nastoji se od strane vlade prikazati stanje u bitno boljem stanju od stvarnog, koja uvijek sključi ši starost i vlažnost prostora kao jednog od osnovnih nedostataka kojima je boravak sam po sebi nedostojan čovjeka.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>641.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>697.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kad se tome doda i preveliki broj zatvorenika koji su smješteni u takvom neadekvatnom prostoru u odnosu na njihovu veličinu, sa WC-ima koji nisu definirani i potpuno odjeljeni od ostatka prostorije, bez dovoljno i tople vode, sa konzumiranjem hrane u samom tom prostoru sa stolom udaljenom pola metra od WC-a, bez dovoljno adekvatnih mogućnosti za držanje osobnih stvari, nedovoljno mjesta za sjedanje, tuširanje, eventualno tri puta tjedno i osobito činjenice da su zatvoreni više od 20 sati dnevno, ukazuje naopčenito loše i nedostojne uvjete u kojima zatvorenici, odnosno podnositelj zahtjeva, je izdržavao kaznu u zatvoru Bjelovaru.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>697.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>712.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Osim toga, sve navedene navodne kulturne i sportske aktivnosti kao i program obrazovanja postoje u predmetnom zatvoru samo kao teoretska mogućnost.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>712.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>756.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>U praksi to ne funkcionira, program obrazovanja u zatvoru Bjelovaru nije moguće provesti, jer za to nema ni prostora, ani drugih uvjeta, dok se sami sportski tereni i teretana nalaze na otvorenom, u dvorištu zatvora, pa zbog toga, ako ništa druga, zbog vremenskih uvjeta i zimskog perioda ili kišnjih dana se uopće ne mogu koristiti, dok i u ostalim dijelu godine, obzirom se zatvorenici puštaju iz svog zatvorenog prostora samo tri sata na dan, što je rečeno i od strane uprave zatvora od 16 do 19 sati.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>756.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>772.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Taj izvještaj je i u ovom predmetu dostavljen, a vidljivo je i iz samih fotografija da onda taj prostor ne mogu adekvatno ni koristiti. Vlada se dalje,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>772.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>787.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>dostavljajući dokaze o prihvatim uvjetima u zatvoru, a ispuštajući kod toga navesti da su određene promjene, doduše vršene, ali u 2011. godine, dakle u vrijeme,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>787.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>797.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>što je priloženo i sa fotografijama iz 4. i 5. mjeseca 2011. godine,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>797.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>811.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>i to zatvorskih prostora 2 i 9, u kojima u to vrijeme i u tom prostoru podnosite zahtjeva uopće nije boravio. Dakle, sve navedeno potvrđuje</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>811.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>821.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>i pritužba samog zatvorenika, odnosno samih zatvorenika od 1. 11. 2010. godine,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>821.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>861.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>koja je u ovom prilogu isto tako dostavljena, i to 14-orice zatvorenika, sucu izvršenja, u kojima navode sve navedene činjenice, kao i da prilikom posjete samog suca nisu mogli iznijeti navedene primjetbe, jer su obilansak vršio uz prisutstvo upravitelja zatvora i pravosudih policajaca, iz kojeg razloga se nisu mogli izjasniti o stvarim uvjetima i stvarnim problemima zbog gubitka, bojazni gubitka ostvarenih pogodnosti. Zbog toga uporno isticanje da ne naknadno</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>861.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>875.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>promjenjenim uvjetima u zatvoru, ukoliko su se ostvarili, potpuno su nebitni u odnosu na današnje i tadašnje stanje, jer od 2009. do 2011. podnositelj</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>875.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>888.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>zahtjeva bio je smješten u zatvor u bijelom, u potpuno neadekvatim uvjetima dostojnih, usvojenih standarda boravka zatvorenika na izvršenju kazne.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>888.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>934.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Navedeni uvjeti boravljenja zatvora dodatno i bitno su otežani zbog prekapacitiranosti samog prostora, koji je bio kapaciteta 53 zatvorenika, navodno dodatno povećenog na 79, ali bez bitne promjene u bilo kom dijelu prostora, a u stvarnosti konstantno preko 100 zatvorenika, odnosno kontinuirano više od 100% od utvrđenog, a to smo mogli i utvrditi preko izjave samog upravitelja zatvora kod posjeta delegacije Županije u 11. mjesecu 2010. godine,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>934.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>948.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>kad je izričito naveo da je u tom momentu u zatvoru 129 zatvorenika ili 243% više, odnosno popunjenosti, točnije opterećenosti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>948.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>970.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Takvo kontinuirano stanje, nažalost, je neki kontinuitet što je utvrdilo i Ministarstvo pravosuđa, uprava za zatvorski sustav, sa svojim izvješćem od petog studenog 2013. godine, u kojem svojemo čitovanju</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>970.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>997.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>o mjerama poduzetim prema preporukama Evropskog odbora za sprečavanje mučine, neljudskog i ponižavajućeg postupanja ili kažnjavanja, navodi, u kojem se posebno brojno stanje zatvorenika i maloljetnika u zatvorima sustavno od 2010. gdje je dosegnut maksimum, do opadanja na 31.12.2011.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>997.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1013.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ali samo u neznatnom dijelu, dakle nebitne promjene koje bi poboljšale stanje i uvjete u zatvorima. Navedeno je izvješće konkretno za zatvor u dijelu</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1013.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1021.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>i zatvor u Bjelovaru, navodi da je tijekom 2012. započeta aktivnost za potrebe</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1021.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1046.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>rekonstrukcije dijela objekta u kojem je smješten zatvor i koji će rezultirati dodatnim prostorom za smještaj, ali 15 zatvorenika, adekvatnim prostorima za pohranu arhivske građe, kao i poboljšanim prostorom kuhnje u kojoj se pripremaju obroci za zatvorenike s pratećim prostorijama za pripremu namjenica i skladište. Vrijednost investicije je 500.000 kuna,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1046.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1063.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>koje izvješće samo pokazuje da su potpuno netočni navodi o uvjetima zatvora u Bjelovaru, odnosno njegovu višesroku prekapacitiranost, naravno za vrijeme kad je u njemu boravio podnostje zahtjeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1063.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1074.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Također Ustavni sud o uvjetima života u zatvorima od 12.6.2014,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1074.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1095.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>na koje smo se također pozivali tokom ovog postupka i u ranijem podnesku o ovom velikom vječju, ukazuje da vlada nije postupila prema nalog Ustavnog suda, između ostalog, i povećanje zatvorskih kapaciteta ni u roku od 5 godina od danog naloga, a koji je bio 2008. i 2009.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1095.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1101.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Znači i 5 godina posle toga stanje je ostalo nepromjenjeno.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1101.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1130.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Upravo u razdoblju boravka podnositelja zahtjeva o zatvoru u Bjelovaru, Ustavni sud je naložio vladi Republike Hrvatske da u primjerenom roku, ne duljim od 5 godina, prilagodi kapacitete potreba smještaja osoba lišenih slobode i da pri kršenju ljudskih prava zatvorenika na smještaj primjeren ljudskom dostojanstvu i zdravstvenim standardima. Citirano iz samog izvješća,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1130.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1135.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>pozivajući se na članak 14. stavak 1 Zakona izvršenju kazne zatvora,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1135.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1155.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>jer da zatvorenici, a ne država, predstavljaju žrtve te povrede, jer oni nisu toj povredi pridonjeli, niti su propustili poduzeti nešto što bi bili dužniji učiniti, pa se ne mogu dodatno penalizirati nemogućnošću države da im osigura primjerni smještaj u zatvorskim kapacitetima.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1155.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1177.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dakle, i Ustavni sud Republike Hrvatske konstatira da je očito došlo na razini cjelokupnog sistema do određenih negativnih posljedica za zatvorenike, pa tako onda i u konkretnom slučaju.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1177.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1182.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>U navedenom izvješću se konstatira da je na dan 31.12.2013.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1182.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1214.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>popunjenost zatvora prelazila čak i 208%, to je bio zatvor u Osijeku, dok u zatvoru u Bjelovaru je preko 160%, dok su u isto vrijeme kaznjonice koje su isključivo namijenjene za osuđenike za izdržavanje kazne zatvora nedovoljno iskoristene, iz čega proizlazi da u Republici Hrvatskoj kao konstantno stanje se zatvorenicima dodatno uskračuju njihova osnovna prava jer ih se drži u neprimjerenim i nehumanim uvjetima.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1214.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1266.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kod toga mogu samo spomenuti da kaznjonice su stvarno prostori namijenjene za izdržavanje dugogodišnjih zatvorskih kazni, dok su zatvori, tako se je nazivaju, u sklopu sudova i predstavljaju prostor samo namijenjen za pritvorenike na kraćem boravku za vrijeme vođenja kaznenog postupka, dok je, nažalost, u te prostore smješten i velik broj već osuđenih zatvorenika, dakle, prekapacitiranost je i s određenom namjerom rađena, a u isto vrijeme su kaznjonice ostale nepopunjene.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1266.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1306.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kako su uvjeti u kaznjonicama i osobito zatvorima neadekvatni, na što je ukazano i od strane ovog suda u više presuda, između ostalog i u presudi Zembauer protiv Hrvatske, jedne od prvih u koje je ovaj sud utvrdio ponižavajuće postupanje obzirom je podnosite zahtjeva djelio čeliju veličine 5,6 metara s drugim zatvorenikom, odnosno oboravio prostoru manjem od 4 metra kvadratna, citiramo odloku suda, a što je minimalno zakonom uvjetovano na jednog zatvorenika, u čelijama s više zatvorenika, stoga takvi uvjeti prema mišljenju ovog suda predstavljaju ponižavajuće postupanje protivno članku tri konvencije.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1306.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1339.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dakle, sud je već ranije zauzeo stajalište o nužnosti poštivanja zakonskog minimuma od 4 kvadratna metra, ponavljam i pocrtavam, zakonskog temeljem zakona o izvršavanju kazne zatvora u Republici Hrvatskoj, kao kriterija čije nepoštivanje predstavlja ponižavajuće postupanje protivno članku tri konvencije, koje smatramo da treba primijeniti i u ovom konkretnom slučaju, odnosno na podnositelja zahtjeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1339.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1347.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Kada se navedeno uzme u obzir da je podnositelj zahtjeva stupio na izržavanje kazne zatvora u dobi od 21. godine, zbog čega mu je bila</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1347.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1380.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>potrebna pojačena fizička aktivnost, boravak izvan zatvorenog prostora, kao i da je pripadnik romske nacionalne manjine, koja činica onemogućavanje boravka na otvorenom prostoru je posebno otežavajuća okolnost, obzirom je cijeli život proveo njihovom stilu života, kao i da je u toku godinu dana imao samo četiri posjete obitelji dodatno opućuje na nehumane uvjete kojima je izdržavao kaznu zatvora u Bjelovaru.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1380.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1401.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Navedenim boravak u takvim uvjetima otežano je i potpuno izostanak zaštite neovisnog tijela, kako to imenuje vlada Republike Hrvatske, obzirom sutkinja izvršenja, jedan nemili događaj od 12.8.2010.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1401.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1418.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>u zatvoreničkoj sobi u kojoj je boravio prijavitelj, a proizlazi da je u tom prostoru, temeljem izvješća uprave zatvora, boravila osmorica zatvorenika i odbilo večeru zatvorilo ulazna vrata čelije.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1418.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1432.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>U svom rješenju, povodom žalbe, odnosno prijave samog prijavitelja od 7.10.2010. navodi da je u sobi broj 8 smješteno sa njime</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1432.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1456.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>petero zatvorenika, iz čega potpuno proizlazi nedosjednost i neobjektivnost u odluci da nema potrebe za sudskom zašitom zatvorenika, odnosno podnosite zahtjeva je na taj način i diskriminiran od takozvanog neovisnog tijela. Smatramo naravno kod toga bitno</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1456.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1484.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>ispomenuti da sutkinja izvršenja koja je donijela odluku u prvom stupnju je ujedno i predsednica suda u Bjelovaru koji sud je bio nadležan odlučivati i u drugom stupnju i to naravno od sudaca istog suda. Naravno, isto tako možemo konstatirati da sudska zaštita</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1484.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1492.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>mu nije pružena. Podnosite zahtjeva imao je i onemogućenu zaštitu</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1492.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1542.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>od drugog stvarno neovisnog tijela, omdusmana, kojim se pismeno obratio izjavljivanjem pritužbe na uvjete u kojima boravi u zatvoru u Bjelovaru i osobnu zaštitu, ali mu je ista i faktično onemogućena obzirom nekoliko dana prije najavljene posjete zatvora u Bjelovaru od strane navedenog omdusmana koji bi imao naravno i direktan uvid na uvjete u zatvoru i razgovora sa podnositeljem zahtjeva, isti je premješten u zatvor u Vareždinu, iako mu je takav zahtjev više puta prije toga onemogućavan i uskračivan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1542.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1565.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Na kraju ističemo da je u odnosu i na predmet Pozajić kontra RH, koji je do duše odbijen, razlika ne samo u duljini boravka, već i fizičkog i mentalnog stanja podnositelja zahtjeva na njegovu dop, na njegovu nacionalnu pripadnost, koja je različita u odnosu na ovaj predmetni slučaj.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1565.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1617.62</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I usprkos tome, sud je i u tom predmetu, u broju 5901 kroz 13, utvrdio nedostatak propisanog osobnog prostora u odnosu na nacionalno zakonodatstvo, ali je očito uzao obzir da je podnositelju zahtjeva pružena adekvatna zaštita kao neovisnog suda, iako smo sada pokazali na jednom primjeru da to nije slučaj, iako je sudkinja izvršenja usprkost konstantnoj prenapućenosti zatvora odbijala tu istu sudsku zaštitu pružiti zatvorenicima, na što je ukazano od više njih, u onom podnesku od 16 zatvorenika, i koje je pogrešno potpuno uzimalo u obzir uvijete u kojima oni borave.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1617.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1679.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Želio bih još također i staknuti da je podnositelj zahtjeva za vrijeme izdržavanje kazne zatvora u Bjelovaru imao i određenih psihičkih problema, od kojih je liječen u više navrata, za to postoji i liječnička dokumentacija koja je priložena kao izravne posljedice stanja u zatvoru i odnosa prema njemu, a također liječen je i kod oftamologa zbog pogrošanja vida uvjetovanog neodisotkom svjetla, odnosno uvjetima u prostoru u kojem je boravio više od 20 sati na dan, što nepobitno ukazuje da zbog neprimjerenih uvjeta neadekvatnu sudsku zaštitu je u konkretnom slučaju imao nažalost sam osjetiti kroz cjelokupni boravak u zatvoru.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1681.62</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1724.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Na osnovu takvih činjenica smatramo da je naš zahtjev u odnosu na podnositelja zahtjeva osnovan, da obzirom je stvarno boravio kontinuirano u nehumanim i neadekvatnim uvjetima i da je na taj način došlo do povrede članka tri konvencije, iz kojeg razloga predlažimo ovom visokom tijelu i sudu da zahtjev usvoji utvrđujući da minimalni uvjeti koji moraju biti zadovoljeni i oni koje je odredilo nacionalno zakonodavstvo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1724.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1724.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hvala lijepto.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1727.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1730.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Vidović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1730.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1733.55</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I call Mrs. Stažnik. You have the floor, please, Mrs. Stažnik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1735.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1736.54</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1736.54</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1748.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges of the grand chamber, in today's hearing I will outline the relevant facts and summarize main legal submissions while my colleagues and me will deal with questions and reply to the applicant's submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1748.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1755.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Merchants case is one of many cases related to prison conditions in the context of Article 3 of the Convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1755.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1766.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>What makes it special is the dissenting opinion in which several different approaches were identified in what seems to be the same prison conditions issues.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1766.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1776.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court may assess this issue and render a unified set of principles for future cases, thus eliminating any doubts regarding the consistency of its case law.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1776.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1785.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In all prison condition cases, the court refers to the quantity of personal space afforded to an applicant as the most important factor to be considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1785.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1788.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It distinguishes two principal approaches.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1788.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1799.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The first approach entails an automatic violation of Article 3 if the personal space of an inmate doesn't meet the required threshold being three or four square meters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1799.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1806.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is what the court calls the lack of personal space that constitutes a violation in itself.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1806.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1815.22</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The second approach entails a strong presumption of a violation if the personal space doesn't meet the required threshold.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1815.22</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1830.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The strong presumption can be, however, rebutted only if there are sufficient and strong country balancing factors such as sufficient time spent outside the cell, good material conditions, purposeful activities, et cetera.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1830.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1842.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This approach, more flexible in nature, simultaneously balances among multiple factors of an applicant's prison stay in order to reach a conclusion on the possible violation.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1842.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1846.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The dilemma can be, in its essence, defined as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1846.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1852.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An automatic approach against the flexible, overall analysis of an individual case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1852.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1862.94</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government strongly advocates for a flexible approach already applied by the chamber as the automatic approach doesn't correspond to real life situations.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1862.94</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1877.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, Article 3 entails a person's right not to be subjected to torture, degrading or humiliating treatment, meaning a treatment that goes beyond that inevitable element of suffering and humiliation connected with imprisonment.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1877.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1881.5</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Suffering and humiliation are, however, subjective categories.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1881.5</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1889.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Their existence depends on the perception of a particular individual and variety of factors existing in real life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1889.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1906.78</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government believes that this very fact call for a more flexible analysis of every individual case, taking into account numerous factors of a person's stay in prison, not only the shared number of square meters at this person's disposal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1906.78</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1914.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The very nature of the prison condition cases naturally puts personal space as one of the most relevant factors to be accounted for.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1914.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1916.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The government doesn't see the need to change this.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1916.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1926.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, the government sees real danger in putting the square meters on the pedestal as the sole factor for deciding on the possible violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1926.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1938.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such automatic approach, due to its simplicity, cannot respond to the complexity of each and every inmate's individual situation, his or her personality, and specific prison regimes.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1938.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1946.82</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On the other side, a flexible approach allows the court to perform its primary role, to protect the practical rights of real people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1946.82</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1952.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Human Rights Protection System was introduced to address the situation of real harm to real people.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1952.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1962.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the court's own words, the convention is intended to guarantee rights that are practical and effective and not theoretical and illusory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1962.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1969.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This certainly doesn't mean that the court should lower the bar of human rights protection standard in prison condition cases.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1969.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1979.96</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Quite the opposite, the court is here to set the pace for member states to adapt and improve their prison systems as to eliminate any possible violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1979.96</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1987.74</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is important to remind ourselves that each inmate, each prison regime, and each prison system is a universe of its own.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1987.74</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>1993.98</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some prison systems and regimes allow minimal personal space while affording maximal time outside the cell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>1993.98</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2004.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Some, on another hand, allow a relatively vast personal space inside the cell while simultaneously limiting the possibility of time outside to a bare minimum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2004.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2013.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, various prison systems cannot be scrutinized evenly, automatically, without the jeopardy of producing results which are well at odds with real life.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2013.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2028.14</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>For example, in Ventura Penitentiary in Croatia, an open prison facility without prison cells, inmates use their cells only for sleeping purposes while spending the rest of time outside the cells and even outside of the prison limits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2028.14</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2035.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This penitentiary cannot be scrutinized in the same manner as some other prisons where the inmates are under strict regime.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2035.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2038.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So how to deal with prison conditions cases?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2038.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2045.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In any case before the court, it should be taken into account that each state has a different criminal and penal system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2045.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2048.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And the causes of overcrowding are not the same.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2048.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2055.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Each member state's objective capability and resources to combat this problem are all not comparable.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2055.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2061.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Against this backdrop, the possible solutions to overcrowding itself take time.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2061.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2072.86</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And their effects on a particular person already in such a prison are limited, as the chamber rightfully noted in the recent judgment of Mironovas and others versus Lithuania.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2072.86</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2078.02</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the state should definitely resolve the underlying causes of overcrowding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2078.02</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2081.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, at the same time, a margin should be left to every state.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2081.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2092.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And every state should be encouraged to implement counterbalancing factors, counterbalancing measures that can immediately and effectively improve an individual's inmate quality of life in prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2092.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2104.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Given their nature, these measures also improve the overall quality of life in a prison for all inmates and provide a solid foundation for future improvements of the system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2104.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2123.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is only the flexible approach that values counterbalancing measures and encourages the state to battle the adverse effects of overcrowding with immediate results, while at the same time influencing the states to implement long-term measures aimed and remedying the causes of overcrowding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2123.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2134.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Reaffirming the flexible approach would not run counter to the court's case law, as one of its foundations is the need to consider the particular circumstances of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2134.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2147.68</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court's approach applied in Croatian cases reflected the consideration of overall conditions of detention and applicable regime in an institution, while giving due regard to personal space afforded to the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2147.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2155.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This approach also appreciated the complexity of a particular applicant's personal situation, his specific needs, and complaints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2155.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2171.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Most importantly, the flexible approach applied in judgments, Senbauer, Novak, Testa, Dolenc, including recent Pozajic judgment, produced tangible results with respect to Croatia's prison system, overcrowding issue, and inmates' rights.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2171.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2181.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As court noted in the Senbauer case, Croatia has continuously shown its willingness to comply with the recommendation of the court and other bodies of Council of Europe.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2181.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2188.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Namely, in terms of legislation, the criminal code and the code of criminal procedure were amended, and the long probation was adopted.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2188.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2199.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The changes enabled broader use of alternative measures, such as community work and implementation of the probation system at national level, which all led to lower number of inmates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2199.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2206.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In terms of material conditions, five prisons and penitentiaries, including Bialovar Prison, were renovated, and their capacities increased.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2206.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2217.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Ministry of Justice continuously monitors the number of inmates in each institution, allowing for more efficient allocations and transfers of inmates between institutions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2217.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2222.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Croatian Constitutional Court and the Obduzwoman strictly and carefully scrutinize prison conditions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2222.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2236.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Constitutional Court examines individual constitutional complaints and monitors the implementation of its recommendations on the prison system conditions, with specific emphasis on overcrowding issue.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2236.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2254.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In order to improve the quality of execution of sentences, reduce assiduous and strengthen rehabilitation of inmates, competent authorities offered additional activities to inmates, as well as group and individual programs, cooperating with the NGOs and local communities in this respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2254.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2270.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>They particularly focused at edits, providing them with psychological and spiritual support, and at achieving restorative justice and rehabilitation, providing education and creative programs, such as writing and music to inmates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2270.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2277.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Post-penal programs facilitate inmates' integration into the community after serving the sentence.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2277.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2284.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Simultaneously, gyms, community rooms, and other facilities for additional recreational and educational activities were equipped.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2284.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2305.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Such multilayered approach, taken by the Croatian authorities, takes into account structure and conditions of a particular prison, as well as the profile of inmates, thus resulting in wider freedom of movement during a day in closed regime prisons, experiencing difficulties with overcrowding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2305.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2320.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>An inmate immediately benefits from these measures, which significantly improve the quality of his or her everyday life, and may be implemented relatively quickly within the objective limits of the state resources.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2320.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2344.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The result of Croatia's continuous work on improving prison conditions within the existing system is the fact that in January 2016, Croatian penitentiary system is filled at 85% of its capacity, meaning that there are 3,323 inmates, while the capacity of prison system allows for 3,900 inmates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2344.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2353.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In other words, today in Croatia, the conditions were created wherein every inmate can have four square meters of personal space available.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2353.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2364.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These results are tangible, influenced by the judgments in which the court took into account overall conditions in the prison in question, and particularities of the inmate in question.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2364.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2371.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>One should not underestimate the impact of the court's judgment that had in this respect.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2371.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2390.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is a result of continuous and simultaneous work on multiplied tracks aimed at reducing overcrowding, strengthening the system to respond to issues arising within it, improving material conditions, and the range of activities and programs in particular prisons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2390.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2396.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Honorable judges, turning back to Muricic's case, the government notes that the chamber applied a flexible approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2396.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2401.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>If an automatic approach was applied, the case would have quite a different outcome.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2401.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2405.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The fact that Mr. Muricic had spent even one night in a cell</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2405.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2412.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>giving him less than four square meters would have led the court to conclude that the applicant's rights were violated due to the lack of personal space.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2412.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2416.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>No other factors would have been considered.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2416.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2418.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, Mr. Muricic requested the transfer</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2418.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2425.7</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>from Bialovar to Varazin prison to be somewhat closer to his family, knowing that Varazin prison was more overcrowded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2425.7</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2428.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It clearly follows that Mr. Muricic himself</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2428.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2435.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>deemed that visitation possibilities in Varazin prison outweighed his need for additional square meters of personal space.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2435.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2446.03</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This case perfectly illustrates complexity of each inmate's situation, which needs to be assessed in light of particular circumstances of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2446.03</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2465.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Without appreciating the complexity of an individual criminogenic needs and risks, the complexity of the prison regime imposed on him and the reasons behind it, simply applying the automatic approach, the court is in jeopardy of becoming the protector of rights that are theoretical rather than practical and effective.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2465.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2472.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This danger does not exist if the flexible overall assessment approach is to be applied.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2472.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2489.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the question of personal space afforded to the applicant, the regime in Bialovar prison enabled him to benefit from a wider freedom of movement during the day, from unobstructed access to natural life and air, as well as from a wide range of recreational and purposeful activities in well-equipped and well-kept facilities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2489.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2498.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As the chamber correctly established in its judgment, the regime in the prison allowed the applicant to spend considerable part of his mornings and afternoons outside the cell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2498.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2503.34</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thus, the applicant did not spend 21 hours a day in his cell.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2503.34</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2511.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In the morning, he and other inmates would wake up at 7 AM on a working day and at 7.30 AM during the weekend and holidays.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2511.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2518.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>After rising, he would do personal morning hygiene, tidy his bed, have breakfast, followed by morning cleaning of the room.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2518.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2527.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Leisure time was scheduled afterwards until 1 PM, when the applicant partook in a number of activities, as described in detail in the government's written submissions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2527.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2531.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Leisure time was followed by lunch served between 1 and 2 PM.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2531.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2538.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The period after lunch was intended for various group activities and meetings with lawyers and prison staff.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2538.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2548.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Between 4 and 7 PM, the doors of all inmates' rooms were opened again, enabling them to move within the prison and use its facilities freely.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2548.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2554.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dinner was served at 7 PM, followed by evening tidying and cleaning of the inmates' rooms and other rooms of the prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2554.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2564.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The inmates' schedule included showering at least three times per week in renovated shower facilities, located both on the ground floor and the first floor of the prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2564.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2572.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>During the morning and afternoon, the applicant had a wide range of movement and activities at his disposal.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2572.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2581.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Outdoor activities and access to fresh air were guaranteed to the applicant and other inmates, both in the morning and in the afternoon.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2581.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2593.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Shortly before the applicant's admission, all the facilities of Bialovar Prison, including the cells, sanitary, and showering facilities, were newly refurbished and regularly maintained during his stay there.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2593.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2603.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Overcrowding in Bialovar Prison, therefore, did not empower any of the applicant's rights, visitation rights, access to health care, sports, and outdoor activities, and others.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2603.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2619.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It did not prevent him from contacting outside world whenever he expressed he wished to do so, from accessing medical care when in need, nor did it impair any other right guaranteed by domestic law or the convention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2619.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2634.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Although a relatively small institution in terms of its inmate capacity and number of cells, Bialovar Prison building complex has a large inner courtyard, wide hallways, and sufficient facilities for indoor activities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2634.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2643.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the applicant's possibility to work in the prison, the government emphasized that there were particular circumstances of his case that affected his eligibility to work.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2643.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2652.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Before his transfer to Bialovar Prison, in a semi-open conditions of Turopoli Penitentiary, the applicant worked and had a wide freedom of movement.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2652.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2662.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, he threatened escape, self-harm, and violence towards himself and others, thus necessitating his transfer to Bialovar Prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2662.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2672.39</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>His behavior remained problematic in Bialovar and later Varazdin Prison, so his potential engagement in work in or outside the prison entails a high security risk.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2672.39</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2685.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Security reasons are the crucial factor in deciding which inmates will be eligible for available work, as almost all work is done outside the prison's premises and in the open in Bialovar town community.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2685.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2695.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, the number of available work posts for inmates was limited due to economic crisis and high unemployment rates in Croatia, where Bialovar community was no exception.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2695.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2702.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the fact that applicant was not engaged in work should not be viewed as a crucial factor in this case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2702.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2712.07</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As to the independent evaluation of his case, the sentence execution judge of Bialovar County Court was the first interviewing the applicant about his complaints.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2712.07</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2718.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He sought and addressed all the documents related to prison condition, regularly visited the prison, and spoke with inmates.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2718.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2729.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As an independent and impartial judge, she was best placed to assess conditions in the prison, and she had a direct contact with the applicant and direct insight to the prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2729.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2731.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>She found that the applicant's rights were not violated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2731.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2740.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Ombudsman also reviewed the applicant's complaint, finding that his central complaint related to transfer to Varazdin prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2740.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2744.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He also noted that the Bialovar prison was recently renovated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2744.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2750.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The Constitutional Court also reviewed the applicant's submission and found that they were manifestly ill-founded.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2750.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2760.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Finally, the chamber itself found that the overall conditions in Bialovar prison in respect of the applicant did not amount to violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2760.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2777.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In addition to chamber's finding in this case, the chamber assessed the conditions in this particular prison in the same time period in the case of Pozaic versus Croatia, and anonymously found a violation, a no violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2777.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2791.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>In light of above, although the applicant was not afforded four square meters at all times, domestic authorities undertook all possible measures to improve his conditions, and all of his complaints were properly examined.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2791.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2799.15</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we deem that the court should reaffirm the flexible approach and find no violation of Article 3.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2799.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2806.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As for the applicant's just satisfaction claim, we find it to be over-excessive and unsubstantiated.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2806.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2808.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank you for your attention.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2809.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2817.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Mrs. Stažnik and I thank both parties for their interventions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2817.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2826.63</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And now I would like to invite the judges of the Grand Chamber to ask the parties the questions they may have.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2826.63</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2831.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Any questions?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2831.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2832.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge President Sajó please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2832.79</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2832.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>András Sajó</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2835.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2836.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2836.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2841.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is a question to both parties, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2841.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2856.26</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Having read the file and various submissions by the parties, I still don't exactly picture how the person at the material time, the applicant, moved in the prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2856.26</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2860.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So I really would like to have a better understanding.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2860.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2873.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I assume that after having breakfast and having cleaned whatever he had to clean, was he, was the cell door open and he could leave wherever he wanted?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2873.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2879.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And then, assuming that this is the case, where was he able to go?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2879.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2882.1</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I understand that there is a courtyard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2882.1</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2885.18</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There are some gym-like facilities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2885.18</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2896.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But I don't, assuming that the same applies to all other inmates, how many of them are at the same time playing basketball, reading in the library?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2896.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2900.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I just don't understand because I don't have a full picture.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2900.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2910.12</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So if you could explain to me or to us what actually happens, how many people are there at the same time, what happens if it's raining?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2910.12</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2914.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So all of them have to leave the courtyard, and so on and so forth.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2914.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2928.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It would be extremely helpful to understand whether really he is not all the time, as the applicant's lawyer claims, is locked up.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2928.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2939.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So even if he's not locked up, I don't understand what exactly happens to him if he wishes to go one place or another within the prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2939.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2948.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>And what is the size of those places compared to the number of all the inmates wishing to do the same thing he might wish?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2948.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2948.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2949.08</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2951.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much Judge Sajó.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2951.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2953.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Judge Pinto de Albuquerque, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2954.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2957.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you, Mr. President.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2957.84</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2962.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>My question is addressed to the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2962.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2984.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>According to Croatian law, and I refer to Section 74 of the Enforcement of Prison Sentences Act, there shall be a minimum space of four square meters and 10 cubic meters per prisoner in each dormitory.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2984.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>2999.44</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This looks like to me as an absolute minimum approach to the size of the available space to each prisoner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>2999.44</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3001.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, my question to the government is the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3001.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3026.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>How can the government today defend before this court a flexible overall approach, a flexible overall standard, which is not only contradictory vis-a-vis the national law, but also with the CPT standards to which the government itself has referred to?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3026.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3026.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3027.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3028.47</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3028.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3029.84</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>President López Guerra, please.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Judge</Role>
		<Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3032.47</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3034.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>A very brief question to both parties.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3034.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3042.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It's in average, how many hours a day is the prisoner locked up in his cell?</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3042.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3045.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I mean, you can give me a figure.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3045.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3045.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3047.11</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3052.31</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much. I understand there are no more questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3052.31</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3071.79</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>So the court will now rise for, say, until 20 past 10, following which the parties will return for a second round of short pleadings to respond to the submissions in the first round and to the judges' questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Announcer</Role>
		<Name>UNK</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>fr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3372.68</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3373.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>La Cour!</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3416.28</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3423.28</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The hearing is now resumed, and I call Mr. Vidović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Applicant</Role>
		<Name>AP1</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3425.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3427.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hvala lipa.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3429.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3446.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Obzirom da su bila prvo određene pitanja koja se tiču i samog podnositelja zahtjeva, ja bi volio istaknuti da uvjeti u ovom zatvoru su praktički ne promjenjeni više od 100 godina.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3446.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3458.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mi smo svi druge standarde usvojili u postupanju ne samo sa zatvorenicima, ali uvjeti su ovdje ostali gotovo neizmjenjeni.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3458.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3470.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Taj zatvor nema osnovne uvjete za kraće boravljenje, a također ni za duže boravljenje, još manje.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3470.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3481.36</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mi smo napomenuli da je prisutna opterećenost gotovo jedna od najviših u Republici Hrvatskoj.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3481.36</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3492.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To smo dokumentirali i sa izvješćem upravitelja zatvora, koji je naveo to i za novine.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3492.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3543.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Isto tako možemo spomenuti da je upravo taj upravitelj zatvora naveo, i to smo koristili u ovom predmetu u višinavrata kao dokaz, da se očelije otvaraju u 16 sati, da zatvornici izlaze van kao što je obaveza minimalno 2 sata dnevno do 19 sati, iz kojeg razloga se može samo utvrditi da njima je omogućeno više od 20 sati izlaženja iz tog zatvorenog prostora, obzirom da u tom prostoru oni ne samo spavaju, nego i jedu, obavljaju nuždu, gledaju televiziju i hrane se.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3543.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3557.16</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>To je stvarno ponižavajući moment za svakog zatvorenika, pogotovo za ovakvu mladu osobu kao što je podnositi zahtjeva.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3557.16</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3566.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Mogu što se njega tiče još napomenuti da se cijelo vrijeme od strane vlade pokušava ga prikazati kao problematičnu osobu.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3566.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3582.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>On je stupio na izdržavanje kazne zatvora prvi puta u svom životu u šestom mjesecu 2009. godine u kaznjonicu u Turopolju,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3582.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3594.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>poloutvorenog tipa. Tamo je bio 3 mjeseca, 3,5. Ta kaznjonica ima i zatvoreni tip na kojeg ga se moglo primjestiti,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3594.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3607.64</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>međutim, on je nakon 3 mjeseca, citiram vladu, zbog prijetnji da će pobjeći, primješten u zatvor u Bjelovaru.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3607.64</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3614.72</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nikakav postupak konkretan protiv njega nije vođen, nije se otvrdilo što se točno dogodilo.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3614.72</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3633.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Možemo naravno samo pretpostaviti da je imao nekih osobnih problema, što, nažalost, nije rijedak slučaj u zatvorima, pogotovo za mlađe osobe, da sad ne idemo u detalje, ali možemo svi pretpostaviti o čemu se radi.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3633.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3668.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I on je na brzinu maknut iz tog tih uvjeta u kojima je i radio i s njim nije bilo praktički nikakvih problema da bi otišao u jedne ovakve nehumanitarne uvjete, jer ga očito nisu mogli zaštititi od drugih zatvorenika premještenjem u drugi odjel zatvorenog tipa. Kad je u Bjelovaru tražio, obzirom nije dobio adekvatnu zaštitu od suda,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3668.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3690.56</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>kad je tražio zaštitu od pučkog pravobranitelja, odnosno obdusmana, koji se bavi konkretnim pitanjima i koji je najavio svoj dolazak u zatvor u Bjelovaru, on je u roku od dva tjedna premješten u drugi zatvor u Varaždinu, iako mu je prije toga u nekoliko navrata taj premješte uskračivan.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3690.56</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3709.8</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Znači, željelo se je isključivo izbjeći mogućnost da on bude u doticaju sa osobom koja će utvrditi uvjete u zatvoru i koji će utvrditi njegovo stvarno stanje u kojem se nalazi i njegove psihičke i ostale probleme koje su iz svega toga proizašle.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3709.8</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3733.76</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Da se radi o osobi koja nije problematična, vidimo i na kraju da je pet mjeseci prije završetka izdržane kazne otpušten na uvjetni otpust. Onaj koji radi probleme koji nema određene ocjene koje su kontinuirano rađene</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3733.76</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3743.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>unutar zatvorskog sustava, on ne bi bio otpušten pet mjeseci ranije od prije isteka kazne zatvora.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3743.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3755.48</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Prije na tome, to sve skupa upućuje da je on kontinuirano dovođen u situaciju da mu taj boravak bude maksimalno težen.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3755.48</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3763.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Drugo što bi još htio istaknuti, cijelo vrijeme se govori o uvjetima koji se nastoje poboljšati.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3763.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3778.52</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Republici Hrvatskoj je, rekli smo, u 2008. i 2009. naloženo od Ustavnog suda da promijeni uvjete u zatvorima.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3778.52</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3790.6</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Dan je i rok, najduže pet godina. Za tih pet godina nije izgrađeno ništa. Nije nijedno zatvorsko mjesto izgrađeno</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3790.6</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3800.99</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>kroz to vrijeme. Govori se sada da će to biti u 2016. Odobrena su određena sredstva iz EU koja nisu iskorištene</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3800.99</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3813.24</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>u 2012. i 2013. osim na ovakvim uvjetima nekakve kozmetičke promjene nekih dijelova zatvora kao što je zatvor u Bjelovaru,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3813.24</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3824.2</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>gdje će se poboljšati kuhnja, gdje će se poboljšati arhiva, ali sam smještaj i sami uvjeti zatvora su ostali isti.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3824.2</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3846.91</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Jedino što se u svemu tome zadovoljava u takvim zatvorima je 10 kubnih metara, naravno zato jer su to stare zgrade sa 5 metara ili 6 metara visine, kao što je i tamo, ali sve ostalo je ostalo na nivou onoga što smo imali prije 100 godina. To smatramo nedopustivim,</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3846.91</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3874.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>pogotovo zato jer su i države, među kojima moram priznati i moja, preuzele određene drugčije standarde i smatramo da ispod tih standarda više se ne može ići. Da tih 4 metara, kao koje je konstatirao i ulaženi sudac, je minimalni dio koji se mora zadovoljiti</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3874.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3887.32</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>da bi ljudi koji su na žalost u takvim uvjetima završili imali kakve takve ljudske uvjete za boravak u tom zatvoru.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3887.32</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3925.88</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Nažalost, ja sam već prije napomenuo i sad još ponovno ističem da je Ustavni sud u svojom izvješću govorio i to je decidirao naveo ne ljudske uvjete zatvora u, ne samo Bjelovaru, nego općenito tih zatvora u koje se kontinuirano smještaju ljudi umjesto u kaznjonice koji su predviđeni za boravak takvih zatvorenika jer se tamo može raditi, tamo se može normalno boraviti, održavati određena fizička aktivnost, a u ovakvim pritvorskim uvjetima je to sve skupao nemogućeno.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3925.88</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3934.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Zato smatramo da je ovo u svakom slučaju u cijelosti opravdano obzirom na sve što je utvrđeno tokom ovog postupka.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>hr</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3934.04</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3934.04</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Hvala.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3935.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3938.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Vidović.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3938.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3940.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I call now Mrs. Stažnik.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3940.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3941.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Please, you have the floor.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>Government</Role>
		<Name>GR2</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3944.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3954.81</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Esteemed judges of the Grand Chamber, I will answer the questions posed by the Grand Chamber in view of Mrs. Stajnik, if you allow.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3954.81</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3959.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, I would like to address the questions number one and number three.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3959.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3964.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>These questions are very similar, so I will answer them simultaneously.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3964.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3976.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Now, as for the applicant's own situation, as for his freedom of movement, the government would like to stress that he had two hours of daily activity in the open.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3976.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3985.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Additionally, he had additional three hours of activity in the out in the indoor when the doors of his cell were opened.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3985.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>3998.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that he could move freely inside the prison building and engage in daily activities such as socializing, social games, watching TV, anything he wished or desired to do.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>3998.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4009.09</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that he was not kept in his cell during the 21 hours, as stressed by the applicant and on some other different occasions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4009.09</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4013.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that he could move freely during five hours at minimum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4013.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4022.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, it is important for you to understand that he was not kept in his cell without any purpose during the day.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4022.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4024.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was engaged in numerous daily activities.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4024.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4028.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Besides the mentioned five hours, he also received visits.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4028.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4031.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He also had interviews with prison staff.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4031.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4033.49</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He also received his lawyer.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4033.49</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4037.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, he was never kept in his cell without any purpose whatsoever.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4037.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4040.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>He was always engaged in some sort of activity.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4040.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4053.85</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Also, as regards the freedom of movement on the yard of the prison, it is important for you to understand that this courtyard has the surface of 305 square meters.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4053.85</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4063.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The prison authorities took great care into allowing for each prisoner to have sufficient space to move within the courtyard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4063.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4075.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This was done by implementing the schedule upon which each prisoner could use the sufficient space and could use sports courtyards and other available activities in the open.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4075.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4080.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, the effect of overcrowding was never present in the courtyard.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4080.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4087.45</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>There was always sufficient space for a particular inmate, including the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4087.45</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4094.89</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>As regards the second question posed by Judge Albuquerque, the government would like to note as follows.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4094.89</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4103.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is true that the Croatian law said that four square meters are a minimum.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4103.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4108.53</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But the Croatian government can defend the flexible approach because of the following.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4108.53</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4115.35</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This approach by the court, taken in numerous judgments against Croatia, produced tangible results in Croatia.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4115.35</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4120.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Today, we are at 84% of the capacity of the prisons.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4120.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4128.17</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>It is precisely because of this flexible approach that we were able to implement measures of two different kinds.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4128.17</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4135.65</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Firstly, we were able to implement measures with immediate effect on each inmate, including the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4135.65</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4144.69</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, each inmate could benefit from those measures, the counterbalancing measures, and therefore, his situation could be eased.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4144.69</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4156.21</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>At the same time, on a totally different level, the flexible approach allowed the government to have more time to deal with the overcrowding problem in the long run.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4156.21</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4174.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This means that it could implement different legislative measures, such as the law on probation, to implement different, to increase and to make better the material conditions of the particular prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4174.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4181.57</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, as already stressed by the government, in 2016, at the beginning of this year, we were at 84%.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4181.57</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4185.05</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, we have experience with overcrowding problem.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4185.05</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4187.13</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We cannot say that we solved it for good.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4187.13</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4194.93</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>But today, the situation is far better than in time when Mr. Muricic was held in the Bialowar prison.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4194.93</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4200.29</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Therefore, due to the Croatian experience, we can definitely defend the flexible approach.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4200.29</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4209.73</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>This is very important for us to say because the flexible approach, again, produced tangible results with respect to Croatia's prison system.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4209.73</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4221.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Additionally, besides answering the questions posed by the Court, we would also like to make some additional references as regards to the things stated by the applicant.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4221.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4225.97</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The applicant exposed his situation in his own subjective manner.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4225.97</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4235.25</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>However, all the applicant has stated today in his oral pleading, all these issues were addressed in detail in written submissions made by the government.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4235.25</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4249.33</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The questions of refurbishing, the questions of his everyday life, access to clean water, access to air, the state of the entire building, everything is explained in detail in the government's observations on multiple occasions during these proceedings.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4249.33</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4253.01</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>With this, I would like to end the government's oral pleading.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4253.01</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4253.37</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
	<SpeakerSegment>
		<Role>JudgeP</Role>
		<Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4254.15</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4257.19</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>Thank you very much, Mr. Mostovac.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4257.19</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4260.59</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4260.59</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4266.95</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4266.95</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4270.83</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The court will now deliberate on the merits of the case.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4270.83</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4273.41</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The judgment will be delivered later.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4273.41</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4276.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</Text>
		</Snippet>
		<Snippet>
			<Language>en</Language>
			<TimestampBegin>4276.43</TimestampBegin>
			<TimestampEnd>4276.43</TimestampEnd>
			<Text>I declare the hearing closed.</Text>
		</Snippet>
	</SpeakerSegment>
</Transcript>
