<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<transcript_4016012_12072017>
  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>18.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>19.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>66.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>67.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please be seated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>75.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>83.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Zubac versus Croatia.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>83.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>98.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The application was lodged with the court on 30 May 2012 under Article 34 of the Convention by a national of Bosnia and Herzegovina, Mrs. Vesna Zubac.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>98.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>108.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The application was allocated to the second section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the rules of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>108.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>117.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On 11 October 2016, a chamber of that section delivered its judgment in the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>117.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>125.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It held by four votes to three that there had been a violation of Article 6, paragraph 1.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>125.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>136.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On 11 January 2017, the government requested that the case be referred to the ground chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>136.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>144.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the panel of the ground chamber accepted the request on 6 March 2017.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>144.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>149.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government are represented by their agent, Mrs. Štefica Stažnik assisted by Mrs. Nikolina Katić and Mrs. Mirjana  Konforta advisors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>156.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>161.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant is represented by Mr. Ivica Ban, counsel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>161.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>164.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant is also present.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>164.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>170.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I welcome the representatives and the applicant in the name of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>170.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>184.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I also welcome groups of rapporteur judges from the Constitutional Court of Turkey and of ombudsmen from Bosnia and Herzegovina who are on a study visit to the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>184.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>194.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representative of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>194.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>201.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. Ban for the applicant will speak first, and then Mrs. Stažnik for the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>201.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>214.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting from Croatian has been authorized for the benefit of the applicant's representative.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>214.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>223.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And interpreting into Turkish and Bosnian has been authorized for the benefit of some of the groups of persons attending this hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>223.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>233.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>233.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>236.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And now I call Mr. Ban.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>236.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>237.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please, Mr. Ban, you have the floor.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>244.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>255.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Poštovani suci Velikog viječa suda, moje ime je Ivica Ban, odvjetnik sam iz Dubrovnika Republika Hrvatska.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>255.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>271.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Čast mi je na današnjoj uspjenoj raspravi u prezidentnom postupku pred Velikim viječem suda zastupati svoju stranku podnositeljcu zahtjeva, gospođu Vesnu Zubac, koja je na ovoj raspravi također prisutna i nalazi se pored mene.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>271.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>286.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Gospođa Vesnu Zubac i ja smo se dogovorili da ću na današnjoj uspjenoj raspravi ja iznijeti uvodni govor u ime podnositeljce zahtjeva, odgovor na uvodni govor predstavnika vlade Republike Hrvatske te odgovarati na pitanja suda.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>286.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>297.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Gospođa Vesnu Zubac će na dopuniti pojedine moje navode i odgove na pitanja suda sa činjenicama koje ona bude smatrala da su važne za pravilnu odluku suda u njenom predmetu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>297.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>304.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Počeo bi sa svojim uvodnim govorom.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>304.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>328.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dakle, ovako, zahtjeve podnositeljce zahtjeva temeli se na tvrdni da je predniku podnositeljce pred hrvatskim sudovima u postupku pred prvostupanskim i drugostupanskim sudom te u postupku pred revizijskim sudom u više navrata i na više različitih načina bilo povriježeno pravo na pristup sudu i pravično suđenje.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>328.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>335.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tvrdnje podnositeljce zasnivaju se na sljedećih šest argumenta.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>335.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>350.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Prvi argument je da je Prvostupanski sud u predmetnom postupku održao i zaključio glavnu raspravu na ročištu od 13. rujna 1995. godine</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>350.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>360.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>u održavanju kojeg ročišta nije obavijestio tužitelja, čime ga je onemogućio u poduzimanju pravnih radni u postupku.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>360.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>385.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Drugi argument je da je Prvostupanski sud bez ikakvog uvaljanog razloga i bez razbori i tog obrazloženja odbio provesti bilo koji dokaz predložen od strane tužitelja radi odsvođenja ništavosti ugovora o zamijanju nekretnina te radi utvrđenja nevaljanosti punomoći za sklapanje predmetnog ugovora o zamijanju nekretnina.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>385.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>402.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Treći argument je da je tužbu sastavio i na prva dva ročišta tužitelja zastupao odvjetnik iz Crne Gore koji prema hrvatskim zakonima nije mogao uredno i valjano zastupati tužitelja.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>402.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>431.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Četvrti argument, a u vezi s trećim argumentom je da je zbog nakladnog angažiranja kvalificiranog opunomoćenika odvjetnika iz Hrvatske tužitelj imao opravdanog razloga tražiti a sud prihvatiti nakladnu izmjenu vrijednosti predneta spora koja je u konačnici i prihvaćena i potvrđena u odlukama, to jest predsudama Prvostupanskog i Drvostupanskog suda.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>431.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>435.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Te o strane tuženika konkludentnim radnjama.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>435.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>441.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Prelazi na peti argument. Peti argument je da je Revizijski sud</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>441.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>470.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>odlučujući o reviziji pravnog prednika podnositeljce zahtjeva zauzeo u pogledu ispljenja uvjeta za izjavljivanje revizije pravno stajalište, suprotno onome koje je pravni prednik podnositeljce zahtjeva spravomogao i trebao očekivati, obzirom na postupak proveden pred nižastupanskim sudovima, onemogućujući ga time na podnošenje daljnjih pravnih ljekova.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>470.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>506.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Te šesti zadnji argument je da je odreživanje pravnog prednika podnositeljce zahtjeva kao tužitelju, obveze plaćanja sudskih pristojbi i priznavanjem tuženicima planičnih troškova prema novo naznačenoj vrijednosti preneta spora o strane prvostupanskog i drugostupanskog suda, uz istovremeno uskraćivanje tužitelju prava na podnošenje revizije prema novo utvrđenog vrijednosti preneta spora o strane revizijskog suda, tužitelj je stavljen u nejednak pološaj u odnosu na tuženike.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>506.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>518.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nakon obratlaganja argumenta, očitujući se na pismeni odgovor vlade Republike Hrvatske od 11. sibnja 2017. godine,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>518.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>545.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>ističući da sudska praksa i stručni članci koji su svoj odgovor priložila vlada Republike Hrvatske, da oni uoče nisu bitni za donošenje pravilne i pravične odluke u ovom postupu, budući da se isti uglavno odnose na nebitna proceduralna ili stručna pitanja, a ne na pravičnost, odnosno nepravičnost suđenja i onemogućavanje pristupa sudu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>545.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>548.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sad bi prešao na obratlaganje argumenta.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>548.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>562.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Prvi argument koji govori u prilog zahtjevu podnositeljice temeli se na činjenici da je Prvostupanski sud u prelijetnom postupku održao i zaključio glavnu raspravu na ročištu 13. ruja 1995. godine,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>562.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>567.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>u održavanju kojeg ročišta nije obavijesio tužitelja.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>567.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>580.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tužitelj je na taj način onemogućeno da priloži nove dokazne isprave, i predloži pribavljanje i provođenje novih dokaza, te da zatraži naknadu troškova postupka i priloži popis svojih troškova.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>580.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>594.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Za naglasiti je da je dodatno tuženik na tom ročištu, dakle u održavanju kojeg nije bio obaviješten tužitelj, predao u spise predmeta svoj podnesak o 13. ruji 1995. godine,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>594.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>601.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>koji također nije dostojen na odgovor, odnosno očitovanje tužitelju, prije donošenja prvostupanske presede.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>604.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>631.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nadalje, u odnosu na drugi argument, u prementnom postupku prvostupanski je sud bez ikakvo valjanog razloga i bez razboreljitog obrazloženja odbio provesti bilo koji dokaz predloženo strane tužitelja na okolnosti da je ugovor o zamijenu nekretnina, čiji je je poništenje tražio, prementno tužbon, zaključen pod prisilom i protivno utvrđenim standardima i normama međunarnog prava o zaštiti ljudskih prava i temeljnih sloboda.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>634.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>649.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I da je vrijednost zamijenjenih nekretnina nekoliko puta manja na štetu tužitelja, te da je punomoć, koje je njegova majka, Kosa Zubac, potpisala sporni ugovor o zamijenjeni nekretnina i njegov aneks krivotvorena.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>652.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>677.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>S obzirom na izloženu pravnom predniku podnositeljce zahtjeva u postupnom predmetu pred hrvatskim sudovima je, i prije sporne odluke revizijskog suda, bilo povrijeđeno pravo na pristup sudu i pravo na pravično suđenje, iz čega je proizlazi da navedeni postupak kao celina nije bio proveden s ukladno standardima, koji proizlaze iz članka 6 stavak 1 Konvencije za zaštitu ljudskih prava i temeljnih sloboda.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>679.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>695.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nadalje, prelazeći na treći i četvrti argument, u postupnom predmetu tužbu o ime tužitelja nosteljčinog prednika sastavio i na prva dva ročišta od ponošenja tužbe 6. kolovoza 2002.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>695.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>700.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>pa do 1. veljače 2005. godine tužitelja zastupao</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>700.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>735.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>odvjetnik iz Crne Gore, koji prema hrvatskim zakonima nije mogao uredno i valjano zastupati tužitelja, a niti je morao i objektivno mogao poznavati mjerodavno hrvatsku pravu, a niti je stvarno poznavao hrvatske propise, što je razizno iz okolnosti da je prihvati odvjetnički zastupati tužitelja pred sudovima u Republici Hrvatskoj, iako prema hrvatskim propisima to nije dopušteno inozi odvjetnicima. Ovdje treba dodati da je takvo zastupanje</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>735.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>743.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>po odvjetniku iz Crne Gore, općinski sud u Dubrovniku, trebalo zabraniti, što nije učinio.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>745.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>756.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Podnositeljčin prednik je u postupnom premjetu bio zastupan po kvalificiranom punomočniku, odvjetniku iz Hrvatske, jedino na raspravama održanim 1. veljače 2005. godine</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>756.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>758.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>i 6. tramvja 2005. godine.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>758.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>763.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>S tim da je za zastupanje na rasprave od 1. veljače 2005. godine</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>763.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>775.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>odvjetnik iz Hrvatske kao punomočnik bio angažiran tek neposredno pred početak te rasprave, tako da objektivno nije mogao proučiti i u cijelosti sagledati premjetni spor.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>778.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>790.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>S toga je prejnačenje vrijednosti premjeta spora od tog punomočnika iz naprijed navedenih objektivnih razloga urađeno tek na sljedećoj raspravi od 6. tramvja 2005. godine.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>791.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>799.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I podnositeljčin prednik je iz tih razloga imao opravdan razlog tražiti, a sud prihvatiti nakladnu izmenu vrijednosti premjeta spora.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>801.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>827.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Važno je naglasiti da je prvostupan sud i sam zakonski bio dužan ispraviti prvotno od uđitelja očito suvišenisko naznačenu vrijednost premjeta spora, pošto je noturno da je stvarna vrijednost vrste nekretnina obitelske kuće koje su bile premjetom spornog ugora o zamjeni nekretnina, najmene nekoliko desetaka puta veća od limita vrijednosti spora od 100.000 kuna i jednu lipu,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>827.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>831.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>koju je određuje dopuštenost podnošenja revizije.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>831.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>843.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nadalje, pravni prednik podnositeljce zahtjeva kao tuštelje na ročištu održanom 6. tramvja 2005. godine, kad je izmijenio</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>843.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>847.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>vrijednost premjeta spora i odredio da ona iznosi 105.000 kuna,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>847.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>898.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>tada je pravni prednik podnositeljce zahtjeva podnio dva podneska u kojima je uzglavni tužbeni zahtjev radi utvrđenja ništavosti ugora o zamjeni nekretnina istaknut u tužbi, istaknio i dodatne zahtjeve za utvrđenje nevaljanosti punomoći, to je bio prvi zahtjev, dakle za utvrđenje nevaljanosti punomoći za sklapanje prejentnog ugora o zamjeni nekretnina, što je zahtjev za utvrđenje, dakle klasično prejenačenje tužbe, te za odreživanje privremene mjere zabranja utvrđenja i opteređenja nekretnina koje su prejentno spora.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>898.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>915.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ovo je privremena mjera i tu bi se mogli prihvati argumenti vlade da u tome nije prejenačena tužba, ali traženje da se utvrdi nevaljanost punomoći je prejenačena tužba. Je li se navedeni dodatni zahtjevi</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>915.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>934.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>istaknuti istovremeno promjeno vrijednosti prejenta spora, mogu ili ne mogu smatrati prejenačenjem tužbe uz koje je dopušteno promijeniti i vrijednost prejenta spora, je pitanje u kojem se mogu voditi i pisati brojne sručne rasprave i o tome donositi različite sudske presude. Prvostupanski i drugostupanski sud su u prejentnom poslugu</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>934.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>943.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>očigledno zaključili da ti zahtjevi predstavljaju prejenačenje tužbe zbog kojeg se tužitelju može odobriti promjena vrijednosti prejenta spora.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>943.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>953.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Novu utvrđenu povećanu vrijednost prejenta spora prihvatili su i potvrdili u svojim odlukama, to je s presudama, prvostupanski i drugostupanski sud.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>953.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>967.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Također, ono što je najvažnije, novu povećanu vrijednost prejenta spora u visini od 105.000 kuna prihvatili su i tuženici na način da su podnijeli</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>967.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>986.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>zahtjeve za naknadnu troškova postupka prema toj novoj povećanoj vrijednosti prejenta spora, te na način da nisu podnijeli prigovor na utvrđenu i obvezu plaćenja sudskih pristojbi za odgovor na tužbu prema novu utvrđenu vrijednosti prejenta spora u visini od 105.000 kuna.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>986.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1002.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dakle, na taj način su posvene nesporno i nedvojbeno tuženici prihvatili ovo povećanje vrijednosti prejenta spora, a u svakom slučaju stranke imaju pravo tijekom postupka suglasno promijeniti vrijednost spora.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1002.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1005.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To je nesporno u praksi hrvatskih sudova.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1005.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1030.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>U odnosu na peti argument, revisijski je sud, odlučujući o reviziji pravnog prednika podnositeljice zahtjeva, zauzev u pogledu spunjenja uvjeta za izjavljivanje revizije pravno stavljiše suprotno onome koje je pravni prednik podnositeljice zahtjeva spravomogao i trebao očekivati obzirom na postupak proveden pred niže stupanskim sudovima.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1030.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1044.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Šesti argument, koji govori u prilog podnositeljčinom zahtjeva, utemelji se na čininici da je tužitelj odlukom revizijskog suda stavljen u nejednak položaj u odnosu na tuženike.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1044.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1079.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Određivanjem pravnom predniku podnositeljice zahtjeva kao tužitelju obveze plaćanja sudskih pristojbi i priznavanjem tuženicima paničnih troškova prema novo naznačenoj vrijednosti preneta spora o strane prvostupanskog i drugostupanskog suda, uz istovremeno uskraćivanje tužitelju prava na podnošenje revizije prema novo utvođenoj vrijednosti preneta spora o strane revizijskog suda, tužitelj je stavljen u nejednak položaj u odnosu na tuženike. Dakle, sve ono što je bilo na štetu tužitelja,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1079.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1083.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>to su mu sudovi priznali. Ono što je trebalo ići u korist tužitelja,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1083.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1087.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>a to je pravo na izjavljivanje revizije, tomu je uskraćeno.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1087.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1102.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Na taj način je narušena jedna od bitnih pretpostavki i prava na pravičnom suženju, odnosno poštenog postupa, a to je jednakostranaka u smislu pravične ravnoteže među strankama, fair balance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1102.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1120.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>U nastavku govora očitovaću se ukratko na odgovor Vlade Republike Hrvatske od 11. sijemnja 2017. godine. Podnositeljca Zakija Istiće da je Vlada</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1120.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1125.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Republike Hrvatske u svom opštinom odgovoru od 11. sijemnja 2017.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1125.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1133.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>uglavnom parafrazira svoje dostadačne navode na koje je podnositeljca Zakija već dala svoje odgovore. Činične i pravne tvrdnje</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1133.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1137.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>koje u svom odgovoru od 11. sijemnja 2017. Vlada Republike Hrvatska</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1137.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1147.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>iznosi i elaborira po prvi put po mišljenju podnositeljca Zakija uopće nisu bitne za donošenje odluka u ovom sporu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1147.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1160.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Istinst tvrdnjava se samo skreše pažnja na posebne bitna pitanja i zamagljuje suština prementnog spora, pa se iz tih razgova podnositeljca Zakija nenamjerava baviti tim tvrdnjama.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1160.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1185.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nadalje, podnositeljca Istiće da domašnja srpska praksa i stručni članci koje je u svoj odgovor priložila Vlada Republike Hrvatske nisu uopće bitni za donošenje pravilne i pravične odluke u prementnom postupu, budući da se isti uglavnom odnose na nebitna proceduralna ili stručna pitanja, a ne na pravičnost odnosno nepravičnost suženja i onemogućavanje pristupa sudu o čemu je riječ u postupnom prementu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1185.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1189.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ili je riječ o sudskoj praksi u nesporedivim predmetima.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1189.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1207.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sudska praksa Vrhovna suda Republike Hrvatske na koju se poziva Vlada Republike Hrvatske u svom očitovanju se osim u jednom predmetu uopće ne odnose na situaciju kad je jedna od pačnih stranaka zbog propusta niža stupanskih sudova kod u stvrđenja vrijednosti predmeta spora uskađeno pravo na podnošenje revizije.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1207.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1210.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Kao što je to riječ u postupnom prementu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1210.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1213.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Te stoga uopće nije mirodan u ovom prementu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1213.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1228.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Samo jedna relevantna presuda Vrhovna suda se u nikom slučaju ne može smatrati čvrstom, ustavljenom i dugogodišnjom sudskom praksom, odnosno dugogodišnjom, jasnom i dostajnom sudskom praksom, kako je u svom očitovanju naziva Vlada Republike Hrvatske.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1228.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1243.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ovo tim više, bošto je Ustavni sud Republike Hrvatske, koji je najviše pravoslovno tijelo u Republike Hrvatskoj, u svojoj odluci od 24. lipnja 2008. godine, koja je u prijevodu prilažena u spise predmeta,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1243.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1254.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>zauzeo posebno jasno i nedvojbeno pravno svačanje da parišna stranka nije odgovorna niti može snositi negativne posljedice bog formalnih propusta suda.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1254.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1266.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A kojim se pravni svačanje potire protivno pravno svačanje Vrhovno suda Republike Hrvatske, na koje se poziva Vlada Republike Hrvatske.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1266.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1297.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Isto tako, pravno svačanje da rizik od bilo kakve greške koju počini državno tijelo mora snositi država, a greške se ne smiju ispravljati na teret dotičnih pojedinaca, zauzeo je i ovaj sud u obrazloženju svoje presude u predmetima Šimecki protiv Hrvatske, Patovu protiv Grčke, Frejtak protiv Njemačke, Dimova protiv Bugarske i drugim.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1297.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1318.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Konačno, zakonske odredbe prije od kojih je u svoj odgovor prilažena Vlada Republike Hrvatske su nepotpune i selektivno citirane, tako da se često ne razumije smisao svrha i doseg pojedinog zakonskog instituta ili je nedostaju sve informacije, odnosno potpune informacije o pojedinom institutu. Nadalje je Vlada Republike Hrvatske u svoj odgovor priložila</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1318.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1331.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>i prijevo dijela zakonskih odredbi koje se, sa obzirom na datum svog donišanja ili izmjena, nisu mogle primijeniti u postupovnom predmetu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1331.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1420.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>U ovom odgovoru se, sa obzirom na izloženo o neprimjenjivosti stvršnih članaka i sudske prakse priloženih od strane Vlade Republike Hrvatske, te sa obzirom na iznesene argumente, dakle, prvi i drugi argument o neobaveštavanju tuštelja o održavanju zaključnog sudskog ročišta pred Prvostupanskim sudom, te o neosnovanom i neobrazloženom odbijanju provođenja dokaza za otvorđivanje ništavosti ugovora o zajemljenju nekretnina te o nevaljanosti punomoći za sklapanje prenetna ugora o zajemljenju nekretnina, nadalje, sa obzirom na treći i četvrti argument, o prvotno nevaljanost za stupanju tuštelja te o nakladnom angaširanju kvalificiranog punomoćnika, što je predstavljalo opravdan razlog za traženje i prihvaćanje nakladne izmjene vrijednosti prenetna spora, koja je u konačnici i prihvaćena i potvrđena od strane sudova i tuženika, te konačno peti i šesti argument, o činjenici da je određivanje pravnom predniku podnositeljice zahtjeva kao tuštelju obveze plaćanja suskih taksi i priznavanjem tuženicima planičnih troškova prema novo nasnačenom vrijednosti prenetna spora od strane prvostupanskog i drugostupanskog suda, na jednoj strani uz istovremeno isključivanje prava tuštelju na podnošenje revizije prema novo utvođenom vrijednosti prenetna spora od strane revizijskog suda, dakle na drugoj strani tušitelj je stavljen u nejednak položaj u odnosu na tuženike.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1420.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1444.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>S obzirom na to, podnositeljice zahtjeva predlaže velikom vijećem Evropskom suda za ljudska prava da odbije kao nosnovanu žalbu vlade Republike Hrvatske u prenetnom postupku te da donese presudu kojom se potvrđuje prvostupanska presuda Evropskog suda za ljudska prava u postupnom premetu. Da je u postupcima presudovima u Republike Hrvatskog</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1444.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1458.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>na štetu podnositeljice zahtjeva došlo do povrede članka 6 stavak 1 Konvencije za zaštitu ljudskih prava i temeljih sloboda.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1458.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1465.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sada bi se kratkim govorom obratila podnositeljica zahtjeva osobno, a ja se zahvalim na pažnju.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1471.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1474.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much Mr. Ban and Mrs. Zubac, please you have the floor.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1476.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1486.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Esteemed Court, Honorable Judges of Grand Chamber of the Court, I consider it as necessary to supplement the delegation from the speech of my attorney, Mr. Ban,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1486.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1492.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>by the following, according to my opinion, important facts for a regular decision in my case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1492.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1494.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I am not a jurist. I am not a lawyer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1494.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1499.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I am a woman who feels and who knows that the path to the truth is long and spinious one.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1499.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1503.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On that path, I was together with my husband, and then I have continued alone.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1503.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1514.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This, what I will expose, maybe is not crucial importance in actual phase of proceedings, but anyway, I consider that it's necessary to tell the following.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1514.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1524.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Firstly, I wish to emphasize that my whole family was immediately, before and after breaking out, around conflicts, constantly maltreated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1524.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1527.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There were four little children in the house of the age from 8 to 12 years.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1527.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1535.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My husband was unreasonable, arrested at the working place, brought home, and maltreated physically and psychically.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1535.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1549.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My mother-in-law was exposed to systematic maltreating and frightening in the manner that an explosive device, a bomb, was thrown into our house yard, that it was firing from firearms on our house.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1549.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1557.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The burglary and robbery were committed by the side of armed persons who were dressed in the uniforms of the Croatian Army.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1557.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1570.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Armed uniformed persons threatened her with murder and in order they instilled her, physically attacked her, beat up and seriously injured her, then they wrapped her friend in our house.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1570.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1579.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A great injustice and too much pain were inflicted to us what brought to the early death of my husband.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1579.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1592.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Also, I consider it necessary to cite that in the procedural case, not only my husband and his mother were threatened, but also the Croatian lawyers who were engaged by my family to represent us in that case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1592.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1597.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A pressure was carried out on them in order not to represent us.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1597.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1605.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In contrary, they will run afoul to the influence judges in Dubrovnik with the region from Bosnia and Herzegovina.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1605.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1641.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mentioned threats toward our lawyers resulted with passivity and cancellation of the power of attorney for representing by the side of those lawyers and also with cancellation of the power of attorney in the part of the proceedings also by the side of actual attorney to whom was also carried out a pressure to cancel a power of attorney to us because he will, in contrary, run afoul to the influential judges in Dubrovnik what could have harmful consequences for his other parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1641.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1663.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, the disputable contract on the changing of real estate and its annex are nulled and void because it is a matter of contract on change of real estate concluded in war circumstances under caution and contrary to established standards and norms of international law on protection of human rights and fundamental freedoms.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1663.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1697.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With regard to all so far exposed and argued, I hereby propose the Grand Chamber of the European Court of Human Rights to reject as groundless the appeal of the Republic of Croatia in the case and to reach a judgment by which the first instant judgment in the European Court of Human Rights in procedural case is confirmed that in proceeding before Croatian courts came to the infringement to my detriment of the Article 6, Paragraph 1 of the Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1697.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1702.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Esteemed Court, Honorable Judges of the Grand Chamber of the Court, I am not a lawyer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1702.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1709.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I am a wife and mother who is looking for justice in the name of past, in the name of future, and my children and believing in this great court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1709.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1710.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much for your attention.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1713.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1716.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you Mrs. Zubac.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1716.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1719.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And now I call Mrs. Stažnik. Please, you have the floor Madam.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1725.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1741.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Honourable Mr President, Judges of the Grand Chamber, allow me to start this pleading by using a popular quote often used when issues of rule of law are discussed, and that is, not only must justice be done, it must also be seen to be done.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1741.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1743.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>How can justice be seen to be done?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1743.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1750.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>By uniform application of the law and consistent and predictable case law which is achieved through court judgments.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1750.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1764.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>National Supreme Courts have a crucial role to play in this endeavour as guardians of the legality of the lower court's decisions and the highest judicial authorities which deliver binding precedence to the lower courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1764.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1780.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The main issue of the present case is the access to the Supreme Court denied to the applicant by the manner in which the Supreme Court applied the provisions of the relevant procedural law, namely the procedures of the Civil Procedure Act.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1780.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1791.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant deems that Razione Valori's inadmissibility of her appeal on points of law, as decided by the Supreme Court, was contrary to the Article 6 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1791.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1795.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The present case, in its essence, is a simple case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1795.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1809.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It maintained issue, its main issue considers the application of a provision of procedural domestic law which led to the inadmissibility of the applicant's appeal on points of law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1809.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1828.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, the applicant has tried to present this case as a complex one, saying that the Supreme Court was not allowed to dismiss her appeal on points of law because she had rightfully and legally raised the value of the subject of the dispute, which ensured Razione Valori's for the revision proceedings before the Supreme Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1828.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1835.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>She talked about the interim measure and amendment to the civil claim as proof of the legality of her actions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1835.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1838.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But these are simply not correct.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1838.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1854.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If we look at the facts of this case, we will see that the case concerns civil proceedings between two private parties, the applicant and her predecessor on one side and the other private party on another side.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1854.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1862.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant, in civil action, sought national court to have the contract for exchange of the houses declared null and void.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1862.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1876.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>At the time of lodging the action, as prescribed by the procedural law, the applicant's predecessor, the plaintiff in the proceedings, indicated the value of the dispute at 10,000 kunas.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1876.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1884.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>He made this choice freely and fully aware of the consequences of the subsequent course of the proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1884.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1901.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Taking into account well-established and consistent case law on the question of alteration of the value of subject matter of dispute, in circumstances such as these in the case before us, the applicant's predecessor willingly took the risk of this outcome.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1901.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1913.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Consequently, he could have had a reasonable expectation that the statutory ratione valoris equirements for lodging the appeal on points of law had been met.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1913.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1942.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Further, the value of the dispute set at 10,000 kunas for a civil action to have the contract for the exchange of houses declared null and void was not an unreasonable one, since the subject of the civil proceedings in question was not the value of the exchange houses, nor was the value of the applicant's house, but merely the declaration of a contract null and void.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1942.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1951.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the subject matter of this case was not monetary in nature.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1951.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1963.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Speaking in terms of the Convention and the language of the Court, the subject of the proceedings did not fall within the Article 1 of Protocol 1 of the Convention, but stayed within Article 6.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1963.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1974.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>By lodging the named action and setting up the value of the dispute, the rules of the game were set and the parties started litigation on the merits of the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1974.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1992.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nevertheless, almost three years later, the applicant's predecessor attempted to change his litigation strategy and unilaterally raised the value of the dispute at 100,000-5,000 kunas, which would then secure him access to the Supreme Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1992.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2017.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, what the applicant's predecessor conveniently forgot or simply did not care is that at this phase of the proceedings, after the parties have begun litigation on merits, domestic law, the Civil Procedure Act, explicitly and undoubtedly prohibits a change in value of the subject matter of dispute.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2017.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2026.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The domestic law and the case law of the Supreme Court are consistent for decades and perfectly clear on this.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2026.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2036.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The same law was also valid at the time the applicant's predecessor lodged civil action before the Dubrovnik Municipal Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2036.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2055.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the applicant's predecessor and his lawyer must have known about the consequences of their actions and the fact that under the applicable procedural law, the relevant value of the dispute would stay at 10,000 kunas, as initially indicated in the filed action.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2055.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2063.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Consequently, Razione Valori's inadmissibility of their appeal on points of law came as no surprise.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2063.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2075.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Honorable judges of the Grand Chamber, the respondent states reiterates that the applicant was not denied the access to the Supreme Court, contrary to Article 6 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2075.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2084.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In fact, her case was decided in merits on two instances, at Dubrovnik Municipal Court and Dubrovnik County Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2084.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2092.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The fact that her appeal on points of law was inadmissible doesn't constitute a violation of Article 6.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2092.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2109.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The respondent state emphasizes that the applicant's appeal on point of law was not declared inadmissible as a result on an overly formalistic interpretation of domestic law, nor did it impair the essence of the right to access to court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2109.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2125.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Supreme Court merely applied clear and precise provisions of the relevant procedural law in a foreseeable manner, in accordance with its constitutional law role and its longstanding case law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2125.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2130.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Its decision was neither arbitrary nor manifestly unreasonable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2130.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2137.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is, in fact, a prime example of the principle justice seemed to be done in practice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2137.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2147.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Precisely by applying the provisions of domestic procedural law, the Supreme Court fulfilled its main role of the guardian of the rule of law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2147.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2155.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The proper application of statutory procedural rules is crucial for proper administration of justice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2155.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2170.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Supreme Court could not have allowed procedural or substantive errors to exist and had to rectify them in a manner which ensured observance of rights of all parties in the proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2170.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2191.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, it would be contrary to the Supreme Court's role in the domestic legal system to be bound by the errors of the parties to the proceedings, by errors or determinations of lower courts, or to allow one party to the proceedings to take advantage of his or her errors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2191.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2204.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is especially important in case of admissibility of extraordinary remedies, since this issue is in the exclusive competence of the Supreme Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2204.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2221.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As we already shown in the written pleading before the Grand Chamber and through the proceedings before the Chamber, the applicant was not denied access to the Supreme Court, although her appeal on points of law was declared ratione valoris inadmissible.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2221.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2226.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Namely, Croatian legal system recognizes two types of the appeal on points of law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2226.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2239.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>One, so-called ordinary appeal on points of law, which the applicant used, and another one also prescribed by the Civil Procedure Act, extraordinary appeal on points of law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2239.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2255.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This second type of the appeal on points of law, the extraordinary appeal on points of law, can be lodged in cases when the ordinary appeal on points of law is not allowed for whatever of the prescribed reasons.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2255.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2271.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It will be admissible if the decision in civil dispute depends on the resolution of a substantive or procedural issue important to uniform application of the law and equality of all in the application of law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2271.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2284.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Namely, the second type of the appeal on points of law is reserved for cases raising important legal issues, such as uniform and consistent application of the law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2284.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2297.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Having this in mind, it can only be concluded that so-called extraordinary appeal on points of law was available to the applicant and securing her access to the Supreme Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2297.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2307.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The fact that this type of the appeal was not used by the applicant cannot be considered as a respondent state fault.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2307.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2316.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Court has always found that the right of access to a court secured by Article 6 is not an absolute one, but may be subjected to limitations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2316.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2322.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The right of access to a court by its very nature calls for regulation by the state.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2322.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2335.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this respect, the contracted states enjoy certain margin of appreciation, although the final decision as to respect of the Convention's requirement rests with the Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2335.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2344.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Honorable judges, the respondent states would like to make some remarks by commenting some of the applicant's statements made in the written pleading and here today.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2344.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2355.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Firstly, we strongly disagree with the applicant's view that the case Dobrić v. Serbia is not applicable in this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2355.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2369.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the case Dobrić, the Serbian Supreme Court did not accept the value of the subject of dispute agreed upon by the parties because there was no separate decision of the municipal court to that effect.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2369.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2379.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Also, like in Zubac's case, the plaintiff in Dobrić's case did not amend the value of the subject of the dispute while he was allowed to do so.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2379.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2396.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, in Dobrić's case, just like in Zubac's case, the applicable value of the dispute was the one indicated by the plaintiff in the original civil action at the beginning of the procedure, or better to say at the appropriate phase of the procedure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2396.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2408.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In Dobrić's case, the Court held that Serbian Supreme Court pursued a legitimate aim and that there was a reasonable relationship of proportionality between the means employed and the aims sought.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2408.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2428.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Court further held that the Supreme Court was fully entitled to reject any appeal on points of law which is deemed inadmissible and was not bound by the lower court's mere reference to the new agreed-upon value as the value of the dispute in question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2428.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2441.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Application of these principles established by the court to Zubac's case leads us to the conclusion that there was no violation of article in the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2441.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2461.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The respondent states notes that now in the proceedings before the Grand Chamber, the applicant for the first time claims that on the hearing of 6 April 2015 before the municipal court, the applicant's predecessor not only lodged proposal for an interim measure, but also requested that the power of attorney be declared invalid.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2461.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2462.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is incorrect and misleading.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2462.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2475.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>From the domestic court's case file, it is evident that on the named hearing, the applicant's predecessor wanted additional evidence to be taken, namely that the original of the power of attorney be obtained.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2475.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2482.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>He did not submit an additional civil claim as the applicant incorrectly states.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2482.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2501.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Secondly, regarding the applicant's allegations that her predecessor was not properly represented during the domestic civil proceedings, it should be said that the decision to hire a lawyer was an act of free will and free choice of the applicant's predecessor.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2501.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2515.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Also, any dissatisfaction which the applicant's predecessor or applicant have with their representation in the domestic civil proceedings is entirely a matter of a private lawyer-client relationship.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2515.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2523.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The respondent says see no causal link between this and the state's responsibility under the convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2523.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2535.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, we deem important to mention that all of the lawyers who represented the applicant's predecessor in the domestic civil proceedings had all rights to represent him before the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2535.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2557.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Also, for the further explanation, it is important to know that both Montenegrin and Croatian Civil Procedure Act originate from the very same 1976 Yugoslavian Civil Procedure Act.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2557.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2564.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the part regarding the value of the subject matter of the dispute, they stayed at the same.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2564.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2572.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the applicant's predecessor's Montenegrin lawyer should have been well familiar with the relevant procedural provisions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2572.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2576.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>After all, ignoratio iuris nocit.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2576.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2588.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To conclude, the Supreme Court establishes its role of a guardian of the rule of law and of the uniform application of laws to its decisions upon the appeals.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2588.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2597.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Its decisions in concrete cases influence on the practice and decision-making on the lower courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2597.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2613.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The accomplishment of these goals set before the Supreme Court and the role the Supreme Court performs in the Croatian legal system is directly connected to the regime of the legal remedies which enable access to the Supreme Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2613.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2629.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Precisely because of this special role and the hierarchy position of the Supreme Court in Croatian legal system, not all cases and all appeals can be decided before the Supreme Court on merits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2629.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2643.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The quality of realization of the goals which are set before the Supreme Court are in direct connection to the regulation of the access to the Supreme Court by parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2643.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2659.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Supreme Court will be prevented from performing its functions if the parties do not have the possibility to access the Supreme Court, but also if the possibility is set on overly broad basis.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2659.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2676.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In both of these situations, the result would be similar, failure and impossibility of the Supreme Court to fulfill its constitutional assignment to harmonize the court's practice and subsequent development of the law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2676.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2685.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We believe that in the present case, the Supreme Court brought a valid and justified decision on the admissibility of appeal on points of law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2685.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2689.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This decision had a legitimate aim and was proportionate.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2689.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2706.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>When deciding on this case, one should look at the proceedings as a whole and in particular at the fact that the applicant had been able to have her claim examined in fact and in law at two levels of jurisdiction.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2706.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2718.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Then one can only decide that the effect of the Supreme Court's decision and the interpretation adopted was in accordance with Article 6 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2718.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2721.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Honorable judges of the Grand Chamber, I thank you for your attention.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2723.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2731.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much Mrs. Stažnik and I thank both parties for their submissions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2731.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2740.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And now I turn towards my colleagues, the judges of the Grand Chamber, to know whether they have questions to be put to the parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2740.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2740.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Yes, please judge Sicilianos.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2750.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2751.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup, M. le Président.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2752.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2755.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je voudrais poser 2 questions au parti.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2755.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2760.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'une pour le gouvernement, l'autre pour les requérants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2761.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2764.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour le gouvernement, tout d'abord.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2764.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2777.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le requérant prétend que les frais d'épargne ont été calculés par les juridictions compétentes sur la base de la valeur modifiée de l'objet de mitiges, c'est-à-dire 105 000 kounas.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2777.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2791.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et il décède là une certaine contradiction entre le fait de calculer ces dépenses sur la base de la valeur modifiée, d'une part, et d'autre part, de rejeter cette même modification.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2791.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2795.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je voudrais avoir votre réaction sur cet argument.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2795.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2831.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour le requérant, le gouvernement prétend, contrairement à ce que vous venez de dire, que l'avocat de Montenegro qui avait représenté le prédécesseur de la requérante avait bien le droit de le faire et que le code de procédure civile de Montenegro et de la Croatie avait essentiellement le même contenu et que, par conséquent, l'avocat du prédécesseur de la requérante connaissait bien les conséquences de son choix de préciser l'objet de litige à une valeur de 10 000 kounas.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2831.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2835.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>J'aimerais votre commentaire sur cette prétention de gouvernement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2835.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2835.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2836.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2843.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup.Yes, please, Judge Pinto de Albuquerque, please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2845.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2848.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I have a question to the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2848.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2857.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's a point raised by the applicant, which I believe the government has not addressed, at least until now.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2857.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2868.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's about the clarity of the legal framework in Croatia on the admissibility criteria for an appeal before the Supreme Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2868.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2875.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The point made by the applicant is that the situation is not entirely clear.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2875.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2881.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There is some contradiction between the Supreme Court and the Constitutional Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2882.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2886.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There are contradictory positions on this precise topic.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2886.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2897.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would like the government to elaborate on this argument, on this alleged contradiction between Supreme Court case law and the Constitutional Court case law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2897.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2897.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2898.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2901.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much. Yes, Judge Turković please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2905.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2927.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Just one question that caught my eye while the government was presenting, stating that actually the applicants only asked for the power of attorney to be given to the court and did not challenge the power of attorney.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2927.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2933.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I will read from the Croatian file how it is stated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2933.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2937.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The power of attorney in the file is given two submissions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2937.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2955.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The first one, which asks for the power of attorney to be challenged, states that Vukasin Zubac allegedly gave his opponent Kosi Zubac for the termination of the contract for the replacement of the property.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2955.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2961.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And after that, it continues to ask for it to be put in the file.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2961.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2963.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would like to know if the government can comment on this.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2969.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2972.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2972.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2989.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If there are no more questions, the court will now withdraw for 20 minutes, following which the parties will be able to submit brief observations in reply to each other's submissions and reply to the questions from the judges.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2989.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2989.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The hearing is suspended.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3108.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3109.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3155.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3161.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please be seated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3161.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3165.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The hearing is resumed. And I call Mr. Ban please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3175.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3183.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Poštovani sude, časni sudci prvo će odgovoriti na pitanja kojim je postavio sud.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3183.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3201.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>U stvari, samo jedno pitanje je bilo postavljeno za podnositeljcu zahtjeva odnosi se na predlaganje i promjenu vrijednosti spora po strane punomočnika tužitelja, odnosno pravnog prednika podnositeljce.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3201.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3210.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>U stvari, stoje ovako. Tužbu je sastavio i predložio vrijednost spora</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3210.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3232.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Unijom odvjetnih iz Crne Gore, koji nije imao pravo sastaviti tužbu za stupati pravnog prednika podnositeljce zahtjeva pred hrvatskim sudovima, što tužitel nije morao znati kao običan građani, kao lajk.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3232.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3238.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Odvjetnik iz Crne Gore je to trebalo znati. Dakle, to je njegova greška.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3238.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3251.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A greška je suda u Dubrovniku koja je uopće dopustio da počne postupak po tužbi koju je sastavio odvjetnik koji nije imao pravo sastaviti i koji nije imao pravo zastupati tužitelja.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3251.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3257.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Taj postupak je trebao nekoliko godina. Doduše nisu se vodile</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3257.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3261.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>rasprave o meritumu nego o proceduralnoj.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3261.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3268.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I tek kad je u taj postupak stupio odvjetnik iz Hrvatske, to sam ja bio.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3268.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3282.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dakle, ja sam prvi put stupio na raspravu kad je kolega iz Crne Gore došao i praktično pet minuta prije rasprave me zamolio da ja pristupim na tu raspravu i dao mi upute jer da on ne može, on je više za stup.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3282.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3287.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I tad mogo ništa učiniti. Došao sam prvi put na raspravu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3287.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3297.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Idući put sam došao i naravno da sam onda predložio da se promijeni vrijednost pora i smatrao da ima na to pravo.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3297.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3305.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ako se ne gleda čisto formalistički, posebno što sam istovremeno podnio dva podneska koje je napisao tužitelj.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3305.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3313.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>U jednom se tražilo utvrđivanje nevaljanosti punom oči temelje koji je sklopjen taj ugovor. To bi se moglo smatrati preinação tužbe.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3313.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3317.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Drugi zahtjev je bio ovaj zahtjev za donošenje prijevijenog mjeru.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3317.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3323.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tu se slažem, to nije preinação tužbe, ali ovaj prvi zahtjev bi se mogao smatrati.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3323.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3328.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dakle, bila su dva razloga za promjenu vrijednosti.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3328.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3340.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Prvi put se u biti ta vrijednost i mogla promijeniti na tom drugom ročištu kad sam ja zastupao stranku. A u tom ročištu su bila ponesena dva zahtjeva</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3340.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3347.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>koja bi se mogla prihvatiti kao preinačenje tužbe, bar prvi zahtjev.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3347.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3364.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Što se tiče tvrdnje vlade, da je zakon bio isti i da je odvjetnik iz Srne Gore isto to mogao valjano i kvalitetno odraditi, ova tvrdnja naravno nije točna.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3364.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3373.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Zakon je bio isti do 1999. godine.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3373.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3383.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I prema tom zakonu koji je bio isti, ova tužba koja je sastavila odvjetnik iz Srne Gore bi bila valjana. Jer je dotad vrijednost spora bila 3000 kuna.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3383.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3396.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Od 6.11.1999 vrijednost predmeta spora kao limiza podnošenje revizije</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3396.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3401.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>se penje sa 3000 kuna na 100 000 kuna. Dakle, za ovu promijenu odvjetnike</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3401.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3406.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Srne Gore nije znao, nije imao pojma. I sad vlada kaže treba poštivati zakone.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3406.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3416.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Slažem se, treba poštivati, ali u ovom predmetu hrvatski sudavi su sve zakone što je bilo nabijeno tumačili i primjenivali na štetu podnositeljice zahtjeva.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3416.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3427.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Što se tiče sudske prakse, vlada se poziva na navodnu ustavljenu praksu Vrhovnog suda. Takve prakse uočene nema. Ima samo jedan predmet</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3427.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3437.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>koji sam već obrazložio da je u suprotnosti sa ustavljenom prakstvom Vrhovnog suda koja, kaže, pospoje suprotno. Dakle, ja mogu priložiti</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3437.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3472.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>nekoliko presuda Vrhovnog suda iz kojih jasno je da je u ustavno-sustkoj praksi zauzajet stav da se odbacivanje revizije podnositelja kao nedopuštene zbog pogrešno utvođene vrijednosti preneta spora kao pretpostavke o kojoj ovisi nezina dopuštenost, smatra da je time povriježeno ustavno pravo podnositelja na pravni vijek. Dakle, to je odluka, evo, recimo,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3472.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3478.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>konkretno nova na koju se poziva iz 2002. godine, 28. oživljaka 2002. godine.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3478.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3491.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nadalje, predmet Dobrić, na koji se također poziva vlada, je posvena u sporednju. U tom predmetu tušitelj nije uoče promijenio vrijednost</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3491.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3500.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>preneta spora, za razliku od ovog, on je promijenio i smatra da ima razloga promijeniti vrijednost spora. Također ni prvostupanski ni drugostupanski</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3500.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3504.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>sudu predmetu Dobrić nisu ni na koji način utvrdili novu vrijednost spora.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3504.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3519.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dakle, posve on je neusporediv slučaj. Vlada kaže, propisaj treba poštivati,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3519.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3536.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>a sama on i podnosi sudu prijevod zakona o paničnom postupku u kojem je članak 40 sa stanjem kakav je bilo u vrijeme podnošenja revizije. Ali nije navijena vlada</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3536.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3544.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>da se taj članak nekoliko puta mijenjao od podnošenja tužbe je bila jedna situacija.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3544.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3554.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>U vrijeme promjene vrijednosti spora je druga situacija i tek treća situacija pred podnošenje revizije. Vlada podnosi samo u treću verziju.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3554.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3566.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Evo, toliko što se tiče vlade i njeznog inzistiranja na poštivanju zakona i sudske praktice. Ne znam da li mi je vrijeme isteklo.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3566.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3591.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ja sam pisao reviziju i da sam imao imalo odvojbi od opuštenosti revizije, sigurno bih bio, kao što inače čini kad nisam siguran, podnio istovremenost revizijom i ustavnu tužbu kako bi osigurao da se o meritumu sporaja raspravi pred Ustavnim sudom i pred Evropskim sudom za ljudska prava.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3591.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3603.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nisam uovoče pomislio da bi se mogli dovedi situacija da Vrhovni sud ne prihvati reviziju zbog vrijednosti spora. Nisam i pomislio uovoče.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3603.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3611.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dakle, poslije sam bio siguran da se to pitanje neće postaviti.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3611.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3616.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ali nažalost, evo, postavilo se. Inače, za kraj htio bi samo ukazati</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3616.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3622.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>da članak 40. stavak 3 zakona o paničnom postupku na koji se vlada poziva,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3622.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3634.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>a u kojem je navedeno da se o utvrđivanju vrijednosti preneta spora, odse ta vrijednost mora utvrditi najkasnije na ročništvu za glavnu raspravu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3634.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3651.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Smatram da je to takvo formalističko ograničenje neukravdano i nerazmjerno svom cilju ubrzanja postupa koji se nastoji ostvariti, jer se time bitno ograničava pravo na pristup sudu. Na način da se narušava sama bit</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3651.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3668.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>tog prava u slučajima kad su razloze za nakladnu promjenu vrijednosti, odnosno ispravak vrijednosti preneta spora, iz opravljenih razloga nisu mogli predvidjeti, najkasnije do prvog ročništva za glavnu raspravu, kao što je to bio slučaj u premetu moje stranke.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3668.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3669.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>hr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Oviliko hvala na pažnju.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3673.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3675.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much Mr. Ban.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3675.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3677.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I call now Mrs. Stažnik, please, you have the floor.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3680.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3682.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3682.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3690.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will address the first issue asked by Honorable Judge Sicilianos.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3690.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3699.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So as regards the costs of the proceedings, parties to the proceedings may claim as much as they want for costs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3699.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3702.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court is not bound by such a request.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3702.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3710.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Indeed, they will be granted only costs for the procedural actions deemed necessary for the conduct of the proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3710.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3734.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, I would like to reiterate a bit more on that issue and would like to say that the issue of possible return of compensation with respect to access, sorry, with respect to the costs and expenses is essentially an issue to be considered under Article 1 of the Protocol 1 to the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3734.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3743.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant could have complained about a violation of her right to peaceful enjoyment of possession, but she didn't do so.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3743.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3755.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The issue of the costs and expenses of the applicant, costs and expenses the applicant paid, was a direct consequence of the actions of her predecessors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3755.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3761.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The domestic courts did not place the burden of their own errors on the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3761.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3775.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The main point the applicant is complaining about in admissibility of the appeal on points of law despite the costs paid is a burden placed on her by her predecessors' actions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3775.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3784.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant's predecessors knowingly made a choice and accepted that he might have to bear a disadvantageous consequences of such a choice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3784.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3793.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In any event, the issue of the costs and expenses paid by the applicant should not be a tipping point in an access to the Supreme Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3793.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3806.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Because an access to the Supreme Court case has many specificities differentiating it from the other access to court cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3806.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3812.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To reiterate only two, the legal remedy resorted to is an extraordinary one.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3812.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3817.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the Supreme Court has a special function in the legal system.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3817.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3825.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant had an opportunity to request the return of the fees paid, as we already elaborated in our written submissions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3825.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3829.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The fees are money paid to the state budget.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3829.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3833.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the state regulates the modalities for their return.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3833.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3838.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Accordingly, the applicant could have requested the return of the fees.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3838.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3849.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Regarding the costs of expenses, the applicant could have sought to be examined from their payment under the Code of Civil Procedure, as we already elaborated in the written submissions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3849.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3859.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We consider it very important to note that the costs, if they were paid, were paid to private individuals, the defendant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3859.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3865.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The cost of the proceedings constitute possessions of a private party to the civil proceedings under Article 1 of the Protocol 1.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3865.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3868.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They are not possessions of the state.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3868.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3886.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This important fact differentiates this case from the case of Zindric and Beslic versus Croatia, and Klaus versus Croatia, in which the costs were paid to the state for the state's representation in the proceedings, which consequently led to the violation of the Article 6.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3886.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3895.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The state does not benefit in any way from the costs paid to defendants, private individuals, nor does it suffer any disadvantage if they are not paid.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3895.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3909.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For these reasons, given that the issue of costs to be paid is also an issue between two private individuals, the state's possibility of interfering in their return is very limited.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3909.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3921.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is debatable to which extent can a state encroach on private possessions of citizens established by a final judgment and for that interference to be in accordance with Article 1 of Protocol 1.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3921.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3937.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, if the state would try, by any kind of legal maneuver, to intervene in the other party's possession, it will expose itself to another violation of the Convention, the violation of conventional rights of the other party.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3937.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3957.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Like it was the case in Berletic versus Croatia, the state would in that case jeopardize the legal certainty and the rule of law setting at naught a judicial process which had ended in a final judgment of Dubrovnik Municipal Court and which had moreover been executed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3957.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3972.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, we consider that the issue of the costs the applicant had to pay to the opposing private party is not of such a nature to be a crucial element in favor of a violation of Article 6.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3972.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3975.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The second question of the court will be addressed by my colleague.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3977.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3977.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please, madam.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3979.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3994.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As to the second question of the court, the respondent state claims that there is no inconsistency in the Supreme Court's and Constitutional Court's case law, as claimed by the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3994.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3999.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This was already presented by the respondent state in its written pleading.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3999.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4010.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The named decision of the Constitutional Court, which was called upon by the applicant, presents the case which is factually and legally different in respect of the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4010.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4023.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This decision relates to a commercial dispute and the issue whether the matter under the dispute falls within commercial matter or stays within the regular civil proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4023.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4032.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The issue of the value of the subject matter therein directly is related to the subject matter of the regular or commercial courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4032.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4046.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The decision whether the regular or commercial courts will decide upon the matter, not to the value of the dispute itself and its rationale of our admissibility before the Supreme Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4046.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4054.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, this case significantly differs from the present case, and it's not even applicable to the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4054.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4054.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4054.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4057.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4059.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4062.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Honorable Judges we would also like to address the third question...</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4063.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4063.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4063.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4066.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>posed by Judge Turković.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4063.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4066.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4066.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4074.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the hearing of 6th April 2005, the plaintiff lodged two submissions, indeed, with the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4074.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4090.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the minutes of that hearing, enclosed with our submissions, it is stated that by that submission, the plaintiff suggests that the court, by way of diplomatic means, requests the original of the power of attorney from the Trebinje municipality.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4090.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4107.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Responding to this submission, the municipal court ruled that it will decide on further proposals to take evidence, that is, the plaintiff's proposal to acquire this power of attorney, at a later stage.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4107.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4118.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, we would like to note that if this was indeed an additional civil claim, then the municipal court would be bound to decide on this claim on the merits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4118.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4120.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But this was not done.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4120.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4126.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And if the applicant's statements were true, this would constitute an absolute violation of the procedural rules.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4126.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4134.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And in that case, indeed, the Dubrovnik County Court would be bound ex officio to quash such a judgment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4134.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4147.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But this was not an amendment of a civil claim, and this was never an issue, indeed, before the municipal or county court, or indeed, before the Supreme Court, that this was not an amendment of a civil claim.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4147.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4157.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It was only evidence related to the first civil claim, that is, the contract.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4157.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4158.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, honorable judges.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4158.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4160.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4162.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4165.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mrs. Stažnik, have you completed?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4165.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4167.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So thank you very, very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4169.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4172.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4172.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4178.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I thank the parties for their submissions and answers to the court's questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4178.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4182.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4182.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4185.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The judgment will be delivered later.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4185.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4189.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4189.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4190.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I declare the hearing closed.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

</transcript_4016012_12072017>
