<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<transcript_1803011_04112015>
  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>60.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>72.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case of Magyar Helsinki Bizottság versus Hungary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>72.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>87.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The application was lodged with the court on 14 March 2011 under Article 34 of the Convention by a Hungarian non-governmental organization, Magyar Helsinki Bizottság.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>87.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>98.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The application was allocated to the second section of the court pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the Rules of the Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>98.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>106.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The application was communicated to the government on 4 December 2012.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>106.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>115.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On 26 May 2015, the chamber decided to relinquish jurisdiction in favour of the Grand Chamber.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>115.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>154.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On 2 September 2015, the President of the Grand Chamber granted the Government of the United Kingdom the organization's media legal defence initiative, Campaign for Freedom of Information, Article 19, Access to Information Programme and Hungarian Civil Liberties Union jointly, and the organization Fair Trials International leave to submit written comments as third parties by virtue of Article 36, paragraph 2 of the Convention and Rule 44, paragraph 3 of the Rules of the Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>154.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>167.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Government of the United Kingdom were also granted leave to take part in the hearing as a third party government by virtue of Rule 44, paragraph 3 of the Rules of the Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>167.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>177.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The respondent governments are represented by their agent, Mr Zoltán Tallódi, and assisted by Mrs Mónika Weller, co-agent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>177.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>193.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant organization is represented by Dr Tamas Fazekas and Dr Tibor Lajos Sepsi, and by Dr Csaba Tordai and Mrs Nóra Novoszádek, advisors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>193.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>206.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The United Kingdom government are represented by Mr Jason Coppel, QC counsel, and by Mrs Anna McLeod, agent, and Mrs Asma Mahmood, advisor.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>206.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>210.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>210.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>227.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I also welcome the groups of judges from the Supreme Court of Latvia and from the Constitutional Court of Kosovo, judges and prosecutors from Turkey, and judges and prosecutors from the European Judicial Training Network who are on a study visit to the Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>227.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>240.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the applicant organization's representative and the representative of the third party, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>240.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>254.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr Tallódi for the government will speak first, and then Dr Sepsi for the applicant organization, Magyar Helsinki Bizottság, and finally Mr Coppel for the United Kingdom government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>254.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>275.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I should explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the Court, English and French, interpreting into Russian and Georgian has been authorized for the benefit of the groups of lawyers from Russia and representatives of the Office of the Public Defender of Georgia attending this hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>275.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>284.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Translational interpreting is not arranged by the Court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>284.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>285.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I call Mr Tallódi.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>285.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>285.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You have the floor, please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>293.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>296.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, Honorable Members of the Court,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>296.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>307.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>ladies and gentlemen, it's a privilege and a pleasure to have the opportunity to appear before the Court to present the oral submissions on behalf of the Government of Hungary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>307.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>318.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>During the written procedure before the Court, both parties, as well as the intervening third parties, have been given ample opportunity to put forward their arguments.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>318.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>329.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Hence, it is not necessary to repeat now the details of the position of the government outlined recently in their memorial of the 7th of September, 2015.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>329.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>335.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will rather focus on the most important issues raised by the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>335.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>356.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First of all, let me reaffirm that the government considers that the right to defense, as well as the right of access to public information, are fundamental human rights to be guaranteed in a democratic society based on the rule of law, and both rights are clearly enshrined in the fundamental law of Hungary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>356.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>370.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The present case, however, is not about the existence or significance of the right of access to official documents in general, but whether this right falls within the scope of Article 10 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>370.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>375.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And if so, what are the limits of the jurisdiction of this Court?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>375.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>384.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The first issue to be considered is whether the right of access to information falls within the scope of Article 10 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>384.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>389.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In other words, whether Article 10 is applicable to the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>389.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>408.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government are of the opinion that the right of access to information is an autonomous right aimed at enhancing transparency and good governance, and it is not simply a part of or auxiliary to the freedom of expression.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>408.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>421.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But even if it were considered as an inherent aspect of the freedom of expression, this aspect was deliberately excluded from the scope of Article 10 by its drafters.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>421.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>449.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Having regard to the wording of Article 10, contrasted with the wording of other international human rights instruments concerning freedom of expression, as well as the travel preparatoire of Article 10, the Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties, and the Court's longstanding jurisprudence in line with its judgment in the case of Leander versus Sweden, the government consider that Article 10 is not applicable to the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>449.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>457.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the present case, the applicant's freedom of expression within the meaning of Article 10 has not been interfered with.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>457.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>482.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant organization was not prevented from publishing its survey and express its opinion on an issue of public importance, and in contrast to the case of Daman versus Switzerland, the applicant was not sanctioned for receiving information which was given to it by the police in breach of the provisions of Hungarian law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>482.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>492.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this case, the applicant's complaint is clearly based on a claim for a right of access to information which doesn't fall within the scope of Article 10.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>492.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>514.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government are of the opinion that the court should not depart from its position in the case of Leander versus Sweden, namely that the right to freedom to receive information basically prohibits a government from restricting a person from receiving information that others wish or may be willing to impart to him.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>514.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>526.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It follows that Article 10 doesn't confer on the individual a justiciable right of access to information which is not intended to be imparted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>526.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>537.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Admittedly, the court's judgment in the case of Társasága Szabadságjogokert versus Hungary has widely been interpreted as a departure from that position.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>537.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>552.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, the government emphasized that the court itself stated in paragraph 36 of the judgment that the case didn't concern the denial of a general right of access to official documents.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>552.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>587.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government realized that their concession concerning the applicability of Article 10 in that case, based exclusively on considerations of domestic law as in force at that time, proved to have unintended consequences on the development of the jurisprudence of the court, and agree with the British government that unilateral concession cannot serve as a basis for expansion of the Convention into areas which it was not intended to cover.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>587.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>599.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government are of the opinion that the living instrument approach invoked by the third parties would not justify the extension of the scope of Article 10 either.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>599.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>605.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The right of access to information is not a new aspect to freedom of expression.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>605.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>614.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It was not unknown to the legal systems of the member states of the Council of Europe at the time of drafting Article 10 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>614.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>621.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Yet, it was deliberately omitted from the scope of this provision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>621.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>630.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This aspect of the right was deliberately not subjected to the international control mechanism established by the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>630.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>649.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, the member states of the Council of Europe, the high contracting parties to the Convention, confirmed that Article 10 did not cover the right of access to information when they adopted in 2009 the European Convention on access to official documents.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>649.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>655.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Official documents meaning any information drafted or received and held by public authorities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>655.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>670.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The explanatory report of that Convention states that it is the first binding international legal instrument to recognize a general right of access to official documents held by public authorities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>670.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>697.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, the government point out that the high contracting parties, as recently as 2009, still didn't intend to subject this right to the jurisdiction of the court and opted for the adoption of a separate treaty with distinct supervisory mechanism instead of adopting an additional protocol to the European Convention on Human Rights.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>697.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>717.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The fact that many of the high contracting parties provide for the right of access to information in the domestic law or adopted other international treaties ensuring the right to seek information does not justify that the same right be interpreted into Article 10 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>717.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>725.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In spite of its wording and the intentions of its drafters, the member states of the Council of Europe.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>725.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>743.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>One of the reasons for the member states' reluctance to extend the court's jurisdiction to cover the right of access to information is the need to preserve the effective functioning of the court, which has already been facing an immense caseload for years.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>743.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>766.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The number of potential applications inviting the court to carry out a forced instance review of rejected requests for information, like in the present case, as well as the scale and complexity of the issues to be considered in each case are prohibitive in this respect.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>766.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>778.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the government considers that the right to seek information is not ensured by Article 10, and the court should not extend the scope of Article 10 to cover this right.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>778.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>792.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, Article 10 is not applicable in the present case, and the application should be declared inadmissible, ratione materie, in accordance with Article 35, Paragraph 3A of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>792.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>804.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Should the court find that Article 10 is applicable in cases of denial of access to information, the next issue to be examined is the scope of jurisdiction of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>804.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>844.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government are of the opinion that the court only has jurisdiction to examine complaints of denial of access to information in cases where the lack of access to a particular piece of information effectively prevents the applicant for expressing, publishing an opinion on an issue of public importance, because there are no alternative means of obtaining that information, and the applicant is liable under civil or criminal law for the factual correctness or well-foundedness of his statements.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>844.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>852.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Only in these cases can be said that denial of access to information interferes with the freedom of expression.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>852.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>864.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The case of Kennedy versus Hungary would have been a close example under slightly different conditions had the applicant been really denied access to the requested information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>864.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>876.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, the correct reading of the facts of that case is that the applicant was only prevented by the authorities from publishing information accessible to him.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>876.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>881.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Not having access at all was his own decision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>881.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>889.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, this case cannot be regarded to have established the right of access to information under Article 10.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>889.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>905.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Should the court interpret the Kennedy judgment as an authority establishing that Article 10 may be engaged, that the state has failed to comply with an established domestic right of access to information?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>905.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>926.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government agreed with the opinion of the British government that the court should refrain from interpreting the domestic law itself, and should accept the interpretation given by the domestic court, which is in a better position to interpret the provisions of domestic law, and which is solely competent to do so.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>926.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>933.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Otherwise, the court will become a forced-instance appellate court in freedom of information cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>933.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>951.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>An exemption to this rule might only be made when, in a most extreme case, the domestic court's judgment is manifestly arbitrary, contrary to a clear and highly specific provision of domestic law, not leaving any room for judicial interpretation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>951.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>977.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Even if the court found that a domestic right of access to information gave rise to claims under Article 10, it should, under no circumstances, go beyond requiring enforcement of an established right, and examine whether access should have been granted to a particular type of information, as it is proposed by the applicant in the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>977.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1015.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Such an examination would imply the consideration of complex social, political, and legal issues, and the balancing of various interests which falls outside the competence of the court, and can best be carried out by the domestic authorities, most of all by the legislator, which enjoy a wide margin of appreciation in this field, having regard to the lack of consensus across the Council of Europe states, on the extent to which there should be access to state information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1015.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1033.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Even the Council of Europe Convention access to official documents not yet in force could not provide sufficient guidance to the court, since it sets out only very general framework rules, deferring the detailed regulation to domestic law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1033.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1052.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The scope of review by the court, as well as the corresponding margin of appreciation of the state, will also depend on whether the rights ensured by Article 10 are construed as entailing only negative or also positive obligations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1052.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1079.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Any positive obligations under Article 10 have so far arisen as an obligation to protect from interference by private persons, and they should not be construed as an obligation to promote or fulfill by creating alternative venues for expression or providing subsidies, or even information which is not willingly imparted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1079.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1097.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In any event, having regard to the lack of consensus at the European level, states should enjoy a wide margin of appreciation in choosing the means of fulfilling their eventual positive obligations under Article 10.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1097.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1111.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Summing up the general considerations, the government submit that any right of access to information under Article 10 can only be construed as a right to receive information willingly imparted by others.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1111.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1129.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There is a negative obligation on the part of the state not to hinder unjustifiable access to publicly available information and not to punish anyone for receiving information from public authorities, even if the information was imparted unlawfully.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1129.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1142.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Turning to the facts of the present case, the government are of the opinion that there has been no interference with the applicant's freedom to receive information as protected by Article 10.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1142.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1161.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Neither was there any interference with the applicant's right to impart ideas, since it was not prevented by the lack of the requested information from publishing its survey, nor did the lack of the requested information affect the quality of the applicant's opinion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1161.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1164.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, honorable members of the court,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1164.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1184.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>in spite of the extensive filings by the third party NGOs and the applicant itself on the issue, the government considered that the court should not base its decision in the present case on the importance of the right to defense enshrined in Article 6 of the convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1184.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1197.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The significance of that right, or the Legal Aid Defense Council's role in contributing to its fulfillment, has never been called into question by the Hungarian authorities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1197.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1223.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The issue at dispute was whether Legal Aid Defense Councils in Hungary qualified as persons performing public duties for the purposes of the Data Act, or they contributed to the fulfillment of public tasks by performing their civic duties without qualifying as persons performing public duties within the meaning of the Data Act.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1223.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1249.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This question is to be answered exclusively on the basis of Hungarian law, and this question was answered by the highest judicial organ competent to interpret the relevant provisions of the Hungarian law to the effect that Legal Aid Defense Councils in Hungary did not qualify as persons performing public duties for the purposes of Section 19, paragraph 4 of the Data Act.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1249.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1259.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Since the decision of the Supreme Court was not manifestly arbitrary, there is no reason for this court to rule otherwise.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1259.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1273.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In accordance with the principle of subsidiarity, this court is not competent to reinterpret the provisions of the Hungarian law or to determine what should have been content of Hungarian law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1273.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1285.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the court must conclude, in accordance with the judgment of the Supreme Court, that the applicant organization had no established right of access to information under domestic law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1285.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1304.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, depending on the interpretation of Article 10 chosen by the court as to the scope of an eventual right to information, the court should conclude that the applicant's perverted right to information was restricted in accordance with law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1304.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1317.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant organization, as a human rights NGO, seems to have lost sight of the fact that the handling of personal data by public authorities, such as the police, is purpose-bound.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1317.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1327.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the police cannot process personal data for purposes other than prescribed by law and without an explicit authorization by the law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1327.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1344.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The fact that the requested personal data are available to the police and that their compilation is technically feasible doesn't mean that the procession of those data according to a request from the public is legally possible.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1344.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1352.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The fact that certain personal data are public for some purposes doesn't mean that they are public for any other purposes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1352.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1374.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The fact that the names of all members of the bar associations and all potential legal aid defense councils are made public by the bar association themselves cannot be construed as an authorization for the police to process and publish those names for purposes not prescribed by law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1374.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1384.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The purpose of the Data Act itself was to ensure the transparency of the exercise of public power and the use of public funds.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1384.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1394.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In none of these respects, the names of the legal aid defense councils actually appointed by the police constituted relevant information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1394.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1410.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Legal aid defense councils do not exercise public power and do not manage the state's property, which in itself qualifies as performing a public duty in accordance with the domestic jurisprudence cited by the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1410.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1432.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Contrary to the applicant's submissions, there is no domestic jurisprudence establishing that private schools fall within the scope of section 19, paragraph 4 of the Data Act, simply on account of performing public services delegated by state authorities and thus qualifying as other persons performing public duties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1432.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1441.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There is domestic jurisprudence only concerning public educational institutions using public funds for performing their tasks.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1441.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1467.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Private schools might only have fallen under the scope of this provision as direct beneficiaries of public subsidies, whereas the direct beneficiaries of the legal aid system are the defendants and the legal aid lawyers whose fees are much below market fees in the legal aid scheme are only partially compensated for their time spent on performing their civic obligations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1467.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1477.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, legal aid fees are determined by law based on the hours actually spent on a case and not at the discretion of the police.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1477.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1496.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Without evaluating the quality of the applicant's research on the functioning of the legal aid defense scheme in Hungary, the government would only point out that the data requested from the police was not necessary and most certainly not essential to that research.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1496.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1508.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The most telling proof of that is that although the applicant organization had received a number of names from the police, none of them was used in the survey.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1508.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1522.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant made a statistical analysis of the data obtained and they could have lawfully obtained similar statistical data from all police departments had they not insisted upon obtaining personal data.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1522.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1546.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this respect, the government point out that the third party submissions of Fair Trials International relied upon by the applicant only identified a general trend towards enabling external commentators to monitor performance of justice systems through statistical data.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1546.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1571.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, the government considered that convention case law concerning the violation of Article 6, Paragraph 3, on account of the poor quality of the defense provided by legal aid lawyers doesn't support the applicant's argument that legal aid defense counsels qualify as public authorities whose actions are attributable to the state.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1571.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1583.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The relevant case law rather confirms that states have a positive obligation to protect defendants from violations by private persons, at least in semi-private relations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1583.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1598.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Summing up the issue of the functioning of the legal aid defense counsel system in Hungary, the government finally point out that there have been no cases against Hungary before the court complaining of the work of the legal aid lawyers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1598.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1613.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This leads us to the question whether the court wishes to introduce a system of actio popularis through the backdoor of Article 10, as proposed by the applicant reinforced by the third party submissions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1613.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1620.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Certain that the court will answer that question in the negative, the government will not further elaborate on this point.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1620.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1623.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, honorable members of the court,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1623.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1654.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>insofar as Article 10 is applicable to the present case, and should the court find that there has been an interference with the applicant's rights under Article 10, the government consider that that interference was not only in accordance with the law and had a legitimate aim, as set out above, and in the government's memorial, but it was also necessary in a democratic society and proportionate to the aim pursued.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1654.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1663.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The denial of access to the requested data served the protection of the rights of others, as explained in the government's memorial in detail.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1663.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1687.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There was no pressing social need for the restriction of Article 8 rights of legal aid defense councils in the manner proposed by the applicant, since the public interest in monitoring the functioning of the legal aid defense scheme could be achieved by less restrictive means, in particular through statistical data.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1687.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1714.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Although the applicant claims that the requested information was essential for it to form a well-founded opinion on the functioning of the legal aid defense system throughout the country, this argument is contradicted first by the fact that they only requested information from 28 local and regional police departments, out of about 180 police departments countrywide.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1714.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1731.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>17 sets of data obtained versus 28 requested makes not much of a difference in forming a well-founded opinion compared to 150 sets of data which were not requested at all.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1731.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1739.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, the data in the form that they were requested were not used by the applicant at all in their report on the issue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1739.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1776.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, there were alternative means of obtaining relevant and even more sophisticated, and thus more useful data on the issue, namely in the form of statistical data or by way of cooperation with the national police headquarters, which was indeed made use of by the applicant at some point, and which enabled it not simply to confirm its original presumption of uneven distribution of cases, but to explore the actual reasons therefore.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1776.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1782.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Availability as claimed by the police, or inactivity as presumed by the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1782.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1791.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Under these circumstances, it cannot be argued that the data requested were essential for forming a well-founded opinion on the issue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1791.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1812.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Since the alternative means of gathering information enabled the applicant to contribute more effectively to the debate concerning an issue of public interest, the denial of access to the requested information didn't constitute a disproportionate interference, if any, with the applicant's freedom of expression.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1812.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1830.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government emphasized that in contrast to the case of Társasága Szabadságjogokért versus Hungary, the applicant in this case did not request the relevant data from the Hungarian authorities in any and most form as a secondary claim.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1830.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1837.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>See paragraphs 14, 16, and 37 of the judgment in that case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1837.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1865.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Taking into consideration the aforesaid and maintaining the government's position set out in their memorial of the 7th of September, 2015, I respectfully request the honorable court to find that insofar as Article 10 is applicable, there has been no violation of the applicant's rights under the convention, even by the standards of the most expanded interpretation of that provision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1865.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1876.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Finally, I would like to make two very brief comments on the applicant's claims for just satisfaction under Article 41 of the convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1876.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1897.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, the government agreed with the applicant organization that the information denied from it and the alleged violation of Article 10 resulting therefrom was so insignificant that it caused no practical or moral prejudice to the applicant, and therefore no claims for non-pecuniary damages are justified.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1897.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1917.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second, the government find that the applicant's claims for lawyers' fees, as well as the preliminary estimates of the expenses emerging with regard to the present hearing, are excessive, highly excessive, and the government will submit their detailed comments in writing as soon as the actual expenses are verified.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1917.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1919.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, that concludes that I</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1919.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1921.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>wish to say at this stage.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1921.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1924.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>May I thank you, Mr. President and members of the court,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1924.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1927.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>for listening to me so patiently and attentively.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1927.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1927.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1929.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1932.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Mr. Tallódi.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1932.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1934.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I call now Dr. Sepsi.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1934.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1934.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You have the floor please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1938.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1943.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President, members of the Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1943.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1955.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As the representative of the Hungarian Helsinki Committee, I would like to present you supplementary information to the written contribution of the applicant in three separated but interconnected aspects of the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1955.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1972.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will open with a brief outline on the applicant's understanding on the main questions of the applicability of Article 10 of the Convention in the case, where arguments and references will be presented as a reaction to the written contributions of the governments of Hungary and the United Kingdom.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1972.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1986.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the second part of my presentation, I will summarize those characteristics of the Hungarian system of appointed defense councils and also the Hungarian freedom of information legislation, which we think are decisive in the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1986.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1994.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This will be done also to clarify in which aspects we find the reasoning of the Hungarian government unfounded.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1994.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2002.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As I will finish my speech with additional information on the factual basis of the application, mostly in connection with three issues.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2002.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2008.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, the applicant's role in monitoring the protection of human rights and criminal procedures in Hungary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2008.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2016.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second, the nature and relevance of the research report of the applicant on the practice of the ex-official appointment of defense councils.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2016.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2027.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And third, the importance of the specific freedom of information requests, both for the preparation of the report and for establishing a practice for similar requests in the future.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2027.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2032.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So let me start with the applicability of Article 10 in the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2032.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2050.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The application is based on Article 10, and it covers a case where the violation of the Convention is assumed to be based on the fact that Hungarian authorities had failed to disclose information on freedom of information requests, and Hungarian courts had later failed to force these authorities to disclose.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2050.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2059.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We see the right of access to information not as a standalone right established by the Convention, but as an inherent right of the freedom of expression.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2059.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2074.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to Article 10 of the Convention, everyone has the right to freedom of expression, and this right shall include freedom to hold opinions and to receive and impart information and ideas without interference from public authorities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2074.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2085.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court reiterated many times that Article 10 also protects the freedom of research as established in the cases Sorgut versus Turkey or Sapan versus Turkey.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2085.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2101.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the present case, it is a fundamental precondition for both the applicant and the general public for holding an opinion in an issue of high public interest to have access to the facts of the operation of the system of ex-official appointments in the criminal justice system.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2101.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2112.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It must not be forgotten that the right to ex-official defense councils is guaranteed by the Convention as well, Article 6, paragraph 3, point A. So what is at stake in the present</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2112.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2126.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>case is whether someone, notably a human rights NGO, can assess how a system of state-founded legal assistance operates, the poor quality of which in itself might lead to the establishment of the violation of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2126.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2150.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus by rejecting access to data, the authorities used their information monopoly as a sensory power, so Hungary failed in its negative obligation not to interfere unjustifiably with the rights protected by Article 10, impending the realization of freedom of research, freedom to hold opinions, and freedom of expression.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2150.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2163.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Although Article 10 of the Convention does not include any reference to the right to seek information, according to the case law of the court, Article 10 also covers state interference in the process of seeking information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2163.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2172.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The European Court of Human Rights decisions of the last decade clearly advanced towards a broader interpretation of the notion of freedom to receive information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2172.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2204.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And cases like Strudzsanyi-Juhaczeszky-Mátkyi versus the Czech Republic, Társasága-Szabadság-Jugokert versus Hungary, Kennedy versus Hungary, Youth Initiative for Human Rights versus Serbia, and Österreichische Vereinigung versus Austria led to the recognition of a right of access to public information in this respect, and also acknowledged that NGOs such as the applicant may be characterized as social vegetables, and in that connection, their activities were on similar convention protection to that afforded to the press.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2204.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2213.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nearly all of the chambers, four out of five sections of the European Court of Human Rights have already delivered judgments supporting this interpretation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2213.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2231.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The written arguments submitted by the government of the United Kingdom make an interesting division of these cases, but the mere fact that some of them, like Kennedy versus Hungary, could have been solved with the same outcome by other legal arguments does not make this line of cases less convincing or less coherent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2231.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2237.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We do not see these decisions as contradicting earlier judgments of this Court, rather as supplementing them.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2237.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2250.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In addition, we do not really see why the cases related to failed requests of personal data, such as Leander versus Sweden, cited by the written submissions of the UK government would be of significance in this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2250.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2263.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nevertheless, the applicant does not presume that there is a general obligation for member states to impart public information regardless of the subject of the piece of information concerned.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2263.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2273.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Establishing the right to access to information as an inherent right of the freedom of expression is not a unique example of unprecedented activism.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2273.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2278.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Important elements of this Court's jurisdiction are based on similarly deduced rights.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2278.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2290.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Most notably, Article 6 on fair trial is the basis of the right to access to court, and Article 2 on the right to life is proved to be the basis of the protection of environmental rights under the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2290.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2304.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The wording of the fundamental international documents on the protection of human rights had been formulated decades before technical development and information society led to the general recognition of the freedom of information in modern democracies.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2304.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2308.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As the Court has reiterated many times, the Convention is a living instrument.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2308.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2318.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The rights enshrined in the Convention have to be interpreted in the light of present-day conditions so as to be practical and effective.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2318.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2329.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sociological, technological, and scientific changes and evolving standards in the field of human rights have to be considered when applying the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2329.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2341.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Similar considerations have led other international bodies of human rights protection to acknowledge aspects of the right to access to information in the process of determination of the scope of freedom of expression.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2341.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2353.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Human Rights Committee came to this conclusion in its general comment number 34 with regard to Article 19 of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2353.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2369.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>While the Inter-American Court of Human Rights held in the case of Claude Reyes and others versus Chile that Article 13 of the American Convention on Human Rights protects access to public information as a part of freedom of expression.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2369.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2389.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Hungarian government argues that the fact that the Member States of the Council of Europe adopted a separate, specific Convention on the right to access to official documents proves that Article 10 was not intended to cover the right to seek information from public authorities, but only the right to receive information that has already been made public.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2389.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2399.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is a rather interesting argument since the specific Convention explicitly refers to Article 10 in its preamble, but it can also be challenged by important counter-examples.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2399.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2417.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The adoption of the Istanbul Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence would obviously not prevent the Court to maintain its Article 3, Article 8 and Article 14 practice defending women against violence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2417.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2423.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But we can also refer to Article 10 and the European Agreement on the Protection of Television Broadcasts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2423.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2440.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nonetheless, the Court has previously relied, for example in the Marx versus Belgium case, on the existence of specific Council of Europe documents in support of establishing a common European approach justifying the dynamic interpretation of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2440.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2458.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To sum it up, Article 10 of the Convention covers decisions of Member States on denying access to public documents, and it is applicable under the circumstances of the present case because the procedure of Hungarian authorities concerns a direct interference with the applicant's Article 10 rights.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2458.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2465.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second, to the status of the data requested.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2465.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2474.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Whether the interference was prescribed by law in the case is mostly determined by the legal status of the requested data.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2474.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2486.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As we all know, the data requests in the case were submitted to police headquarters that disclosed the names of defence councils appointed and the number of cases in which each of them was appointed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2486.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2504.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Hungarian government cited a number of judgments on personal data protection from the Court of Justice of the European Union in its written comments to support its position, but none of them provide us guidance in the present case because the issue here is monitoring the work of public authorities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2504.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2524.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, the nature of the requested data is in no way related to the private sphere or privacy of the ex-official defence councils, neither to issues falling under the attorney-client privilege or their official confidentiality requirements, as they did not cover any information about the individual cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2524.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2530.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The system of appointing defence councils is different from Member State to Member State of the Council of Europe.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2530.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2552.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, these differences should not affect the decision of the Court, as the case and the status of the data might well be decided on the basis of the Hungarian public defence system alone, where the duty of the public council is clearly performed as a result of a decision exercising public power and financed by public funds.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2552.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2565.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant argued from the start of the national judicial proceedings that the public interest nature of mandatory defence establishes the status of public data of public interest for the requested data.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2565.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2572.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The First Instance Court accepted this argument, but the Second Instance Court and the Supreme Court rejected it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2572.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2599.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The definition of the applied article of the Hungarian Freedom of Information Act, namely Article 19, paragraph 4 of the Act on the Protection of Personal Data and the Public Nature of the Public Interest Data, clearly set out in a general manner that unless otherwise provided by law, all personal data of persons performing public duties shall, inasmuch as they are related to their duties, constitute public data of public interest.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2599.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2610.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We think that the public data of public interest status, the public nature of the requested information, was clearly provided by the Hungarian legal system on the basis of three facts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2610.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2624.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, the name of the defence council, regardless of being private or appointed ex officio, cannot be erased from any published court decision since 1 January 2006.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2624.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2638.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That is the entering into force of Article 18, paragraph 2, point B of Act 90 of 2005 on the Electronic Freedom of Information, which requires the publication of nearly all decisions of the Supreme Court and Courts of Appeals.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2638.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2646.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second, the ex officio appointed defence council's fee and expenses shall be advanced and often paid by the State.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2646.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2656.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In terms of the name and the number of cases, the public funding alone constituted clear ground for the public nature of the data under Hungarian law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2656.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2671.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And third, the court hearings are open to the public, even for the press, and audio and video recordings of the defence council can be made without his or her permission under Article 74B, paragraph 1 of Criminal Procedure Code.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2671.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2685.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Accordingly, the appointed defence council's name and the fact that he or she was appointed and how many times he or she was appointed does not constitute personal data protected by the right to informational self-determination.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2685.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2694.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Consequently, the courts denied the access to the requested information on the basis of a legal provision that clearly could not have been applied in the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2694.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2699.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the prescribed by law requirement has not been complied with.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2699.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2712.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Even if the court had recognised this limitation as prescribed by law, we think that under the Hungarian regulation mentioned above, there is no pressing social need for denying the access to the requested information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2712.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2717.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And now, third and finally, to the consequences of denials.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2717.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2732.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant would not normally use any of his 30 minutes of publicity to talk about his own work and activities, but the written submission of the government contains some arguments on the aim and nature of the research and the informational requests which have to be commented on.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2732.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2748.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will submit these remarks along with some other clarifications regarding the facts of the case, which can also be relevant in case the court comes to assess whether the interference had a legitimate aim and whether it was proportionate and necessary in a democratic society.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2748.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2758.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The state is not entitled to question or criticise the aim of freedom of information requests or to question the research methodology an individual or an organisation applies.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2758.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2769.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, the government's memorial chose to address in detail the applicant's research methodology and the justifiability and necessity of its freedom of information requests.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2769.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2775.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the applicant wishes to point out some misleading statements in relation to the research.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2775.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2786.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Hungarian Helsinki Committee is one of only a handful of organisations regularly and systematically monitoring the protection of human rights in Hungary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2786.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2792.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The number of independent Wajdaw organisations actively monitoring Article 6 of the Convention is even smaller.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2792.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2804.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Unfortunately, the research report is not just one of several empirical studies accessible on the appointment practice of defence councils, but the first and only of its kind.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2804.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2814.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, without other public sources of information, the findings and grounding of the research have had direct effect on the public and scientific debate on the topic.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2814.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2819.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And thus, the applicant's data requests serve the public interest.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2819.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2842.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant has not only proven through the freedom of information requests in the framework of the research that the distribution of appointments is disproportionate, being in fact the first in Hungary to do so, but has also developed and tested an alternative pilot model of a new appointment system in close cooperation with some police headquarters and the bar associations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2842.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2853.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, in order to prove that there is in fact a problem which needs to be handled on national scale, the applicant needed comprehensive data first on the practice of appointments.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2853.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2864.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, solely the cooperation with the police as suggested in the government's memorial would not have been enough to provide evidence on the flaws of the appointment system.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2864.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2883.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As to the remark of the government's memorial that there was no explanation in the methodology of the survey on the selection of police departments, the applicant would like to submit that, as also showed by the research study, the 28 police departments were selected to cover all seven regions of Hungary equally.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2883.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2892.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Four police departments were selected in each region, with a view to cover large and smaller cities and county police departments as well.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2892.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2909.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant did not conclude in his research study, quote, that the most frequently appointed legal aid defense counsels are those who are the least active in the course of the criminal proceedings, and they provide the lowest quality of service, unquote.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2909.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2929.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Instead, it stated that the data obtained showed a disproportionate appointment practice, proving the existence of in-house lawyers, lawyers who base their practice on ex-official appointment, and that the performance of ex-official defense counsels in general was lower than that of retained counsels.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2929.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2935.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The latest statement was based on the applicant and other stakeholders' previous researches.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2935.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2946.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, it is wrong to conclude that the non-disclosure of the data requested was justified by the necessity to protect the reputation of others, as argued by the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2946.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2953.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In addition, it has to be noted that the later argument was not evoked by the authorities in the domestic procedure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2953.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2965.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The fact that the research study did not contain any names of the legal aid defense counsels only means that the applicant used but chose not to disclose the names.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2965.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2975.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, obtaining the names of appointed defense counsels was necessary for assessing the number of appointments a defense counsel had received per year.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2975.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2982.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To that end, the applicant also had to see when a law office was appointed instead of an individual lawyer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2982.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2992.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It has to be borne in mind that according to the research, some individual attorneys received hundreds of appointments per year, the highest number being 453.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2992.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3000.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, requesting anonymous statistical data suggested by the government's memorial would have been inadequate.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3000.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3015.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The argument that compares journalists to non-governmental organizations and states that they are, quote, bound by stricter professional standards as regards the factual foundations of their statements, unquote, is also misleading.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3015.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3023.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The liability of the applicant and its researchers for unfounded statements is as strict as any publishers and authors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3023.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3032.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This, of course, creates a clear legal obligation for the applicant to criticize the work of the system under research only on the basis of facts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3032.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3051.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Finally, the applicant refuses the government's insinuation that it had any ulterior motive with regard to the freedom of information request, quote, as an association with a network of lawyers providing legal aid, also in criminal cases, who might be potential competitors to the legal aid defense councils, unquote.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3051.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3070.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant has been advocating for almost a decade for the reform of the appointment system with a view to ensure its transparency and the right of indigent defendants to effective defense, recommending that appointments are made by an independent entity instead of the police and or for randomizing the appointment system.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3070.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3078.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is hard to see how these advocacy efforts could have led to any advantage for the attorneys contracted by the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3078.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3089.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Lastly, it must be emphasized that the around 10 defense councils usually contracted by the applicant typically represent victims of ill treatment and asylum seekers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3089.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3103.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the applicant typically pays for defense council work only when the ill-treated person is also charged with violence against official persons, meaning only a handful of cases per year from the hundreds of cases the applicant provides legal aid in.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3103.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3114.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That said, the applicant submits that the consequences of the state's failure to comply with its obligation flowing from Article 10 of the Convention were twofold.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3114.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3120.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, refusing the freedom of information request did in fact affect the research of the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3120.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3132.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It goes without explanation that the credibility and well-founded nature of a scientific study is necessarily weakened when the amount of empirical data serving as its basis decreases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3132.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3147.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this relation, it is important to point out that the denied requests underlying in the present case concern Debrecen, the second largest city of Hungary in terms of population, and the fourth largest county from among the 19 counties of Hungary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3147.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3160.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Since Debrecen is a seat of a regional court with 390 practicing attorneys at law, the missing data obviously affected the grounding of the findings of the research.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3160.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3167.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second, the Supreme Court's decision in the case had a chilling effect with regard to similar freedom of information requests and research.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3167.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3185.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Supreme Court's decision in the present case was referred to in two subsequent decisions of the Supreme Court, both approving the denial of the applicant's similar freedom of information requests submitted in the framework of the same research, and both pending before the European Court of Human Rights.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3185.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3200.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, the decision of the Supreme Court was published separately as BEH 2011-69, thus as a published court ruling which in the Hungarian system strongly influences and orientates the practice of courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3200.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3214.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government's memorial itself quotes the decision under the heading jurisprudence, even though the debated decision obviously cannot be a reference point in determining applicable law in the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3214.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3220.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Supreme Court's decision was a leading case on the issue, even in the view of the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3220.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3235.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Consequently, the Supreme Court's decision has a chilling effect on any individuals or organizations which would intend to research the practice of ex-official appointments in the future, and thereby on freedom of expression.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3235.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3243.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Let me finish with a verbatim incorporation of documentary evidence supporting the arguments on the effect I just described.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3243.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3268.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Hungarian online investigative journalism portal, Átlátszó, submitted a freedom of information request on the 15th of September to the Szeged Police Department, asking for the disclosure of names of defense counsels appointed by the department in the criminal procedures initiated for the newly imposed border blockade crimes, and the number of appointments the individual counsels had.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3268.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3285.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These crimes are prosecuted in a special simplified fast-track procedure, and the vulnerability of defendants, mostly asylum seekers, make the accountability for the decision of the appointments of defense counsels even more important than in other criminal cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3285.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3296.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In its response, sent on the 28th of October, the department denied to disclose the requested data, with an argument specifically citing the same Supreme Court judgment this case is about.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3296.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3318.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As the wording of the 2011 Act on the Freedom of Information maintained the rule on public data of public interest, as it was included in the 1992 Act applied in the case, the police found no need to consider the specific nature of the data requested or consider other legal arguments.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3318.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3326.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This proves that the challenge court decision had led to a situation where the requested data are inaccessible for the general public.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3326.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3344.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To sum it up, the Supreme Court's decision did in fact affect the effectiveness of the applicant's contribution to the debate of an issue of public interest, and the effectiveness of any such future attempts in relation to the practice of appointments, either by the applicant or by other actors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3344.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3345.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, members of the honorable court, thank you for your attention.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3349.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3352.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Dr. Sepsi.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3352.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3355.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now I call Mr. Coppel, who has 15 minutes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3355.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3355.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please, Mr. Coppel.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3364.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3366.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3366.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3369.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President and members of the court,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3369.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3376.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>the United Kingdom is grateful for the permission of the court to intervene in these proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3376.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3379.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is an important case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3379.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3390.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It represents a long overdue opportunity for the Grand Chamber to state a definitive position on the question of whether Article 10.1 of the Convention</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3390.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3393.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>confers a right to freedom of information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3393.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3415.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And by a right to freedom of information, I mean a prima facie right of access to information which is held by public bodies, regardless of whether that information has been made available to the public or whether the public body in question is willing to impart it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3415.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3421.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Until a few years ago, the answer to that question was not in any doubt.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3421.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3434.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is clear from the travaux to the Convention that the framers deliberately chose not to include any right approximating to a right to freedom of information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3434.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3457.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Consistent with the travaux, there is a long and consistent line of Grand Chamber judgments, in particular Leander and Sweden, Gaskin and the UK, Guerra and Italy, Roche and the UK, and Gilbert and Sweden, which find that Article 10.1 means what it says.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3457.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3485.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It imposes an obligation upon contracting states not to interfere with the receiving of information which somebody wishes to impart, but not a positive obligation to impart information on request, whether that information be personal data, environmental information or other types of information held by the state.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3485.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3493.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Fifth Section of the Court has recently confirmed in Weber and Germany that that remains the position.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3493.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3508.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Court, it stated, does not consider that a general obligation on the state to provide information in a specific form can be inferred from its case law under Article 10.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3508.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3510.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>End of quote.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3510.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3517.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But as the Court will be aware, other section judgments have adopted different approaches.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3517.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3530.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In our view, the time has come for the Grand Chamber to resolve the confusion which has arisen in recent times by reaffirming the previous Grand Chamber case law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3530.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3545.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This case is important not only because of the implications of the alleged right to freedom of information which the applicant organisation submits that you should identify within Article 10.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3545.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3551.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Those implications are a matter of the greatest significance for many contracting states.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3551.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3565.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This case is important also for what the Court's judgment will mean for the legitimacy of the Court's activities in deciding cases which arise under the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3565.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3579.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If the Court is to remain within the limits of interpretation of the Convention, there can be no doubt that the previous Grand Chamber judgments should be affirmed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3579.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3598.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>All of the applicable principles of interpretation of treaties in the Vienna Convention and in the case law of the Court point to the conclusion that Article 10 does not confer any implied and general right to freedom of information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3598.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3608.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The language of Article 10 is against such a right and the traveau confirm that that was no accident.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3608.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3615.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The most authoritative case law of the Court points only in one direction.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3615.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3627.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We recognise that there are two other recent strands of authority from sections of the Court which, contrary to Grand Chamber authority, purport to find within Article 10.1</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3627.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3633.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>a general or a more limited right to freedom of information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3633.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3641.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In our view, both of these strands of authority are wrong in principle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3641.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3671.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As for the more limited right, the second, third and fourth sections have all decided cases, in particular Kennedy and Hungary, Rossiano and Romania, and Guseva and Bulgaria, which appear to state that there may be a violation of Article 10 where one arm of the state has recognised a right to receive information, but another arm of the state has frustrated or not given effect to that right.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3671.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3699.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The more extreme manifestation of that doctrine can be found in judgments of the first, second and fifth sections, Mäkij and the Czech Republic, Tarszaszág and Hungary and Oskar Rysz-Szyszyn and Reineggen against Austria, which appear to find a general right of access to information which is of equal status to the right of freedom of expression, which is expressly stated in Article 10.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3699.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3712.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We acknowledge that there are examples in the previous case law of the Court where it has changed its mind about the effect of a provision of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3712.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3727.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But none of these isolated instances to which I refer has required departure from such a long and distinguished line of Grand Chamber judgments as that with which we are concerned today.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3727.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3744.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>None has involved the Court recognising what is in effect a new and highly significant right as being implicit within a provision of the Convention whose wording suggests the opposite.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3744.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3767.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, those few instances of change, for example on the rights of homosexuals and of transsexuals under Article 8 of the Convention, have always been in the context of a perceived need to update the case law of the Court so that it reflects contemporary social attitudes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3767.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3773.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There is no such need in the case of freedom of information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3773.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3778.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The practice of contracting States on this subject varies widely.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3778.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3788.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Council of Europe has acted only in late 2008 to agree a Convention on access to official documents.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3788.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3795.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That Convention has been ratified by only seven contracting States and is not in force.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3795.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3819.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It illustrates some, and only some, of the complexity and detail which must accompany any right of access to official information, none of which is to be found within Article 10, and with which the Court will have to grapple in this case if it is to accept the submissions of the applicant organisation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3819.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3831.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nor is this a matter of social morality, where it may be possible to justify the Court seeking to provoke a change in social attitudes in some States.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3831.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3849.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In short, if the Court were now to recognise a right of access to information held by the State, that would far exceed legitimate interpretation of the Convention and would amount to judicial legislation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3849.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3864.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For the reasons we have given in our written observations, none of the Chamber judgments to which I have referred provide any satisfactory basis for the Court declining to follow the previous case law of the Grand Chamber.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3864.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3876.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In those cases, it was either expressly conceded or just not argued by the parties that Article 10.1 conferred an appropriate right</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3876.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3889.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>to access information which the State wished to withhold, or else that issue simply did not arise on the facts properly analysed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3889.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3900.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>None of the Chamber judgments faces up to the Grand Chamber case law and tries to explain why that case law should no longer be followed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3900.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3909.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We submit that those judgments have little or no persuasive value in the current proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3909.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3931.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If, despite what we have said, the Grand Chamber is not content to stand by its previous case law and wishes to give further recognition to a right of access to official information, we have suggested in paragraph 4.10 of our written observations</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3931.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3944.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>the only principled basis upon which the Court could find that Article 10.1 provides a limited right to freedom of information,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3944.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3953.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>that is, in circumstances where domestic law has already recognised a right to the information in question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3953.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3978.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In that situation, which was the factual position in some of the Chamber judgments, such as Guseva and Bulgaria, it may be said that one arm of the State is willing to provide information, but another has acted in breach of the negative obligation which is expressly stated in Article 10.1</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3978.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3983.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>by interfering with the receipt of that information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3983.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3997.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That is, we submit, the only coherent basis on which any freedom of information right may be found within Article 10, but it is not without significant difficulties and dangers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3997.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4013.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The UK Supreme Court has questioned the logic of relying upon Article 10, rather than in particular Article 6, in order to address the issue of defiance of domestic court orders.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4013.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4034.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Further, this explanation of Article 10 will inevitably create a temptation at the level of this Court to find a domestic law right to information, even where that was not the conclusion of the domestic courts which dealt with the matter.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4034.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4042.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This Court is not, of course, an appellate tribunal and that temptation must be firmly resisted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4042.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4065.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the absence of a final domestic court order requiring the disclosure of information, it would not be open to this Court, we submit, to find that there is a domestic right of access to information which is capable of giving rise to an Article 10 right on this analysis.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4065.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4078.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So in conclusion, we urge the Court to confirm the previous case law of the Grand Chamber, which, as an interpretation of Article 10.1,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4078.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4084.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>is long-standing, principled and plainly correct.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4084.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4100.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But whichever approach is ultimately adopted, the United Kingdom would invite the Court to address previous Grand Chamber judgments and to explain in clear terms why these ought or ought not to be followed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4100.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4112.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That is the very least that must be done in order to maintain the legitimacy of and universal respect for the decision-making of the Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4112.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4122.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For those reasons, together with the reasons set out in our written observations, we invite the Court to decide that Article 10 of the Convention does not create an implied right to freedom of information.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4128.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4131.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Mr. Coppel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4131.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4134.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now I turn towards my colleagues in case they have questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4134.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4136.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I see Judge Spano, please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4139.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4141.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4141.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4168.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As the parties are aware, this case was relinquished to the Grand Chamber, so the convention stipulates that we are dealing with a serious question affecting the interpretation of the convention and is on that basis, and due to some of the arguments made here today, that I would like to pose a question, mainly to the applicants, but I would like, with the permission of the president, to ask the government and the third-party intervener to maybe comment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4168.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4187.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There was some notion or suggestion here that we, in examining the applicability issue, should look at the implications, the possible consequences of that approach, and that issue is not dealt with directly by the applicants in their brief, so that's why I put forward the question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4187.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4196.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I would like to focus here on what the applicants consider to be the possible consequences of that approach in the following terms.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4196.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4206.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We see that freedom of information legislation sometimes provides, or often provides, for absolute limitations under domestic law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4206.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4217.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In certain circumstances, there simply is not a document, for example, dealing with national security issues, law enforcement issues, they are simply excluded from the domestic right.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4217.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4234.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>How would the applicants invite the court to deal with those types of situation, assuming that there is a right under Article 10, and thus, in general, Article 10 would necessitate a proportionality-type analysis?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4234.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4241.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>How would we, the court, be able to deal with those kinds of situations in particular?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4241.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4257.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And on that note as well, would the court, assuming that such a right would be recognized, what about notions such as what constitutes a public authority, a quasi-public authority, an official document?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4257.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4268.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Would these kinds of notions have to be autonomously interpreted by the court, or do you foresee a possible different way the court could proceed on that basis?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4268.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4274.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My second question is linked to an argument made by the applicants here today.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4274.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4281.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They invite us to look at, the court to look at, other international instruments and decisions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4281.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4297.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Inter-American Court of Human Rights, the UN Human Rights Committee, if I'm not mistaken, the provisions they are dealing with explicitly mention a right to seek information, which, as you know, Article 10 does not.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4297.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4323.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Can the applicants confront that issue in particular, and could they tell the court, are there any examples either in international norms, or even in constitutional norms, where the right of access to documents has been considered an inherent rule in a similar textual formulation like Article 10 of the Convention?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4323.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4323.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4324.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4326.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Judge Spano.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4326.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4327.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Judge Sicilianos, please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4330.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4332.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4332.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4340.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My question is mainly addressed to the government, but it is also open to the applicants if they wish to comment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4340.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4356.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to Article 31, Paragraph 3C of the Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties, the court must take into account any relevant rules and principles of international law applicable in the relations between the contracting parties, in our case, Hungary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4356.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4366.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As you know, this provision has been repeatedly invoked and applied by our court as an important rule of interpretation of the European Convention of Human Rights.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4366.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4371.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The UK government has correctly referred to Article 31 of the Vienna Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4371.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4383.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now, Hungary is bound by the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights of 1966, whose Article 19 explicitly recognized the right to seek information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4383.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4390.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Hungary has also ratified the Council of Europe Convention on access to official documents.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4390.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4404.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, Hungary is a member of the EU whose Charter of Fundamental Rights and relevant 2001 regulation recognized the right of access to documents of the EU institutions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4404.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4423.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So in view of those apparently relevant rules and principles of international and European law binding upon or accepted by Hungary, how do you see the functioning of Article 31, paragraph C, of the Vienna Convention in the present case?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4423.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4423.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4424.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4425.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Judge Sicilianos.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4425.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4425.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Judge Motoc, please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4429.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4431.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup, M. le Président.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4431.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4440.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ma question s'adresse également au gouvernement hongrois et aussi au requérant, s'il veut en faire partie, s'il veut commenter.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4440.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4447.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Quelque chose est lié à la question qui a été mise par le juge Sicilianos.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4447.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4470.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, on connaît que la première règle d'interprétation du droit international qui existe dans la Convention de Vienne, c'est la règle qui est prévue par l'article 31, normalement l'article 31, paragraphe 3, et qui fait référence aux autres instruments internationaux qui ont été déjà cités et à leur jurisprudence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4470.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4489.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et on connaît aussi que l'interprétation des droits de l'homme, des traités des droits de l'homme, des traités multilatéraux des droits de l'homme, est différente par rapport aux traités qui ne sont pas, qui ne concernent pas les droits de l'homme, vu que dans les traités des droits de l'homme, la question de réciprocité ne s'applique pas.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4489.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4515.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, normalement, on dit dans la doctrine que dans les traités des droits de l'homme, on n'a pas le même type d'interprétation vu le fait que les intentions des partis, et ici je fais référence aux travaux préparatoires dont le gouvernement britannique a fait référence, ne jouent pas le même rôle comme ils jouent dans les traités bilatéraux ou les traités multilatéraux qui ne traitent pas les droits de l'homme.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4515.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4531.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc voilà une question qui est reconnue dans la doctrine et qui fait la différence entre les deux types d'interprétation dans les traités multilatéraux qui traitent les droits de l'homme et dans les traités multilatéraux qui ne traitent pas les droits de l'homme.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4531.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4561.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et en relation avec cette question, je voulais poser une question plus concrète au gouvernement hongrois parce que dans le paragraphe 11 de votre mémoire, le gouvernement hongrois se réfère au fait que dans l'affaire Taraschuk, ils n'étaient pas capables de contester l'applicabilité de l'article 10 vu qu'ils n'étaient pas partis dans l'affaire Mackey contre la République tchèque.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4561.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4587.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais comme on reconnaît dans la doctrine et comme le Lord Brown l'avait expliqué dans l'affaire Sugar, on regarde ces trois affaires, ça veut dire l'affaire Mackey, l'affaire Taraschuk et l'affaire Kennedy, comme une trilogie de notre cours, ça veut dire trois affaires qui reconnaissent d'une manière progressive ce type de droit.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4587.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4590.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et ma question au gouvernement hongrois est la suivante.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4590.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4616.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Est-ce qu'au moment où l'affaire Taraschuk était devant le gouvernement hongrois, pourquoi est l'affaire Mackey précédente à l'affaire Taraschuk de l'année 2006, pourquoi est-ce qu'en ce moment-là, le gouvernement hongrois n'a pas contesté comme il le fait aujourd'hui l'applicabilité de l'article 10 à ce genre de question?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4616.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4630.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La deuxième question que je pose au gouvernement hongrois et qui est plus concrète et qui vise aussi l'article 31, le paragraphe 3, se réfère au droit de l'Union européenne.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4630.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4669.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et le gouvernement hongrois donne plusieurs exemples du droit de l'Union européenne concernant la protection des données, mais ils ne font pas référence, par exemple, à une affaire qui est très importante pour le droit de l'Union européenne, notamment pour l'article 8 de la charte des droits fondamentaux, ça veut dire « austerite contre le Randfund » où on sait qu'il y avait un accès concernant les données qui étaient plus privées concernant les salaires vu que le requérant demandait un contrôle de dépense publique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4669.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4687.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, quelle est la position du gouvernement hongrois par rapport à cette jurisprudence de la Cour de Luxembourg et par rapport au fait que la Hongrie est membre de l'Union européenne et qu'elle est soumise aux dispositions et aux sources du droit européen?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Iulia Antoanella Motoc</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4687.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4688.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous remercie beaucoup, Monsieur le Président.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4689.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4691.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup Madame la juge Motoc. Judge Kūris please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4694.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4696.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4696.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4704.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My question goes, first of all, to the representatives of the government, but of course, the applicants can also comment on it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4704.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4709.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the question relates to — it's a factual question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4709.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4714.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It relates to a broader context of the applicant situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4714.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4722.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Most of the police departments provided the information to the applicant, which the applicant requested.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4722.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4728.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, a couple of departments refused to provide it, and that's why we have the case here.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4728.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4737.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the basis for that, according to the interpretation, was that the information contained private data which cannot be disclosed under the domestic law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4737.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4741.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's what the government defended, this position.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4741.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4750.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I have a question which then splits into probably four questions, and I will now tell all of them in certain consequence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4750.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4771.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First of all, are there any provisions, and if so, what provisions in the Hungarian domestic law regarding liability for disclosure by public officials of information which is not to — which cannot be disclosed under the domestic law, which is protected, such information as private data?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4771.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4792.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second, if the answer to this first question is in the positive, that such provisions exist, and I believe that they must exist, then have these provisions been applied to any public official, any police department that disclosed the information which was requested by the applicant?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4792.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4803.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My third question is, if the answer to this question is no, if it is in the negative, then why they have not been applied, if they have not been applied?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4803.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4835.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the fourth question, or the fourth part of this big question is, if they have not been applied because persons concerned have not initiated this application, still, have there been any ex post facto — I mean ex post facto, that is, after the final judgment of the Supreme Court — instructions by the executive or by whichever authority to the police departments that they should not disclose such information in the future if such information is requested?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Egidijus Kūris</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4835.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4835.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4836.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4838.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Judge Kūris.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4838.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4846.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If there are no more questions, now the court will rise for, I would say, roughly a quarter of an hour.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4846.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4857.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We can resume at 10 to 11, following which the parties will return for a second round of short pleadings to respond to the submissions in the first round and to the judges' questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4857.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4857.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the hearing is suspended.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4979.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4980.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5018.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5019.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please be seated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5019.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5029.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the hearing is now resumed and I call Mr. Tallódi who has 10 minutes, please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5040.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5045.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much for the possibility of answer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5045.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5052.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First of all, I would like to react to the question of Mr. Sicilianos and Judge Motok</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5055.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5062.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>concerning the Vienna Convention. The right to seek information is indeed recognized by</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5062.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5076.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>international treaties ratified by Hungary, and it is accordingly ensured by the Hungarian Fundamental Law as well. The only relevance of the text of Article 10 in this case is</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5076.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5088.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>that it sets out the limits of the jurisdiction of this court. As it was pointed out in the</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5088.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5130.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>in my former speech, when the new convention was adopted by the Council of Europe concerning the European, the access to official documents, still didn't intend to subject this right to the jurisdiction of the court, and opted for the adoption of a separate treaty with distinct supervisory mechanism, instead of adopting an additional protocol to the European Convention on Human Rights. So the Hungarian government absolutely agrees with the approach</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5130.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5140.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>of the question, and it is the main aspect of our answer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5140.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5152.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I, Mr. Motok, also asked the possibility of the dispute concerning the case of</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5152.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5162.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Társaságvál, Szabadságjogok versus Hungary, and why the Hungarian state didn't refer to it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5162.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5176.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As pointed out, it was based on the considerations of the pure domestic law, without taking into account the possible consequences at the European level of this decision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5176.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5212.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The question of EU law, concerning the question of EU law, we would like to add that the public should endure more interference than private professionals operating on the private market, like mere legal aid defense councils in Hungary, who were taking part in the process in this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5212.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5222.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Concerning the question of Mr. Kúris, I would like to add, and I would like to answer, that</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5222.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5239.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>there is a possibility in the Hungarian law to file a lawsuit against public authorities violating personal or personality rights, including the right for data protection.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5239.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5262.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this context, there have been no lawsuits filed, since the actual names of the legal aid defense councils were not published by the applicant, and therefore the affected parties didn't become aware of the violation of their rights.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5262.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5281.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I have to add that the government has no information on any ex officio sanction against police departments, which unlawfully disclosed personal data in this context.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5281.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5283.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These were my answers, thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5286.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5289.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Mr. Tallódi.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5289.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5290.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And now I call Dr. Sepsi, please, you have the floor.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5293.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5295.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5295.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5299.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First to answer the two questions of Judge Spano.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5299.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5332.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The first is about the merits and the consequences of applying access to information in this case, and the special problems regarding the data which are clearly under the obligation not to disclose under national legislation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5332.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5346.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would stress out that the aim of the applicant was not to force or to advocate for creation of a new right in this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5346.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5362.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We would rely on existing jurisprudence which actually contains the merits and the provisions which can be used in these cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5362.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5389.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Of course, if the issue would have been a creation for a jurisdiction on a standalone right on the access to official document, then the court would come to the same problem which other human rights protection organs, for example, national constitution courts, faced when they had to create their own practice on this issue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5389.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5403.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But we think that in this case, the court can clearly rely on its existing practice on the protection of Article 10.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5403.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5436.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As to the second question, seeking information and its relation to other documents of international human rights protection, I have to admit, of course, that we did not find any other example where the seeking of documents was not incorporated in these international documents.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5436.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5451.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So both in the case of the Inter-American practice and in the case of the Human Rights Committee practice, their texts are actually containing the reference to seeking.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5451.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5479.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's true, but I have to add, partly in connection with what has been said by the Hungarian government earlier, that in this situation, we cannot say that by the time those documents were drafted, there was actually a concept for the access to documents or the concept of freedom of information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5479.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5490.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So I have to say again that a lot had been changed in the past decades in these terms.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5490.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5522.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And one short answer to the question of Judge Kudis is that we also did not encounter any kind of consequences for disclosing those personal data in the case of the departments who actually answered the request of freedom of information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5522.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5522.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5523.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5526.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much Dr. Sepsi.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5526.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5534.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now, since the intervening government received a question by Judge Spano, I would give the opportunity to Mr. Coppel to reply for five minutes, please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5540.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5559.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In answer to the question of Judge Spano, we submit it in line with our opening observations that the consequences of a recognition of a convention right to freedom of information would be very serious.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5559.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5563.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I'll give you three examples of that.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5563.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5579.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First of all, the complexity and detail of the freedom of information right to which I referred earlier would have to be worked out by the court, potentially as autonomous concepts of convention law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5579.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5589.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So who is entitled to ask for information, under what conditions, which persons and bodies are required to disclose information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5589.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5600.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's a very contentious issue in the UK, has led to a number of cases and was recently in the Supreme Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5600.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5619.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What exemptions and exceptions can be relied upon by public bodies, which exemptions can be absolute exemptions, so long as the information falls within the subject matter of the exemption, it need not be disclosed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5619.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5628.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But some exemptions will not be absolute, some will have to depend upon the facts of the individual case, so which is it to be.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5628.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5635.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the mechanisms for the enforcement of freedom of information rights is another matter.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5635.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5650.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The UK Freedom of Information Act, which is by no means the most complex around, runs to several hundred sections and paragraphs dealing with these issues.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5650.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5671.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second example of implications, the logic of the applicant's position is that each of these facets of a domestic right to freedom of information, if it exists, would be subject to some sort of proportionality reasoning and analysis by the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5671.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5697.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That proportionality analysis would overlay complex domestic law and require difficult and sensitive decisions to be taken by the court as to the drawing of lines for the freedom of information right, and would require those decisions to be retaken in effect according to the different proportionality standards.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5697.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5711.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Many of these decisions relate to matters such as national security information, which are, and ought to remain, squarely within the jurisdiction and discretion of contracting states.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5711.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5725.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this can't, we submit, all be left to be worked out according to the margin of appreciation, which as we know can be quite narrow in Article 10 cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5725.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5736.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Third example of implications is the procedure which is necessary in a freedom of information case, and would be necessary in this course.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5736.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5756.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I tell you from my own personal experience of freedom of information cases in the UK, where the question is whether a public body was justified, was entitled to withhold information, the court or tribunal which is examining that question must of course look at the information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5756.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5761.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It must consider the information in question for itself.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5761.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5777.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the complicating factor in the procedure of the court is that the applicant cannot be allowed to look at the information and to make those arguments on the basis of the information, because otherwise the litigation would be determined.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5777.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5796.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the UK tribunals have developed procedures for closed, open and closed documentary material, open and closed sessions of the court, so there are sessions where the applicant can be present and where they can't, special arrangements for documents.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5796.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5799.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now it's all very difficult.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5799.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5803.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This court has no such procedures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5803.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5817.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It could develop some, indeed it may be required to develop some, if you go down the road of recognising a freedom of information right, but we would counsel very strongly against that.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5817.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5827.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I think I was also offered the opportunity to comment on the question relating to the Vienna Convention, and I would do so very briefly, if I may.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5827.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5838.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We say that Article 31, subparagraph 3, subparagraph C strongly supports the interpretation of Article 10 that we put forward.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5838.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5855.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Yes, one should take account of relevant rules of international law when interpreting the European Convention, but the Council of Europe Convention on the Right of Access to Official Documents is not a relevant rule of international law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5855.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5859.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is not in force, it may never come into force.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5859.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5868.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The EU Charter of Fundamental Rights does not confer a right of access to information held by the state, by the member states.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5868.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5875.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It could have done, but it only confers a limited right of access to information held by the EU institutions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5875.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5878.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's quite different.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5878.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5894.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It also, of course, contains a right of access to personal data, which was the right at issue in the Oesterreiche-Rundfunk case, but that, of course, is dealt with under Article 8 ECHR, not Article 10.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5894.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5912.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And finally, Article 19 of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights is a relevant rule of international law, but it demonstrates the limitations of Article 10 rather than requiring Article 10 to be interpreted more broadly.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5912.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5938.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It has an express right to seek information in contrast to Article 10, and the effect of Article 31 of the Vienna Convention is not to require the European Convention on Human Rights to be interpreted beyond what the framers stated in Article 10, so as to accord with other treaties which have plainly gone further.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>ThirdParty</Role>
        <Name>TP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5938.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5944.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the contrary, those other treaties operate as a limiting factor on the interpretation of Article 10.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5946.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5950.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Mr. Coppel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5950.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5953.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5953.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5959.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I thank the parties for their interventions and their replies to the questions of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5959.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5963.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5963.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5966.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The judgment will be delivered later.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5966.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5971.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery, and I declare the hearing closed.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

</transcript_1803011_04112015>
