<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<transcript_904305_15102013>
  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>11.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>11.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>62.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>63.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Good morning.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>63.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>72.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Natsvlishvili and Togonidze versus Georgia.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>72.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>90.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The case was lodged on 9 March 2005 with the court under Article 34 of the Convention by two Georgian nationals, Mr. Amiran Natsvlishvili and Mrs. Rusudan Togonidze.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>90.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>100.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The application was allocated to the second section of the court, Pursuanto Rule 52, Paragraph 1 of the Rules of the Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>100.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>113.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On 1 February 2011, the court changed the composition of its sections and this case was assigned to the newly composed third section.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>113.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>121.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The application was declared admissible on 25 June 2013.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>121.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>129.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government are represented by Mr. Gocha Lortkipanidze and Mr. Alexandre Baramidze,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>129.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>138.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Deputy Ministers of Justice, and Mr. Levan Meskhoradze, agent of the government, who are</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>138.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>145.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>assisted by Mrs. Shorena Mezurnishvili, a senior counsel at the Ministry of Justice,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>145.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>151.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>and Mrs. Natia Mezvrishvili, a senior public prosecutor.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>151.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>161.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants are represented by Mrs. Maka Gioshvili, Mrs. Elene Fileeva, and Mr. Kirill Koroteev,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>161.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>164.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>legal counsels.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>164.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>169.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>169.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>181.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I also welcome a delegation from the Office of Public Defender of Georgia and a group of judges from the Russian Federation who are on a steady visit to the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>181.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>196.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this respect, I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting into Russian has been authorized for the benefit of the later group of judges.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>196.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>207.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>207.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>216.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Having consulted the agent of the government and the representatives of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>216.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>225.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. Koroteev, Mrs. Gioshvili, and Mrs. Fileeva for the applicants will speak first, and then</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>225.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>232.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. Meskhoradze for the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>232.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>232.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Before starting, I call Mr. Kirill Korotev.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>238.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>242.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci. Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les juges,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>242.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>254.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette affaire concerne en premier lieu l'imposition d'une peine pénale suite aux négociations sur le plaidoyer entre l'accusation et la défense. L'accord procédural entre les</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>254.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>260.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>parties a été validé par le juge. Pour les accusés ayant plaidé coupable, le droit</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>260.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>266.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>juridique interdisait de faire appel. Le premier récurrent soulève notamment la question</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>266.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>271.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>de compatibilité de cette procédure avec l'exigence de l'article 6 de la Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>271.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>286.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vais traiter des questions liées aux critères d'appréciation de la régularité de procédure pénale entachée des négociations entre les parties qui découlent de la jurisprudence de votre court et des courts et tribunaux qui se sont prononcés sur le même problème.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>286.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>306.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ensuite, mes collègues, Maître Gheochvili et Maître Filley-Ivan, vous parleront de non-respect de ces critères dans l'affaire du premier récurrent ainsi que de griller des récurrents tirés des violations alléguées de l'article 1er de protocole additionnel à la Convention et de l'article 34 de la Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>306.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>326.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, la question que la Cour nous pose en premier lieu consiste à savoir si la rénonciation par le premier récurrent de son droit en passé équitable était valide au vu de l'importance de ce droit et si les garanties contre l'abus de pouvoir par l'accusation étaient suffisantes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>326.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>338.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En effet, le premier récurrent a plaidé nolo contendere, c'est-à-dire qu'il ne s'est pas reconnu coupable mais qu'il a accepté la peine proposée par le procureur.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>338.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>346.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais pour les besoins de l'affaire pénale, plaider nolo, c'est plaider coupable, ce qui constitue, entre autres, la rénonciation à certains droits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>346.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>362.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A cet égard, votre Cour rappelle, dans l'arrêt d'Ewer contre Belgique, que le droit en tribunal avait une trop grande importance dans une société démocratique pour qu'une personne en perde le bénéfice du seul fait qu'il a souscrit un arrangement parajudiciaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>362.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>370.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>De plus, une mesure ou une solution dénoncée comme contraire à l'article 6 appelle un contrôle particulièrement attentif.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>370.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>385.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Parmi les garanties essentielles confirmées par la jurisprudence de votre Cour se trouve le droit d'être assisté d'un avocat dès la première édition par les autorités d'enquête, puisqu'un accusé se trouve souvent dans une situation particulièrement vulnérable à ce stade.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>385.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>399.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour l'a reconnu dans l'arrêt Salludos contre Turquie et a conclu à une violation de l'article 6 de la Convention dans l'affaire Stoïkovitch contre France et Belgique, où le récurrent était passé aux aveux sans avoir été assisté d'un avocat.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>399.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>414.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toute menace, pression ou la violation par l'accusation de la Cour entre les partis va aussi conduire au conseil de la violation de l'article 6, comme dans l'affaire Marpas et Lent contre les Pays-Bas.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>414.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>428.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les systèmes juridiques des autres partis à la Convention prévoient d'autres garanties contre l'abus de pouvoir par l'accusation, notamment le contrôle renforcé du juge dans le contexte de plaidoyer coupable ou de négociation entre les partis à la procédure pénale.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>428.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>439.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ainsi, le droit et la jurisprudence anglais et allemand se focalisent sur le rôle assez actif de juge dans les négociations sur la culpabilité et la peine.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>439.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>451.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Selon l'arrêt Goodyear de la Court of Appeal d'Angleterre, c'est le juge de fond qui a la faculté d'indiquer la peine ou au moins son type, l'amende ou l'emprisonnement, à la demande de l'accusé.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>451.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>462.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il doit également demander à l'accusé de réformuler par ses propres mots les faits dont il a reconnu l'existence pour s'assurer du caractère volontaire de plaidoyer coupable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>462.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>481.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour constitutionnelle fédérale allemande insiste, dans son arrêt du 19 mars 2013, sur l'obligation du juge de fond d'établir les faits réprochés à l'accusé avant de proposer une solution qu'il va adopter si l'accusé plaide coupable, et cela en toute connaissance des conséquences d'un tel plaidoyer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>481.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>491.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le droit italien se distingue par le contrôle renforcé exercé par le juge sur les accords entre l'accusation et la défense.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>491.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>519.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Selon la jurisprudence de la Cour constitutionnelle italienne, en particulier dans les arrêts de 2 juillet 1990 et 6 juin 1991, il appartient au juge de fond de vérifier non seulement les indices de l'infraction dans les faits réprochés à l'accusé, mais aussi les indices de sa culpabilité, même s'il s'agit d'un standard de preuve moins élevé que celui applicable aux procédures contentieuses.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>519.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>529.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le juge peut aussi établir des circonstances atténuantes et modifier par conséquent la peine proposée dans l'accord entre les parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>529.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>545.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ensuite, le Code de procédure pénale français limite à un an d'emprisonnement ou à la moitié de la peine encourue, la peine que la procureure de la République peut proposer dans le cadre de la procédure de compression sur reconnaissance préalable de culpabilité.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>545.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>563.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La présence d'un avocat est obligatoire et la constitutionnalité de cette procédure a été validée par la décision du Conseil constitutionnel du 2 mars 2004, sous réserve de l'obligation pour le juge de vérifier la réalité des faits réprochés à l'accusé.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>563.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>582.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Finalement, selon la jurisprudence russe, dont les références sont noticiées dans nos observations du 2 septembre dernier, les peines réellement prononcées suite à emploi des coupables ou à l'accord entre les parties ne se distinguent pas des peines prononcées suite aux procédures contentieuses.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>582.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>609.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Outre-Atlantique, la Cour suprême des États-Unis attache une grande importance à l'enregistrement minutieux dans le procès verbal des admissions de l'accusé, du caractère volontaire de son plaidé coupable, des explications du juge et du caractère explicite de son rénonciation à trois droits constitutionnels, droit d'être jugé par les assises, droit de confronter l'accusation et droit de ne pas témoigner contre soi-même.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>609.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>619.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>« Presuming waiver from a silent record is impermissible », l'accord suprême américain a-t-il jugé dans l'arrêt Boykin v. Alabama.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>619.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>626.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En McCarthy v. United States, la Cour suprême a invalidé à l'anonymité la peine prononcée</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>626.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>628.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>suite à un plaidé aillé coupable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>628.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>635.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En était la raison que le juge de fond n'avait pas expliqué à l'accusé les éléments de l'infraction de l'évasion fiscale.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>635.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>644.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si tel avait été le cas, il aurait été envisageable que l'accusé peut être coupable en infraction de moins en grand.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>644.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>656.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans tous ces systèmes, l'appel de jugement de condamnation suite à un plaidé coupable est possible, même s'il est associé à des conditions plus restrictives que l'appel contre une condamnation suite à une procédure pénale contentieuse.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>656.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>674.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour en faire un résumé, dans les systèmes qui permettent à l'accusé de plaider coupable ou de participer aux négociations sur le plaidé aillé, la présence de l'avocat est obligatoire dès le premier interrogatoire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>674.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>691.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ensuite, soit c'est le juge qui propose la solution, soit il contrôle le fond de l'accord entre les parties, y compris la réalité des faits et les indices de culpabilité, soit c'est le législateur qui pose un certain nombre de limites à l'action de l'accusation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>691.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>698.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En tout état de cause, le rôle du juge ne se limite pas à une validation de l'accord entre les parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>698.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>708.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, nous assistons sur la conclusion que ces critères n'ont pas été respectés en l'espèce, comme ma collègue Maître Ghiocchvili vous l'expliquera tout à l'heure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>708.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>722.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, en ce qui concerne la question de la cour portant sur l'égalité des armes entre le procureur et la défense pendant les négociations sur le plaidé aillé, le requérant dénonce fermement l'absence de cette garantie fondamentale.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>722.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>740.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Comme le notent les rapports de Transparency International Georgia et du commissaire à droits de l'homme du Conseil de l'Europe, cité dans la décision de la Cour sur la récivabilité, le taux d'acquittement en Georgia ne dépasse pas un pour cent de jugement au pénal.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>740.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>750.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est une arme puissante de procureur qui est assurée d'obtenir une condamnation s'il accusé insiste sur son innocence et les négociations sur le plaidé échouent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>750.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>769.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A cela s'ajoutent les conditions de détention et traitement médical en se faisant les deux étant contraires à l'article 3 de la Convention, comme la Cour l'a reconnue dans les arrêts tels que Ramishvili et Korkhidze contre la Georgia et Pogosian contre la Georgia.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>769.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>771.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je m'attarde sur ce dernier point.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>771.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>783.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il est bien connu et les recherches empiriques citées dans nos observations de 2 septembre dernier le démontrent, que plusieurs accusés se considérant innocents plaident coupables aux charges contre eux.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>783.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>798.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cela est fait pour éviter le procès dans son ensemble où une peine plus lourde pouvant être prononcée à l'issue de la procédure contentieuse, pération de liberté au lieu d'une amende ou encore les conséquences dont une telle peine peut être attachée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>798.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>807.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous sommes d'avis que la situation des accusés est différente selon le taux d'acquittement dans les procédures pénales contentieuses dans un système juridique donné.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>807.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>820.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si 50% des accusés sont acquittés par les tribunaux, celui qui doit décider de plaider coupable ou non a des chances réelles de se défendre devant le juge.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>820.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>834.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans les systèmes où le taux d'acquittement est inférieur à 1% comme la Georgia, l'accusé qui fait face à la même décision sait que s'il insiste sur son innocence et opte pour une procédure pénale contentieuse, il va sûrement être condamné.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>834.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>846.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>De ce croix, en Georgia, et contrairement à la Fédération de Russie, il y a une vraie différence entre les peines prononcées suite aux accords procéduraux et celles prononcées suite aux procédures pénales contentieuses.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>846.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>856.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il ne s'agit donc pas d'égalité des armes entre les parties à la procédure pénale georgienne impliquée dans les négociations sur le plaidoyer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>856.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>865.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Avec votre permission, Monsieur le Président, je céderai la parole à Me Gheorghevili qui va apporter à votre cour les réponses aux questions sur les faits spécifiques de cette affaire.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>873.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>887.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les Juges, La première question que la Cour nous pose est de savoir si le modèle georgien de l'accord procédural, applicable en 2004, était conforme avec les exigences de l'article 6, paragraphe 1.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>887.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>889.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La réponse du premier récurrent est non.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>889.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>895.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous allons traiter cette question à travers des autres questions de la Cour concernant l'accord procédural.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>895.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>909.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour nous demande ensuite si le modèle georgien de l'accord procédural avait pour résultat la rénonciation aux certains droits procéduraux et si c'était le cas, quels étaient les garanties contre l'abus de pouvoir de la part de l'accusation?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>909.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>915.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Un géorgie, à l'accusé en concluant l'accord procédural, rénonce à ses droits procéduraux.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>915.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>925.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour que cette rénonciation soit considérée comme conforme à l'article 6, garanties doivent exister afin d'éviter l'abus de pouvoir de la part de l'accusation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>925.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>938.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Notamment, il est important, de ce point de vue, et qu'à être juridiquement défini, la garantie du droit de la défense, l'égalité des parties et un contrôle juridique efficace effectué par les tribunals.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>938.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>941.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Malheureusement, ces garanties n'existaient pas en l'espèce.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>941.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>953.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le Code de procédure pénale attribuait de larges pouvoirs au procureur, les droits de l'accusé étaient restreints et les tribunals n'exerçaient qu'un contrôle inefficace et formel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>953.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>966.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Concernant le pouvoir du procureur, tout d'abord, l'initiative de l'accord procédural relévé du procureur, le Code de procédure pénale n'est précisé nulle part des infractions concretes dont la Commission permettait de conclure l'accord procédural.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>966.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>975.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Faute de ces précisions, le procureur disposait d'une pleine liberté de décider à son gré à quel accusé il pourrait proposer l'accord procédural et pour quel type d'infraction.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>975.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>980.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Lors de l'accord sur la peine, deux conditions préalables étaient requises.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>980.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>986.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'accusé devait être d'accord avec le procureur sur la peine, des condamnations et devait coopérer avec l'enquête.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>986.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>994.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En ce qui concerne la peine, les procureurs disposaient du droit d'appliquer une sanction plus légère que prévue pour une infraction commise.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>994.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1005.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En outre, en vertu de l'article 42 du Code pénal, lors de la conclusion de l'accord procédural, une peine d'amende est susceptible d'être appliquée à titre accessoire ou à titre principal.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1005.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1013.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans la pratique, la peine d'amende à titre de peine principale ou à titre de peine accessoire a lieu dans 99%.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1013.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1020.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La loi n'est déterminée ni le maximum ni le minimum de la peine d'amende et ni le minimum de la peine d'emprisonnement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1020.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1028.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Lors de la négociation de l'accord procédural, les procureurs, de ce point de vue aussi, avaient une totale liberté de choix de la peine.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1028.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1041.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le rapport de transparence internationale indique que, dans certains cas, au moment de la conclusion de l'accord procédural, les procureurs auraient demandé le paiement d'une peine d'amende de 100.000 laris pour une infraction légère et le paiement</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1041.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1046.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>d'une peine d'amende nettement inférieure à la dite 100 pour une infraction beaucoup plus grave.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1046.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1054.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ainsi, les procureurs avaient la liberté totale de déterminer à son gré la sanction à l'égard de l'accusé.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1054.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1056.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce dernier ne pouvait que l'accepter ou pas.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1056.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1063.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Au cas où il n'acceptait pas la peine proposée, l'accord procédural n'aurait pas lieu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1063.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1066.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La deuxième condition de l'accord sur la peine était la coopération avec l'enquête.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1066.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1074.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les codes de procédure pénale ne donnaient pas une définition concrète ou des critères d'appréciation de la coopération avec l'enquête.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1074.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1079.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Par conséquent, ils offraient la possibilité à l'accusation d'être interprétée vaguement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1079.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1103.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il en découle que le procureur était habilité et avait la possibilité de décider à son gré à quel accusé allait-il concrètement proposer la conclusion de l'accord procédural, quel type de peine allait-il appliquer envers quel accusé, quel montant de l'amende ou quelle durée d'emprisonnement à proposer, et ce qu'il pourrait considérer comme une coopération avec l'enquête.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1103.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1108.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>À ce qui concerne les droits de l'accusé, il avait le droit d'assister d'un avocat.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1108.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1115.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'accusé qui a conclu un accord sur une peine n'avait plus le droit d'y renoncer et de demander l'examen du dossier au fond.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1115.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1122.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'accusé ne pouvait pas non plus former un recours contre la décision du tribunal sur l'homologation de l'accord procédural.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1122.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1135.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il en découle que la version Georgienne initiale de l'accord procédural appliqué dans l'affaire du récurrent n'y comportait pas de garantie suffisante contre l'abus de pouvoir par les procureurs et pression sur l'accusé.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1135.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1144.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cela est dû au large pouvoir du procureur et des droits limités de l'accusé, en absence du contrôle du juge, comme je l'expliquais tout à l'heure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1144.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1160.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Quant à la question de l'existence des intérêts publics impérieux qui s'opposent à la rénonciation de l'accusé à ces droits prévus par l'article 6, nous rappelons que le respect de l'égalité des armes entre les parties à la procédure pénale est une garantie fondamentale contre l'abus arbitraire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1160.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1175.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le gouvernement, à son tour, ne s'est pas prévu de l'existence des intérêts publics qui nécessitaient la restriction des droits de l'accusé et du contrôle du juge à l'exercice par les procureurs de ces pouvoirs déjà larges.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1175.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1182.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour nous demande ensuite si l'acceptation du premier requérant à l'accord procédural était volontaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1182.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1184.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La réponse du premier requérant est non.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1184.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1191.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Lorsque le requérant a accepté l'accord procédural, il s'est trouvé déjà en prison depuis six mois.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1191.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1199.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les premiers quatre mois, il les a passés sous pression psychologique à cause de la présence de son ravisseur et d'un accusé d'un meurtre dans sa cellule.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1199.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1204.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il est à noter que le requérant a été interrogé plusieurs fois et il n'a jamais plaidé coupable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1204.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1209.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'accusation présentée au requérant prévoyait une condamnation de six à douze ans.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1209.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1213.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'étau d'acquittement en Géorgie est inférieur à 1%.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1213.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1224.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le requérant avait le choix soit de passer au moins six ans en prison, soit d'accepter la proposition du procureur sur l'accord procédural avec des conditions établies par le procureur.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1224.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1233.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il savait que s'il n'acceptait pas cette proposition, le procureur demanderait la peine d'emprisonnement sévère et le tribunal aurait approuvé cette demande.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1233.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1240.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans ces circonstances, l'acceptation par le premier requérant de l'accord procédural ne peut pas être vue comme volontaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1240.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1246.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'accord nous demande quel fut le mécanisme de défense contre la coercion possible.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1246.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1250.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ces mécanismes n'étaient pas effectifs, voire n'existaient pas.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1250.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1261.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le requérant ne pouvait pas refuser l'accord qu'il avait déjà donné et il ne pouvait pas non plus former un recours contre la décision du tribunal homologuant l'accord procédural.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1261.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1269.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>S'il déclarait qu'une pression a eu lieu à son égard, il ne cesserait pas à mesure de l'approuver.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1269.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1276.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si le tribunal prenait en compte sa déclaration et rejetait la conclusion de l'accord procédural, ceci ne changerait pas sa situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1276.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1290.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Au contraire, elle impérerait, puisque le tribunal réellement avait deux choix, deux possibilités, soit homologuer l'accord procédural, soit renvoyer le dossier au procureur afin de conclure un acte d'accusation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1290.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1306.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si le tribunal renvoyait l'affaire pour investigation, le requérant ne pourrait pas se faire rembourser les cents qu'il avait déjà payés et un autre, le procureur démanderait la peine d'emprisonnement sévère lors de l'examen judiciaire ou derrière, ce qui probablement serait pris en considération.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1306.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1316.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'accord nous demande ensuite si le requérant a été informé que par la conclusion de l'accord procédural, il renonçait à ses droits procéduraux.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1316.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1326.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ni les parquets ni les tribunaux n'ont jamais prévenu les premiers requérants qu'ils seraient privés de tous ses droits procéduraux à la suite de la signature de l'accord procédural.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1326.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1335.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'accord nous demande si le déroulement des négociations entre le procureur et le requérant a été bien enregistré par le procureur.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1335.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1336.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La réponse est non.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1336.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1347.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il faut remarquer que l'on ne peut ni préciser ni confirmer depuis quand le procureur a commencé à proposer l'accord procédural au requérant, puisque cette proposition a été orale.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1347.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1358.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cependant, lorsque le requérant et les collaborateurs ont cédé les actions à l'Etat également, lorsqu'un proche du requérant a versé une somme au Fonds d'Etat, l'accord avait déjà été conclu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1358.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1369.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pourtant, des procès-verbaux sur la proposition du procureur et ensuite sur les négociations ultérieures n'ont pas été dressés et le déroulement de la négociation n'a non plus été enregistré.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1369.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1375.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Par conséquent, les enregistrements évoqués n'ont pas été déposés devant le tribunal puisqu'ils n'existaient pas.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1375.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1384.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La question suivante de la Cour est de savoir si l'examen de l'accord procédural par les tribunals représentait une forme suffisante de contrôle judiciaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1384.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1386.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La réponse du requérant est non.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1386.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1391.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le procureur a déposé une requête au tribunal le 9 septembre 2004.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1391.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1395.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le même jour, le requérant a payé une amende de 35 000 arrêts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1395.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1400.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il est à noter qu'il a été fait payer avant que le tribunal homologue l'accord procédural.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1400.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1409.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Selon la loi, les juges devraient vérifier si l'accord procédural a été conclu par mensonge ou contrainte et si les consentements de l'accusé étaient volontaires.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1409.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1430.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Selon la ligne A2 de l'article 679-3 du Code des procédures pénales géorgiennes, les juges devaient poser huit questions à l'accusé pour s'assurer non seulement que l'accord était volontaire mais aussi que l'accusé comprenait les charges contre lui et les faits que la conclusion de l'accord procédural constituait la rénonciation à ses droits constitutionnels.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1430.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1445.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, selon le procès verbal de l'audience du 10 septembre 2004, devant le tribunal d'Ekutaïsi, la seule question posée par les juges au premier requérant portait sur le caractère volontaire du consentement à l'accord procédural.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1445.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1454.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le tribunal devait également vérifier selon la loi si l'accusation était argumentée et si la peine indiquée dans la requête était légitime.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1454.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1458.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans la pratique, cette vérification avait un caractère purement formel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1458.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1469.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>D'après les rapports des Transparencies internationales et commissaires des droits des langues cités dans la décision de la Cour sur la récevabilité, il est peu probable que les juges vérifient réellement les preuves.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1469.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1478.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les juges tenaient presque toujours en compte des preuves déposées par les procureurs et, dans la majorité des cas, ils approuvaient la démande présentée par les procureurs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1478.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1488.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En l'espèce, le tribunal n'a pas étudié les détails de l'affaire, notamment le fait que le requérant détenait au total que 15,5% d'actions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1488.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1494.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le tribunal a examiné l'accord procédural les lendemains de dépôt d'une requête par les procureurs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1494.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1497.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les pièces du dossier présentées par le parquet comportaient 12 volumes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1497.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1501.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le tribunal n'avait pas physiquement le temps d'en prendre une réelle connaissance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1501.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1510.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le juge a copié la requête du procureur et a considéré que, représentée par le procureur, prouvait la commission de l'infraction par le requérant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1510.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1524.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Par conséquent, le tribunal n'a pas effectué les contrôles réels et suffisants sur les déroulements et la conclusion de l'accord procédural et n'a pas intéressé à examiner s'il représentait par le procureur prouvait la commission de l'infraction par le requérant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1524.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1529.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Quant à la question de savoir si l'audience était publique, la réponse est non.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1529.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1532.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'audience était nue à huis clos.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1532.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1542.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En fait, elle ne pourrait pas être publique, puisque la requête sur l'homologation de l'accord procédural, en vertu de la lignée 4 de l'article 679.2 du Code de procédure</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1542.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1543.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>pénale, était confidentielle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1543.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1547.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et elle n'était pas applicable que pour les partis.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1547.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1554.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est pour cette raison que les personnes intéressées n'ont pas été admises à l'audience.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1554.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1564.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La question suivante de l'accord consiste à savoir si l'absence de recours possible contre la décision du 10 septembre 2004 était compatible avec l'article 2 du protocole n°7.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1564.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1579.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La jurisprudence de votre cour n'admet pas les interdictions inconditionnelles totales de faire appel d'une condamnation terminale, plus dans les cas des infractions minières, comme en Cacabase contre Georgie, ou pour les accusés qui ont fui le procès, comme Crombard contre France.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1579.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1586.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ainsi, l'interdiction totale de faire appel du jugement homologue à l'accord procédural n'est pas compatible avec l'article 2 du protocole n°7.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1586.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1592.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Avec votre permission, M. le Président, j'accèderai la parole à Mme Phileva, qui</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1592.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1594.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>va apporter à votre cour les réponses aux autres questions.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1597.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1598.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mrs. Fileeva.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1600.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1604.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, I start with the violation of Article 6,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1604.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1606.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Paragraph 2 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1606.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1624.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The European Court of Human Rights has repeatedly pointed out that the presumption of innocence provided by the Convention in the second paragraph of Article 6 is violated if the court decision or a public affair statement reflects that the accused is guilty when his guilt is not lawfully established in advance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1624.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1631.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the present case, the prosecutor, accompanied by journalists, appeared at the first applicant's workplace in order to arrest him.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1631.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1639.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A TV broadcast that same evening showed how police officers took the accused down the stairs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1639.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1649.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This served as background for an interview with the Kutaisi governor, who stated that those who embezzled the state property would be criminally punished.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1649.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1663.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The fact that the prosecutor decided to arrest the applicant in the presence of the journalist and the governor's interview were purposely made to ensure that the society believed that the applicant was guilty of repatriation of the state property.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1663.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1669.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There was no final and binding judicial decision convincing the first applicant at the time of his arrest.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1669.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1672.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the presumption of innocence was violated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1672.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1680.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The second question I start is the violation of Article 1 of the Additional Protocol of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1680.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1689.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The prosecutor asked the applicants to transfer their shares to the government and also to transfer 50,000 Georgian lari to the state fund.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1689.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1702.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This was the condition for concluding the plea agreement with the first applicant for a seizure of property to comply with the Article 1 of the Protocol 1 that has to be carried out in accordance with the law and meet the public need.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1702.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1709.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the present case, the Georgian state was granted victim status in criminal proceedings against the first applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1709.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1717.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government could sue the first applicant for damage after the court approved the plea agreement and found him guilty.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1717.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1726.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to the prosecutor's request to return the share to the government before the conclusion of the plea agreement was not lawful and not based on any legal rule.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1726.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1732.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The first applicant did not transfer the share voluntarily and it was not recorded as a part of the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1732.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1737.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>He was forced to cede shares to the government in exchange for release.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1737.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1746.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The transfer of 50,000 Georgian lari carried out by the applicants relative to the state fund was directly related to the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1746.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1752.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It happened on the 8th September, 2004, so the plea agreement could be signed the following day.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1752.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1763.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As it follows from the witness statement in the case file, the prosecutor has explicitly required that the transfer be a precondition for the conclusion of the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1763.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1774.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If anything, this case reminds the case of Kucinski against Russia, where the applicant was required to transfer his share in a broadcasting company to the Russian government to exchange of release.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1774.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1781.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>No public need was established in Kucinski and not was argued by the respondent government in the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1781.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1793.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In sum, the requirement to return share to the government and to pay 50,000 Georgian lari to the state fund had no legal basis, and therefore, we are not in accordance with the Article 1 of Protocol 1.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1793.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1795.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The next question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1795.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1803.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Article 34 of the Convention and Rule 32 of the Rules of Court, Paragraph 2 of the Rules of the Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1803.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1809.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>After the government became aware of the present application, it started requesting it be withdrawn.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1809.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1812.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We have submitted copies of the government letter to the end.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1812.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1823.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As regards any possible friendly settlement, the applicant insisted on the conduct of negotiation within the framework of the proceeding before the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1823.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1829.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government, however, refused and returned with a new indictment and cancellation of the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1829.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1849.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court has held a number of occasions, including in Balinovich against Croatia, that the requirement of confidentiality of friendly settlement or negotiation contained in Rule 62 of Rules of Court is absolute and does not allow for an individual assessment of how much detail was disclosed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1849.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1861.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In present case, given that the negotiation, contrary to the applicant's insistence, were conducted outside the framework of the proceedings before the court, Rule 62 did not apply.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1861.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1870.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Even if it didn't apply, we submit that no information was disclosed by the applicant to the press, to the public, or to any third party.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1870.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1873.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>All the communications were with the court only.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1873.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1887.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As the commission ruled in 1996 decision of Malic against France, the requirement of confidentiality serves to protect the party, in particular the applicants and the convention bodies from the attempt to exert pressure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1887.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1902.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We view in the light of the protection, streets of view proceeding against the applicant if the application is not withdrawn, even if made in the context of friendly settlement negotiation is precisely the kind of undue pressure against which the convention and rules protect the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1902.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1907.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We submit such streets violate Article 34 of the convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1907.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1910.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This concludes oral observation of behalf of the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1910.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1925.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We respectfully invite the court to find violation of articles 6, paragraph 1 and 2 of the convention, article 1 of the protocol 1 to the convention, as well as respondent governments failing to comply with the requirement of article 34 of the convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1925.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1926.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1928.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1930.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1930.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1933.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I call Mr. Meskhoradze.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1948.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1952.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Good morning, Mr. President, honorable members of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1952.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1958.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is a great honor for me to appear before you today on behalf of the Georgian government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1958.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1964.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In my submission, I will raise the following issues in response to the court's questions and argue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1964.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1972.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, the Georgian model of plea bargaining applied in the applicant case was compatible with Article VI, Paragraph 1 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1972.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1976.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second, the criminal proceedings with regard to the applicant was fair.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1976.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1982.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>He was afforded all the safeguard against any undue influence or intimidation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1982.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1988.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And in the course of the conclusion of plea agreement, he acted in a genuinely voluntary manner.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1988.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1994.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Third, the applicant's right to presumption of innocence was respected in the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1994.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2001.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Fourth, no hindrance with the effective exercise of the applicant's right of application has occurred.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2001.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2012.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, I will submit that by disclosing the contents of friendly settlement negotiations, the applicants undermined the confidentiality principle in breach of the rules of court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2012.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2020.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Last, I will submit that no violation of Article I, Protocol 1 of the Convention can be observed in the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2020.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2025.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your Excellencies, let me start with the first submission.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2025.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2034.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The plea bargaining, a form of consensual and abbreviated criminal justice, has been widely accepted in the procedure of different legal systems for a long time.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2034.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2046.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It has been successfully incorporated in the legislation and practice of various European states and worldwide in harmony of international criminal law and criminal procedure principles.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2046.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2053.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>None of the international human rights tribunals have suggested that plea bargaining undermines human rights provisions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2053.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2075.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Quite contrary, International Criminal Tribunal for former Yugoslavia and International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda, the institutions dealing with the most egregious human rights violations, crimes against humanity, genocide, and mass murders, and therefore, known by strong procedural safeguards, use plea bargaining as a standard practice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2075.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2086.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As practice shows, in those Western European and American states where plea bargaining is most extensively used, these rights appear to be best protected.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2086.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2097.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Emergence and spread of plea bargaining system in the world is driven by the increased interest of procedural economy as it provides for an efficient and rapid disposal of cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2097.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2114.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As early as in 1987, the member states of the Council of Europe were being advised by the committee of ministers to develop means of simplifying and expediting trial procedures, which included summary judgments, out-of-court negotiations, and guilty pleas.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2114.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2126.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Looking across the Europe as a whole, it is crystal clear that plea bargaining has rapidly become an essential aspect of criminal procedure, which allows consensual disposal of a vast majority of cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2126.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2133.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is further an effective system, allowing great flexibility in resource management.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2133.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2150.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The most powerful inducement for the establishment of a regime of plea bargaining is that it represents a tried, practical, and arguably the most successful weapon against corruption and organized crime, with an impressive record both in Europe and internationally.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2150.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2162.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Expressed simply, plea bargaining offers the opportunity for prosecutors to break through the walls of silence and fear, which surrounds and protects such criminality.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2162.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2168.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With the global spread of plea bargaining in the last few decades, Georgia has followed the suit.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2168.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2184.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is important to note that the introduction of plea bargaining in Georgia in 2004 cannot be fully understood without appreciating the context of endemic criminality and corruption pervading the country at that moment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2184.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2190.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Plea bargaining was thought to be an urgent response and means to address these systemic problems.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2190.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2200.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your Excellencies, my submission will be that plea bargaining system is in full conformity with human rights and liberties, among which it is the right to a fair trial.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2200.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2209.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the Georgian model of plea bargaining applied in the applicant case was compliance with Article VI, paragraph 1 of the convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2209.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2224.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I submit that the concept of plea bargaining implies the waiver of some rights in exchange of certain benefit in the form of reduced sentence, conditional sentence, non-custodial sentence, and the defendant gets the final decision without delay.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2224.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2240.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As noted in paragraph 59 of Dimitrov and Hamono versus Bulgaria case, it is common feature of the criminal justice system in Europe for a defendant to receive a reduction in his or her sentence for a guilty plea in advance of trial.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2240.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2251.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Let me now refer to the Kwiatkowska versus Italy case, in which the court underlines that the waiver of certain rights under Article VI means that the trial is shortened.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2251.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2256.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Witnesses are not questioned, and the evidence is not examined in details.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2256.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2269.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court has constantly emphasized in the case law that neither the letter nor the spirit of Article VI of the convention prevents a person from waiving of his own free will.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2269.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2290.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will allow myself to refer to the Divya versus Belgium case as well, where the court in paragraph 49 clearly stated that in contracting states, the waiver is frequently encountered in civil matters in the shape of arbitration clause in contracts or criminal matters in the shape inter alia of fines paid.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2290.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2302.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The waiver, which has undeniable advantages for the individual concerned as well as for the administration of justice, do not in principle offend the convention system.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2302.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2314.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Honorable members of the court, I would like to emphasize that despite a waiver of certain rights, a pre-agreement procedure in no way results in the evasion of trials.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2314.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2328.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is of paramount importance to underline that in Georgia, like in other states, the reduced and expedited trials in substance retain all necessary characteristic to ordinary court hearings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2328.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2332.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Let me enlist these fundamentals.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2332.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2335.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The agreement must be reached voluntarily.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2335.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2339.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The both parties shall participate in the conclusion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2339.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2345.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The right to remain silent and the right not to incriminate oneself remain in force.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2345.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2349.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The participation of the counsel is mandatory.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2349.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2352.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court supervision is ensured.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2352.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2357.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The case must be decided by independent and impartial tribunal.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2357.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2361.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Prima facie evidence must be evaluated by judge.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2361.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2365.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The case must be examined in public trial.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2365.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2377.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your excellencies, I will submit that the applicant, despite waiving the right to have a full-scale trial, had offered each of the guarantees I have just listed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2377.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2391.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pre-bargaining, like all other aspects of criminal justice procedure, cannot operate in a successful and non-abusive way unless it is accompanied by the effective implementation of essential due process safeguards.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2391.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2407.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would like to stress that criminal legislation in force at that material time provided sufficient safeguards against abuse of power by prosecution authorities during the conclusion of plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2407.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2411.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Namely, the participation of the counsel was mandatory.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2411.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2417.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A prior consent of a defendant was necessary for an agreement to be reached.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2417.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2431.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The pre-bargaining procedure required the written declaration signed by the accused or his lawyer reflecting voluntary consent to the judicial ruling without examination of the merits of the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2431.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2437.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court must have examined the motion in public trials.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2437.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2451.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court must have been convinced that the agreement was not the result of duress, intimidation, or undue promise, and that defendant was in a position to enjoy the qualified legal assistance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2451.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2459.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court must have ensured that the defendant had full awareness of his accusation and the menacing sentence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2459.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2466.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Judge must have guaranteed that the defendant fully understood the contents and the legal outcome of the agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2466.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2471.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court must have warranted the defendant consented freely.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2471.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2481.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The defendant was entitled to reject the agreement before the final approval by the court as provided by Article 6793EG.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2481.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2485.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The judge was authorized to reject the agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2485.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2492.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant was afforded each of the mentioned safeguards during the criminal proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2492.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2507.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your Excellencies, I will allow myself to move on the second submission and argue that the criminal proceedings toward the applicant was fair as a whole, and no breach of Article 6 of the Convention can be observed in the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2507.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2512.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To this end, I would like to focus, with your permission, on the following points.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2512.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2529.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, the applicant's decision to accept the plea bargain was made in full awareness of the effects and legal consequences, and he acted in a voluntary manner without any coercion or undue promise on the part of the prosecution authorities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2529.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2538.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second point is that the case was heard at an open hearing, and the court approved the plea bargain after the requisite examination of the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2538.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2545.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will refer to the facts of the case to corroborate my first point.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2545.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2556.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The facts of the case highlights that the applicant had full awareness of the contents of the plea agreement and the consequences thereof, and acted in one voluntary manner.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2556.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2567.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant was detained on 15 March 2004 for alleged misappropriation and embassment of property, resulting in damages incurred upon the state.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2567.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2581.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would like to draw the honorable court's attention to the fact that the applicant was assisted by the lawyer of his choice from the very next day of his arrest, which is 16 March 2004.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2581.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2589.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Since 6 August 2004, the applicant was assisted by the second lawyer, also on his choice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2589.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2601.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Noteworthy is the fact that initial intention on cooperation was declared by the applicant in 10 days after his detention, namely on 25 March 2004.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2601.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2609.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Let me refer to this early letter addressed to the respective authorities and cite the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2609.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2625.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Since I am not indifferent to the future of the automobile factory and considering the prospect of settlement or problems therein with the support of the state, I express the readiness to transfer the shares, both mine and my wife's, to the state.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2625.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2627.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>End of citation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2627.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2634.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this form, the applicant intended to repair the damages identified by the two expert examinations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2634.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2639.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The mentioned written statement was made in an absolutely voluntary manner.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2639.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2650.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is fact, which is proved by the following facts on 31 March 2004 during questioning, also attended by his lawyer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2650.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2663.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant reiterated his will to cooperate with the investigation and to this end transfer the shares in the automobile factory to the state in exchange for the damages incurred by him.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2663.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2676.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the meantime, the investigative authorities kept on carrying out various activities, inter alia questioning the witnesses, conducting specific expert examinations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2676.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2682.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As a result, on 6 September 2004, the final charges were brought against the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2682.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2692.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The investigator accused him of misappropriation and embezzlement of money in large amounts, resulting in substantial damages upon the state.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2694.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2711.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Having been familiarized with the final charges, the applicant, assisted by two lawyers, again expressed his readiness to cooperate with the investigative authorities and the same day transferred voluntarily the shares to the state.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2711.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2719.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would like to further demonstrate that the applicant was fully versed in the contents of the plea agreement and the consequences thereof.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2719.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2724.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Below, I would like to illustrate the statement by the following.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2724.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2727.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On 9 September 2004, Mr. Nutzle-Shwille</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2727.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2735.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>filed a written statement with a public prosecutor requesting him to arrange for a plea bargain agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2735.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2747.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this very letter, the applicant noted, I quote, with the purpose of reparation of damages incurred upon the state, my will is to conclude a plea agreement as regard this sentence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2747.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2752.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To this end, I will pay $35,000.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2752.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2759.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I am aware of the concept of the plea agreement and fully agree to it, end of quotation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2759.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2764.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The same day, prosecutor visited the applicant at the penitentiary institution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2764.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2772.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The meeting was held with the defendants, with the attendance of the applicant, together with his two lawyers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2772.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2785.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The written record was duly drawn up, which was included in the case file and subsequently submitted to the court for examination.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2785.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2793.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your excellencies, the record clearly stated that Mr. Nutzle-Shwille, I quote,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2793.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2803.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>fully assuming the content of the bargain and denying any duress, pressure, or any kind of undue promise, agreed to conclude the plea agreement, end of quotation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2803.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2810.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Notably, the record is signed by the applicant and his lawyers without any comments whatsoever.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2810.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2818.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>After the meeting with the applicant, the prosecutor applied to the court with a motion requesting the approval of the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2818.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2827.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The motion included a clear explanation of the accusation of the applicant, sentence range, and purpose of the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2827.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2850.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Namely, the motion stated, I quote, despite the commission of great grave crime by the applicant, which envisions the imprisonment of 6 to 12 years, considering the cooperation of the applicant with the investigation by repairing damages and interest of the efficient use of state resources, the plea agreement was concluded with the applicant, end of quotation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2850.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2856.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These details of the motion were also introduced to and signed by the applicant and his lawyers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2856.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2866.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the light of the above, the criminal case file makes evident that the applicant ought to know legal consequences of his choice to reach the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2871.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2878.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Let me now move to my second point, judicial examination of the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2878.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2888.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As I already mentioned above, the court is the most important safeguard against possible coercion or any undue promise towards defendants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2888.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2900.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is a further forum, the role examining the fairness of the negotiation between the parties and examining prima facie evidence establishing the guilt of the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2900.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2905.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The final say on the approval of the plea bargain agreement is always up to the courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2905.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2920.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I submit that at the court session held on 10 September 2004, the domestic courts verified whether the plea agreement was concluded based on the free and informed will of the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2920.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2929.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will allow myself to once again cite the applicant's response to the court's question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2929.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2933.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I understand the contents of the right explained to me.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2933.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2935.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I don't have any requests.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2935.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2941.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I have not been subjected to any kind of coercion to conclude the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2941.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2947.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The conclusion of a plea agreement was the result of a joint and voluntary agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2947.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2950.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>End of citation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2950.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2959.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would also like to cite the applicant's lawyer, who additionally noted, the agreement is voluntary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2959.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2963.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is not a result of any coercion or unlawful act.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2963.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2966.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nobody has influenced him to conclude this agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2966.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2970.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Quite to the contrary, it was Mr. Natsui Shirley</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2970.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2972.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>who requested the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2972.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2977.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Both me and my client attended the meeting on agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2977.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2980.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. Natsui Shirley had been instructed</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2980.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2983.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>on the consequences thereof.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2983.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2990.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Having declared the above mentioned, they both asked the judge to endorse the bargain, as submitted by the prosecutor.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2990.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2999.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court further examined the case file, which included documentary evidence, two expert examinations, and the witness testimonies.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2999.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3014.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Without examining the merits of the case in details, and considering the submissions of the parties along with the evidence in the case file, the court found the charges brought against the applicant were well-founded.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3014.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3017.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court had accordingly approved the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3017.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3035.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Summing up, I submit that firstly, despite the prosecutor's exclusive prerogative to initiate the plea bargain procedure, it was the applicant himself who had repeatedly addressed the prosecution authorities to cooperate and incite these authorities to engage in plea bargaining.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3035.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3050.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Hereby, I invite the respectful applicants to disclose a single proof which would suggest that these initiatives were a result of undue pressure on influence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3050.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3058.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Secondly, the criminal legislation regarding the plea agreement procedure blatantly defined the essence of the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3058.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3070.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sadly, the applicant was never precluded from the legal assistance of his lawyers, and both of them attended each and every meeting with the prosecutor and signed the relevant records.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3070.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3084.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is out of question that the responsibility of the lawyers implies no more than legal counseling of their clients, implying the explanation and instruction about the content and consequences of each and every legal procedure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3084.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3090.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Finally, the court's supervision as a safeguard against possible coercion was properly exercised.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3090.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3096.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would like to briefly comment on public hearing and the confidentiality principle concerning the plea bargaining.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3096.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3103.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant case was deliberated at a public hearing with the presence of the applicant, his lawyer, and the prosecutor.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3103.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3108.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>No decision had been made by the court to preclude any interested party to attend the session.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3108.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3114.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Accordingly, the Georgian government finds any allegation to this entirely unsupported.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3114.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3124.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Even if assumed that some persons were not allowed to be present at the court hearing, neither the applicant nor his lawyer had ever contested this fact.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3124.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3129.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court minutes does not contain any allegation whatsoever.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3129.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3142.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To comment on confidentiality principle, it should be mentioned that it applies solely to the agreement between the prosecution and the defense on the cooperation, and not the whole content of the agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3142.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3151.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Such a reservation intends to protect the accused from retribution or reprisals for the information he or she might disclose to the law enforcement bodies.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3151.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3162.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is important to note that the said clarification was also made to Article 6794 of the Criminal Procedure Code of Georgia on 25 March in 2005.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3162.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3173.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In substantiation of the above mentioned, I would like to note that the minutes of the court session does not declare any part of the hearing confidential.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3173.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3185.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The context of the request for plea be agreement, as well as the motion of the prosecutor, and the minutes of the meeting of 9 September 2004 had been discussed at the hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3185.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3195.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Hereby, I would like to briefly refer to the applicant's allegations concerning inability to appeal the court's decision approving the plea bargain.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3195.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3204.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant, being fully aware of the concept of plea agreement voluntarily and knowingly, waived his right to appeal.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3204.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3211.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Bearing this in mind, no violation of Article 60 of Protocol 7 is to be observed in the case at hand.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3211.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3227.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If the court decides otherwise, I would like to point out that amendment made in the Criminal Procedure Code of Georgia in 2005 enshrined the possibility to appeal the court decision approving the plea agreement in both sentence and charge bargain.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3227.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3235.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With your permission, now I would like to move to the third submission that the first applicant's presumption of innocence was respected in the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3235.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3242.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In Alain de Ribemont versus France, the highest ranking officers in French police referred to Mr. Alain de Ribemont</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3242.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3251.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>at the press conference without any qualification or reservation as one of the instigators and accomplice of the matter.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3251.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3265.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To the contrary, in the case at hand, the regional governor never made a specific reference to the particular circumstances of the applicant's case while reminiscing the government's policy towards eradication of corruption.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3265.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3273.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The governor neither referred to the applicant personally, nor most importantly, gave a determination as to his culpability.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3273.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3282.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the governor's interview does not amount to an equivocal declaration of guilt transgressing the applicant's presumption of innocence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3282.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3285.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will now turn to the issue of public nature of the applicant's arrest.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3285.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3294.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Beforehand, it is not established whether the prosecutor invited the media to be present at the moment of arrest of the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3294.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3308.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Again referring to Alain de Ribemont case, the court held and constantly reaffirmed thereafter that Article VI, Paragraph 2 cannot prevent the authorities to inform the public about criminal investigations in progress.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3308.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3322.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>While the broadcast of the arrest by the local television may raise the issues of the public perception as clearly demonstrated in the case at hand, it had been done so without impairing the applicant's right to presumption of innocence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3322.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3338.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the light of the above mentioned, neither media coverage of the applicant's arrest in general, nor regional governor's interview in particular, had usurped the role of judiciary and prejudged the guilt of the applicant to use the language of this honorable court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3338.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3346.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As a full submission, I will demonstrate that no violation of Article 34 of the convention can be observed in the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3346.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3366.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your Excellencies, the government is well aware of the many principles enshrined in the court's case law, which clearly stipulates that the steps taken by state in the context of settlement negotiations with an applicant should not take any form of pressure, intimidation, or coercion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3366.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3390.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this context, and at the outset, I would like to invite the honorable court to pay attention to the fact that the applicant's daughter was the first who approached her friend, the representative from the general prosecutor's office, to explain the procedure as to how the friendly settlement negotiations might be secured and the case solved.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3390.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3402.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In response, the representative from the general prosecutor's office, in all her electronic mails, was providing her with all relevant information and possible terms of friendly settlement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3402.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3409.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It should be underlined that the text of the electronic mails of the government official do not indicate any form of pressure or intimidation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3409.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3424.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A contrario, in the case Constantine Markin versus Russia, the court elaborated on the prosecutor's night hour visit at the applicant's home in order to question him with regard to the application pending before the Strasbourg courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3424.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3438.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>While acknowledging the applicant may have felt frightened by prosecutor's visits, the court held that this fact did not meet the hindrance threshold sufficient to find the violation of the right to petition.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3438.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3450.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is principal to highlight that the representative had never asked the applicant's daughter to withdraw the case, but rather tried to arrange a friendly settlement acceptable for both sides.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3450.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3460.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To this end, I would like to quote her electronic mail address to the applicant's daughter on 16 December 2006.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3460.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3469.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We are not asking you to firstly withdraw the application and only afterwards arrange everything at national level.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3469.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3471.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Let us first start working at national level.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3471.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3477.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As soon as everything is finished, only then you will write to Strasbourg.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3477.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3479.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>End of quotation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3479.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3489.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, the manner of communication by the government official is nothing more than the attempt to find simplest way to solve the dispute at the national level.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3489.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3495.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My submission is further proved by the fact that the parties had not succeeded in friendly settlement negotiations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3495.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3502.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, this failure had never resulted in any negative consequences for the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3502.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3514.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As to the applicant's allegations regarding the hindrance from some other prosecutors, I would like to comment that no evidence is included in the case file in support of these allegations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3514.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3522.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is essential at least to know the contents of the negotiation for establishing the least pressure on the applicant if it existed at all.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3527.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3548.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alongside with what Ebo mentioned, I would like to point out that by disclosing the contents of the friendly settlement negotiations, the applicant undermined the confidentiality principle enshrined in the Rule 62, Paragraph 2 of the Rules of Court, which renders the instant application inadmissible.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3548.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3557.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your Excellencies, let me first demonstrate that confidentiality principle is applicable to friendly settlement negotiations, regardless the involvement of the courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3557.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3569.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To support my submission, I would like to make reference to Evgeny Alexeyev versus Russia case, which relates to friendly settlement negotiations without the involvement of these honorable courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3569.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3573.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would like to quote the court's assessment made in Paragraph 172.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3573.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3585.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Article 34 does not prevent the state from taking measures in order to improve the applicant situation or solve the problem which is at the heart of the trustworth proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3585.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3594.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, acting on the principle, the convention system is open to out-court and in-court settlements or agreements, end of quotation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3594.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3601.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the light of the above cited case, I submit that the confidentiality principle is applicable to the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3601.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3611.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Let me briefly approach to the facts of the case to prove that in principle, this principle was violated by disclosing the contents of the friendly settlement negotiations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3611.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3625.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On 19 November 2007, the court, this honorable court, received the submission of the applicant's representatives in reply to the government's submissions on their satisfaction claims.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3625.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3637.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this pleading, submitted as part of the contentious proceedings, the representatives indicated about the electronic mails exchange within the framework of friendly settlement negotiations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3637.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3644.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They asked the courts to take into account their submissions while examining the initial application on the merits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3644.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3656.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>By failure to submit the contents of the friendly settlement in a separate document, I submit that the applicant violated the confidentiality principle applicable to friendly settlement negotiations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3656.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3679.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this line, let me refer to the Rule 62, Paragraph 2 of the Rules of Court, as well as the practice direction on written pleadings, which clearly stipulates that no written or oral communication and no offer or concession made in the framework of the attempt to secure a friendly settlement may be referred to in contentious proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3679.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3693.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In view of the confidentiality of friendly settlement proceedings, all submissions and documents filed within the framework of the attempt to secure a friendly settlement should be submitted separately from the written proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3693.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3706.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, the usual letter sent to the applicants by the court registry following the communication of the application clearly indicates the warning on confidential nature of the friendly settlement negotiations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3706.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3715.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Noteworthy is the fact that the applicants were assisted by the lawyers, who should have been well aware of the mentioned principle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3715.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3722.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This being so, the government considers that the applicants abused the right of individual petition.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3722.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3729.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your Excellencies, let me now use the remaining time to comment on the applicant's property rights.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3729.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3742.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I submit that both the payment of a fine and the transfer of shares to the state were prescribed by law, pursuant to the general interest and were proportionate to the legitimate pursuit.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3742.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3752.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The factory shares were transferred to the state within the framework of the plea bargaining procedure, which is prescribed under the criminal procedure code of Georgia.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3752.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3764.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The cooperation with the investigation under the plea bargaining procedure served the public and legitimate interest as to have crimes effectively investigated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3764.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3783.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The total cost of shares transferred to the state, also effeminate in the just satisfaction comments of the applicants, is less than commensurate to the financial losses incurred by the state, more than $4 million, because of the offense committed by the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3783.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3793.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the shares transferred to the state are in no way disproportionate to the legitimate pursuit, particularly given the right discretion available to states in this regard.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3793.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3796.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Let me move to the payment of fines by the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3796.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3812.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I submit that the criminal court of Georgia, in which it is a fine for the crime the applicants was accused for, I argue that this type of penalty was in the public interest to prevent further criminality and preserve public order.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3812.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3822.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I further submit that there exists a reasonable relationship of proportionality between the means employed and the aims sought to be realized.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3822.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3830.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To this end, the fine as a penalty was entirely necessary and effective means of combating misappropriation and embargo.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3830.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3840.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It conferred on the domestic authorities a weapon in the fight against financial crimes and operates in a way of a deterrent of such activities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3840.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3849.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As for the transfer of money to the Law Enforcement Development Fund, the government notes that this sum was not prescribed by the judgment rendered against the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3849.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3860.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the payment remains outside the scope of the case, more so as the issue has never been raised and the payment has never been challenged at domestic level.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3860.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3865.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, no violation of Article 1 or Particle 1 can be observed in the instant case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3865.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3870.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your Excellency, this brings me to the end of my argumentation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3870.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3871.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I thank you for your kind attention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3871.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3871.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3880.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3883.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much Mr. Meskhoradze.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3883.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3892.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I turn to my colleagues for questions, Judge Tsotsoria.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Nona Tsotsoria</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3898.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3904.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you. Questions to both parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Nona Tsotsoria</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3904.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3910.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>When exactly in time was the plea bargaining initiated?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Nona Tsotsoria</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3910.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3924.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And second, who did initiate the friendly settlement negotiations with the prosecutor's office? Was it applicant's daughter, the applicant themselves, or the representatives</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Nona Tsotsoria</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3924.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3931.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>of the prosecutor's office? Now question to the applicant. What is the applicant's</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Nona Tsotsoria</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3931.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3953.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>explanation for the fact that the plea agreement had not been offered to the first applicant during the first four months of his detention in the same cell as the persons charged with his kidnapping in 2004, and another person serving a sentence for murder? And why did</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Nona Tsotsoria</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3953.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3961.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>he decide to accept it only two months after his transfer to another cell? And now question</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Nona Tsotsoria</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3961.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3969.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>to the government. What was the significance of the fact, if any, that the transfer of</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Nona Tsotsoria</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3969.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3978.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>the factory shares and of the monetary payments had occurred before the procedural agreement was reached? Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3979.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3984.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Judge Gyulumyan.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3988.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3989.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3989.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3990.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3990.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3997.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I have some questions for the government and for the applicants, too.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3997.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4001.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My first question is for the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4001.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4029.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to the Article 6793, second part point E of the Georgian Code of Criminal Procedure, before approving a procedural agreement, the court must ensure that the accused understands that he has constitutional rights, the right to a defense, the right to refuse to enter into agreement stating his admission of guilt, and the right to have the merits of his case examined.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4032.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4043.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Could you explain whether the applicants mentioned rights, particularly the right to have the merits of his case examined?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4043.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4048.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Was followed, whether there was examination of the merits of the case?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4048.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4053.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the second, the right to refuse to enter into agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4053.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4065.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As we can see from this provision of law, it is just in case of admission of guilt, so-called church bargain.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4065.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4080.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What in case of sentence bargain, which was the case in the applicant's case, whether he could refuse entering into the agreement for the sentence bargain?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4080.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4081.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is the one question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4081.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4086.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the second question relates to Article 34.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4086.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4092.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My colleague already raised the question before getting these shares.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4092.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4107.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the mail exchange between the applicant's daughter and the representative of the prosecutor's general office, the prosecution authority was ready to return partially the factory shares to the applicant's family.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4107.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4122.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My question is whether it was ex-gratia returning, or it was some kind of admittance by the prosecution authority of the arbitrariness committing during the investigation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4122.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4140.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the second question, which is from the same email exchange, that the prosecution authority stated that the prosecution could unilaterally annul the player bargain and declare the first applicant wanted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4140.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4151.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What it means, whether it means the reopening of the criminal proceeding or not, and what was the grounds in the law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4151.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4161.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the last question for the applicant, does the applicant understand that the possible finding of a violation under Article 6.1 of the Convention</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4161.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4167.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>might entail the reopening of the criminal proceedings, as was asked by the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4167.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4177.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And in this case, is this something he really wishes and is ready for such a course of action for the opening of the criminal proceedings?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Alvina Gyulumyan</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4177.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4177.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4178.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4179.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4179.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4188.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Well, taking in account the number of questions, I suggest to give you time enough to prepare your answers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4188.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4189.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We will take a break, a 15-minute break.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4268.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4270.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4305.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4306.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sit please.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4311.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4313.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The hearing is resumed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4314.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4316.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I give the floor...</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4320.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4322.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. Koroteev, I suppose?</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4325.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4339.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames, Messieurs les juges, d'abord, je vais répondre aux observations orales du gouvernement et après répondre aux questions des juges.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4339.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4351.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le gouvernement nous rappelle que la procédure de plaidé coupable existe dans les tribunaux internationals.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4351.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4366.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous ne le contestons pas, mais par contre, dans le cas du tribunal pénal international pour le Rwanda, il y avait certainement des plaidés coupables.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4366.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4378.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ces plaidés coupables concernaient les faits que tout le monde connaissait, vraiment, tout le monde dans le sens de tous les milliards de personnes qui habitent sur la Terre.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4378.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4395.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et en même temps, assorti des garanties procédurales telles que l'imposition de la peine par le juge suite à la procédure contentieuse et aussi le droit de faire appel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4395.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4405.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et par exemple, Jean Kambanda, ancien Premier ministre de Rwanda, qui a plaidé coupable, après, ensuite, il a fait appel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4405.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4413.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et tel appel a été considéré par la Chambre d'appel à l'AIG.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4413.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4431.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Deuxièmement, le gouvernement répondeur nous dit aujourd'hui que le contexte de cette affaire, qui est important, consiste à ce que le gouvernement georgien a loté contre la corruption.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4431.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4447.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>D'abord, un tel argument n'a jamais été soulevé par le gouvernement dans ses observations précédentes, notamment dans les observations de 2007 sur la recevabilité et le fond de l'affaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4447.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4459.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et deuxièmement, même si la lutte contre la corruption est une politique tout à fait légitime, nous ne contestons pas la légitimité de cette politique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4459.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4492.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Aucune politique, la lutte contre n'importe quel problème dans la société, même la lutte contre le terrorisme, ne justifie pas la restriction des garanties que l'article 6 accorde et ne justifie pas le positionnement des accusés dans les situations d'inégalité profonde vis-à-vis de l'accusation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4492.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4519.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En ce qui concerne le caractère volontaire et le lettre d'un requérant à la procureure du 9 septembre 2004 citée par le gouvernement, il faut rappeler que ce ne sont pas les mots de requérant, ce sont d'abord les formulations standards que le procureur demande à signer de n'importe quel accusé.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4519.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4529.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et par conséquent, le texte de cette lettre était proposé par le procureur.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4529.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4538.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Aussi, le caractère volontaire de l'accord n'est pas la seule condition de son volidité.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4538.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4570.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En effet, le Code de procédure pénale georgien demandait au juge de vérifier non seulement si l'accord était volontaire, mais notamment que l'accusé comprenne les faits qu'il admette et que, aussi, l'accusé comprend qu'il renonce à ses droits procéduraux, notamment le droit d'être jugé sur le fond.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4570.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4587.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>À aucun moment, le juge n'a posé les huit questions que le Code de procédure pénale l'exige de demander à l'accusé, mais seulement la question sur le caractère volontaire de l'accord.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4587.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4594.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cela nous rappelle l'affaire McCarty versus United States de l'accord suprême américain.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4594.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4608.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et je dirais que l'absence de caractère volontaire ou pression n'est pas le seul vice que l'accord procédural peut être entaché.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4608.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4615.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, il peut être conclu volontairement, mais sans compréhension de rénonciation des droits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4615.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4634.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il peut être conclu volontairement, mais dans une situation où, nous disons, il était le premier requérant, dans la situation où les droits de l'accusation et de la défense n'étaient pas égaux.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4634.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4642.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et c'est aussi un vice qui nous amène à la conclusion qu'il y avait une violation de l'article 6.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4642.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4654.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Quant à l'article 6, paragraphe 2, certes, le gouverneur de Côte d'Ivoire n'a pas mentionné le nom de requérant dans son interview.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4654.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4661.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais il disait que ceux qui détournent les fonds publics sont des criminels.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4661.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4669.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et cela était sur le fond des images de requérants qui viennent d'être arrêtés.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4669.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4678.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, il est aussi clair que possible que le procureur de Côte d'Ivoire a parlé de requérants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4678.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4702.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et quant au caractère volontaire de la venue des journalistes avec le procureur, si le gouvernement nous dit que le procureur ne les a pas invités, alors d'où, de quelle source les journalistes savaient que le procureur va en tel moment arriver au bureau de requérant et l'arrêter?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4702.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4713.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, soit c'était le procureur qui les a invités, soit il y avait une fuite d'informations énormes sur les actions du procureur de bureau de procureur.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4713.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4736.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En ce qui concerne l'article 34 et l'applicabilité de l'article 62 du règlement de la Cour, nous notons un problème dans les observations du gouvernement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4736.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4751.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Certes, et nous l'admettons, la Convention permet non seulement les négociations sur le règlement amiable dans le cadre de procédures devant la Cour, mais aussi des négociations hors cadre de cette procédure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4751.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4756.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais alors, le régime juridique de ces deux procédures est différent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4756.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4769.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et l'article 62 s'applique seulement aux procédures qui sont menées dans le cadre de la considération de l'affaire par la Cour.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4769.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4794.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le gouvernement insiste que les négociations sur plaidés coupables ou au moins la partie judiciaire de ces négociations étaient ouvertes, mais en même temps, il insiste sur le fait que les mêmes négociations, mais au niveau interne, étaient confidentielles.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4794.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4796.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, de deux choses.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4796.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4809.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ici, je réponds aux questions du juge Sotsovia, qui parle de l'initiation des négociations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4809.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4852.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, c'est par email du 29 novembre 2006 que Tina Burgeljiani, qui est de ministère de justice géorgienne, a adressé à la fille du récréant, mademoiselle Nancy Vichlwili, que cette lettre demande la conclusion de règlements à l'amiable et demande à la fille du récréant et à la partie récréante d'être patriote dans cette heure difficile pour la géologie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4852.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4884.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, des telles phrases liées à une demande de ne plus maintenir la requête ne sont que la pression sur le récréant, et c'est après madame Burgeljiani qui demande à la fille du récréant de l'appeler, et c'est comme ça que les négociations ont été entamées.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4884.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4927.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, en ce qui concerne les griffes tirées de l'article premier du protocole premier de la Convention, le gouvernement nous dit que la cession des actions était une coopération avec l'enquête, mais nous l'avons démontré que la définition de ce qui constitue la coopération avec l'enquête n'était pas claire et le procureur pouvait déterminer ce qui ne constitue pas la coopération avec l'enquête à son gré.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4927.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4946.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, une telle base légale n'est pas conforme aux exigences de la sécurité juridique inhérentes à l'article premier du protocole additionnel à la Convention comme à d'autres dispositions de la Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4946.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4956.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous ne contestons pas le paiement de 35 000 laris comme amende et le gouvernement se trompe sur ce point.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4956.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4977.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Par contre, en question, nous constatons le paiement de 50 000 laris à la fondation de l'Etat et la cessation des actions, donc qui, à notre avis, n'étaient pas faites à la base légale prévisible.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4977.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4982.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dernièrement, je voudrais répondre à la question du juge Gullemain.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4982.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4998.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si le requérant comprend qu'il pourrait être la réouverture de son procès et de nouvelles charges contre lui si la Cour constate une violation de l'article 6.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4998.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5001.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Notre position est la suivante.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5001.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5009.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>D'abord, il faut que la Cour constate une violation de l'article 6 et nous l'invitons à la faire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5009.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5017.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais après, la réouverture de la procédure en termes n'est pas automatique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5017.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5044.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il est une pratique constante du comité de ministre qui surveille l'exécution des arrêts, notamment suite à l'arrêt dans l'affaire Moïsev contre la Russie, qu'il n'est pas possible d'ouvrir la procédure, d'ouvrir une nouvelle procédure au niveau interne suite à l'arrêt de la Cour européenne des droits de l'homme sans une demande explicite du requérant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5044.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5066.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, après que la Cour rend son arrêt, nous pourrons l'examiner et après présenter du conseil au requérant pour voir si une telle réouverture aura des conséquences positives ou négatives pour lui.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5066.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5090.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et je conclue sur la question encore du juge Tsotsoria, à savoir quand la Cour était proposée au requérant et pourquoi elle l'a acceptée si tard.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5090.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5096.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour, oralement, était proposée au requérant dès le premier jour de son détention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5096.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5107.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Après l'arrestation, il a été dit que soit tu payes les amendes, soit il est possible de passer plusieurs années en prison.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5107.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5112.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc pourquoi il l'a acceptée si tard?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5112.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5127.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il est vrai qu'il a résisté à la détention dans la même cellule avec ses ravisseurs et après il a cédé seulement après avoir transféré dans une autre cellule.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5127.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5133.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'était le jeu que le procureur menait de bons policiers et de mauvais policiers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5133.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5150.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc après que le requérant était assujetti à des conditions plus restrictives, plus difficiles, quand il était dans des conditions moins restrictives, il avait peur que ça revienne.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5150.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5157.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Surtout, et cela conclut mes observations, le requérant a toujours insisté sur son innocence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5157.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5165.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>D'ailleurs, il n'a jamais admis sa culpabilité dans les procédures enterres.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5165.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5175.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est pourquoi même la Cour n'a pas en cause sa position qu'il était innocent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5175.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5176.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci, Monsieur le Président.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5176.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5181.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous invitons la Cour de constater les violations de la Convention comme nous l'avons demandé.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5181.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5181.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5182.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5185.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci Monsieur Koroteev.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5185.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5190.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>J'appelle Mr. Meskhoradze.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5190.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5191.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You can dispose with 12 minutes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5191.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5193.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5206.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5213.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, Your Excellencies, let me first rebuke some points raised by the applicants</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5213.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5226.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>in their submissions, and may then I reply to the questions posed by this honorable court. Mr. President, in their submissions made on behalf of the applicants, our respectful</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5226.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5242.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>colleagues stated that there was no recording, no record or protocol subsequent to the negotiations drawn up after the meeting on 9 September 2004. Your Excellencies, in front of me I</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5242.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5249.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>have a document. This is a record which states that even itself in the penitential institution</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5249.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5256.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>subsequent to the meeting, the record was drawn up. Most importantly, this record was</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5256.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5263.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>signed by the applicants, by their representatives, and by the prosecutor. Nothing in the case</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5263.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5288.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>file suggests, and despite the invitation, the applicants did not submit it or did not disclose, even in the course of the communication, observations made in the course of the pleadings, no this morning, that such intention to cooperate and to enter into plea bargain agreement was made under the pressure or influence. Therefore, my submission is that the applicants'</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5288.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5295.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>submission statement is inaccurate. Same stands with regard to the issue that the domestic</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5295.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5303.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>court did not in detail and in substance examine the case file under consideration.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5303.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5323.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your Excellencies, protocol which is in the case file also before this Court states that the judge acquired information during the proceedings on national level whether there was a pressure or influence, questions were separately posed to the parties. Also, the</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5323.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5336.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>evidences which were included in the case file was requisitely considered by the judge, and subsequently the approval of the plea agreement took place.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5336.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5349.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Hereby I would like to note that the criminal case file, which was 12 volumes, 9 volumes out of the 12 was financial documents. Only 3 volumes concerned the criminal investigation,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5349.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5356.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>and most importantly, those 3 volumes were against 3 persons. In fact, only 1 volume</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5356.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5362.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>concerned the applicants. Therefore, the argumentation that domestic court quickly</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5362.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5369.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>examined the case file is not substantiated. And hereby I would like to note that</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5369.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5387.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>the main substance and essence of concept of the plea bargaining means that no court case file is determined in detail, no witnesses are examined, no cross-examination take place. This is the main characteristic of these concepts. In comparison</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5387.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5393.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>to a full-scale trial, this fact does not render that the proceedings were fair.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5393.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5406.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And in comparison to ordinary hearings, such proceedings may take short time than the proceedings which I mentioned above. Now I would like to move on the questions</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5406.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5413.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>posed by the honorable judges. I would like to start by the question posed by Judge</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5413.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5419.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sotsoria about the initiating of the plea bargaining procedure. According to the</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5419.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5438.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>criminal case file, plea bargaining procedure was initiated on 9th September, 2004, by the applicants, subsequent to the acquaintance with the criminal case file and charges which were brought against him on 6th September, 2004. Though being</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5438.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5458.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>exclusive prerogative of the prosecutor, initiating a criminal plea bargaining procedure, nothing prevents the applicant to express the intention to cooperate or enter into the procedure. And this fact that the applicant expressed first the</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5458.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5471.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>initiation and intention to cooperate does not have any negative consequences vis-a-vis the guarantees under Article VI of the Convention. As regards to the second</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5471.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5508.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>question, which is about the payments made in the course of the plea procedure, I would like to note that on 6th September, 2004, when final charges were brought against the applicant, the letter expressing his intention to cooperate, transferred the shares to the States, there is nothing in the case file that states that the applicant is not willing to cooperate. Despite the invitation to the applicant</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5508.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5531.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>to propose anything, if there is something at your disposal, that such intention was made under pressure or intention to return the shares to the States under pressure or influence. As regards to the fines, they were paid on 9th September, 2004.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5531.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5552.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the deposit, which does not mean the payment, according to the case file, and there is a document in the criminal case file, this fine will be executed only after the agreement on plea bargaining was adopted by the domestic courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5552.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5566.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With your permission, now I would like to move to the question posed by Judge Blumian about the possibility for the applicant to reject the plea agreement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5566.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5580.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your Excellency, Georgia legislation in force at the material time provided such possibility to reject the agreement before it is approved by the domestic courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5580.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5606.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is not subject to Article 6793eG, which stipulates that before the adoption of the final conclusion on the case by the courts, convict or accused defendant may refuse or may choose oral hearing of the case in such circumstances.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5606.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5615.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this is explicitly noted in the abovementioned article. As regards the question</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5615.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5637.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>in the -- in respect to Article 34 of the Convention, I would like to note that, first of all, to ascertain whether there was a hindrance in exercise the right to petition, communication as a whole should be generally examined.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5637.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5651.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Extracting certain passages or splitting the messages which we are exchanged may lead us to the wrong direction. As regards this specific passage which was mentioned</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5651.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5672.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>by Judge, stipulates that the representative of the prosecutor's office expressed the desire to open the case in a manner that might declare defendant or convict in that particular time wanted. Your Excellencies, the Georgian legislation</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5672.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5685.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>in force did not foresee the possibility to reopen the case or to declare convict wanted. In general, and in theory, it's only possible in the course of the newly</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5685.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5692.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>established law. It's worth the note in this respect that even though the friendly</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5692.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5707.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>settlement negotiations did not finish successfully, there was no negative consequences with regard to this particular case. Nobody was declared wanted or no hindrance</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5707.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5714.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>took place subsequently or beforehand. As regards the possibility to return the fine</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5714.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5731.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>and financial payments to the applicants in case the friendly settlement negotiations were concluded successfully, Your Excellency, this kind of exchange of information was in the course of the friendly settlement negotiations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5731.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5749.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If the agreement was made, such payment, ex gratia, could be made for the execution in the course of the execution of the decision which would be rendered by this honorable court, and such payment could be enforced. If you don't have any further questions,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5749.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5751.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>with your permission, I would like to stop here and thank you for your kind attention.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5762.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5764.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5764.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5768.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Well, we have now come to the end of the hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5768.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5775.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the court's questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5775.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5778.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court will now deliberate on the merits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5778.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5782.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The judgment will be delivered later.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5782.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5786.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The parties will be informed of the date of the delivery.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5786.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5790.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I declare the hearing closed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Josep Casadevall</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5790.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5790.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Have a nice day.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

</transcript_904305_15102013>
