<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<transcript_1648312_22062016>
  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>31.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>31.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>96.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>104.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Bonjour, je déclare ouvert l'audience publique sur le fonds de l'affaire Khlaifia et autres contre l'Italie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>104.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>127.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'affaire a été introduite devant la Cour le 9 mars 2012 par trois ressortissants tunisiens, Messieurs Saber Ben Mohamed Ben Ali Khlaifia, Fakhreddine Ben Brahim Ben Mustapha Tabal et Mohamed Ben Habib Ben Jaber Sfar, en vertu de l'article 34 de la Convention. Elle a été attribuée</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>127.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>133.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>à la deuxième section de la Cour conformément à l'article 52.1 du règlement de la Cour.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>133.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>141.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La requête a été communiquée au gouvernement le 27 novembre 2012. Le 1er septembre 2015,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>141.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>148.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>une chambre de la deuxième section a rendu un arrêt. Le 1er décembre 2015, le gouvernement</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>148.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>161.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>a demandé le renvoi de l'affaire devant la grande chambre conformément à l'article 43 de la Convention. Cette demande a été acceptée par le collège de la grande chambre le 1er février 2016.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>161.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>186.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le 28 avril 2016, les centres sur le droit de la personne et le pluralisme juridique de l'université McGill, l'Air Centre, le conseil européen sur les réfugiés et les résilés, ainsi que quatre associations faisant partie de la Coordination française pour le droit d'asile, ont été autorisés à soumettre des observations écrites en tant que tiers parti en vertu de l'article 44.3</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>186.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>193.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>du règlement. Le gouvernement est représenté par son alliante, Madame Paola Accardo, assistée</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>193.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>201.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>de Madame Maria Laura Aversano, Paola Giusti, Raffaella Renzi et Roberta Cipressa, conseillère.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>201.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>210.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les requérants sont représentés par M. Luca Masera et Stefano Zirulia, avocats, assistés de</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>210.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>218.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Madame Francesca Cancellaro et M. Cesare Pitea, conseil. Je salue les comparants au nom de la Cour.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>218.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>226.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je salue également le groupe de magistrats suivant en visite à la Cour. Indélégation des magistrats</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>226.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>239.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>français de l'École nationale de la majoritature, indélégation des juges turcs, indélégation des juges polonais de la Cour d'appel de Bialystok et indélégation des juges russes. Ayant consulté</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>239.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>244.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>l'alliance du gouvernement et les représentants des requérants, j'ai fiché ainsi l'ordre de parole.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>244.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>252.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous entendrons successivement M. Masera et Zirulia pour les récurrents et puis Madame Aversano</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>252.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>259.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>pour le gouvernement. Je dois expliquer qu'ensuite de l'interprétation dans les deux langues</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>259.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>270.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>officielles de la Cour, l'anglais et le français, l'interprétation en turc, en polonais et en russe a été autorisée au profit des groupes de magistrats qui assistent à cette audience. Cette</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>270.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>281.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>interprétation n'est pas assurée par la Cour et ne fera donc pas partie de l'enregistrement officiel de la procédure. Alors la parole est à M. Masera.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>283.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>286.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci, Monsieur le Président.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>286.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>293.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les Juges, les faits à la base de la présente requête sont très simples.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>293.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>304.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les requérants sont trois ressortissants tunisiennes qui, comme des milliers de leurs compatriotes, ont débarqué avec une embarcation de fortune sur l'île de Lampedusa en septembre 2011.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>304.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>320.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Là, avec des centaines d'autres personnes de nationalités diverses, ils ont été retenus pendant une semaine au centre d'accueil initial et d'hébergement avant d'être transférés sur un navire dans le port de Palerme, à la suite de la destruction du centre d'un incendie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>320.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>335.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Après l'identification grâce à leur empreinte digitale et la confirmation de leur nationalité tunisienne, ils ont été rapatriés en vertu d'une procédure accélérée de réadmission en vigueur à l'époque des faits entre l'Italie et la Tunisie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>335.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>348.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le requérant, et on va revenir sur ce point après, n'affirme pas qu'il avait le droit de sojourner en Italie, ni que leur retour les a exposés au risque des traitements inhumains ou dégradants en Tunisie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>348.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>358.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La question ici n'est pas de savoir si le requérant avait droit à la protection internationale, ni si la Tunisie, à l'époque des faits, était un pays qui respectait les droits de l'homme.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>358.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>376.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La question sur laquelle cette Cour doit statuer aujourd'hui est de savoir si la procédure suivie par les autorités italiennes pour procéder au rapatriement, qui était la procédure normalement suivie à l'époque, est compatible avec les droits reconnus par la Convention et ses protocoles.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>376.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>392.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>De la requête, nous avons affirmé que cette procédure était contraire à plusieurs dispositions de la Convention et de ses protocoles, et l'arrêt rendu par la Chambre a en substance fait droit à tous les greffes exposés.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>392.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>400.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Avant d'analyser bienvement chacune des principales violations alléguées, nous souhaitons préciser un aspect de nature générale.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>400.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>409.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il ne faut pas se cacher que la décision que cette Cour doit prendre dans la présente affaire ne concerne pas seulement les droits récréants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>409.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>419.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le traitement auquel ils ont été soumis est en effet identique à celui que des milliers d'immigrants ont subi au cours de la période à laquelle se réfère l'effet en cause.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>419.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>431.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et ces mêmes modalités sont aujourd'hui souvent encore pratiquées lors du premier accueil des migrants dans les centres où est mise en œuvre l'approche des hotspots.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>431.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>436.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette Cour doit donc établir si ces pratiques sont conformes aux droits conventionnels.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>436.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>467.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Compte tenu de la nature structurée des violations alléguées et de la nécessité d'une intervention normative pour y rémédier, en particulier concernant les violations de l'article 5 et de l'article 4, protocole 4, nous demandons à la Cour de bien vouloir imposer à l'État, au titre de l'article 46, l'adoption de certaines mesures générales de nature législative, réglementaire et opérationnelle permettant d'empêcher que ces violations se poursuivent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>467.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>479.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous commençons maintenant par la question de la violation de l'article 4 du protocole 4, question qui occupe presque exclusivement le mémoire du gouvernement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>479.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>504.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'arrêt rendu par la Chambre a reconnu qu'il est récréant, bien qu'il a été identifié par leur empreinte digitale et qu'une décision formellement individuelle d'expulsion leur a été notifiée, ont fait l'objet d'une procédure d'expulsion collective, à raison des différents indices que nous n'avons pas le temps ici d'analyser singulièrement, voire le paragraphe 156 de l'arrêt.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>504.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>519.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Chambre a notamment observé, je cite, « les gouvernements n'ont produit aucun document susceptible de prouver que des entretiens individuels portant sur la situation spécifique de chaque récréant auraient eu lieu ».</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>519.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>533.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les juges dissidents et les gouvernements adressent des critiques à l'arrêt, que nous avons déjà réfutées dans notre mémoire du 23 avril, au paragraphe 69 et suivant, auquel nous renvoyons.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>533.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>561.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans cette plaidoirie, nous souhaitons plutôt réfléchir à la question que, dans une lettre du 3 mai du greffier adjoint de la Grande Chambre aux amis chikouris admis à intervenir, a été signalée en particulier à leur attention, à savoir la question, je cite, « des droits du migrant économique qui n'a pas fait demande d'asile ou de protection et qui n'a pas légué le risque de traitement contraire aux articles 2 et 3 en cas de repatriement ».</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>561.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>566.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette question est en effet déterminante pour la résolution de la présente affaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>566.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>595.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'arrêt rendu par la Chambre, sans motiver expressement sur ce point, a jugé implicitement que la garantie de l'article 4, protocole 4, s'applique indépendamment du statut de demandeur de protection ou de migrant économique, et a affirmé que cette disposition impose de garantir à tout étranger, avant son repatriement, le droit à un entretien individuel, au cours duquel il peut soumettre son cas à l'appréciation des autorités.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>595.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>604.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les juges dissidents et le gouvernement estiment en revanche que trois conditions suffisent pour que cette disposition soit respectée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>604.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>610.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Identification, nationalité, pays de retour sûr.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>610.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>616.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si ces conditions sont remplies, l'entretien individuel ne serait pas nécessaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>616.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>632.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En substance, ils jugent que le statut de migrant économique, établi sur la base de la provenance d'un pays sûr, exclurait l'applicabilité de la garantie d'une appréciation individuelle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>632.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>634.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tel est donc le point crucial.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>634.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>653.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour que l'interdiction des dispositions collectives soit respectée, est-il nécessaire que le droit à une évaluation individuelle et donc à un entretien individuel soit garanti à tout étranger et donc également au migrant économique où ce droit n'est irréconnu qu'aux demandeurs de protection internationale?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>653.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>662.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La réponse à cette question n'est peut-être trouvée qu'en s'interrogeant sur la nature de la garantie de l'article 4, protocole 4.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>662.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>693.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette disposition, comme l'affirment également toutes les interventions des amici courriers, a une nature exclusivement procédurale, c'est-à-dire qu'elle ne vise pas directement à garantir le respect d'un droit de nature substantiel tel que ceux protégés par les articles 2 et 3 de la Convention, mais entend faire en sorte que l'exécution de l'expulsion intervienne dans le respect de certains procédures qui en garantissent le caractère individuel et non pas collectif.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>693.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>719.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En raison de sa nature procédurale, certains amici courriers parlent à ces propos d'un devoir d'équité procédurale, l'application de cette garantie n'est peut-être qu'indépendante des caractéristiques de la personne à laquelle elle doit s'appliquer, car une garantie procédurale perd sa raison d'être si elle ne s'applique pas à tous sans distinction, mais seulement à certains.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>719.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>732.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce n'est pas le statut des migrants économiques ou de demandeurs de protection qui détermine le droit à la procédure, mais au contraire, c'est la procédure qui permet de déterminer ce statut.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>732.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>745.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A cet égard, l'analogie avec la garantie d'un procès équitable, formulée dans les observations mises par les amis courriers Air Centre et Ecret, nous semble éclairante.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>745.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>758.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les garanties reconnues, par exemple, à l'accusé lors d'un procès pénal, nous pensons au droit de l'accusé à être entendu au cours du procès, s'appliquent à tous, innocents et coupables.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>758.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>772.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il serait inimaginable de penser que dans un cas où le droit à être entendu aurait été violé, on pourrait affirmer que la violation n'est pas pertinent au sein de l'article 6 car l'accusé a été jugé coupable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>772.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>776.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La présente affaire répond à une logique similaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>776.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>804.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans la mesure où l'interdiction des expulsions collectives consiste à une garantie procédurale autonome qui assure une appréciation individuelle de chaque cas, si une telle appréciation n'a pas eu lieu, comme dans les cas d'espèce, on ne peut pas répondre, comme le font les juges dissidents et le gouvernement, que même si la personne avait été entendue dans le cadre d'un entretien individuel, elle aurait tout de même été rapatriée puisqu'elle provenait d'un pays jugé sûr.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>804.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>821.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si la garantie de l'article 4 du protocole 4 était limitée aux personnes ayant droit à la protection internationale, cette garantie procédurale serait vidée de son sang et son champ d'application autonome et n'est serait qu'un double inutile des articles 2 et 3 de la Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>821.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>832.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il est évident que la garantie procédurale de l'interdiction des expulsions collectives pour garder son esprit doit intervenir avant toute violation d'un droit substantiel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>832.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>838.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Autrement, on aboutirait à une interprétation abrogative de l'article 4 du protocole 4.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>838.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>853.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La présente affaire est donc exemplaire puisque le requérant n'invoque pas une violation du droit au non-refoulement, mais il affirme que leur droit procédural à l'appréciation individuelle de leur situation avant le rapatriement a été violé.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>853.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>870.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La meilleure occasion pour vérifier l'autonomie effective d'une violation procédurale est précisément lorsqu'elle est invoquée en elle-même, indépendamment d'éventuelles violations substantielles qui pourraient en suivre.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>870.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>893.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ayant établi que l'interdiction des expulsions collectives s'applique à tout étranger, la seconde question importante à résoudre est de savoir si l'obligation pour l'Etat d'une appréciation individuelle doit être considérée comme remplie, comme le soutiennent les gouvernements et les juges dissidents, dès lors que la personne a été identifiée et que sa nationalité a été établie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>893.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>904.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Aussi, en revanche, comme l'affirme l'arrêt rendu par la Chambre, l'étranger a droit à un entretien individuel qui n'a pas eu lieu dans l'espèce.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>904.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>917.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'effet que le requérant n'ait pas été entendu individuellement doit être considéré comme implicitement admis par le gouvernement lui-même, qui dans son mémoire pour la Grande Chambre n'a pas contesté l'affirmation de l'arrêt sur ce point.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>917.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>936.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans le mémoire, nous avons indiqué les différents précédents relatifs à l'article 4, protocole 4, en premier lieu l'arrêt de la Grande Chambre dans l'affaire Hirsi, ainsi que l'arrêt Charify, dans lesquels la Cour a affirmé explicitement ou implicitement la nécessité d'un tel entretien.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>936.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>945.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En effet, affirmer le contraire viderait de son sang une fois encore la garantie de l'article 4, protocole 4.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>945.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>962.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En effet, les gouvernements estiment que l'expulsion des requérants n'est peut-être qualifiée de collectif, puisqu'ils ont été identifiés en tant que ressortissants tunisiens et qu'une décision d'expulsion formellement individuelle leur a été notifiée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>962.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>991.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toutefois, si l'on juge que des formulaires préimprimés, tous identiques, ne répliquent qu'avec les données individuelles de chaque migrant, satisfont à l'exigence d'un examen individuel, on permettrait à l'Etat d'opérer des rapatriements qui ne sont nullement basés sur une réelle appréciation individuelle, mais uniquement sur l'appartenance à un groupe national, ce qui est un exemple absolument classique d'expulsion collective.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>991.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1007.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>De ce quoi, le déroulement d'un véritable entretien individuel est la seule garantie qui protège de façon effective le droit à la protection internationale, qui demeure un arrière-plan de la règle procédurale en cause, bien qu'il n'en soit pas l'objet.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1007.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1028.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si on permet de procéder à des rapatriements sous la base de la simple constatation que la personne intéressée est ressortissante d'un pays jugé sûr, comment peut-on s'assurer que cette personne n'ait des motifs particuliers de protection à faire valoir s'il n'a pas même la possibilité concrète de les faire examiner?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1028.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1041.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Même si le gouvernement, dans son mémoire, craint les effets déstabilisants que l'accueil de nos requêtes pourrait avoir sur les systèmes de gestion de l'immigration, nous ne demandons en réalité pas beaucoup à cette Cour.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1041.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1057.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous ne demandons que d'affirmer qu'avant de procéder aux rapatriements d'un étranger, l'État doit lui permettre d'être entendu par un fonctionnaire de l'État, même s'il provient d'un pays jugé sûr.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1057.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1066.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il s'agit d'ailleurs du même principe affirmé par la Cour de justice de l'Union européenne, d'Alejandre Mukalubega et Bujilda.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1066.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1083.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Malheureusement, cette garantie simple et théorementaire a été refusée au récréant, comme à des milliers de leurs compatriotes à l'époque des faits litigeuses, et elle est aujourd'hui encore souvent refusée aux étrangers de certaines nationalités.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1083.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1114.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans un rapport de février 2016, la Commission extraordinaire pour la protection et la promotion des droits de l'homme, instituée par le Sénat italien, le rapport est annexé à notre mémoire, a adressé aux autorités plusieurs recommandations urgentes concernant la gestion des centres d'accueil tels que celui toujours actif de l'AMP12, dont la première recommandation est de prévoir le déroulement d'un véritable entretien individuel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1114.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1136.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce rapport témoigne d'un côté qu'en 2016, encore, le droit à un entretien individuel n'est pas garanti, et de l'autre que l'exigence d'un tel entretien n'est nullement jugée déstabilisante par une Commission parlementaire officielle qui a directement visité tous les principaux centres d'accueil.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1136.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1175.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour conclure sur l'article 4, protocole 4, nous demandons que la Grand-Chambre confirme qu'il y a eu une violation de cet article et, compte tenu de la nature structurelle et persistante de celle-ci, qu'elle impose à l'État l'adoption des mesures générales au titre de l'article 46, de manière à établir explicitement au niveau normatif qu'aucune procédure de rapatriement, quelle que soit la qualification qui lui est donnée par la loi nationale, ne peut faire abstraction du déroulement préalable d'un effectif d'entretien individuel, même si l'étranger provient d'un pays jugé sûr.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1175.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1191.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est faisant, il ne s'agit pas de faire peser sur l'État italien une charge excessive dans l'organisation et la gestion des flux migratoires, comme le confirme le fait que cette démarche a été demandée aussi par une Commission du Sénat de la République.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1191.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1209.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En tout cas, il s'agit d'une charge nécessaire afin d'assurer le respect réel de l'exigence de donner un visage et une voix aux personnes éloignées, ce qui représente le fondement profond de l'interdiction des expulsions collectives.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1209.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1216.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En me tournant à la violation maintenant de l'article 5, je vais être très bref.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1216.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1221.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Non parce que nous jugeons qu'elle soit moins significative que celle que je viens d'exposer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1221.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1229.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tout au contraire, nous estimons que la violation de l'article 5 est la plus grave parmi celles subies par les requérants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1229.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1237.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais elle est tellement évidente qu'il ne nous semble pas nécessaire d'apporter des précisions particulières par rapport aux mémoires.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1237.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1242.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous renvoyons en particulier au paragraphe 15 et suivant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1242.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1244.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les faits sont très clairs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1244.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1277.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Avant le rapatriement, les trois requérants ont été retenus pendant plusieurs jours dans des structures fermées desquelles il leur était impossible de s'éloigner, sans que cette privation de liberté n'ait eu aucune base légale, sans qu'il a été informé des motifs et du fondement juridique de leur privation de liberté, sans qu'aucune décision ne leur a été notifiée pour justifier leur situation, sans avoir la possibilité de former un recours devant l'autorité judiciaire à l'égard de cette privation de liberté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1277.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1290.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'arrêt rendu par la Chambre reconnaît, dans ce cas à l'unanimité, que le traitement auquel les requérants ont été soumis viole l'article 5, paragraphe 1, 2 et 4.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1290.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1304.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les gouvernements s'ébornent à réitérer qu'il n'y aurait pas eu une violation de l'article 5 au motif que la loi italienne qualifiait le centre de Lampedusa en tant que lieu d'accueil et non pas de détention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1304.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1326.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais cet argument formaliste est contraire à la jurisprudence bien établie de cette Cour, selon laquelle, pour apprécier la violation de l'article 5, ce qui compte, ce n'est pas si la personne était formellement détenue ou non, mais si elle était ou non privée de sa liberté dans les faits, ce qui était sans doute le cas dans l'espèce.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1326.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1336.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'argument du gouvernement, donc, loin de justifier la privation arbitraire de liberté subie par les requérants, la rend encore plus grave.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1336.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1343.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Malheureusement, la violation de l'article 5 a également un caractère structurel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1343.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1353.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette forme illégale de privation de liberté, à laquelle les requérants ont été soumis en 2011, continue aujourd'hui à être pratiquée dans les hotspots.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1353.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1364.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Comme nous l'avons décrit de manière plus approfondie dans les paragraphes de 21 à 28 de notre mémoire, les problèmes s'y posent aujourd'hui même au niveau des sources normatives.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1364.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1386.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les gouvernements, dans différents actes officiels, ont précisé que les hotspots sont, comme l'a explicitement demandé l'Union européenne, des lieux fermés, dont les étrangers ne peuvent s'éloigner dans l'attente de leur identification et transfert dans des structures de deuxième niveau.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1386.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1407.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, selon la loi italienne, les seuls lieux où il est prévu que l'étranger puisse être privé de liberté dans l'attente de son identification ou de son rapatriement sont les centres d'identification et d'expulsion, pour lesquels, en effet, la loi italienne prévoit une procédure incluant l'intervention de l'autorité judiciaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1407.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1416.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toutefois, les structures hotspots, comme celle de Lampedusa, ne sont pas, selon la loi, des centres d'identification et d'expulsion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1416.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1429.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'illégalité de cette privation de liberté, souvent pratiquée dans les hotspots, a été signalée par plusieurs observateurs et commissions institutionnelles, dont certains rapports sont annexés à notre mémoire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1429.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1446.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Bien que la nécessité d'une intervention du Parlement soit évoquée depuis plusieurs mois pour régir les activités d'identification et d'accueil initial et définir les limites et garanties d'éventuelles formes de privation de liberté, à ces jours, aucun texte n'a été approuvé, ni même discuté par le Parlement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1446.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1476.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Aujourd'hui encore, les migrants qui arrivent en Italie sont privés de la liberté immédiatement après leur débarquement et donc avant que le statut de migrant économique ou demandeur de protection puisse être apprécié, jusqu'à leur identification, qui peut intervenir parfois après plusieurs jours, sans aucune base légale, ce qui constitue une violation de labia corpus sans précédent dans l'histoire de l'Italie républicaine, compte tenu de son caractère systématique et de son ampleur.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1476.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1489.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors que cette violation n'est connue de tous, les gouvernements et les forces politiques au Parlement continuent à ne pas intervenir et la magistrature, malgré les signalements répétés, a jusqu'à présent refusé toute forme d'intervention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1489.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1509.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Notre souhait est que la Cour veuille apporter sa contribution pour que cette situation insoutenable cesse, en imposant à l'Etat italien, au titre de l'article 46, d'adopter les mesures législatives indispensables pour rendre conforme aux garanties de l'article 5, les phases d'accueil initial des étrangers qui débarquent en Italie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1509.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1526.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour conclure, très brèvement, sous l'article 5, l'article 4 et le protocole 4, nous demandons à la Cour d'affirmer que pour tous les étrangers qui sont migrants économiques ou demandeurs de protection, la procédure d'identification et de rapatriement doit respecter certaines conditions très simples.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1526.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1532.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'éventuelle privation des libertés doit avoir une base légale et prévoir le contrôle d'un juge.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1532.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1540.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et l'étranger a droit, avant son rapatriement, à un entretien individuel avec les autorités au cours duquel il pourra faire valoir ses motifs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1540.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1546.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Une loi, un juge, l'écoute de chaque personne avant son éloignement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1546.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1561.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous ne demandons pas beaucoup, mais compte tenu de la difficulté situation des migrants en situation irrégulière aujourd'hui en Italie et en Europe, la réaffirmation claire de la part de la Cour de ces principes de base peut se révéler très importante.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1561.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1561.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci de votre attention.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1574.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1592.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les juges de la Cour, nous allons maintenant traiter la violation de l'article 3 de la Convention, subie par les récréants dans la période comprise entre leur débarquement sur les côtes italiens et leur rapatriement en Tunisie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1592.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1595.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous aborderons deux points.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1595.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1600.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En premier lieu, les conditions de détention au centre d'accueil de l'AMP12.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1600.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1609.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En deuxième lieu, les conditions de détention au sein des navires prison amarrés dans les ports de Palerme.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1609.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1618.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Commençons donc par la question des conditions de détention dans les centres d'accueil de l'AMP12, qu'il a rendu par la Chambre à qualifier des traitements dégradants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1618.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1637.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il s'agit en effet de conditions qui ont été largement décrites et critiquées dans un rapport de l'APC de 2011, ainsi que dans les rapports des enjeux les plus fiables en charge de la protection des droits fondamentaux, tels qu'Amnesty International et Médecins sans frontières.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1637.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1647.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En plus, ces conditions ont été confirmées même par le Sénat italien, dans son rapport de 2012 sur l'état des droits de l'homme dans les lieux de détention en Italie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1647.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1668.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tous ces rapports, qui nous avons annexés à notre mémoire, nous parlent de surpeuplement constant, isolement total de l'extérieur, répas consommés par terre dans la cour du centre, promiscuité et absence d'intimité, conditions d'hygiène globales désastreuses.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1668.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1679.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette situation a été la conséquence directe de la décision du gouvernement de plier les centres de Lampedusa en une fonction qui n'était pas la sienne.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1679.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1685.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il avait été projeté comme un centre d'accueil initial pour 300 personnes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1685.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1697.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, il n'était pas approprié structurellement pour l'usage qui en était fait à l'époque des faits litigeux, à savoir de servir des centres de détention pour plus de 1000 migrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1697.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1712.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cependant, les justes dissidents et les gouvernements ont affirmé que les traitements subis par les requérants n'ont pas duré suffisamment longtemps pour dépasser les seuils de gravité au-delà duquel la violation en question est constituée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1712.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1718.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tout comme la majorité au sein de la Chambre, nous ne considérons pas cet argument fondé.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1718.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1730.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous voudrions en effet souligner que, pour apprécier la légalité du traitement, il convient de prendre en compte l'ensemble des conditions existantes dans les cas d'espèce.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1730.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1744.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il s'agit donc d'une appréciation inconcrète qui doit certes prendre en considération les facteurs temporels, mais ne peut pas se réduire à un calcul abstrait d'heures et de jours.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1744.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1757.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans la présente affaire, il y a à notre avis trois ordres d'arguments pour affirmer que le traitement subi par les requérants, bien que de court duré, a été effectivement dégradant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1757.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1778.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Un premier, par rapport aux conditions matérielles de détention que nous avons démontrées, ce sont des conditions qui, selon la jurisprudence bien établie de cette Cour, ont la capacité de créer chez la victime des sentiments d'humiliation, de honte et d'infériorité, qui sont les ingrédients essentiels du traitement dégradant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1778.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1791.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Deuxièmement, il faut souligner que, pendant leur détention à Lampedusa, les requérants étaient des personnes vulnérables. L'arrêt rendu par la Chambre a relié la vulnérabilité</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1791.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1800.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>des requérants au fait qu'ils provenaient d'un voyage dangereux à travers la Méditerranée, qui avait certainement réduit leur défense physique et psychologique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1800.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1814.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Enfin, en troisième lieu, nous voudrions rappeler que la détention dans les centres d'accueil avait nature illégale. Ce n'est pas la même chose, du point de vue psychologique,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1814.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1822.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>d'être détenue légalement qu'être à la complète disposition des autorités, sans savoir la plus palidée de ce qui se passe et de son destin.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1822.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1843.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La souffrance inhérente à la détention, qui selon la jurisprudence et la Cour ne peut pas constituer une violation de l'article 3, doit nécessairement être attendue comme une souffrance découlant d'une détention légale, à savoir respecteuse de la loi nationale et des garanties définies par l'article 5 de la Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1843.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1853.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En revanche, la détention arbitraire entraîne un surplus de souffrance psychologique que la Convention ne peut certainement pas légitimer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1853.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1874.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous passons maintenant, Mesdames et Messieurs les Justes de la Cour, au deuxième point que nous souhaitons aborder, à savoir les conditions de détention au sein des navires prison à Marais-da-les-Portes-de-Palerme, par rapport auxquelles la Chambre a estimé qu'il n'y avait pas eu violation. La Chambre a en effet jugé fiable l'exposition des faits</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1874.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1887.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>par les gouvernements, selon lesquels les étrangers étaient logés dans des cabines passagers des navires, avaient à disposition des draps propres, des vêtements de réchange, avaient accès à l'eau chaude et recevaient des repas réguliers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1887.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1901.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En revanche, les récréants affirment qu'ils avaient été entassés à l'intérieur du salon-restaurant jour et nuit, avaient consommé leurs repas par terre et n'avaient eu que quelques minutes par jour à l'extérieur.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1901.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1923.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A l'appui des allégations des récréants, il faut rappeler que les navires étaient tout simplement des prolongations provisoires du centre de Lampedusa et que les traitements décrits par les récréants étaient dans la continuité des pratiques qui avaient caractérisé les procédés des autorités italiennes sur l'île de Lampedusa.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1923.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1932.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Certes, contrairement à ce qu'ils ont fait au propos du centre de Lampedusa, les récréants n'ont produit à l'appui de cette allégation aucun rapport d'institution et d'organisation internationale.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1932.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1942.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais ça pour la simple et bonne raison qu'à l'époque des faits, aucune institution ou organisation n'avait eu l'autorisation d'accéder aux navires.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1942.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1952.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour ces motifs, nous estimons que les indices qui nous avons fournis entraînent une inversion de la charge de la preuve dans les chefs du gouvernement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1952.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1965.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si tel n'était pas le cas, on permettrait en effet au gouvernement de se soustraire à ses responsabilités à travers l'escamotage de la création de centres isolés et inaccessibles.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1965.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1974.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, à notre avis, le gouvernement n'a pas fourni d'éléments suffisants pour remplir son obligation probatoire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1974.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1994.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On se demande, par exemple, pourquoi le gouvernement n'a pas produit les contrats d'élocation des navires privés, dans lesquels étaient probablement indiqués les termes d'utilisation des espaces, comme par exemple la possibilité d'éloger les migrants dans les cabines privées des navires.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1994.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2007.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pourquoi également le gouvernement n'a pas produit les documents démontrant l'organisation et la fourniture des services tels que la distribution des draps, des vêtements propres, des repas réguliers?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2007.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2019.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le seul élément de preuve que le gouvernement a fourni est une ordonnance du juge des investigations préliminaires de Palerme, qui affirme que les étrangers n'avaient pas subi d'abus à bord des navires.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2019.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2032.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toutefois, il s'agit d'une décision qui s'appuie principalement sur l'entretien donné à la presse d'un membre du Parlement, qui était monté à bord des navires et avait parlé avec certains migrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2032.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2045.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce n'est pas donc un témoignage qui a été entendu directement par les juges qui ont rédigé l'ordonnance, ni même c'est une preuve contenue dans un rapport officiel rédigé par les parlementaires.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2045.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2053.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tout simplement, il s'agit des informations tirées d'un bref extrait de presse.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2053.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2069.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>De sur quoi il nous semble important de souligner que l'entretien entre les parlementaires et les migrants s'est déroulé en présence des forces de police, une circonstance évidemment de nature à compromettre la fiabilité des déclarations rendues par les migrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2069.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2082.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En effet, si ces dernières avaient voulu faire des réproches, la présence des forces de l'ordre, c'est-à-dire des personnes qui les surveillaient, les aurait dissuadées par crainte de possibles répercussions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2082.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2097.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour toutes ces raisons, nous estimons que le gouvernement n'a pas satisfait à la charge de la preuve qui lui encombait par rapport à la situation à bord des navires prison.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2097.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2126.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous estimons que dans un contexte tel que le contexte actuel en 2016, caractérisé par un afflux massif des étrangers vers l'Europe, il est particulièrement important que la Cour rappelle avec force l'obligation des États de respecter la dignité humaine, même dans les opérations complexes d'identification et de répatriement des migrants en situation irrégulière.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2126.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2152.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Lorsque les États font recours à l'instrument de la détention à ces fins, ils doivent nécessairement le faire dans le respect des normes internationales en matière de privation de liberté personnelle, et en particulier dans le respect de la recommandation du comité des ministres aux États membres sur les règles pénitentiaires européennes de 2006, comme déjà mentionné dans l'arrêt rendu par la Chambre au paragraphe 123.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2152.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2164.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Seule la mise en œuvre de ces directives garantit le respect de la dignité de ceux qui, avant d'être des migrants économiques ou des demandeurs d'asile, sont avant tout des êtres humains.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2168.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2170.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci, monsieur Pitea.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2170.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2172.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors la parole est à madame Aversano.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2174.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2186.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Honourable President, Honourable Judges, with this request of referral to the Ground Chamber, the Government has disputed the sentence delivered on 1 September 2015 by the Chamber.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2186.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2214.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Government firmly believes that the disputed decision has not appropriately assessed the facts and the diligent conduct of the Italian authorities that instead have always acted in perfect compliance with the principles set out in the Convention, namely the Articles 3, 5, 4, Protocol 4 and 13, even situations of such extraordinary emergency as the huge immigrant flows experienced by Italy in 2011 and well known to all Europe.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2214.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2239.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Court is well aware of the peculiar context in which the events in question have occurred, but it has not taken that into due consideration, disregarding the principle that the application of the Convention must be always related to the specificity of the case, a fortiori when the different and apparently conflicting human rights of those involved must quickly find a fair balance in situation of urgent need.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2239.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2262.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Italian Government is fully confident that the Ground Chamber will take into due account the pressing needs with which Italy has had to deal during the humanitarian emergency of 2011, and will also appreciate the fair balance between the handling of the immigration emergency and the full respect of the human rights of the individuals involved achieved by Italy in the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2262.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2280.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This party draws the attention of the Court to all the pleadings previously filed before the Chamber and the Ground Chamber, here to be intended as entirely recalled and before this Honorable Ground Chamber renews all its claims of inadmissibility and unfoundedness in the merit of the applicants' complaints.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2280.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2312.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Government firmly pleads that the examination of the case shall be focused exclusively on the theme of the sedendum of the assessment and evaluation of the specific facts concerning the three applicants, Claifia, Tobal, and Sfar, and of the conduct held by the domestic authorities in their regard during the very few days spent on the national territory as illegal immigrants well aware of the legality of their attempt to enter Italy.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2312.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2317.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A brief reconstruction of facts and contexts in which they have occurred is necessary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2317.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2328.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In 2011, time of the events, Italy experienced an extraordinary flow of immigrants coming from North Africa, determining a situation of a proper national humanitarian emergency.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2328.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2348.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Just to give the Court the precise idea of the amount of such flows, in the world 2011 on the island of Lampedusa and Linusa, the Italian landing place closest to Africa have disembarked a total of more than 51,000 third-country nationals, about half of them Tunisian nationals, including the Eastern applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2348.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2353.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In such an emergency, the Italian authorities have adopted many extraordinary measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2353.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2364.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the island of Lampedusa, firstly, we have reopened the first reception center, and after a short time, also the military base lower than intended for accommodation of families and accompanied minors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2364.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2379.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Many operators from lots of humanitarian organizations, like UN, CHR, OIM, Save the Children, Italian Red Cross, Caritas, Terre des Hommes, worked inside these centers to offer support, assistance, and information to the immigrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2379.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2384.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Medical assistance was announced to guarantee first 24 hours.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2384.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2389.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this context, one of the authorities' main concern has always been the immigrants' health care.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2389.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2409.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It has been always ensured to them the first medical check right after their recovery at sea or their landing to the pier, the transfer by helicopter to medical center on the mainland, and the performance in their favor and actual medical assistance plan set out by Ministry of Health throughout their stay in the center.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2409.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2420.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On 17-18 September, the three applicants who were intercepted and sea on board of a precarious boat were rescued by the Italian authorities and entrusted to the care of the first reception staff.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2420.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2425.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Once ascertained that they were in good health, they were transported to the center.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2425.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2433.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Only on these two days, the same of the applicants' arrival in Lampedusa, far farther landings of Tunisian nationals were recorded.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2433.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2444.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>At that time, the center was fully functioning, equipped with the instruments and the persons, such as 124 operators, able to guarantee the necessary aid and reception to the immigrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2444.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2456.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>During this three-day stay of the applicants, the presence of foreigners inside the center was compatible with the structure's capacity of 1,000 persons assessed by the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2456.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2475.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Unaccompanied minors and other vulnerable persons were hosted at Lorambes, which highlights the special attention given by the Italian authorities not only to the mere rescue activities, but also to the requirements of a specific and differential treatment of vulnerable persons as required by the international obligations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2475.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2489.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Further attention was paid to the specific situation of the three applicants by the authorities, conducting individual talks with each of them in the presence of and supported by an interpreter and a cultural mediator.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2489.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2500.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Precisely to this end, and in order to facilitate the minimum needed stay of Tunisian citizens in the national territory, the identification procedures were divided into two phases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2500.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2508.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the first one, the applicants, like all the other immigrants, were subjected to the preliminary identification by personnel of the police and by an interpreter.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2508.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2520.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Information sheets were filled in with individual circumstances possibly worthy of consideration, demonstrating the specific attention paid to every single position concerned.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2520.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2539.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Such fact not disputed by the applicants is also demonstrated by the presence of a multitude of information sheets concerning the immigrants who landed immediately before and immediately after the applicants' landing and not destroyed like those of the applicants in the fire broke out in the center on 20 September.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2539.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2543.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This documentation is at the disposal of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2543.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2566.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>All these information sheets filled in during these individual interviews reported the signing of the operator and of the interpreter and the presence of the letter shows that the interviews with the immigrants, including the applicants, have been held right after their arrival in a language comprehensible to them for the specific purpose to provide them all the information on their right to request asylum or international protection.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2566.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2592.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Upon the applicants' arrival in September 2011, the conduction of individual interviews with each single immigrant was mandatory for all border police and that to necessarily comply with the guidelines and operating procedures set by the head of police on 29 June 2011 to evaluate on a case-by-case basis the personal situation of the immigrants illegally present in Italy.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2592.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2617.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the contrary of what they stated, Eastern applicants upon arrival at center certainly had the contact with the authorities and interpreters and the opportunity to state all the significant facts strictly related to their individual position as well as to make any other request, including the possible application for asylum or international protection, exactly as required by the Article 4, Protocol 4.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2617.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2633.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But no one of the Eastern applicants has shown his intention to apply for international protection that would have let them accede to different reception conditions, such as the possibility of being expelled and accommodation in the reception center for asylum seekers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2633.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2656.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant had a concrete opportunity to accede to asylum procedures, among the immigrants who landed on Lampedusa on the same days of the applicants, 72 persons, asylum seekers and vulnerable persons, on 22 September were transferred by charter civil flight to Palermo and Mari for the final destination to the reception centers of Trapani, Caltanissette and Foggia.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2656.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2668.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>After their landing, the applicants have been in the center of Lampedusa only two, three days until the big fire started by Tunisians hosted on 20 September.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2668.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2680.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government strongly emphasizes this circumstance as an element even decisive in the assessment of the case and that instead the court has failed to take into the proper account in its decision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2680.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2724.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>About the experience in the center during this very short time, the Eastern applicants, as the other immigrants hosted in the center, could freely move within the perimeters of the entire structure, accede to all services at disposal, medical assistance, clothes, several meals per day, water supply and sanitary facilities, enjoy wide freedom to communicate with the outside and free purchase of items having been provided with a calling phone card of a 15-euro economic voucher to be spent within the facility, also have contacts with representatives of humanitarian organizations, lawyers, as demonstrated by the document attached to the application form under number 20 drafted by the applicants' representatives.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2724.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2750.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As to the condition of facilities presented at the time of the applicant's stay, 18-20 September, the government contests a way of proceeding of the court by reference to the information acquired from the general reports drafted by the PAC and the extraordinary committee of the Senate based on visits respectively May 2011-2009, which took place definitely a long time before the events of this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2750.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2763.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court should evaluate more thoroughly the certification of suitability of the structure issued by the health authority of Palermo on the occasion of the investigation carried out on 21 September, the day after the fire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2763.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2773.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What stated therein about the suitability of the center the day after the fire, a fortiori demonstrate the suitability of the structure in the days before, during the applicant's stay.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2773.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2805.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this context, primarily intended for aid and assistance, the presence of the security forces had not police purposes, but was and still is aimed exclusively at preventing self-inflicted injuries, disorders and incidents in the building, very often committed by immigrants for the sole purpose of having an opportunity to avoid checks and flee to unknown place, as well as preventing incidents with the local inhabitants, considered to be extremely likely, as demonstrated by the evolution of the facts of the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2805.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2815.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This police presence was clearly aimed at ensuring the safety and well-being of the immigrants themselves and of the locals, as well as maintaining public order.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2815.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2836.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Indeed, on 20 September, just two days after the applicant's arrival and during their stay in the center, a large group of Tunisians met the world during the individual talk of their condition of unlawful immigrants and of the imminent repatriation for the purpose to postpone their return started a fire of large dimensions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2836.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2849.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The immigrants left the property and reached the center of the island, creating high tensions with residents, which resulted in disorders of 21 September, resolved thanks to the intervention of security forces.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2849.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2881.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Following the fire and the partial unfit condition of the center, the authorities, given the unavailability of other facilities on national territory, all already occupied due to great immigration flows of the time, found that a quick transfer aboard of a three cruises ship anchored in the port of Palermo was the only possible alternative to provide immediate shelter to the guests of the center and at the same time to be able to continue the operations just started in the center of the first assistance and identification of such huge amount of persons.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2881.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2889.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Many of the activities in progress, like the continuing identification procedure, were performed in favor of the immigrants on land.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2889.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2909.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As demonstrated by facts, the applicants, like all immigrants who have reached Italy by sea, have been rescued from the danger of death, welcomed, assisted, cared for, identified, heard about their individual needs and organized in such a way to minimize their stay on the territory and to return home in the shortest possible time.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2909.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2925.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Clearly, the fulfillment of these procedures for each individual immigrant, multiplied by the large numbers of immigrants arriving at the same time in the same place, normally took a minimum of time, very often aggravated by the poorly collaborative attitude of the immigrants themselves.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2925.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2945.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Additionally, in the Eastern case, all these procedures have been further readily aggravated by the fire of 20 September and the disorders of 21st and by the consequent need to organize differently the guests and transfer them as well for their safety in view of their repertory to Tunisia, according to the agreement between the two countries.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2945.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2967.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, the overall performance of the first reception activities started in the center and then continued on the ships required a minimum of technical execution time, further extended cause of the incidents deliberately determined by the immigrants to who therefore should be given the responsibility of the extension of their stay beyond the minimum needed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2967.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2987.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In view of their possible repatriation, the applicants underwent the second phase of identification procedures as set out by the Italy-Tunisia agreement, having an individual talk, an additional one from the arrival with the Tunisian Council for the final ascertainment of their nationality and possible existence of a personal obstacles to repatriation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2987.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2994.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The authenticity, effectiveness, and genuine individual nature of these talks with Tunisian authorities has been demonstrated by fact for circumstances.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2994.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3009.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The documents attached by this party allow that not all immigrants in the list of those previously identified by Italian authorities in the first phase of procedure that never been repatriated because of questions of nationality, age or other impediments.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3009.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3015.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As a matter of fact, at the end of the individual talk, some immigrants ascertained as not Tunisian national were not repatriated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3015.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3025.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And another immigrant registered as born 1992 was ascertained as born 1994 and not repatriated to his special position minor accompanied.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3025.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3044.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the basis of the assessment of individual position, the questura of agrigento, having ascertained that the applicants were third country national just rescued at sea while unlawfully approaching the Italian frontier and not asylum seeker, released individual removal orders for each of them, duly reasoned and translated into Arabic.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3044.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3050.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Such measures of the further full man were provided by the Italian law and well matched the condition of the instant applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3050.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3059.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Aliens who having unlawfully entered the national territory have been temporarily admitted to stay for the mere purpose of aid and assistance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3059.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3075.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the lawfulness of such measures against the applicants, the government recalls the assessment of national authorities that in this respect, all having evaluating all the circumstances affecting concrete situation deemed in any case timely with the applicants repatriation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3075.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3091.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The extremely short time spent by the instant applicants in the territory first at Santa and then on ship is not evilly remotely comparable to a state of a limitation of personal freedom and even less to a state of a detention as intended by the convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3091.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3101.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants seen their landing at new information about their position and many opportunities to see their personal condition individually assessed by the authorities and to make personal requests.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3101.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3108.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Then each removal order issued against each of them was based on conclusion that they were irregular immigrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3108.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3126.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In light of that, the government claims it's right to see a knowledge of the diligence with which had proceeded to repatriation of the applicants in compliance with the principles of the convention as a strongly disputes the alleged existence in the case of a collective expulsion under article four, protocol four.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3126.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3143.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As to the legal conclusions of the court of the government, first of all contest that very short stay of the applicants at the center, only two days and on board the ships just few days more could be qualified as detention or deprivation of the personal freedom under article five of the convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3143.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3164.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government reminds according to the court's case law in order to determine whether someone has been deprived of his liberty within the meaning of article five, the starting point must be the is concrete situation and account must be taken over a range of criteria such as type, duration, effects, and manner of implementation of such measure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3164.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3180.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Garner challenges the correct interpretation of the facts in the light of conventional principles as well the inappropriate use of some sources of general information on the center and the failure instead to take into due consideration fundamental aspects of the story.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3180.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3195.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The current deconstruction of the events set by the government in all its defenses has demonstrated that in the present case are missing all the factual requirements of a condition of a detention as set forth in the case law, properly recalled but inappropriately applied in decision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3195.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3230.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Is a certainly missing the kind and the manner of implementation of the state concern since it's not inferable from facts any element of a cohesion but only a humanitarian activity in favor of the applicants who were rescued at sea, immediately refreshed, dressed and taken on the first mainland port nearest rescue operation place where they received the shelter, health monitoring, personal assistance and economic independence where they were identified one by one, heard individually their mother tongue by police operator and made aware of the opportunity to seek asylum or other international protection.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3230.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3232.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And possibly to be transferred to other state.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3232.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3248.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Is missing the duration of the stay since the applicant stay has been extremely limited over all nine and 12 days and it would have been far shorter if the Tunisian themselves hosted in the center had not started the fire and created an additional emergency in the emergency.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3248.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3261.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Is missing the effect since the applicants could freely move within the war perimeter of the structure and the opportunity to maintain social relationships with relatives at home, with the lawyers and all the operators present in the center.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3261.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3273.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The surveillance on the center and only preventive purpose aimed at prevention, criminal and harmful acts among them or against the local population such as the fire, the center and riot occurred during the applicant stay.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3273.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3288.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's a strong government belief that it's admittedly not possible to speak in the Eastern case of deprivation of liberty under Article 5 on the strength of any one of these factors taken individually, neither cumulatively or in combination between them.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3288.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3292.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>No other fail or standard Article 5 could be found in the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3292.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3294.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It cannot be found at the fact of a legal basis.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3294.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3304.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Such situation of first aid, reception, assistance and identification related to the rescue of immigrants as see are regulated by framework of rules.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3304.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3326.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Article 5 immigration, 10 immigration acts, implementation immigration acts, Article 14 immigration act providing that transfer to CA is ordered only when the full amount requires a supplementary investigation on identity or nationality of the immigrant or when additional time for the acquisition travel documents or regimental transportation is required.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3326.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3340.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But it was certainly not the instant case where in consideration of the facilitated repatriation procedures toward Tunisia, such activities of identification and issuing of travel documents were definitely much faster.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3340.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3348.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government contested the court's assessment that international agreement between Italy and Tunisia about repatriation was not at time a capable legal basis.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3350.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3357.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this respect, it must be noted that the object of this agreement was the strengthening of border controls by Tunisian authorities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3357.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3374.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As provided by documents, all the Tunisians directed to Italy already the day after the signing were aware of the current procedures thanks to the information diligently spread within both countries through the institutional websites of Italian Ministry of Internal and Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Tunisian government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3374.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3380.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Simultaneously, other internet sites, Italian, French, Arabic, widely spread information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3380.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3394.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, it's not absolutely likely that the instant applicants having easy access to modern information instruments could not have news about the repatriation procedures which they could have been subjected having chosen to reach Italy by sea.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3394.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3405.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In any case, according to the agreement, the repatriation should occur in presence of the Tunisian consular authority and in compliance with the human rights and human dignity as it occurred in the instant case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3405.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3425.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It cannot be found that the fact of information, the applicants already on their own aware of the legality of directions during their stay were further informed by the operators of the legality of their condition of irregular immigrants attempting to enter Italy and that they could have possibly subjected to an imminent repatriation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3425.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3441.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It cannot be found that the fact of judicial scrutiny, the applicants as illegal immigrants rescued at sea were just as the instructor intended for aid that since the reception that would have been there, the minimum time needed if the immigrants had not started the fire in the center.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3441.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3450.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For this reason, in a first aid situation completely different from a state of deprivation of liberty is not required a judicial scrutiny by the law regulating it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3450.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3458.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government having demonstrated the absence of detention conditions also challenges the assessment of an alleged violation of Article 3.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3458.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3464.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court is well aware of extraordinary humanitarian emergency experienced by Italy in 2011.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3464.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3473.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And although it gives note of that in the contested decision, however, it shows to have not adequately assess the impact that is unexpected.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3473.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3485.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A massive arrival of large numbers of immigrants has had on the reception system, which, however, and despite the difficulties, was still widely respectful of human rights of those involved.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3485.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3493.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court has evaluated the center conditions only in the light of the reports drafted and the base of visits carried out much time before the facts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3493.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3505.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nor they have properly assessed that the presence in the center that according to the data mentioned in the sentence could accommodate up 1,000 persons did not result at all in a condition of very serious overcrowding.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3505.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3521.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to the court's case law, an infringement of Article 3 can arise only if it's reached a minimum level of severity determined by the concurrent existence of multiple elements, such as duration, physical, and psychological effects, sex, health, condition, and context.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3521.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3536.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The dissenting judges have disseminated the well-centered decor of the question, corrected assessing the facts in the case in the light of conventional principle, and properly excluded a violation of Article 3 of lack of minimum threshold of gravity.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3536.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3548.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Defectual substances of the case nor individual need cumulatively assessed lead to outline a stain in human degrading condition and a conventional violation neither with reference to the center nor to the ship.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3548.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3554.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants, adult males in good health, first of all, were in the center only two days and few others on the ship.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3554.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3574.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Have not lived overcrowded condition could freely move within interpropriety and access to food and sleeping rooms that were not cells but rooms adapted to the rest, having at their disposal the space of the wall structure, which even makes the court's reference to the regioning similar cases on detention conditions manifestly inappropriate.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3574.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3581.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, they have never been physical nor psychological abuse, nor any opposite evidence by the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3581.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3598.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>At this point, it's evident that Italian state, which even in the emergency of the emergency with the utmost efforts has ensured to such a large number of immigrants are lawfully present on the territory, a comfortable short stay in view of their quick return home has never intended to inflict the applicants inhuman and degraded treatments.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3598.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3606.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But as it's well-known habits, it has always guaranteed to them aid, assistance, information, and definitely human rights.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3606.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3611.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Honorable judges arrived at the last, but absolutely not the least issue on the table.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3611.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3629.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This party represents to the court of the many perplexities and concerns about the decision and consideration carried out therein, also and not only with regard to an alleged existence of a collective expulsion in violation of Article 4, Protocol 4, that instead the government strongly and firmly contests.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3629.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3648.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government recalls the court's case law whereby collective expulsion within the meaning of the Article 4 is to be understood as any measure compelling aliens as a group to leave a country, except where such a measure is taken on the basis of reason and objective examination of particular case of each individual alien in the group.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3648.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3668.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, the fact that a number of aliens are subjected to similar decision, maybe even with deportation orders phrased in similar terms, does not in itself lead to the conclusion that there is a collective expulsion if each person concerned has been given the opportunity to put arguments against his expulsion to the competent authorities on individual basis.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3668.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3674.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government strongly challenges the existence in the Eastern case of the collective expulsion requirements.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3674.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3682.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants have not been repatriated as a group, and before the repatriation, they received an individual assessment of their personal situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3682.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3702.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's why the government also challenges strongly the comparison between the experience of the applicants and the case concoct whereby the expulsion was based on the mere belonging of a specific ethnic group, and the repatriation was ordered within a police operation carried out after a long time from the entrance into the territory of the individual's concern.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3702.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3725.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The dissenting judges have correctly centered the question, finding that the Eastern case does not fall within any kind of collective expulsions, nor in the case of expulsion due to the mere belonging to a national ethnic or racial or religious group, neither in the case of a repatriation of a group as a whole without the pre-assessment of individual position of each individual alien as Irsha Sharifi.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3725.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3738.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Huge attention was paid to the individual position of each applicant undergone to individual talks with police operator interpreter to personal identification according to repatriation producer under the agreement between Italy and Tunisia.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3738.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3756.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The circumstances, the teacher repatriation order did not report other facts unless the personal data depends on the fact that in preliminary stages of the procedure, the applicants have never represented even having the opportunity to do it, anything special worthy of a specific attention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3756.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3766.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the other hand, the applicants until now have never alleged to be in a real condition of asylum seeker or to be entitled to receive an international protection, a crucial aspect of the question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3766.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3776.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As the court teaches, the fact that a number of aliens are subject to similar decision does not in itself lead to a conclusion that there is a collective expulsion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3776.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3793.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, Tunisia at the time could be surely considered a country respectful of human rights, as it even says by court in Al-Anji, and as inferable for the concrete experience of the applicants who after their return to Tunisia have not suffered any persecution or other attack to their human rights.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3793.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3805.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Lastly, under the angle of the articles 13 of the convention, individual removal order issued each against the applicant were drafted in Arabic contain the warning of the possible remedy of the application before the judicial departure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3805.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3818.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants complained of the absence of a remedy against such measure is manifestly groundless, even more in consideration of the fact that the applicants, even after the measure, had continued to have contact with Italian lawyers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3818.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3830.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But instead of opposing the domestic remedies available against the order and possibly bringing a subsequent action, have directly lodged the case before the court in violation of the principle of subsidiarity.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3830.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3848.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Conclusively, the government reminds the court that Italy, with intense and constant commitment, carries out the immigrants rescue operations, always faced with humanity, experience, and professionalism on the part of all the operators involved in such first aid activities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3848.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3860.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court is certainly aware that these operations still in progress only now with the operator union participation allowed and still allowed to save a countless amount of lives.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3860.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3871.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mare Nostrum, strongly desired and supported by the Italian government, is one of the examples of the Italy's commitment in preventing the recurrence of a further disaster in the sea.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3871.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3895.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For these reasons, the Italian government firmly disputes the judgment in issue, find that it does not do justice to all the efforts, human and economic, to the commitment and humanity used to address the immigration flows phenomenon, still of extraordinary dimension, and nevertheless always endless in the full respect of human rights of all individuals involved.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3895.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3918.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the Italian government, requesting the annulment of the decision of the chamber on all counts, not intends only defend itself from the groundlessness of the applicant's complaints, but above all, it intends to defend its right and duty, legal and moral, to continue to save human lives.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3918.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3918.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you for attention.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3921.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3924.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci pour votre intervention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3925.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3931.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Maintenant, j'invite les juges de la grande chambre qui les souhaite à poser leurs questions au parti.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3931.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3932.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Juge Møse.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3937.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3946.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My first two questions are about Article 3, and they concern the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3946.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3960.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government have stressed the challenges it faced in connection with the huge immigrant flow in 2011.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3960.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3965.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And now, in your oral intervention, you even gave up some figures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3965.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3974.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You said that there were 51,000 in 2011, of which 26,000 came from Tunis.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3974.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3977.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These were the figures you referred to just now.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3977.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3999.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now, in the pleadings in this case, in writing, it has been argued that the crisis or the flow, the influx in September 2011 was not really so unexpected because there had been similar flows previously.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3999.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4003.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Do you consider that a valued argument or not?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4003.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4010.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That was my first question to the government concerning Article 3.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4010.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4021.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My next question to the government concerning Article 3 relates to the conditions at the center in September.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4021.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4036.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And there you have stressed that the chamber has put too much emphasis on reports from 2009 and May 2011.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4036.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4044.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That was when these two visits by the Senate and the parliamentary assembly delegation took place.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4044.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4047.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You say it's unfair.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4047.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4060.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>May I ask you, what is your view, if you should be a little bit more precise, what were then the exact conditions in September 2009?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4060.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4067.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I know that you have indicated this, but a little bit more detail.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4067.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4082.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Three elements as regards overcrowding, as regards the way meals were being digested, and as regards sanitary facilities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4082.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4086.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These were the three elements I focused on.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4086.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4091.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These were the questions to the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4091.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4095.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now I have questions to both parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4095.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4107.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But I will start here to take as a point of departure the government's emphasis on the fact that there were two phases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4107.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4111.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, there was a compulsory individual talk.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4111.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4115.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this question relates, of course, to Protocol 4, Article 4.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4115.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4117.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's what we are in now.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4117.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4123.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And you stressed that there were two phases in the interviewing process, so to speak.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4123.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4137.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The first was the compulsory individual talk with the identification of the immigrant by personnel of the police operators and an interpreter.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4137.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4147.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>When it comes to that first phase, what was the focus of the conversations with the individuals during that first round?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4147.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4158.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I take it that it was to establish the nationality and certainly also the identification and taking of fingerprint of the individual concerned.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4158.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4162.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But what about any other elements?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4162.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4172.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You have indicated in your oral intervention that there was also information about the opportunity offered by the system to the immigrant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4172.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4178.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What does this element, information, imply?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4178.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4179.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That was the first phase.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4179.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4186.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now I move on to a similar question relating to the second phase.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4186.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4195.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There, there were these individual conversations with the Tunisian consular authority aimed at ascertaining, again, nationality.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4195.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4201.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then the government says, and the absence of possible obstacles to repatriation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4201.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4206.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The absence of possible obstacles to repatriation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4206.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4211.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That element, does that follow from the bilateral agreement?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4211.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4218.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or is that element rather a way you are using to describe the practice?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4218.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4220.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Was this then done in practice?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4220.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4229.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And what, who would then raise possible concerns in that connection?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4229.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4246.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You have said that the applicants, and this is the third question, and again, the applicants are also invited to comment if they so wish, just like with my previous two, had information about their positions since their landing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4246.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4251.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Which kind of information are we here referring to?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4251.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4256.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Some kind of general information in which language?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4256.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4265.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's also stated that there were many opportunities to see the, to raise their situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4265.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4270.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Many opportunity to make requests.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4270.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4272.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What is this referring to?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4272.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4280.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I suppose it's the individuals initiative that we are talking about here.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4280.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4304.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And finally, and this question is linked in a way to this individualization issue under protocol four, article four, and it's stated in the oral intervention today that 72 asylum seekers and vulnerable people were actually transferred from the center to other destinations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4304.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4312.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that was done in the same period as the applicant in the present case arrived and were there.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4312.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4320.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now this separation, was that in any way linked to phase one or phase two?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4320.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4324.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or how can that separation be explained?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4324.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4325.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Erik Møse</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4325.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4325.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These are my questions.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4326.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4328.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, judge Sicilianos.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4332.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4334.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4334.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4342.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is a question to the government, but of course the applicant may wish to comment also.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4342.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4350.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In your written observations, you made the distinction between a refusal of entry and an expulsion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4350.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4356.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And you say that the applicants were issued with individual refusal of entry orders.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4356.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4373.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So as far as I understand, you seem to challenge the very applicability of Article 4, of Protocol 4, saying that we don't have to do with an expulsion, we have to do with something else, a refoulement or a refusal of entry.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4373.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4382.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Today in your oral presentation, as far as I understood you, but I would like to have a confirmation of this, you seem somehow to change your stance a bit.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4382.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4415.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You seem to take into account the court's case law, you referred to the CONCACA judgments and to the standards established in the CONCACA judgment, namely the necessity of having a reasonable objective examination of the particular case of each individual alien of the group, and you have said that the applicants were heard about their individual needs, there was an assessment of their individual position, they were heard in their mother tongue, and there was a concrete opportunity to submit an application of asylum.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4415.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4423.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Well, the applicant affirmed that their right to be heard was not respected.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4423.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4435.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So apparently, if I understand well, we move from a legal difference concerning the applicability of Article 4 to a factual difference of positions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4435.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4444.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I would like to have the opportunity to go more in depth into this issue from possibly both sides.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4444.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4444.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4445.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4447.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, judge Wojtyczek.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4450.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4452.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci, Monsieur le Président.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4452.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4464.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>J'ai plusieurs questions aux deux parties concernant les accords internationaux qui ont été invoqués dans cette affaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4464.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4481.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le gouvernement italien invoque, dans les observations écrites devant la grande chambre, deux accords internationaux entre l'Italie et la Tunisie, l'accord de 1998 et le procès verbal de 2005.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4481.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4490.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Par ailleurs, l'arrêt de chambre examine un troisième accord international entre ces deux Etats, l'accord de 2011.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4490.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4498.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous avons donc trois accords internationaux entre l'Italie et la Tunisie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4498.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4507.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La première question concerne la place de ces trois accords internationaux dans l'ordre juridique italien.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4507.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4511.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sont-ils parties intégrantes de l'ordre juridique italien?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4511.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4515.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sont-ils directement applicables?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4515.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4522.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La deuxième question concerne leur statut dans l'ordre international.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4522.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4531.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Selon l'article 102 de la Charte de l'ONU, tout accord international doit être enregistré auprès du secrétariat de l'ONU.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4531.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4538.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et ce même principe est confirmé par l'article 80 de la Convention de Vienne sur les droits de traité.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4538.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4558.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je voulais savoir si les deux parties à ces accords internationaux, l'Italie et la Tunisie, ont rempli leurs obligations découlant de l'article 102 de la Charte de l'ONU et de l'article 80 de la Convention de Vienne sur les droits de traité.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4558.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4571.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Enfin, la troisième question, toujours concernant ces trois accords internationaux, peuvent-ils être invoqués devant la Cour européenne des droits de l'homme?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4573.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4579.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je voudrais avoir l'opinion de deux parties sur cette question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Krzysztof Wojtyczek</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4579.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4580.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci, Monsieur le Président.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4585.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4586.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Juge Nußberger.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4588.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4589.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4589.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4594.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would have one question in addition to the question of Judge Wojtyczek.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4594.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4597.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Why was the agreement not published?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4597.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4598.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Why was it secret?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4598.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4604.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then I would have a question to the lawyers on the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4604.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4618.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You talk about a procedural right to be heard and you say that it was not enough to identify them to ask them about nationality and the country to which to be sent back.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4618.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4624.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But at the same time you say they don't want to claim asylum, they don't want international protection.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4624.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4641.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So what arguments would the applicants have liked to advance to tell the Italian authorities in order to change the situation, in order to stay in the country if they don't want to claim asylum?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4641.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4644.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What arguments would they have liked to be heard with?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Angelika Nußberger</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4644.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4644.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4646.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4647.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4647.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4650.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Any other question?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4650.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4651.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Judge Mits.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Mārtiņš Mits</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4655.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4662.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Yeah, I would like to ask a question to the government concerning Article 3.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Mārtiņš Mits</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4662.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4674.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You started your presentation by referring to the pressing needs that the authorities had to deal during the emergency of influx of migrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Mārtiņš Mits</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4674.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4688.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And you also, in your written observations, referred to the separate opinion of Judges Shayo and Vucinic, who also show the need to respond to the emergency situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Mārtiņš Mits</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4688.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4706.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I wonder, is there a room under Article 3 to take into account emergency circumstances when we are deciding on the minimum level of severity under Article 3 in the context of the conditions of detention?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Mārtiņš Mits</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4706.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4706.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4710.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4712.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il a noté une autre question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4712.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4727.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La cour va maintenant se retirer pendant 25 minutes, après quoi les partis pourront présenter de brèves observations en réponse aux prévoirs de la partie adverse et aussi répondre aux questions des juges.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4727.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4727.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5532.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5533.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5584.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5588.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors la parole est à monsieur Masera et Zirulia.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5592.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5602.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors, je commence à répliquer à la plaidoirie du gouvernement et en même temps à répondre à quelqu'un des questions des juges.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5602.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5627.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors, pour ce qui concerne l'article 4, le protocole 4, nous sommes, pouvons dire, contents que le gouvernement, dans cette occasion, a affirmé que l'entretien individuel est nécessaire pour que soit respecté le droit de refus collectif, des expulsions collectives.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5627.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5648.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et nous devons noter que le gouvernement a totalement changé sa défense des mémoires écrites à la plaidoirie orale, parce que dans les mémoires écrites, dans aucune occasion, le gouvernement avait parlé de ce, pas seulement un, on dit deux, on dit deux entretiens individuels.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5648.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5655.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tandis que dans tout le procès devant la Chambre, on n'a jamais parlé de cette question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5655.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5659.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et le problème, alors, c'est, il y a eu ou non cet entretien individuel?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5659.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5671.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors, compte tenu que l'entretien individuel était nécessaire aussi pour le gouvernement, et ça, pour nous, c'est très important de l'affirmer, le problème est, il y a la preuve de cet entretien individuel?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5671.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5676.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je crois que le gouvernement n'a donné aucune preuve, aussi, dans ce moment-là.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5676.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5692.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il a dit, pour la première fois, je répète, même parce que dans les mémoires écrites, il n'avait jamais dit qu'il y aurait des fiches qui témoignent de l'entretien individuel, mais ces fiches, si j'ai bien compris, ont été détruites dans l'encendie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5692.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5703.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais ça signifie ne donner aucune preuve qu'il y a eu cet entretien individuel, tout simplement parce que cet entretien individuel n'a pas eu lieu, il n'y a aucune preuve.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5703.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5709.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et ça ne peut pas être suffisant de dire qu'elles ont été détruites par l'encendie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5709.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5723.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je veux souligner une chose qui n'est pas centrale dans mon argumentation, mais dans la pléboirie du gouvernement, ça semble, on donne l'impression que les requérants sont responsables de l'encendie, et ça, ça doit être très clair.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5723.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5730.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les requérants n'ont aucune responsabilité pour l'encendie qui a été provoquée, ça c'est à clarifier.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5730.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5751.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et alors, donc, il n'y a pas eu un colloque individuel, et nous devons noter avec la demande du juge Siciliano qu'en effet, c'est surprenant, ce changement de défense, parce que dans les mémoires écrites, on disait qu'on ne pouvait pas parler d'expulsion parce que c'était des refoulements.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5751.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5761.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Maintenant, on n'utilise plus cet argument, et on utilise l'argument qu'il y avait l'entretien individuel, mais on ne donne aucune preuve que cet entretien réellement a eu lieu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5761.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5774.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et la demande sur la question du colloque individuel, je réponds à la première question qui a été posée, en quoi consistait cette phase, cet entretien individuel, le premier et le deuxième.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5774.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5791.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et je ne peux que confirmer ce qu'on disait dans la question, le seul rapport qui ont eu les requérants avec l'autorité, c'est avec l'autorité de police pour prendre les empruntes et pour assurer la nationalité.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5791.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5800.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il n'y a eu aucune autre occasion de parler de son cas, de mettre son cas à l'attention de l'autorité.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5800.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5809.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pas dans la première phase du colloque, pas dans la première phase qui s'était avec la police, ça a duré peu de minutes seulement pour les empruntes, pas dans la deuxième phase.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5809.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5820.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans la deuxième phase, c'est important de souligner, la phase du rapport avec le représentant de la Tunisie s'est déroulée à la report.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5820.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5831.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La première fois, l'entretien, le rapport avec le représentant de la Tunisie, c'était à la report quand l'avion était déjà prêt à partir.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5831.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5838.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et la seule chose qui a vérifié le représentant tunisien, c'était justement la nationalité tunisienne.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5838.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5848.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il n'y avait aucun autre élément qui a pu être prouvé dans cette occasion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5855.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5862.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Oui, je passe très brèvement à la question de l'article 5.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5862.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5874.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors, ça c'est une nouveauté par rapport au mémoire écrit, on dit qu'il n'y a pas de privation de liberté relevant au centre de l'article 5.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5874.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5879.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Vraiment, je n'arrive pas à comprendre quels sont les éléments pour nier qu'il y avait une privation de liberté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5879.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5891.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il y a tous les rapports que nous avons cités et qui sont annexés à la mémoire qui disent le Conseil d'Europe, l'Assemblée parlementaire du Conseil d'Europe, le Sénat de la République, qu'il y a, qui est tout à fait un lieu de détention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5891.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5899.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les personnes ne pouvaient pas sortir de ce lieu, n'avaient pas contact direct avec l'extérieur, et surtout ne pouvaient pas sortir.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5899.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5900.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'était un lieu fermé.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5900.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5903.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et c'était un lieu fermé, et ça, il n'y a aucun doute.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5903.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5907.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et la durée, la durée, ce n'est pas une durée, une durée trascurable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5907.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5914.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'était une durée de 4, pour Calaifia, 4 jours, et à Lampedusa, 7 jours sur les navires.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5914.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5917.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour les autres, 3 jours dans le centre et 5 jours dans les navires.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5917.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5923.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, ce sont des périodes de temps significatifs dans lesquelles le sujet était privé de la liberté personnelle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5923.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5932.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On ne voit pas cette partie récréante, comment on peut nier qu'il y a une violation de liberté relévant au sein de l'article 5.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5932.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5952.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et puis, on dit aussi qu'il y a, et c'est contradictoire de la part du gouvernement, d'un côté, on dit qu'il n'y a pas de privation de liberté, et de l'autre côté, on cherche une base légale de cette privation de liberté dans l'article 10 du test unique sur l'immigration.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5952.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5955.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette norme n'a rien à faire avec la privation de liberté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5955.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5958.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est une norme qui régit le refoulement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5958.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5961.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais il n'y a aucune référence à la privation de liberté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5961.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5971.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et si nous devons chercher une base légale, et ça me surprend que le gouvernement n'ait pas pensé à ça, il y a l'article 13 de la Constitution italienne.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5971.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5980.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Constitution italienne dit que personne ne peut être privé de la liberté sans un contrat juridicional après 48 heures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5980.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5984.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Après les 48 heures, il doit y avoir un contrat de l'autorité judiciaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5984.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5986.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et ça, c'est la base légale.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5986.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5992.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si on parle de base légale en droit interne, c'est avant tout l'article 13 de la Constitution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5992.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5997.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'article 10 n'a rien à faire avec la question de la privation de liberté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5997.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6019.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, la dernière chose à dire, on semble que le gouvernement veut justifier la privation de liberté, s'il y a une privation de liberté selon le gouvernement, parce qu'il arriverait aussi à nier ça, parce qu'on dit que les récréants étaient fermés pour protéger leur sûreté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6019.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6020.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On est arrivé à dire ça.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6020.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6025.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors, on peut tolérer qu'on prive quelqu'un de la liberté pour lui protéger.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6025.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6034.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est ça qu'on veut dire, que la finalité de la privation de liberté aurait l'effet de soutraire cette privation de liberté aux règles de l'article 5.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6034.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6049.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je crois que c'est une conclusion qui n'a aucun fondement dans la jurisprudence bien établie de cette Cour, qui fait référence à la réalité des faits, pas à la question de la qualification juridique sans d'accord et sans détention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6049.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6053.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La jurisprudence dit qu'on doit voir si cette personne était privée de la liberté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6053.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6058.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et ça, c'est le cas.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6058.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6068.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Très rapidement, sur la question des accords internationaux, la troisième question qui a été posée par les juges.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6068.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6087.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et nous pouvons tout simplement constater qu'il n'y a eu aucun respect de ces normes invoquées par les juges qui ont fait la question sur le droit des traités, tout simplement pour la raison que ces accords étaient des accords secrets.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6087.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6091.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'étaient des accords secrets qui n'avaient aucune occasion de rendre public.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6091.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6109.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et c'est aussi à souligner que devant la Chambre, le gouvernement n'a pas allégué cet accord, seulement devant la grande Chambre, seulement dans la face devant la grande Chambre, a allégué, annexé cet accord.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6109.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6123.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et en tout cas, toujours pour répondre à la troisième question, même s'il y avait un respect de ces accords, ça n'a rien à voir avec le respect de la Convention des droits de l'homme.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6123.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6130.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tous les accords internationaux pour la jurisprudence bien établie de cette Cour doivent respecter les droits de l'homme.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6130.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6136.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, on ne peut pas invoquer un accord pour justifier le non-respect des droits de l'homme.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6136.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6148.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, les accords internationaux ne sont pas valables du point de vue du droit international parce que n'a pas été suivie la procédure, normalement prévue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6148.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6157.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et en tout cas, ce n'est pas décisif, la question, si ont été respectés ces accords, parce que ces accords ne peuvent pas justifier une violation de la Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6157.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6163.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Deuxième question avant de passer la parole à mon confrère.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6163.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6174.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La quatrième question qui nous a été posée, nous disons que c'était nécessaire un entretien individuel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6174.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6181.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Un juge nous a dit, mais quels sont les arguments que les requérants voulaient faire valoir dans ce entretien individuel?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6181.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6194.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors, dans la première partie, je crois qu'on a cherché à souligner pourquoi, selon nous, ce n'est pas celle-ci la question décisive dans le cas d'espèce.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6194.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6199.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nos requérants n'ont pas allégé une violation du droit au non-refoulement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6199.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6207.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si les requérants avaient droit à rester en Italie, nous aurions invoqué aussi la question du non-refoulement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6207.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6218.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous ne l'avons pas fait parce que, dans notre colloque avec les requérants, ne sont pas émergées des données telles à constituer une violation de l'article 3.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6218.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6222.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais nous ne pouvons que répéter ce que j'ai dit avant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6222.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6226.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La question, ce n'est pas si les sujets avaient droit à la protection.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6226.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6237.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La question est si les sujets ont eu la possibilité d'avoir un entretien individuel, de voir sa propre position individuelle évaluée par l'autorité judiciaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6237.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6238.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est ça la question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6238.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6242.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La question est que cet article 4, par l'article 4, c'est une garantie procédurale.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6242.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6251.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On ne peut pas donner une garantie procédurale seulement à ceux qui invoquent aussi une violation substantielle du non-refoulement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6251.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6253.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est ça pour nous.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6253.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6259.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je ne peux pas répondre à ceux qui l'avaient dit parce que ce n'était pas la question que nous avons traitée aussi avec les requérants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6259.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6268.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Avec les requérants, dans notre colloque à Tunis, nous avons parlé de la procédure qu'ils ont suivie et de la violation des droits des hommes qu'ils ont subie au long de cette procédure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6268.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6270.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je passe la parole à mon confrère.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6277.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6292.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vais faire des brefs considérations quant à la situation d'urgence humanitaire invoquée par le gouvernement à l'appui de l'égalité de ses actes et qui a constitué aussi l'objet de certaines questions posées par les juges.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6293.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6311.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En premier lieu, l'argument de la situation d'urgence n'est pas fondé du point de vue juridique compte tenu de l'impossibilité de déroger à l'article 3 de la Convention et du fait que la faculté de déroger à l'article 5, comme prévu par l'article 15 de la Convention, n'a pas été invoquée par l'Italie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6312.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6334.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En deuxième lieu, nous souhaitons insister sur le fait que la situation qui s'est créée en 2011 en Italie, à Lampedusa, n'était absolument pas exceptionnelle parce que des conditions analogues à celles décrites par les récréants ont été mises en lumière par des observateurs indépendants avant et après le 2011.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6335.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6351.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il découle donc qu'il est possible d'exclure tout lien de causalité entre l'augmentation des flux de migrants à la suite des promptes arabes et les conditions de détention dégradantes qui lui ont été réservées dans le centre de Lampedusa.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6352.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6369.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le surpeuplement du centre de Lampedusa était en réalité le fruit d'un choix politique précis du gouvernement italien de confiner l'accueil initial des migrants sur l'île de Lampedusa plutôt que de les transférer rapidement vers d'autres centres sur le territoire italien.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6369.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6375.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et ça pour donner à l'opinion publique l'idée d'une invasion sur le territoire italien à exploiter pour des fins politiques.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6376.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6384.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A cet égard, ce n'est pas nous qui l'avons dit, c'est Amnesty International qui a parlé d'une humanitarian crisis of Italian authorities' home making.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6384.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6389.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est vrai que les rapports des organisations regardent la condition avant...</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6390.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6394.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>que les rapports de ces organisations regardent la condition avant ou après 2011.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6395.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6402.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et c'est vrai qu'il y a peu de rapports, il y a moins de références à la situation du septembre 2011.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6403.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6410.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais le problème, c'est que le gouvernement avait limité ou interdit l'accès au centre de Lampedusa et au navire dans l'été 2011.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6411.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6413.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et c'est pour ça qu'on n'a pas de preuves de ce qui s'est passé à l'intérieur.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6414.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6426.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais en fait, pour ceux qui regardent les surpeuplements à l'intérieur du centre, en fait, c'est le gouvernement même, dans sa mémoire, qui nous a donné... qui a fourni des données.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6427.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6434.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Parce qu'il nous a dit que le centre avait 804 places, et ça pour des situations exceptionnelles, parce que la normalité du centre, c'est 381.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6435.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6440.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc pour des situations exceptionnelles, la capacité peut être augmentée jusqu'à 880 places.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6440.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6454.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais le gouvernement nous dit que les personnes à l'intérieur du centre étaient 1357 les 16 septembre, 1325 les 17 septembre, 1399 les 18, 1265 les 19, et enfin 1017 les 20.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6455.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6457.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est-à-dire le jour où les requérants étaient dans le centre.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6458.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6463.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc le surpeuplement, au moins, est complètement démontré par les données fournies par le gouvernement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6464.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6486.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette considération, et là, je conclue, montre une situation qui est très difficile à déterminer, et c'est une situation, et là, je conclue, montre une situation dans laquelle la violation des garanties de l'article 5 et 3 de la Convention revêtait des caractères systématiques, devenant une partie structurelle du système italien de gestion du débarquement à Lampedusa.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6486.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6486.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous remercie pour votre attention.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6490.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6491.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci, la parole est a Madame Aversano.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6503.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6525.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Honorable President, Honorable Judges, the Italian government concerning the issues raised before recalls all its previous submissions and insists in arguments during highlighting that the facts alleged already offered the court the ground for the annulment of the decision delivered.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6525.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6542.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Anyway, it reserves to file afterwards further written submissions in order to deepen the issues raised and the word duels on some aspects of this case, even to be considered in the reply submission of the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6542.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6556.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Underlined that in this case, the third intervener said not provided for new factual circumstances limited themselves to very general consideration because as the court is well aware, there was a third intervener.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6556.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6563.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But the issues raised and the arguments submitted by the government are to be intended in reply to the third intervener as well.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6563.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6589.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Concerning the specific issue about the Article 4 or Protocol 4 raised during the question to the government, the government states that it has always stated that the instant case falls within an hypothesis of a different refoulement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6589.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6604.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this applied and issued just for requirements of assistance and rescue in favor of the applicants and all the immigrants in the same situations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6604.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6622.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The legal basis of the different refoulement is under the Article 10, 2 of the Immigrants Act.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6622.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6644.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to this procedure of a different refoulement, it's always provided an individual interview as always stated by the government because this interview is necessary to assess all the personal position and condition of the immigrants involved.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6644.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6661.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Such interviews that are carried out not only by the police or the operators acting inside the centers are also according to the agreement Italy and Tunisia held and carried out by the Tunisian Council.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6661.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6675.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this interview is extremely relevant and necessary to assess the personal condition in view of the further and the subsequent repatriation of the immigrants involved.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6675.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6720.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Such interview is not only aimed at the identification of immigrant concern, as we have repeatedly stated, but as we have also demonstrated by factual circumstances, this interview is also and relevantly aimed to assess other conditions, the personal condition, individual condition of the immigrant who has invited, who has asked to represent all his personal situation, not only the identity, but also the characteristics and personal concerns like the minor age or other situation of health conditions or vulnerability.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6720.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6729.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As we have demonstrated during the same time, the applicants were in the center of Lampedusa.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6729.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6735.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Many people assessed as vulnerable people were not repatriated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6735.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6747.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And before the interview with the Tunisian Council, we already distinct to other facilities and to other protocol of reception.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6747.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6772.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We have already demonstrated that according to the list filed by the Italian government, at that time, 72 people, immigrants, representing vulnerable condition or other request for asylum seeker or international protection was accommodated in a different reception condition.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6772.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6804.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In any case, the importance of this individual talk with the Tunisian Council is, in addition to the assessment of all these situations concerning the immigrant, are aimed at the release of the travel document, which is a condition, a necessary condition in each case of repatriation, as this deferred referement is.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6804.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6824.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And so, because if the Tunisian Council does not assess, is not able to assess the nationality, or even if it, for example, assess other obstacles to repatriation, for example, it happened that maybe can emerge some elements about criminal responsibilities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6824.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6832.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And so the involvement of other Italian authorities in the case, maybe it could be also an obstacle to repatriation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6832.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6845.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So it's not an identification issue underlying these individual talks, but the assessment of all the conditions involves that specific immigrant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6845.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6891.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For this reason, we firmly contest the comparison made by the court in decision between the instant case of deferred referement just carried out for rescue and assistance purpose, as we always, and until now, we have repeated, and the case law concerning collective expulsion, because we have found, as repeatedly state, that in this case, the immigrants involved have received the assessment of all the conditions and the situation strictly related to the personal situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6891.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6914.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Just the last issue, we have also stated in the formal pleadings that this deferred referement has a legal basis in Italy in Article 10, and it was assessed as lawfully carried out also by the domestic judicial authority, and we insist in this argument.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6914.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6929.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>About the other reply to the other questions posed by the honorable judges, I give the floor to my colleague for the expulsion about the detailed data that the court has required.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6929.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6931.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you for your attention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6931.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6944.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I reiterate that we are not able to deepen nowadays our arguments about the question, which serves to file written submission.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6944.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6945.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6945.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6945.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I give the floor to my colleague.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6960.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6991.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Your Honorable Judges, as about your questions to the figures of immigration flows which affected Italy and Sicily in particular in 2011, I would like to stress that in Sicily, in the period from March to September 2011, about 57,000 migrants landed just in Sicily.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6991.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6996.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And of these, about 28,000 were Tunisian nationals.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6996.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7007.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And of these 28,000 Tunisian nationals, almost the majority of them were young males in good health conditions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7007.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7012.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And in the majority of cases, they were economic migrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7012.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7041.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And so specifically in the very days when the applicants stayed at the center at Lampedusa, there were about exactly 900, let me check, 917 people were staying at the facility in Lampedusa at Contrada Imbriacola.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7041.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7049.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And again, they were all males, young males, and in good health conditions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7049.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7079.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Since other migrants were found in serious conditions or who had anyway shown that they wanted to apply for asylum and that they needed anyway any other kind of protection, they were moved to the other center located in Lampedusa, or they were transferred by air to the mainland or to other centers in Sicily.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7079.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7113.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And about the conditions in the Contrada Imbriacola Center, we would like to stress that we have a certificate from the provincial health unit of Agrigento stating that the conditions at the facility were proper and that meals were served, warm meals that were cooked on site.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7113.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7117.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then they were sealed to be given to the migrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7117.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7125.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And so of course, there were about 900 people, so it was not an ideal condition.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7125.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7134.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But you have to consider that it was just the moment that it was not easy to deal with.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7134.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7139.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And again, there were young people, males, in good health conditions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7139.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7150.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And there's no evidence at all that any of them suffered any physical suffering.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7150.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7165.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There's no certificate, no medical proof that any of these people actually suffered so serious conditions that caused physical or psychological serious permanent damage.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7168.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7209.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Again, about the individual talks, we would like to stress that besides identification, which consisted in assessing the nationality and the personal data of the person concerned, these interviews took place at the presence of not only of staff from the police, but also the presence of an interpreter or a cultural mediator was ensured so that the migrant could speak in his or her mother tongue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7209.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7243.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And if in any way they would show that they had any reasons to stay in the country, I mean, if they had health issues or family issues, I mean, that they would risk any sort of damage they could suffer if not accepted in the national territory, of course, that was considered by the authorities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7243.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7250.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's why other people were moved to the other center in Lampedusa.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7250.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7264.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the fact that, as we have told previously, there's a huge quantity of this information sheet, which is available in the case file, and it's at disposal of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7264.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7270.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And these huge thousands of sheets that were filled out for migrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7270.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7281.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And it's quite serious that the counterpart says that these interviews never took place and that these sheets don't exist.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7281.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7290.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As we have said many times, there was this big fire, a serious one, that destroyed part of the center.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7290.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7307.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the fact that the paper is not available doesn't mean at all, it's no evidence at all of the serious allegations of the counterpart that these interviews never took part.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7307.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7320.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the other hand, the evidence is given by the fact that other migrants who expressed their wish to apply for any kind of protection were taken somewhere else.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7320.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7350.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And one thing the court should take into account is that the applicants, as the majority of the Tunisian migrants who arrived at the same time, they never intended to apply for any kind of protections because they were well aware that that would have brought them to enter the Dublin system.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7350.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7365.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's to say, to stay in Italy for the whole procedure, something they didn't want to do at all because they were wishing to go in other countries, especially in North Europe.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7365.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7388.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And so about the agreement between Italy and Tunisia, it was just the agreement was just setting operational procedures to make repatriation and identification faster.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7388.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7404.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But the agreement, the content of agreement, was widely available even on the internet and the website, both of the Italian Home Office and of the Tunisian Ministry of the Interior.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7404.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7408.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>At that time, the agreement had been signed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7408.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7420.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's to say, in April 2011, so many months before the applicants' arrival, it was available on their websites.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7420.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7457.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And even if you just make a simple search on Google, if you just Google, you will find out that news about this agreement, about the content, the fact that it was dealt to manage with its extraordinary migration flows from Tunisia, they were widely available, not only on the websites of the states' institutions, but even on some newspapers from France, Arabic countries, and even on some blogs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7457.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7482.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So we think that it's pretty unlikely that young people intending to reach Italy in an illegal position didn't know anything about the fact that they would have been repatriated soon and according to these new procedures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7488.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7509.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So in conclusion, Your Honor, any further evidence you may need about the identification and about the interviews that took place will be provided.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7509.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7517.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I mean, of course, it's not related to the three immigrants because, as we said, they got destroyed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7517.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7526.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But that doesn't mean that they never took place, which, again, is a quite serious allegation from the counterpart.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7526.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7539.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And so we are at your disposal to provide any of these information sheets that were filled out for the other migrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7539.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7539.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7541.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7542.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ok, thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7542.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7547.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous arrivons au terme de l'audience.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7547.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7555.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je remercie les comparants qui ont assisté à la Cour par leur intervention et leur réponse à ces questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7555.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7561.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour va maintenant délivrer le fond de l'affaire et le reste sera rendu ultérieurement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7561.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7564.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les partis seront informés de la date du prononcé.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Luis López Guerra</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>7564.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>7564.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'audience élève.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

</transcript_1648312_22062016>
