<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<transcript_4714306_24092014>
  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>24.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>25.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>65.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>67.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please be seated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>77.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>89.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I declare open the public hearing on the admissibility and merits in the case of Roman Zakharov against Russia. The application was lodged with the Court on 20 October 2006 under Article</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>89.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>96.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>34 of the Convention by a Russian national, Mr Roman Andreyevich Zakharov. It was allocated</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>97.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>109.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>to the first section of the Court pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the Rules of Court and communicated to the Government on 19 October 2009. On 11 March 2014, the Chamber decided</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>111.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>123.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>to relinquish jurisdiction in favour of the Grand Chamber, none of the parties having objected to a relinquishment. The Government are represented by their agent, Mr Georgy Matyushkin,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>123.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>141.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Head of the Office of the Representative of the Russian Federation at the European Court of Human Rights, assisted by Ms Oxana Sirotkina, Ms Irina Korieva, Ms Oksana Iurchenko, Mr Oleg Afanasyev, and Mr Aleksei Lakov, Advisors. The applicant is represented by Mr Philip</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>141.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>152.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Leach, Ms Kate Levine, Mr Kirill Koroteyev, Ms Anastasia Razhikova, Counsel assisted by Ms Elena Levchishina, Advisor. The applicant is also present. I welcome the representatives of the parties and the applicant in the name</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>165.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>172.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>of the Court. I also welcome a delegation of judges and prosecutors from the European</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>172.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>217.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Judicial Training Network, a delegation of Russian judges, a delegation of Turkish judges from the Compensations Commission, a delegation of judges and prosecutors from the Kosovo Judicial Institute, a delegation of judges of the Constitutional Court of Belarus, of prosecutors from the Belarus Prosecutor General's Office, and of Belarus professors, a delegation from the Supreme Court of Mexico, and from the Office of the Permanent Observer of Mexico to the Council of Europe, and a delegation of the Georgian Bar Association and the High School of Justice of Georgia. Having consulted the agent of the government and the representatives</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>217.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>224.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>of the applicant, I have determined the order of addresses as follows. Mr Matyushkin for</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>224.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>238.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>the government will speak first, and then Mr Leach, Ms Levine, Ms Razhikova, and Mr Koroteyev for the applicant. I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>238.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>249.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>languages of the Court, English and French, interpreting into Russian has been authorised for the benefit of the Russian and Belarus delegations. Furthermore, interpreting into</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>249.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>261.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Albanian has been authorised for the benefit of the Kosovo delegation, and interpreting into Georgian has been authorised for the benefit of the Georgian delegation. That interpreting</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>261.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>273.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>is not arranged by the Court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings. I call Mr Matyushkin.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>284.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>290.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, Honorable Judges of the Grand Chamber,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>290.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>315.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First of all, the authorities of the Russian Federation would like to draw the European Court's attention to the fact that the present application is manifestly inadmissible under Article 35 of the Convention, as the applicant has not exhausted the domestic remedies before applying to the International Court. The applicant lodged a claim with the National Courts only</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>315.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>330.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>against private mobile phone companies, requesting that they turn off their special equipment which allegedly allowed third parties to intercept his telephone conversations. The Ministry</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>330.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>343.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>of Information Technologies and Communications of the Russian Federation was involved in the proceedings on the request of the applicant only as a third party, but not as a respondent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>343.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>356.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant did not challenge any Russian legal acts that regulate the interception of telephone conversations at the National Courts. The applicant did not lodge any complaints</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>356.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>368.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>with the National Courts about any decisions or actions or omissions taken by the state authorities and their officials. All of the applicant's statements that he allegedly did</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>368.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>382.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>not have an opportunity to challenge the legislation of the Russian Federation regarding phone interception are not supported by the materials of the case file. If the applicant believed</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>382.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>407.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>that the mere existence of the Russian legislation on phone interception itself violated his rights and freedoms, he could have lodged an application with the National Court on the recognition of a certain regulatory legal act to be contrary to the law in full or in part. Such opportunity is prescribed by the legislation of the Russian Federation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>407.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>421.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Constitutional Court of the Russian Federation also made it possible to challenge state authority regulations which have not been duly registered and published. In this connection, the example</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>421.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>436.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>provided by the applicant's representatives allegedly evidencing the absence of opportunity to challenge the Russian legislation is significantly distorted. Thus, in particular, the supervisory</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>436.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>459.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>appeal submitted by company Pascal was dismissed because the dispute was not under the jurisdiction of the commercial court, as it was not of an economic nature and should therefore have been examined by the general jurisdiction courts, and not because the dispute regulation was of technical character.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>459.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>480.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant's statement that he did not have an opportunity to challenge the order of the State Communication and Information Technologies Committee of the Russian Federation of 1999, since the indicated order was not published, does not correspond to reality.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>480.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>504.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The indicated departmental act, together with enclosures, was published in Svyazinform magazine in 1999, is available in the Consultant News National Database, can be freely accessed through the Internet, and was attached by the applicant to the materials of this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>504.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>527.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant also was not deprived of the opportunity to lodge a complaint with the Constitutional Court of the Russian Federation, having pointed out which provisions of the Russian legislation do not comply with the Constitution of the Russian Federation, as, for example, in Klaus and others versus Germany.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>527.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>541.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, if the applicant had good reason to believe his phones may be tapped, he could have lodged a complaint challenging any decisions or actions or omissions of the State authorities and their officials.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>541.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>550.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The memorandum of the oral hearings contained a number of examples from judicial practice confirming the effectiveness of this domestic remedy.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>550.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>564.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Summarizing the present arguments, it should be noted that the applicant did not rise any claim or complaint against the relevant public bodies of the respondent state at the national courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>564.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>578.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Correspondingly, the application is manifestly inadmissible, and the domestic remedies have not been exhausted and should be dismissed pursuant to Article 35 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>578.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>587.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Also the authorities of the Russian Federation believe that the applicant is not a victim of a violation of rights guaranteed by the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>587.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>596.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Based on the Court's case law, the applicant must personally be affected by a government's interference in other work.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>596.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>606.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As follows from Article 34 of the Convention, he must be a direct victim of a violation of rights guaranteed by the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>606.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>631.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Previously in the Commission's case law, it was specified that an individual may, under certain conditions, claim to be the victim of a violation accussion by the mere existence of secret measures or of legislation permitting secret measures without having to challenge that such measures were in fact applied to him.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>631.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>635.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>See Klaus and others versus Jomlin.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>635.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>641.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Previously the Court departed from that position, deeming it too broad.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>641.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>657.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the Court's opinion, as established by its case law, it would be mistaken to recognize all persons who feared that the security services may have conducted surveillance of them as victims of rights violations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>657.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>672.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is necessary for the applicants to demonstrate that there was a reasonable likelihood that the surveillance measures had been applied to them.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>672.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>682.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>See Kennedy versus United Kingdom and Almas and 112 others versus Netherlands.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>682.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>705.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to the Court's new standpoint, for an applicant to be considered a victim of a violation of his rights, he must be charged by the monitoring measure and the proofs are necessary that his personal data have been processed or used in a manner constituting an interference with respect for private life.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>705.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>708.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>See Köpcke versus Germany.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>708.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>736.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For example, the application of Weber and Saravia versus Germany was declared inadmissible because the Court noted that the applicants, even though they were members of a group of persons who were likely to be affected by measures of interception and strategic monitoring, they were unable to demonstrate that the impugnant measures had actually been applied to them.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>736.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>749.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus proceeding from the standards of the Court and the circumstance of the present case, it is evident that the applicant is not a victim of violation of rights guaranteed by the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>749.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>754.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants' telephone conversations were not intercepted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>754.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>766.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The measures provided for by the federal law on operational search activities and criminal procedure legislation were never applied to the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>766.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>791.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, there was clearly no reasonable likelihood that the applicant's telephone conversation would be intercepted because he was not a person suspected or accused of commission of any crimes of medium gravity, grave or especially grave crimes, and no preliminary investigation was being carried out in his respect.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>791.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>820.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant publicly referred in the national proceedings to the fact that he filed a claim not related to any specific violations committed by the defendant's private mobile phone companies, but because the defendants have special equipment which, according to the applicant's unfounded allegations, probably allowed them to intercept telephone conversations without court judgment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>820.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>831.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this connection, the applicant has not proven the presence of any risk that he would be subjected to secret surveillance measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>831.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>848.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore the applicant's application is manifestly founded by virtue of Article 35, Paragraph 3A of the Convention and should be dismissed under Article 35, Paragraph 4 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>848.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>867.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Before answering the Court's question with respect to conditions under which an individual may claim to be a victim of a violation of rights guaranteed by the Convention, accussion by the mere existence of legislation permitting secret surveillance measures, we would like, in short, to distinguish two such conditions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>867.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>881.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Firstly, the applicant must have exhausted the domestic remedies before applying to the Court and address his claims to the state authorities and not private respondents' mobile phone companies.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>881.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>899.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Secondly, the applicant must prove the existence of a reasonable likelihood that his phone conversations were truly being intercepted, that his personal data could have been processed and used in a manner constituting an interference with respect for private life.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>899.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>905.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant has not observed none of these conditions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>905.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>921.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With respect to the Court's question on interception authorization procedures, which must be established to provide adequate and effective guarantees against abuse, I consider it necessary to draw the Court's attention to the following.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>921.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>935.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to the general law and as follows from the Court's case law, the legislation of the Member States of the Council of Europe must infringe minimum guarantees in order to avoid abuse of power.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>935.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>945.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sometimes the Court also allows for these guarantees to be foreseen not in the country's legislation but in its national case law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>945.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>951.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For example, in the case of Köpke v. Germany, the Court declared inadmissible the application</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>951.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>965.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>of an employee who was subjected to cover video surveillance of her workplace by her employer without any appropriate basis and conditions laid down in the German statute law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>965.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>971.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Such provisions appeared in German legislation only seven years after the fact.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>971.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1000.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In rendering its decision as to inadmissibility, the Court noted that even though Germany did not have the appropriate legislation when the secret surveillance was being carried out, the Federal Labor Court in its case law developed important limits on the admissibility of such video surveillance, which safeguarded employees' privacy rights against arbitrary interference.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1000.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1029.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Additionally, it should be especially emphasized that the Russian legislation provides sufficient and effective guarantees, supervision, and protection against abuse in the sphere of telephone communications interception, which is evidenced inter alia by the judicial judgments of the national courts, copies of which were attached to the memorandum of Russian authorities to these hearings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1029.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1069.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Operational search measures in the form of control and record of telephone conversations are allowed in the Russian Federation only pursuant to judicial authorization and only with the presence of information pertaining to the signs that a crime is being organized, is taking place, or has taken place, to individuals organizing, committing, or having committed a crime, and to events or actions or missions which create a threat for the state, military, economic, informational, or environmental safety of the Russian Federation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1069.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1076.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Telephone calls may be intercepted without preliminary judicial authorization only in the following three urgent cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1076.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1082.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, if there is a threat that a grave or especially grave crime will be committed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1082.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1094.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second, if there is information about an event or action or mission that creates a threat to the state, military, economic, or environmental safety of the Russian Federation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1094.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1110.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Third, in case of existence of threat to a person's life, health, or property, following such person's request or with such person's consent to monitoring the telephone conversation from his or her telephone line.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1110.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1121.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this case, the authority conducting the operational search activities notifies the court within the time limit prescribed by the law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1121.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1136.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the law obliged the authorities conducting the operational search activities firstly, to notify the judge about the operational search measure, and secondly, to obtain judicial authorization to apply such measure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1136.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1149.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If at the time of applying to the court of operational search measure has been terminated, in his judgment, the judge evaluates the lawfulness of the conducted operational search measure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1149.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1167.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If at the time of judicial recourse, the operational search measure has not been discontinued, in a single judgment, the judge evaluates the lawfulness of the operational search measure and either authorize its subsequent use or do not authorize it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1167.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1189.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Russian Federation interception of telephone and other communications may be used only in relation to a fairly narrow group of individuals, persons suspected or accused of committing a medium-gravity crime, serious crime, or particularly serious crime, as well as persons who may have information pertaining to these crimes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1189.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1196.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In case of Groteur v. Netherlands, the court demonstrated an even broader position.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1196.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1211.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court found justified the interception of telephone conversations of a person who was neither a suspect nor an accused in a criminal case, and neither did the applicant have information pertaining to a crime.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1211.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1222.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Russian legislator has established the time limit for duration of control and record of telephone and other communications, which is equal to six months.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1222.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1229.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If the term must be extended, the judge shall render a judicial judgment on the basis of newly provided evidence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1229.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1244.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In comparing this maximum time limit for intercepting telephone communications in Russia with the limits established by the court case law, it should be noted that the Russian Federation is not exceed the established standard in this particular aspect.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1244.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1250.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>An especially illustrative case in this regard in the case of Van Pelt v. Netherlands, where</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1250.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1263.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>the commission deemed justified that in the course of a preliminary investigation the telephones of the applicant suspected of drug trafficking were tapped for a period of almost two years.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1263.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1269.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The investigating judge prolonged this authorization 21 times.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1269.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1286.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is important to note that the legislation of the Russian Federation also includes safeguards to be used when transferring information to other authorities and storing information obtained while intercepting telephone and other communications.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1286.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1302.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Recording obtained in the results of intercepting telephone and other communications are stored in sealed form in a manner that excludes the possibility of them being heard or distributed by third parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1302.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1308.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Information pertaining to the results of operational search measures is deemed a state secret.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1308.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1325.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court judgment allowing the conduct of operational search measure as well as materials which serve as the grounds for rendering this judgment are stored only with the agency conducting the operational search activity.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1325.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1342.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The right to declassify information obtained during the operational search activities to be provided to the inquirer, investigator, or the court is vested in the hands of the agencies conducting the operational search activities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1342.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1359.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In doing so, the agency conducting the operational search activities files a petition to the court on declassifying their court's judgment to provide a copy of it to the investigator, inquirer, the prosecutor, or the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1359.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1377.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Upon examining their providing documents, evidence, and circumstances which render their further protection of the state secret unnecessary, the judge renders a judgment on declassifying this corresponding court judgment about conducting the operational search measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1377.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1388.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>All this gives grounds to conclude that the Russian legislation provides for adequate and effective guarantees against abuse of state officials by their powers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1388.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1405.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With regard to the court's question of whether the scope of review the authorizing authority may be limited in respect of the reasons for the surveillance measures and the supporting evidence, the authorities see it especially important to submit the following.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1405.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1419.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The basis for the court judgment authorizing operational search measure in the form of control and the record of communications is a subservient decision submitted by one of the heads of the agency conducting operational search activities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1419.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1437.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>At that, the judge is not obliged to give authorization for these measures to be conducted only because he received a corresponding petition if the judge believes that the petition is unsubstantiated or unlawful.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1437.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1449.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this instance, the obligation to justify the necessity to control and record communications rests with the state officials who petition the court for authorization.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1449.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1463.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As examples, it is possible to refer to the same information notes of the Babayurtasky District Court of the Republic of Dagestan and the Leninsky District Court of the Tula region, seated by the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1463.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1480.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is noted therein that in judicial practice of these courts, all petitions lodged by the heads of competent bodies for authorization of operational search measures received in the considered period of time were justified.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1480.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1503.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The mention in this information notes that the judges do not request additional materials during consideration of petitions of the heads of competent bodies for interception of telephone communications do not provide evidence of violation by this court of federal law on operational search activities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1503.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1516.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Seen by virtue of its provisions, the judge can request additional information in case of insufficient justification of the petition, but not obliged.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1516.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1530.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In whole, to justify his position, the agency head who is seeking authorization to control and record communications provides all materials and evidence related to the basis for undertaking these measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1530.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1551.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The only exclusions are information about individuals who are infiltrated in organized criminal gangs, undisclosed agents, individuals who are aiding agencies in a confidential manner, as well as information about the organization and tactics of conducting operational search activities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1551.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1576.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It should be noted that the present exclusion responds to the state's obligation to ensure the confidentiality of the individuals who are aiding the agencies conducting operational search activities, as well as protection of these individuals, their family members, and close persons from unlawful attempts to their life and any danger to their health and property.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1576.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1583.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>From our point of view, these legislative provisions fully correspond to the European Court case law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1583.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1590.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is essential that in case Rajkumar v. United Kingdom, the European Court drew attention</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1590.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1599.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>to the fact that the entitlement to disclosure of relevant evidence is not, however, an absolute right.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1599.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1616.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In any criminal proceedings, there may be competing interests, such as a national security or the need to protect witnesses, undisclosed agents, informants at risk of reprisal, which must be weighed against the rights of the accused.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1616.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1633.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the Russian legislation does not contradict the court case law pertaining to agent provocateur, see Mueller v. Austria, Speckman v. United Kingdom.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1633.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1644.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In connection with the European Court's question regarding information that must be indicated in the interception authorization to make it sufficiently specific, we submit the following.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1644.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1653.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The judicial authorization sanctioning the control and recording of communications contains the following information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1653.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1702.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the agency conducting the operational search activities and the official who petitioned the court, on the grounds for recording and controlling communications and on complying with the requirements for undertaking this type of operational search activities, the justification for the need for recording and controlling of telephone communications, on the individual whose communications will be controlled and recorded, on the sign of a crime in the actions of the individual and his involvement in committing this act, on the signs that the crime is being prepared, committed, or has been committed, the telephone number or the identifier code of the device that will be intercepted, specific term of the authorization not exceed six months.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1702.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1704.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Other necessary information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1704.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1727.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It should be added that the examples of judicial decisions mentioned by the applicant in a negative way, which allows conducting operational search measures in relation to indefinite in number of individuals and without specifying the telephone number to be tapped, do not absolutely provide for evidence of violation of law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1727.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1749.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, in exceptional cases, a petition for carrying out operational search measure limiting the constitutional rights of citizens may not exclude data on a particular person in whose respect the authorization for operational search measures is required or such authorization may be asked in respect of indefinite number of individuals.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1749.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1755.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This approach has logical explanation and corresponds to the national legislation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1755.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1769.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In particular, such petitions are filed for authorization of taking information from technical communication channels with the purpose of discover persons involved in commission of crimes in certain time and certain place.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1769.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1779.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If there is information that unidentified persons involved in committing of a crime used mobile connection at the time it was committed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1779.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1786.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In any case, conduct of such measures take place only on the basis of the court authorization.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1786.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1795.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The analysis of the obtained data usually identifies persons involved in the crime committed in the certain place and time.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1795.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1807.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>After receipt of necessary information, the bodies conducting operational search activities apply for the authorization for operational search measures in relation to certain individuals and certain telephone numbers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1807.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1817.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is evident that such practice is connected with specific character of operational search activities and is aimed, first of all, at identification and search of criminals.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1817.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1843.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is clearly evident that these provisions are fully in line with the court's case law, which has established that the warrant itself must clearly specify either by name or by description one person as the interception subject or a single set of premises or places at the premises, places in respect of which the warrant is ordered, say, Kennedy v. United</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1843.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1845.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Kingdom.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1845.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1859.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In conclusion, it is worth noting that the judgment of the Russian judge concerning the control and recording of communication is motivated and contains guarantees against abuse of state officials by their powers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1859.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1867.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With regard to the court's question of characteristics which must embody supervision interceptions process, I would like to submit the follows.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1867.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1878.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The independent body that supervises the operational search measures that includes controlling and recording communications is the Prosecutor's Office of the Russian Federation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1878.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1894.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Public Prosecutor's Office executes its official duties independently from the federal authorities, authorities in the Russian constituent territories, local authorities, and public organizations while strictly complying with the current Russian legislation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1894.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1906.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Prosecutor General of the Russian Federation and his deputies are appointed and removed from their posts by the legislative body, the Federal Council of the Federal Assembly of the Russian Federation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1906.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1919.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is important to note that the prosecutors do not have the right to petition the courts to authorize conduct of operational search measures including control and recording of communications.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1919.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1924.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This right is vested instead in the bodies that conduct operational search activities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1924.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1940.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It should also be added that the prosecutors request the heads of bodies carrying out operational search activities provide them with official documents which include materials about operational search measures using surveillance equipment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1940.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1947.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The prosecutors ensure that the information contained in these documents and materials is protected.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1947.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1963.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, the prosecutor's supervision is possible not only in connection with materials, information, and complaints of individuals about violations of the law, but also on the own initiative of the authorized prosecutors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1963.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1973.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Without this prosecutor's supervision over compliance with the laws in the sphere of operational search activities would be episodic and one-sided.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1973.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1981.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>All of these factors ensure that the prosecutor's office is independent in its supervision of operational search activities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1981.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1996.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Answering the court's question, whether the intercepting authorities are obliged to give identification of the interception or to give access to documents relating to the interception to the person concerned, it is important to highlight the following.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1996.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2004.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Russian legislation does not provide for preliminary notifying the individual who is under secret surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2004.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2010.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Operational search activities cannot be objectively carried out without a significant degree of secrecy.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2010.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2019.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This primarily concerns information about the persons partaking in it or contributing to it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2019.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2043.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The person concerned is notified of operational search measures, investigative actions conducted in his or her relation within the framework of the criminal case under investigation during the preliminary investigation, after the end of the preliminary investigation, and also during the examination of the criminal case on the merit in court proceeding.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2043.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2066.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Upon completion of a preliminary investigation, the accused has the right to examine all of the information of the criminal case, write out extracts, make copies of the case file, lodge complaints about actions or omissions and decisions of investigator, prosecutor, or courts, and to participate when they are heard by the courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2066.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2090.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The person whose guilt was not proved in committing of the crime, namely in whose respect the institution of a criminal case was denied, the criminal case was discontinued for lack of criminal event or corpus delicti, is entitled to claim from the authority carrying out operational search activities to provide him with information about the data collected.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2090.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2102.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If the provision of the claimed data is refused or if the said person believes that the data has not been supplied to him in full, he shall have the right to appeal against it in court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2102.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2121.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>After the case is being examined in court, the duty falls on the agency conducting operative search activities to prove their justification for refusing to provide this person with the requested information, including the reason for not providing it in full.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2121.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2133.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the event that the agency's decision to reject the individual's request is deemed unfounded, the judge forced the agency to provide the individual with the requested information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2133.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2154.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Relying on the aforementioned information can be briefly summarized that the Russian legislation governed the identification of an individual whose conversations were being intercepted, as well as the provisions related to assessing any obtained information fully correspond to the standards set forth by the European Court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2154.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2171.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>An obvious example is the case of Mersh and others versus Luxembourg, where the Commission emphasized that the respondent states could have a total absence of provision for notifying this affected by surveillance measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2171.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2177.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, the Commission observed that ex post facto review and appealing must be available.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2177.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2196.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As regards the course question regarding the possibility for the person who suspects that his communication are being or have been intercepted to have recourse to remedies, we would like to note that the domestic remedies prescribed by the Russian legislation are accessible and effective in practice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2196.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2204.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In particular, any person believing himself or herself to be subjected to operational searcher measures may apply to the Court of the Russian Federation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2204.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2219.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In doing so, the individual does not have to prove or justify that his rights have been violated, because the federal law presumes that an individual's rights have been limited due to the specific character of operational searcher measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2219.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2233.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, the burden of proving the legality and validity of the operational searcher activities in relation to a particular person has been imposed by the legislator on the agency conducting the operational searcher activity.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2233.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2242.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The detailed information in relation to domestic remedies was stated in the memorandum of the Russian Federation authorities to these hearings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2242.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2254.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The effectiveness of the indicated domestic remedies was demonstrated earlier through examples provided in the copies of judicial judgment attached to the memorandum to oral hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2254.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2254.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you for your attention.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2256.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2259.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you Mr. Matyushkin. Can I give the floor to Mr. Leach?</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2262.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2266.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, I shall address the court as regards question one.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2266.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2269.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My colleague, Mr. Levine, will respond to question two.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2269.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2272.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. Rizhikova will respond to questions three and four,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2272.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2276.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>and Mr. Korotayev to question five.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2276.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2283.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In response to question one, we recall that the court accepts two types of challenge to secret surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2283.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2289.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Firstly, general complaints about legislation and practice permitting secret surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2289.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2295.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And secondly, complaints in which applicants allege actual interception of their communications.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2295.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2297.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this case is the first type.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2297.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2300.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. Zakharov is the victim of a convention violation</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2300.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2306.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>caused by the mere existence of legislation permitting secret measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2306.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2311.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This type of general complaint has been recognized by this court since the 1970s.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2311.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2326.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The principles were established in the class judgment and have subsequently been reiterated in a series of cases primarily brought by human rights activists, journalists, and lawyers, such as Weber and Saravia, Akimgev, Liberty, Yodachi, and Kennedy.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2326.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2333.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In such cases, the applicants do not have to allege that surveillance measures were, in fact, applied to them.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2333.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2348.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As the court explained in the Liberty judgment, the rationale is that legislation permitting secret monitoring of communications amounts to a threat of surveillance for all those to whom the legislation may be applied.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2348.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2365.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A number of these cases concern laws which created a system of surveillance under which everyone in the country could potentially have their communications monitored without their ever knowing it, unless there's been some indiscretion or subsequent notification.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2365.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2373.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And therefore, it directly affected all the users of the telecommunications services in the country.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2373.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2380.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to the court in class, a mere existence type challenge is assessed in the light of three factors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2380.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2384.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Firstly, the convention rights alleged to have been infringed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2384.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2388.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Secondly, the secret character of the measures objected to.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2388.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2392.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And thirdly, the connection between the applicant and those measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2392.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2401.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In Kennedy, the court restated the class factors and stipulated two particular issues which the court would take account of in making its assessment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2401.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2406.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Firstly, the availability of any remedies at the national level.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2406.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2412.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And secondly, the risk of secret surveillance measures being applied to the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2412.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2423.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the court will take account of the connection between the applicant and the surveillance measures, or as alternatively expressed, the risk that the measures may be applied to the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2423.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2427.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But the court in these cases does not apply a reasonable likelihood test.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2427.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2430.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This was explicitly ruled out in a Kimjijev.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2430.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2438.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the government's therefore wrong in its written submissions long again today to invoke the reasonable likelihood test.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2438.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2452.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In both Kennedy and Yodachi, the court was satisfied that the applicants did have victim status on the basis that either it could not be excluded that secret measures were applied to them, or that they were potentially at risk of being subjected to such measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2452.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2461.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Similarly, in the Liberty case, the test was met because the applicants were persons to whom the surveillance powers might have been applied.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2461.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2470.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I pause there to make two more general points which may assist the court in its consideration of the appropriate test.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2470.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2477.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Firstly, it's of course essential that the law keeps pace with rapidly changing technical environments.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2477.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2487.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We would emphasize that the powers of interception at issue in this case cover not only the content of telephone conversations, but also the related metadata.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2487.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2493.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And also, information on subscribers kept in service providers' databases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2493.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2509.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, the surveillance at issue now covers all the forms of internet telephony which have been developed in recent years, including emails and texts, as well as the means of communications possible through internet-enabled smartphones, Facebook, YouTube, Twitter, instant messaging.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2509.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2516.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Such communications play an increasingly important role in political debate and activism.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2516.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2528.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, the information recently revealed by Edward Snowden shows the extent to which governments are now capable of carrying out mass surveillance programs, often without individual warrants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2528.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2541.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The second point is that as to the question of legal standing, more generally, the court's tendency is to be more expansive rather than restrictive, as evidenced by the recent grand chamber judgment in Campiano.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2544.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2547.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, I would like to apply the three class</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2547.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2549.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>factors to this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2549.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2551.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Firstly, the convention rights alleged to have been infringed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2551.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2560.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And like all the other cases I've cited, it's the applicant's Article 8 rights which are an issue, the right to respect for his private life and correspondence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2560.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2564.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Secondly, the secret character of the measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2564.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2576.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The regime in Russia is established by the Operational Search Activities Act, the Federal Security Service Act, and the regulations adopted by the Ministry of Communications, some of which are not published.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2576.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2588.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They allow the FSB to monitor phone communications remotely without any obligation to produce the decision authorizing telephone tapping to any person, including the mobile service providers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2588.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2591.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The results are not communicated to the person concerned.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2591.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2597.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The law allows the FSB to intercept in some circumstances without judicial authorization.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2597.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2607.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The authorization process that does exist is woefully inadequate and is not subject to independent scrutiny, as you will hear from my colleagues.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2607.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2614.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As the court held in Kennedy, also relevant to this second issue is the availability of any remedies at the national level.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2614.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2620.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant has been wholly unable to mount an effective domestic challenge to the legislation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2620.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2625.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And on this point, I rely on the submissions to be made by Mr. Korotayev.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2625.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2633.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thirdly, the connection between the applicant and the surveillance measures, or the risk of their being applied to him.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2633.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2642.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant is a journalist and since 2003 has been employed as the staff correspondent of the Glasnost Defense Foundation in St. Petersburg,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2642.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2653.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>a well-known human rights organization which monitors journalist rights and freedom of speech, provides legal advice to journalists, and mounts litigation to protect journalists' professional activities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2653.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2666.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>His daily work, therefore, is monitoring and publishing on the situation of journalist rights in the region and is centrally concerned with the confidentiality of journalist sources of information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2666.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2677.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This court will be only too aware of the extent of the pressures now being placed on human rights organizations by the authorities in Russia, as exemplified by the so-called foreign agents law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2677.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2683.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There is also a plethora of evidence as to the extent of the pressure on and intimidation of journalists in Russia.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2683.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2689.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Committee to Protect Journalists report that 56 have been killed in Russia since 1992.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2689.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2695.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the internet database of such deaths is in part based on the monitoring work of the Glasnost Defense Foundation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2695.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2705.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Reporters Without Borders has attested to the control of the media by political authorities, as well as the state of impunity for acts of violence against journalists.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2705.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2709.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Accordingly, we say that there is a very real and obvious risk that Mr. Zakharov</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2709.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2713.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>may have been subject to surveillance by the authorities in Russia.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2713.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2718.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, he's fully entitled to claim to be a victim of his Article 8 rights.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2718.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2720.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, I now hand over to Ms. Levine.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2725.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2728.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, I will address the court on question two</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2728.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2734.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>regarding the procedure for authorizing secret surveillance measures and the content of authorizations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2734.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2750.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As general points, in Ekimgev, amongst other cases, the court noted that national laws on surveillance must be sufficiently clear so as to give adequate indication of the conditions and circumstances in which the authorities may resort to these measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2750.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2765.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In Weber and Saravia, the court stated that the law must also indicate the scope of the discretionary power in relation to surveillance and the manner of its exercise with sufficient clarity to ensure adequate protection against arbitrary interference.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2765.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2774.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Also in Weber and Saravia, the court elaborated on minimum safeguards that must be set out in the law in order to avoid abuses of power.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2774.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2786.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These include the nature of the offense giving rise to surveillance, a definition of the categories of people who may be subject to surveillance, and a limitation on the duration of surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2786.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2791.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The authorization usually starts with a request for approval to conduct surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2791.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2818.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court approved Bulgarian law in this regard, which above and beyond requiring requests to state reasons and identify the individuals who may be subject to surveillance, also required requests to explain the circumstances grounding the suspicion that a qualifying offense is being planned or has been committed, the steps which have already been taken and the results yielded, the duration of the measures, and the methods to be used.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2818.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2828.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As to the procedure for authorizing requests, we submit that the authorizing body should consider the application of the minimum standards from Weber and Saravia.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2828.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2833.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Firstly, the nature of the offense giving rise to surveillance must be sufficiently clear.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2833.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2840.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Secondly, the category of individuals who may be subject to surveillance must also be sufficiently clearly identified.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2840.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2845.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And thirdly, the surveillance measures must be limited in duration.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2845.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2858.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court underlined in Iordaci that telephone surveillance is a very serious interference with a person's rights, and only very serious reasons based on a reasonable suspicion should be taken as a basis for authorizing it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2858.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2870.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In light of this, we submit that the authorizing body must also establish whether there are indeed serious reasons for the measures requested, and if these are based on a reasonable suspicion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2870.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2875.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court has taken account of evidence on the practice of authorization.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2875.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2890.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For example, in Ekimgev, the court noted that more than 10,000 surveillance warrants were granted over two years out of a population of less than 8 million in Bulgaria, and concluded that this was evidence of the overuse of the system for surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2890.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2909.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In Iordaci, the court noted that more than 98% of requests for surveillance were granted over a three-year period, and given the general absence of safeguards in Moldovan law, concluded that this indicated that judges did not consider if there was compelling justification for authorizing surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2909.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2917.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In numerous cases, the court has approved the existence of a necessity and proportionality test for authorizing surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2917.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2937.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For example, in Kennedy, the court approved UK law requiring the authorizing body to consider if the information to be obtained by surveillance could reasonably be gathered by other means, whether the measures requested were necessary on the grounds specified under the relevant law, and proportionate to what was sought to be achieved.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2937.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2948.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court has not yet addressed the question of whether it would be justified for the scope of review of the authorizing body to be limited, where the reasons for surveillance relate to, for example, national security.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2948.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2959.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On this point, I would like to draw an analogy with the court's principles on the restrictions of the prosecution's duty to disclose material evidence in criminal proceedings in the context of Article VI.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2959.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2970.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As set out in Rowan Davis, the duty to disclose evidence should only be limited where it is strictly necessary, such as where there are public interest grounds for doing so.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2970.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2983.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this situation, where the prosecution makes an ex parte application to the court, the judge must conduct a substantive review, weighing up the public interest grounds against the interests of the defendant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2983.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2996.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>By analogy, in the Article VIII context, we submit that where public interest grounds are raised, there should be a substantive review of the reasons for and the proportionality of the measures requested.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2996.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3019.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As to the content of authorizations, in Kennedy, the court approved the provisions of UK law that require authorizations to specify a person or a single set of physical premises, either by name or description, and be accompanied by an annex setting out the names, telephone numbers, and other relevant information on the subjects of surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3019.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3033.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As regards the nature of the authorizing body, the court has approved this rule falling to a judge, or has at least required there to be judicial oversight of the body examining requests for authorization.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3033.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3037.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As to the application of the court's standards in the present case, Mr. President,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3037.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3047.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>we submit that the Operational Search Activities Act does not provide for adequate or effective safeguards in relation to the authorization of requests for surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3047.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3052.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The act does not specify what a request for surveillance must contain.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3052.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3064.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is silent on whether the request must identify the individuals who may be subject to surveillance, the nature of the suspected offenses giving rise to the request, or the duration of the proposed measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3064.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3072.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The act merely requires the judge to consider, quote, a reasoned decision, unquote, from one of the heads of the bodies conducting surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3072.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3080.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There is no mention of what kinds of reasons should be included, or whether there needs to be a basis of a reasonable suspicion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3080.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3085.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The act does not specify the nature of the judge's examination of requests.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3085.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3091.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It does not require the judge to consider the breadth of the offenses giving rise to the requested measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3091.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3101.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Unlike in previous cases, the act allows telephone surveillance in respect of medium gravity crimes, as well as grave and especially grave crimes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3101.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3108.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The act also permits the telephone tapping of people who simply possess some knowledge about such crimes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3108.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3115.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Under the act, surveillance measures may be granted for up to six months, unless otherwise indicated by the judge.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3115.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3123.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, there is no mention of when the judge may authorize surveillance for longer than this, or if indeed there is any maximum duration.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3123.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3130.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The act does not require the judge to establish if there are serious reasons for the requested measures, based on a reasonable suspicion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3130.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3135.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The judge may seek limited information on the grounds for the request.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3135.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3137.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In practice, this very rarely happens.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3137.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3151.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For example, I refer here to annexes 14 to 16 of the applicant's submission of June 2014, which confirmed that no such requests were made in recent years by the judges of the courts referred to therein.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3151.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3163.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The act does not require the judge to consider whether the requested measures are necessary for the achievement of the aims listed in section 7 to 9 of the act, or proportionate to what is sought to be achieved.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3163.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3174.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There is nothing under Russian law regulating judicial authorization of surveillance in particularly sensitive situations, for example, where the confidentiality of journalistic sources is at stake.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3174.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3194.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I also wish to draw the court's attention to annexes 9 to 13 of the applicant's June 2014 submissions, which show that in 2013, for example, the Russian courts were requested to authorize surveillance measures around 610,000 times, and did so in 97% of cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3194.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3206.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We submit that this is indicative of the inadequacy of the judicial authorization process, and also underlines the overuse of the system for covert surveillance on account of its extremely weak safeguards.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3206.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3212.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The act does not require all secret surveillance measures to be authorized by a judge.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3212.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3222.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Where there is a risk to an individual's life, health, or property, surveillance may be authorized on the basis of a decision of the head of the relevant surveillance body and where the individual concerned consents.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3222.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3233.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The act merely requires that in these situations, a judge be notified of, as opposed to being asked to authorize, the measures taken within 48 hours of their implementation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3233.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3238.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The decision of the surveillance body does not need to contain reasons.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3238.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3243.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There is no indication of the safeguards in these situations to ensure informed consent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3243.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3250.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Further, there is no reference to the rights of the other people whose communications may well be caught by these measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3250.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3259.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Finally, the act does not indicate what information should be included in an authorization to ensure that it is sufficiently specific.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3259.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3266.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For example, it is silent on whether the authorization should identify the subject of the surveillance measures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3266.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3274.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government even acknowledges in its submissions of June 2014 that judges may authorize surveillance in relation to unidentified persons.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3274.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3276.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, I now hand over to Ms. Rajagopal.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3280.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3285.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, I will address the court in question three</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3285.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3289.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>as to the characteristics of a body supervising interception.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3289.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3300.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This court has consistently reiterated that whatever system of surveillance the state establishes, it must be subject to adequate and effective supervision in order to prevent abuse.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3300.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3307.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will refer to the court's principles concerning supervision before applying those principles in this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3307.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3318.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In Iordace, the court said that there must be judicial control or control by an independent body over the authority issuing warrants for surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3318.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3326.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The supervising body's members must have certain qualifications ensuring their independence and adherence to the rule of law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3326.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3342.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In Kennedy and in Elle versus Norway, this court expressed its approval that members of respective supervisory bodies hold or have held high judicial office or were qualified lawyers of several years standing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3342.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3345.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The supervisory body's activities must be transparent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3345.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3366.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In Ekimgiv, the court was highly critical of the fact that the supervising minister was not required to regularly report to an independent body or to the general public on the operation of the surveillance system and referred to examples to the contrary in Klass, Elle versus Norway, and Christie versus UK.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3366.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3370.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Supervisory body must have adequate powers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3370.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3400.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This court has expressed its approval of the regime established in the UK law, as the investigatory powers tribunal has the power to quash interception orders, to order the destruction of material obtained, and to order compensation, and the right of the interception of communications commissioner and the tribunal to have access to all classified materials and of the corresponding obligation on interception authorities to disclose to them any such materials.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3400.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3413.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In Weber and Serevia, the court approved of the fact that G10 commission in Germany had supervising power in relation to all stages of interception, not only to authorization.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3413.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3418.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Under the 1995 Act, supervisory control is entrusted to prosecutors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3418.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3429.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Prosecutors are neither independent nor impartial since they present a state in criminal proceedings and may rely on information obtained by means of secret surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3429.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3448.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, by virtue of the Prosecutor's Office Act, prosecutors have a statutory duty to coordinate the activities of law enforcement bodies, including the Ministry of the Interior, the FSB, and drug control bodies, the very bodies which it supervises under the 1995 Act.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3448.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3456.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, pursuant to the Criminal Procedure Code, the prosecutor may participate in the telephone tap and authorization hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3456.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3465.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Under the 1995 Act, the prosecutor does not have the power to review the lawfulness of judicial authorization and cannot challenge or quash it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3465.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3473.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The prosecutor has no express legal power to ensure that information obtained is securely stored and processed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3473.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3478.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The prosecutor cannot order the destruction of any material obtained.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3478.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3483.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, he reports biannually only to a superior prosecutor.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3483.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3488.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>His reports are classified and thus inaccessible to the general public.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3488.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3506.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, the prosecutor's supervisory functions are significantly limited by the FSB Act, according to which information about undercover agents, organization, tactics, methods, and means of work of FSB bodies are excluded from the scope of supervisory control.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3506.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3532.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The FSB Act also provides that materials related to FSB counterintelligence and counterterrorism operations, which restrict individuals' right to secrecy of correspondence, are provided to a prosecutor only upon receipt by the letter of materials, information, or petitions of individuals testifying to the fact that the FSB has acted in breach of Russian law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3532.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3542.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Finally, under the 1995 Act, overall control of surveillance activities is entrusted to the president, parliament, and the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3542.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3548.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, there are no further provisions in law which set out what functions such control entails.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3548.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3551.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, I now turn to question four</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3551.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3554.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>on the issue of notifications.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3554.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3567.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the case of Klaas, the court found that when surveillance is first ordered and while it is being carried out, it should be effected without the individual's knowledge, as otherwise this would jeopardize its effectiveness.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3567.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3572.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, the court's position is quite different as regards subsequent notification.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3572.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3583.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As soon as notification can be made without jeopardizing the purpose of the surveillance after its termination, information should be provided to the persons concerned.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3583.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3604.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court has also reiterated that the question of subsequent notification is inextricably linked to the effectiveness of remedies before domestic courts and to the existence of effective safeguards against abuse, since there is in principle little scope for recourse to courts unless an individual concerned is advised of the measures taken without his knowledge.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3604.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3614.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In Ekimchiev, the court found the Bulgarian legislation wanton, as it did not provide for any notification at any point and under any circumstances.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3614.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3620.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On that basis, the court not only found a violation of Article 8, but also Article 13.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3620.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3628.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, it is clear that this court views subsequent notification as an important safeguard against abuse.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3628.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3647.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the case of Segerstedt-Wieberg, this court found that the denial of full access to a secret police register may be necessary when the state legitimately fears that the provision of such information may jeopardize the efficacy of a secret surveillance system designed to protect national security and to combat terrorism.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3647.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3668.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In Mesh and others, the commission accepted the government's claim that absence of subsequent notification of surveillance measures was limited only to offenses against the external security of the state of Luxembourg, and concluded that the surveillance system was appropriately designed to protect democracy from the threats to which it might be exposed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3668.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3681.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, we submit that a refusal to notify may only be justified in very limited circumstances, for example, when a country's national security or comparable interests are at stake.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3681.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3689.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I reiterate that under Russian law, a person who is under surveillance is not notified, even after it is over.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3689.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3694.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If a criminal case is initiated, it could be that access is obtained to the criminal case file.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3694.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3706.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>However, even then, materials submitted by the government demonstrate that it is usually the case that neither the application for a warrant nor a warrant itself are included in the criminal case file.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3706.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3713.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, even a defendant in criminal proceedings will not be informed about the reasons for the surveillance in the first place.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3713.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3725.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The domestic law provides that a person may only seek access from an intercepting body to the data collected when they possess facts as to the surveillance measures having been applied to them.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3725.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3731.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What is meant by facts is not set out in law, and this sets an impossibly high burden.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3731.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3738.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Only persons whose guilt has not been proven in a procedure established by law may seek request.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3738.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3749.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Even then, he may still be denied access to information or may obtain only partial access, as there is no obligation on the intercepting authorities to disclose information to him.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3749.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3760.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is because the law provides that surveillance information may only be disclosed with due observance of the principle of conspiracy and excluding the disclosure of state secrets.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3760.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3766.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thus, it is not a question of considering whether disclosure could jeopardize the initial purpose of surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3766.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3777.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Instead, what matters is that the results of surveillance are considered to be a state secret in accordance with Article 12 of the 1995 Act and will thus not be disclosed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP3</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3777.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3777.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, I now hand over to Mr. Kertil.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3783.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3787.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, I will deal with the Court's fifth question relating to the right</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3787.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3792.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>to an effective remedy under Article 13 of the Convention. We will argue that, firstly,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3792.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3815.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>an effective remedy in cases of telephone tapping usually requires some degree of adversarial proceedings, that, secondly, persons subject to surveillance must be notified of it once the measures applied are no longer warranted, and, thirdly, that the scope of review must include assessment of proportionality of the measures and the reasons must be given for the decisions. I start with the</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3815.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3820.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>procedural guarantees. What is required under Article 13 is a remedy that is as effective</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3820.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3830.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>as can be having regard to the restricted scope for address, which is inherent in the context of secret state surveillance. In Acum G, the Court ruled that even</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3830.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3839.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>when surveillance is ongoing, a limited remedy is nevertheless still possible, for example, where the proceedings are secret and where no reasons are given.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3839.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3851.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alternatively, an ex parte review conducted by a body composed of judicial officers is possible. This system was found compatible with the Convention by the Belgian</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3851.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3861.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Constitutional Court in the case of Order of Flemish Lawyers and League for Human Rights in September 2011. Even where the issue of national security is at stake,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3861.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3879.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Article 13 taken together with Article 8 requires some form of adversarial proceedings, although the parties may be required to be represented by lawyers who have undergone security clearance, as confirmed in Al-Nashif against Bulgaria and Sijai and others against Bulgaria. I turn now to the issues of burden of proof.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3879.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3889.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this regard, it is the requirement of the Convention that the person who is subject to surveillance is notified of it once the measures are over. Failure to provide</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3889.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3893.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>such notification led to a violation of Article 13 in Acum G.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3893.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3903.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Accordingly, the existence of the system where the service provider or an independent monitoring body is aware of the ongoing surveillance is crucial. This would allow</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3903.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3913.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>to double-check the submissions of the surveillance agency should the latter deny any involvement in tapping. With regard to the legality of telephone tapping,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3913.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3923.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>we submit that it falls on the body that conducts surveillance to prove that the measures were in conformity with the applicable law, including the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3923.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3932.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This law was entrenched in the Court's cases under Article 2, 3, and 5, as in Timutash against Turkey. It was also applied in Article 8 cases, for example, in Fadeva against</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3932.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3933.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Russia.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3933.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3950.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We submit that it is applicable to the present case for the same reason as in those cases, that is, the executive alone has knowledge of all the circumstances of the case which justified surveillance and that the decision to undertake it was taken in the individual's absence. I now move to the scope of review and the</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3950.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3955.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>obligation to give reasons. In class, the Court was satisfied with the combined</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3955.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3972.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>availability of civil, administrative, and constitutional remedies, and in Kennedy, with the combination of powers of the Investigatory Powers Tribunal and the review exercised by the Interception of Communications Commission. We submit that the National</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3972.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3983.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Court or other supervising authority must be able to take full cognizance of the merits of the case, including the review of proportionality. We rely on the Grand Chamber's</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3983.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3987.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>findings under Article 13 in Hutton and others against the United Kingdom.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3987.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3998.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And where the surveillance measures are no longer under way, no justification may be invoked for not giving reason judgment at the end of the proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3998.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4009.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The obligation to give reasons in post facto judicial review was upheld by the already mentioned judgment of the Belgian Constitutional Court. As the European Court held</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4009.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4029.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>in Alnuschief, even where domestic court or supervising authority is obliged to accord a wide margin of appreciation to the executive in matters of national security, that can by no means justify doing away with the remedies altogether whenever the executive has chosen to invoke the term national security. In C.G. and others,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4029.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4045.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>the obligation to scrutinize whether a reference to national security is genuine and whether there is sufficient factual basis for it were important factors in assessing the effectiveness of the domestic remedy. We argue further that the remedies available</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4045.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4049.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>under Russian law fall short of the requirements of Article 13.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4049.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4055.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Domestic court proceedings do not offer an effective remedy in practice. We submit</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4055.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4061.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>as follows. Firstly, the government did produce a number of domestic judgments</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4061.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4066.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>in cases decided in favor of individual applicants. However, they failed to specify</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4066.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4072.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>the selection criteria. It thus cannot be said that the judgments are anyhow representative</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4072.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4078.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>of the totality of Russian cases concerning surveillance. In any event, none of the</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4078.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4089.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>noncriminal judgments concern a finding of illegality of telephone tapping or any similar measure. Instead, they all relate to assessments of the lawfulness of searches</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4089.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4094.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>or seizures, which by definition are known to persons subject to them. Secondly,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4094.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4110.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>the government admitted in paragraph 140 of their observations of June 2014 that the Russian law does not provide for notification of persons subject to surveillance even after it is discontinued, unless criminal proceedings are opened against them.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4110.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4122.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thirdly, applicable Russian regulations do not provide for notification of the decision to undertake surveillance measures to the provider of telephone or Internet services.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4122.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4132.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So if the authorities engaged in surveillance are denying that the measures were or are being applied, it is impossible to independently verify their submissions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4132.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4143.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Fourth, in no domestic case referred to by the government did the Russian courts assess the proportionality of the operative search measures employed by the executive.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4143.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4154.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Such a remedy cannot be deemed effective under the Court's case law, Ekimchiev, Arnashiev, and Khatun in particular. In conclusion, we submit that the Court's</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4154.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4171.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>finding in Ligutin against Russia that the failure to conduct judicial review in the cases under the Operative Search Activities Act is a structural failure of the Russian law applicable to telephone tapping. Accordingly, we invite the Court to find</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4171.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4176.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>violation of Article 8 of the Convention taken alone and together with Article 13.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4176.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4180.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, that concludes the submission on behalf of the applicant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4180.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4180.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4182.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4183.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4183.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4184.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I turn to the judges.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4184.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4186.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Are there questions?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4186.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4187.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Yes, Judge Sicilianos.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4192.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4193.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4193.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4196.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's a question to both parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4196.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4201.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to submissions by the parties, Order No. 70 on technical requirements</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4201.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4228.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>for the system of technical facilities enabling the conduct of operational search activities using telecommunications network, issued by the Ministry of Communications on 20 April 1999, stipulates that equipment installed by communications service providers must meet certain technical requirements which are described in the addendums to the order.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4228.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4232.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Those addendums have never been officially published.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4232.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4248.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would like to know more about the functioning of this order in practice and its impact on the various safeguards and guarantees provided by the applicable legislation, especially the authorization procedure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Linos-Alexandre Sicilianos</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4248.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4248.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4249.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4250.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Judge Ziemele.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4254.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4256.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4256.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4281.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In view of the applicant's submissions, and since the second part of the submissions addressed the question of notification in greater detail, I would like to ask the government to explain exactly this aspect in your sort of rebuttals.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4281.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4296.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Because would the government really confirm that there is no obligation to notify of surveillance that had taken place and that had not led to any criminal proceedings?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4296.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4300.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So would the government confirm that that is indeed the case?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4300.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4305.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the applicant just referred to your written submissions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4305.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4315.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And if that is so, could the government explain the reasons for such approach in the Russian legislation?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4315.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4333.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And is the government of the view that you basically don't have to provide this opportunity to your citizens to have the information that the Surveillance Act had taken place?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4333.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4354.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In that context, how would you explain that in the applicant's case, the domestic courts, in fact, did not accept his submissions saying that he has failed to discharge the burden of proof?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4354.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4367.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>He has failed to demonstrate the facts that might lead to consideration that he has been submitted to surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4367.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4385.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>How would he be able to meet that burden of proof in domestic proceedings if there is no way for him to find out what is happening, that there is no this notification obligation?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4385.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4391.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So if you would really address specifically this part outside the criminal proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ineta Ziemele</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4391.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4391.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4393.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4394.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Judge Lemmens.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4398.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4399.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4399.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4409.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's a bit following up on the previous question also about the notification of the interception to the subject.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4409.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4428.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Both parties have referred to the fact that according to Russian law, the major part, and now I'm quoting from the government's memorial, the major part of operational search activities requested by the relevant authorities from the court is secret in nature.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4428.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4440.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that may be partly an explanation or an answer to Judge Seymour's question, but I would like to know more about the notion of a state secret under Russian law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4440.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4443.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What is a state secret?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4443.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4447.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Who decides that something is a state secret?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4447.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4451.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And is it possible to challenge that qualification?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paul Lemmens</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4451.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4452.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4455.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4455.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, so.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4455.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4458.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We will have a short break, 20 minutes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4458.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4463.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And sorry, Judge Turković, I'm sorry.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4463.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4484.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A question for the applicants, we have heard today that the government is raising the issue of non-exhaustion of domestic remedies. And you did not refer to that. We didn't hear about that before.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4484.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4488.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is for the first time that the government is raising that issue. So I think it would</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Ksenija Turković</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4488.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4491.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>be valuable for all of us that you address that. Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4495.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4501.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So we will have a short break now for 20 minutes and we will resume at 10 to 11.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4961.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4961.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5007.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5009.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please be seated, Mr. Matyushkin.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5018.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5030.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Answering the first question, the question of Judge Sicilianos, I should just come back to what I told during my submission.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5034.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5055.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The order of the State Communication Information Committee of the Russian Federation of 1999, number 70, was published with all technical amendments completely.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5055.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5078.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It was published in Svyazin Form magazine, number six, in 1999, and available in national constant database and in internet, and attached to applicants' submission to the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5078.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5083.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's why it was published completely with all amendments.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5083.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5115.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Answering the question two by Judge Zimily, I should tell that exercising their personal search measures, namely control and record of telephone conversation, the state guarantees their citizens' rights in part of keeping and deleting of data received as a result of this interception.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5115.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5137.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The number subject, the terms of storage, the order, and the duty of destroying of data, and existing the strict judicial control are the factors of non-violation of Article 8 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5137.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5146.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The disclosure of this information entails criminal liability of relevant state officials.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5146.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5163.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Consequently, the absence of notification of telephone interception is well-balanced by available set of effective remedies applicable in criminal and civil proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5163.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5168.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>See, for example, Merch and others versus Luxembourg.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5168.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5183.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There are multiple examples of such remedies in the form of judicial decisions rendered by the Russian courts, though exposed as their addendum to the memorandum of Russian authorities to these hearings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5183.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5197.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Answering the question three by the Judge Lemons, I should tell that we, in Russian Federation, we have federal law on state secret.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5200.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5223.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This law contains the information on the data which could be represented as state secret and who exactly exercised this power.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5223.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5239.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And we also like to state that, in accordance with the Civil Procedure Court of the Russian Federation, any citizen can challenge actions or omissions of any state authorities and decisions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5239.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5250.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And there presented some information as the state secret could be appealed to the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5250.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5250.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5256.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5258.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Mr Matyushkin.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5258.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5263.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr Leach or who wants to take the floor? Mr Leach.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5264.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5265.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5265.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5271.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>May I start with Judge Lemon's question about state secret?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5271.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5276.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And as the government has said, it's subject to the Federal State Secrets Act.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5276.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5289.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In our submission, that allows a very wide range of public officials, even junior public officials, to classify documents and information as being secret.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5289.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5293.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There is one body, one commission, that is able to declassify information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5293.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5296.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We say it's a body that's not independent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5296.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5302.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And it's extremely difficult in practice to challenge the decisions of that body in the courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5302.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5323.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then staying on that point, the state secrecy point in relation to this particular case, we also refer to Article 12 of the 1995 Act, which sets out the information which is secret under the 1995 Act.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5323.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5327.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I'm just looking for that provision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5327.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5338.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the Article 12 of the 1995 Act says that the following is a state secret in relation to searches under the Operational Search Activity Act and other forms of surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5338.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5349.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It says, the information on the forces, the means, the sources, the methods, the plans, and the results of this operational search activity, and then goes on to list other things.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5349.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5351.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Those are state secrets under Article 12.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5351.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5356.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I think that's an important point to underline.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5356.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5371.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>May I then turn to Judge Sicilianos' question about the impact of Order Number 70, the addendums to which have not been published.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5371.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5387.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I want to just stop there for a moment, because contrary to what the government has said, the government has again asserted today that the publication in a magazine, which hasn't been disclosed, the actual publication, publication in a private database and on the internet is sufficient.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5387.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5395.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nor is it relevant that the fact that this applicant, who is an investigative journalist, was able to obtain a copy and submit it in the domestic proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5395.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5406.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Under the Russian regulations themselves, under the Constitution and the 1998 regulations, those laws must be published and certified by the Ministry of Justice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5406.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5410.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So it cannot be said that they were published.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5410.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5420.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And Judge Sicilianos' question was about the impact of that provision on the various safeguards.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5420.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5440.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We would want to emphasize that the provision requires mobile phone operators to set up the technical means for the FSB to remotely control the monitoring equipment inside the phone networks.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5440.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5445.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is a system, a regime, that's very unusual in Europe.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5445.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5448.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And we say it's especially intrusive.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5448.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5460.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What happens in most countries in Europe is that the state bodies would require the telephone companies or the internet service providers to have the capability to undertake lawful interception.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5460.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5469.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the phone companies are served with the warrants so that they can then switch on their intercept capability.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5469.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5472.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that's not what happens here.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5472.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5481.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We say it's exceptionally intrusive and therefore underlines even further the need to have adequate legal safeguards.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5481.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5486.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And as you heard from us today, we say very clearly it doesn't.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5486.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5492.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If I could then turn to Judge Turkovich's question about domestic remedies.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5492.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5498.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the government started off the morning talking about domestic remedies.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5498.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5501.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And our position on this is very, very clear.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5501.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5503.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. Zakharov was not in a position</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5503.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5510.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>to know if he was or wasn't subject to surveillance because of the nature of secret surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5510.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5522.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>He brought domestic judicial proceedings which established that he could not, in fact, in practice challenge the surveillance regime because he was required to prove that his phones were tapped.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5522.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5526.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>He went to the town court and to the city court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5526.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5539.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>He brought proceedings against the mobile phone operators and the Ministry of Communications and the FSB complaining about his right to privacy in relation to telephone communications.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5539.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5543.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And those claims were rejected.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5543.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5554.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There is also clearly in Russian law no judicial review available of unpublished regulations because they are said to be technical.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5554.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5560.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is confirmed by the Supreme Court decision and a high commercial court decision that we've referred to in our pleadings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5560.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5567.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that's as a result of a 1998 federal cabinet decree.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5567.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5579.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now, the government has also referred in its pleadings to various Article 125 appeals and civil claims, which, as Mr. Korotayev has already said,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5579.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5585.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>they relate to searches of premises and seizure of documents and computers, search and seizure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5585.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5592.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>By definition, of course, the defendants in those cases would have been aware.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5592.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5602.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We make the point that, of course, whereas someone subject to secret phone tapping has no knowledge that they are so subject to the interception.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5602.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5606.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So it's a completely different situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5606.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5622.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The constitutional courts in Russia would only be able to consider points that were an issue in the domestic proceedings and that were cited by the lower courts in their reasoning.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5622.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5627.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the constitutional court only permits abstract challenges to legislation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5627.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5642.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And we refer also on this point to the judgment last week, this court's judgment last week in Avonissian against Russia, 18th of September, which was another case about a search under this same act, the Operation Search Activities Act of 95.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5642.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5649.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And in that case, the applicant brought supervisory review proceedings, which were dismissed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5649.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5653.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>He also brought constitutional court proceedings, which were also dismissed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5653.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5658.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the court in that case found violations of Article 8 and Article 13.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5661.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5667.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A few other points to conclude with, Mr. President, if I may.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5667.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5680.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government in its 2014 submissions and referred again today to a small number of domestic criminal cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5680.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5690.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I just wanted to refer to those because we say that, actually, those criminal cases confirm that the authorization process is flawed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5690.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5691.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They're full of examples.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5691.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5701.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Very quickly, the Supreme Court judgment of December 2012 shows that surveillance took place before judicial authorization was granted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5701.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5704.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And therefore, the domestic courts themselves said it was unlawful.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5704.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5710.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A decision from Krasnyi Arsk shows that surveillance was authorized against the wrong person.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5710.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5714.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The decision from the Republic of Marielle had a number of problems.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5714.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5718.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The judge's order for surveillance was inadequate.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5718.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5722.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There was no concrete data serving as a basis for making the decision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5722.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5731.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The judgment contained only general wording, no reference to the criminal code, didn't have sufficient information on actual circumstances of the wrongful act being committed, and so on.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5731.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5737.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And finally, there were two other cases in which unlawful surveillance was carried out by public officials.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5737.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5746.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So we say on their evidence that this authorization process is flawed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5746.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5764.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We also want to emphasize that in response to what the government said, the 1995 Act has no requirement to consider the necessity of the surveillance measures, contrary to what the government, I think, seems to be suggesting.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5764.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5775.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And one can make a very, very stark contrast with legislation such as the REPA legislation in the UK, which very clearly incorporates proportionality and necessity tests.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5775.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5789.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government referred today to the possibility of the judge in the authorization process requesting additional materials.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5789.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5793.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this is Article 9.4 of the 1995 Act.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5793.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5797.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So there is a possibility to request additional materials.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5797.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5800.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We note, though, that there is an exception.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5800.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5801.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There are several exceptions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5801.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5809.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the exceptions include the organization and tactics of the operative search action.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5809.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5827.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the judge is excluded from asking for additional materials about the organization and tactics of the operative search action, which seems to us to be extraordinarily broad and includes information that the judge would require to carry out a proper review.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5827.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5839.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government, again today, acknowledged that under this system, unidentified persons can be subject to surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5839.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5843.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That hasn't really been explained today or in the written pleadings, we say.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5843.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5846.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But it seems to be a fishing expedition.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5846.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5858.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The capability of the authorities to, for example, locate who was in a particular area at a particular time through this surveillance, the SORM system.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5858.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5872.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And finally, we also heard today that the offenses which can be subject to surveillance include medium gravity, as well as serious offenses.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5872.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5878.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And most of the cases that this court has considered have related to serious and very serious cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5878.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5884.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They don't, the domestic legislation doesn't include medium gravity cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5884.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5893.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Just one example for you, in Russia, the offense of pickpocketing is a medium gravity case and therefore could be subject to this surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5893.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5896.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, that concludes the submissions</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5896.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5898.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>on behalf of the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP4</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5898.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5898.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5900.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5905.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much. We have now come to the end of the hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5905.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5912.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I thank the parties for their interventions and answers to the Court's questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5912.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5917.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Court will now deliberate on the admissibility and merits of the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5917.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5922.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The parties will be informed of any decision in due course.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Dean Spielmann</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5922.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5922.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I declare the hearing closed.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

</transcript_4714306_24092014>
