<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<transcript_3728313_17102018>
  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>12.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>13.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>52.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>53.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please be seated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>65.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>72.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I declare open the public hearing on the merits in the case of Strand Lobben and others versus Norway.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>72.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>86.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The application was lodged with the court on 12 April 2013 under Article 34 of the Convention by five Norwegian nationals, Mrs. Trude Lobben, her two children,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>86.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>92.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>X, the second applicant, and Y, the third applicant, and Mr. and Mrs. Leif and Cecil Lobben.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>92.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>102.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The application was allocated to the fifth section of the court, pursuant to Rule 52, paragraph 1 of the rules of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>102.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>110.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On 13 November 2017, a chamber of that section delivered its judgment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>110.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>117.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It held by four votes to three that there had been no violation of Article 8 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>117.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>129.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On 6 February 2018, the first and second applicants requested that the case be referred to the Grand Chamber in accordance with Article 43 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>129.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>136.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the panel of the Grand Chamber accepted the request on 9 April 2018.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>136.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>173.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On different dates between 12 June and 27 July 2018, the president of the Grand Chamber granted leave to the governments of Belgium, Bulgaria, the Czech Republic, Denmark, Italy, the Slovak Republic, and the United Kingdom, and to ADF International, the AIR Center, l'Association Italienne des Magistrats de la Jeunesse et de la Famille, and the second applicants' adoptive parents to submit written comments as third parties by virtue of Rule 44, paragraph 3 of the rules of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>173.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>180.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The respondent governments are represented by their agents, Mr. Fredrik Sejersted, Attorney General</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>180.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>201.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>of Civil Matters, assisted by Mr.  Marius Emberland and Mrs. Henriette Lund Busch, counsel, and by Mrs. Anne Sidnes-Egeland, Mr.Henrik Vaaler, Mr. Dag Thomas  Gisholt, Mr. Christina  Five Berg, Mrs. Hilde Bautz-Holter Geving and Mrs. Lene Witt, advisors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>201.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>208.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants are represented by Grégory Thuan Dit Dieudonné, counsel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>208.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>211.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The first applicant is also present.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>211.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>215.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I welcome the representatives in the name of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>215.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>223.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I also welcome, among others, the delegations of judges from Norway and Russia.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>223.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>233.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Having consulted the agents of the government and the representative of the applicants, I have determined the order of addresses as follows.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>233.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>240.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. Grégory Thuan Dit Dieudonné for the applicants will speak first, and then Mr. Sejersted for the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>240.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>261.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would explain that in addition to interpreting in the two official languages of the court, English and French, interpreting into Russian and Armenian has been authorized for the benefit of the group of judges from Russia and the representatives of the investigative committee of the Republic of Armenia attending this hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>261.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>271.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That interpreting is not arranged by the court, and no transcription of the oral translation will be included in the official record of the proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>271.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>273.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I call Mr. Thuan Dit Dieudonné.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>273.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>273.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Vous avez la parole.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>276.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>300.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs de la Cour, Monsieur le Gréfier, permettez-moi très brièvement, avant de commencer d'exprimer à titre professionnel comme personnel, l'immense honneur qui m'est fait de plier devant vous, devant la formation la plus solennelle de la Cour, juridiction que j'ai eu la chance, l'immense chance et le bonheur de servir pendant de nombreuses années.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>300.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>305.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cela étant dit, et je voulais le dire, Monsieur le Président, je diviserai ma pédoirie en deux parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>305.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>317.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>J'exposerai tout d'abord le contexte spécifique norvégien relatif à la protection de l'enfance, puis je tenterai de répondre aux questions écrites, posées par la Cour et aux arguments de mon adversaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>317.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>328.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il existe bien un contexte tout à fait spécifique à la Norvège, et d'ailleurs aussi aux autres pays scandinaves, que l'arrêt de la Chambre n'a pas pris en compte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>328.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>335.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce contexte, cette spécificité a fait l'objet de nombreuses critiques, au niveau international comme national.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>335.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>346.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les prises de position de plusieurs organisations internationales et de la société civile norvégienne, n'en déplaise au gouvernement défendeur, semblent révéler un sérieux problème systémique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>346.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>351.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le système norvégien de protection de l'enfance est bien sous surveillance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>351.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>378.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Au niveau international, je voudrais relever tout d'abord la position des Nations unies, la position en particulier du Comité des droits de l'enfant et des Nations unies, qui, dans le cadre, très récemment, en juin 2018, dans le cadre des cinquièmes et sixièmes rapports périodiques combinés de la Norvège, 1er juin 2018, a adopté des conclusions critiques à l'égard du système norvégien.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>378.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>386.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans ses observations finales du 1er juin 2018, le comité a alerté l'attention de la Norvège sur les points suivants en particulier.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>386.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>400.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tout d'abord, le nombre particulièrement élevé de cas signalés de séparation d'enfants de leur famille d'origine, qui apparaissent selon les propres mots du comité comme n'étant pas toujours dans leur meilleur intérêt.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>400.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>406.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et nous savons que c'est un jugement fort dans la bouche d'un comité onusien.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>406.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>419.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ensuite, la diminution parallèlement du nombre d'enfants recevant de l'assistance des services sociaux à domicile, tandis que le nombre de personnes placées à l'extérieur de la famille a parallèlement augmenté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>419.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>431.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le comité a recommandé à la Norvège de revoir de fond en comble ces pratiques actuelles en matière de placement extra-familial, de privation des droits parentaux et de limitation des droits de contact.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>431.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>445.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>De revoir les procédures pour retirer les enfants en cas d'urgence et de prévoir une approche plus sensible et adaptée aux enfants, qui est aussi un jugement particulièrement fort de la part d'un comité des Nations unies.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>445.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>471.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce rapport de 2018 fait ensuite, en fait suite à un précédent rapport d'il y a plus de 13 ans de cela, qui date de 2005, dans lequel le comité, dans ses observations finales du 21 septembre 2005, ou paragraphe 24 précisément, s'était déjà inquiété du nombre croissant d'enfants retirés de leur famille et avait déjà rappelé à l'État norvégien l'importance à privilégier la protection du milieu familial naturel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>471.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>476.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est donc un problème qui dure depuis au moins 13 années.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>476.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>499.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pareillement, le comité onusien des droits économiques, sociaux et culturels, dans ses observations finales de 2013, s'était ému de la problématique et avait recommandé à l'État norvégien de prendre les mesures pour identifier et traiter les causes sous-jacentes du problème et surtout de redoubler d'efforts pour fournir aux parents en demande l'assistance et le soutien nécessaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>499.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>507.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je rappelle que Mme Loben a elle-même fait la demande d'assistance pour le résultat que l'on connaît.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>507.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>515.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais c'est surtout en Europe, au sein même du Conseil de l'Europe, que les critiques se sont faites les plus vives, les plus virulentes, voire les plus violentes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>515.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>524.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'Assemblée parlementaire du Conseil de l'Europe a récemment adopté un rapport particulièrement critique et virulent contre la Norvège en particulier.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>524.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>545.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le rapport du rapporteur parlementaire Valerio Ghilacci joint à la procédure intitulée Un équilibre à maintenir entre l'intérêt de l'enfant et le besoin de rapprocher les familles, ainsi qu'une résolution adressée aux Etats membres du Conseil de l'Europe, dont la Norvège, ont été adoptées le 28 juin 2018, soit très récemment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>545.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>551.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En Assemblée plénière, et je tiens à le souligner, à une très large majorité, seulement deux votent contre.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>551.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>556.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Une parlementaire hollandaise et un parlementaire italien ont voté contre seulement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>556.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>576.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce qui prouve de manière incontestable, contrairement aux allégations de l'État défendeur, c'est qu'il y a bien un consensus européen large et puissant au sein des Etats du Conseil de l'Europe sur la manière dont l'État est censé intervenir dans ce type d'affaires et sur les obligations qui pèsent sur lui.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>576.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>584.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce rapport, contre lequel vous noterez que l'État défendeur, bien embarrassé, ne s'étend pas du tout, dénonce les pratiques suivantes en Norvège.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>584.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>591.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le manque, premièrement, le manque de clarté des motifs dans les décisions de retrait, d'adoption et de placement d'enfants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>591.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>603.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le rapport relève que les avocats et les autres professionnels dénoncent l'utilisation des motifs beaucoup trop vagues, beaucoup trop flous, qui laissent la porte ouverte à l'arbitraire dans la prise des décisions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>603.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>610.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ces motifs flous sont le préjudice émotionnel futur possible.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>610.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>617.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Non seulement c'est un préjudice émotionnel qui est possible, donc on n'en est même pas sûr, mais il est possible dans le futur.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>617.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>620.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous laisse apprécier le flou du concept.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>620.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>630.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Incapacité à réconforter un enfant, manque de base de capacité parentale sans autre détail, laissant ainsi la place à l'arbitraire dans les prises de décisions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>630.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>638.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le rapport dénonce, deuxièmement, l'extrême difficulté de contester une ordonnance de placement devant les tribunaux norvégiens.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>638.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>662.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Paragraphe 23 du rapport, le rapport souligne qu'environ 90% des cas, des demandes de placement formulées par les services sociaux, 90% des cas, ces demandes formulées par les services sociaux sont accordées par les bureaux des affaires sociales compétentes territorialement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>662.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>672.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et dans 90% des cas également, les recours dirigés contre les décisions des bureaux des affaires sociales sont enterrinés.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>672.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>696.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce qui contredit là, frontalement, les statistiques avancées, mais d'ailleurs non étayées par le gouvernement, au paragraphe 128 de ses observations finales du 25 septembre 2018, dans lesquelles il affirme avoir été informé par le ministère des Enfants et de l'égalité qu'en 2017, 34% des demandes d'annulation des ordonnances de placement avaient été révoquées.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>696.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>706.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On ne vous produit pas ce document qui est essentiellement en langue norvégienne, ce qui ne me permet pas d'en vérifier son exactitude.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>706.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>713.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Troisième point du rapport qui est dénoncé, ce sont les droits de visite extrêmement limités peu après la naissance, et j'y reviendrai dans plus de détails un peu plus tard.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>713.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>731.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En effet, le rapport évoque les temps de visite excessivement courts, qui est aussi entre 2h, 4 à 6 fois par an, soit 8 à 12 heures par an de temps de visite avec votre enfant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>731.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>749.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ainsi que les conditions des droits de visite qui sont souvent supervisées pour en conclure avec des droits aussi courts et aussi rares et dans de telles conditions, tout est réuni pour que la mère naturelle ne puisse jamais être réunie avec son enfant, car le seul passage du temps, on le sait bien, change inexorablement l'intérêt supérieur de l'enfant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>749.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>765.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En conclusion, le rapport n'est pas très optimiste, puisqu'il conclut, il estime que malgré une précédente recommandation de l'Assemblée parlementaire du Conseil de l'Europe de 2015, la situation a en fait empiré.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>765.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>772.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les pratiques abusives de placement et d'adoption d'enfants n'ont fait en fait qu'augmenter, et notamment en Norvège.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>772.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>775.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sur le plan national, la situation n'est pas meilleure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>775.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>799.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Au fin de participer à l'élaboration des rapports périodiques devant les Nations unies, l'Institut national norvégien des droits de l'homme a attiré l'attention du comité des droits de l'enfant sur un rapport récent de Save the Children Norway, qui conclut que les autorités norvégiennes n'agissaient pas toujours d'une manière adaptée aux enfants dans les affaires de placement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>799.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>816.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Plusieurs médias internationaux, en particulier la BBC anglaise, comme Nationaux, il y a dans la salle des journalistes ainsi que la télévision norvégienne aux abords de cette salle, alertent régulièrement sur cette situation et tentent de sensibiliser l'opinion publique au problème.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>816.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>852.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pas plus tard que hier, j'ai appris, hier le 16 octobre, j'ai appris que dans l'un des principaux journaux d'Aggblet, un article était paru amplement commenté sur l'affaire Loebben et qui démontrait de manière assez inquiétante, qui révélait en fait une discussion, un fil de discussion sur un réseau social, Facebook, pour ne pas le citer, entre la mère adoptive dans l'affaire Loebben et la chef locale des services sociaux, qui révélait une proximité très douteuse.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>852.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>858.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Avec votre autorisation, Monsieur le Président, je me propose même de vous le livrer, de vous le produire par une note en délibéré.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>858.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>862.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La société civile norvégienne a également exprimé ses graves préoccupations à ce sujet.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>862.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>869.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Une pétition a été signée par 200 experts norvégiens travaillant dans le domaine de la protection de l'enfance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>869.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>877.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Psychologues, avocats, psychiatres, travailleurs sociaux, spécialistes de la protection de l'enfance, ils nous disent tous la même chose.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>877.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>880.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ils ont officiellement soumis cette pétition au gouvernement norvégien en 2016.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>880.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>883.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Aucune réponse n'a été apportée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>884.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>893.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sur les réponses aux questions posées par votre cours ainsi qu'aux observations de mon adversaire, je ferai valoir les réponses suivantes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>893.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>901.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sur l'objet de l'affaire, votre compétence rationnée, matérielle, qui est un élément important dans ce dossier.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>901.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>910.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'Etat défendeur conteste la compétence de la Grande Chambre à examiner les procédures qui précèdent la décision de retrait ainsi que la décision d'adoption.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>910.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>918.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il estime que les griefs dirigés contre ces procédures sont soit irrecevables, soit en tout état de cause, hors champ de votre compétence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>918.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>920.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A cela, je réponds.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>920.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>935.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Premièrement, si la requête initiale ne concernait en effet que le retrait de l'autorité parentale et de l'adoption, elle se plaignait bien et même surtout des décisions antérieures ayant conduit aux mesures de retrait et d'adoption critiquées.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>935.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>988.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Deuxièmement, votre cours est une juridiction internationale, de pleine juridiction pour ce qui concerne l'interprétation de la Convention et de ses protocoles et son application, ce qui signifie que vous avez bien le pouvoir d'examiner toute l'affaire dans sa globalité, même si votre constat de violation ou de non-violation porte sur une partie du dossier, et souvent c'est la fin du dossier, ce qui signifie que votre cours peut et doit nécessairement examiner la première procédure de placement dans la mesure où, comme l'exprime si bien la juge dissident, cette première procédure a inexorablement forgé la décision d'adoption et de retrait de l'autorité parentale en favorisant le passage du temps et en influençant donc sur la notion d'intérêt supérieur du mineur au moment de décider de son adoption.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>988.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>996.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dire le contraire reviendrait pour vous à vous amputer d'une partie de vos prérogatives et de votre contrôle européen.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>996.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1002.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Enfin, la jurisprudence de la Cour sur la question est tout à fait claire et elle est sans ambiguïté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1002.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1012.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Vous avez déjà répondu dans un certain nombre d'affaires sur cette question quand les procédures en cause sont, comme en l'espèce, intimement liées.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1012.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1045.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je m'appuie en particulier sur l'affaire Zou contre Italie, 2014, particulièrement bien rédigée et claire, où la Cour a constaté une violation de l'article 8 au sujet de la procédure de la déclaration d'adoptabilité de l'enfant, mais compte tenu des mesures prises ou plutôt des mesures non prises dans le cadre des décisions précédentes de placement et, en particulier, le manque de visite, de droits de contact entre Madame Zou et sa fille.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1045.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1055.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous renvoie aux affaires Akini Bossoum contre Italie, RMS contre Espagne, KAB contre Espagne, Johansen contre Norvège, 1993.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1055.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1061.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cela fait 25 ans que vous vous êtes prononcés sur cette question de compétence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1061.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1071.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Johansen, vous l'avez dit très clairement, vous avez expressément établi un lien entre les mesures de placement et la mesure d'adoption.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1071.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1076.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je crois que vous pouvez en tirer les conséquences juridiques sur votre compétence rationnelle et matérielle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1076.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1091.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sur la marge d'appréciation et sur l'étendue de votre contrôle, c'est là aussi l'un des enjeux majeurs dans ce dossier, puisque l'Etat défendeur, avec ses alliés, insiste, pousse pour limiter votre contrôle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1091.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1117.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour rappel, il estime que la déclaration politique de Copenhague ainsi que la déclaration politique de Brighton, adoptée d'ailleurs sous la présidence, et ce n'est peut-être pas un hasard, est danoise et anglaise, doit trouver, qui souligne l'importance du principe de subsidiarité, doit trouver une traduction juridique dans vos décisions afin de limiter votre contrôle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1117.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1130.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je note d'ailleurs que dans votre avis, en plénière et par le touchement de votre bureau, le 19 février 2018, sur le projet de déclaration, vous avez à juste titre rappelé la définition du principe de subsidiarité.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1130.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1142.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Vous avez estimé que le principe de subsidiarité ne devait être compris que comme la responsabilité qui incombe aux Etats de s'acquitter de leurs obligations sous le contrôle de la Cour.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1142.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1156.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le gouvernement estime ensuite, de manière assez audacieuse, qu'en l'absence d'un consensus européen sur les modalités et sur l'opportunité d'intervention de l'Etat en matière familiale, la marge d'appréciation des Etats doit être élargie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1156.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1165.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il estime qu'il en est de même lorsqu'il s'agit d'affaires comme selon lui en l'espèce, touchant à des questions éthiques ou morales sensibles.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1165.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1194.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il cite alors les affaires Gardez-Hautes contre Rium Uni, 2007, qui n'a strictement rien à voir, cela concerne l'accès à un traitement médical expérimental aux Etats-Unis pour un enfant mourant, l'affaire Paradiso et Campanelli contre Italie, qui porte sur les effets juridiques à apporter à la gestation pour autrui, et Pario contre Italie, 2015, qui concerne l'interdiction de donner des embryons acquis par PMA à la recherche scientifique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1194.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1196.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Rien à voir avec l'effet de l'espèce.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1196.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1216.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En réalité, ce que le gouvernement souhaite, sous couvert d'une responsabilité partagée dans le système de protection de la Convention, c'est de réduire votre contrôle, de réduire le contrôle européen dans les affaires d'article 8, à la seule erreur manifeste d'appréciation, c'est-à-dire un contrôle des plus limités.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1216.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1232.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et je note d'ailleurs, avec une certaine inquiétude, une affaire anglaise assez récente, l'affaire NDD contre le Royaume-Uni, où la Cour a abandonné, à mon avis, un peu trop facilement son contrôle européen.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1232.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1236.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Heureusement, c'est une jurisprudence isolée en matière d'immigration.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1236.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1243.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le gouvernement souhaite vous faire appliquer aux affaires portant sur l'article 8 la doctrine de la quatrième instance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1243.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1250.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et je pense que la quatrième instance n'est pas la marge d'appréciation, ce sont deux choses différentes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1250.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1255.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Quatrième instance est uniquement applicable à l'article 6, à mon sens.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1255.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1264.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, nous pensons au contraire que le principe de subsidiarité, la marge d'appréciation des Etats membres et la doctrine de la quatrième instance ne sont pas incompatibles.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1264.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1277.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et qu'au contraire, votre jurisprudence ancienne et constante est tout à fait cohérente et satisfaisante en ce qui concerne la place de chacun, la place de l'Etat qui lui est réservée dans le mécanisme de protection de la Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1277.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1279.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et ce, pour plusieurs raisons.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1279.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1296.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous renvoie à mon mémoire pour la définition de la marge d'appréciation et de la doctrine de la quatrième instance, qui a d'ailleurs été habillée par un juge de cette composition, le juge Degha Etta, dans son opinion dissidente dans l'affaire YC contre le Royaume-Uni, qui est très convaincante.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1296.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1319.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour plusieurs raisons, parce que la Cour ne peut pas se contenter de contrôler uniquement le volet procédural d'une affaire relative à l'article 8 sans contrôler les motifs adoptés par le juge interne, sans faire de mise en balance des intérêts, sans contrôler la proportionnalité de la mesure et donc de rentrer au fond du dossier afin de contrôler les motifs adoptés par les juges nationaux.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1319.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1333.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La deuxième raison, c'est qu'en cette matière si particulière, il s'agit d'un domaine dans lequel la demande de protection contre les interférences arbitraires de l'Etat est encore plus forte que d'habitude et la marge se réduit inexorablement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1333.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1340.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Plus l'ingérence de l'Etat est intense et plus la marge d'appréciation se réduit et plus l'examen de la Cour est méticuleux.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1340.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1351.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Vous l'avez d'ailleurs rappelé dans une affaire norvégienne qui faisait partie du groupe des neuf affaires communiquées dans l'affaire Janssen contre Norvège, 6 septembre 2018 à peine.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1351.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1363.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La troisième raison, c'est qu'il y a bien un consensus européen de très longue date sur la question des obligations de l'Etat en cas d'ingérence dans le droit au respect de la vie familiale des individus.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1363.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1370.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et, pareillement, j'estime que le gouvernement s'égare lorsqu'il estime que l'affaire porte sur des questions morales ou éthiques.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1370.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1384.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Jamais vous n'avez considéré qu'une affaire, somme toute classique, d'article 8 concerne des questions morales ou éthiques qui devraient libérer, qui devraient donner une marge d'appréciation supérieure, plus large à l'Etat membre.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1384.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1388.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est même le contraire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1388.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1397.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En définitive, sur la marge d'appréciation, j'invite la Grande Chambre à ne pas appliquer cette doctrine de la quatrième instance dans les affaires d'article 8.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1397.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1422.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La quatrième instance, à mon sens, ne s'applique qu'à l'article 6, qui n'est qu'une disposition de nature purement procédurale, un article qui n'implique pas d'examiner la proportionnalité du procès et qui a pour seule limite l'erreur manifeste d'appréciation, au risque sinon de dénaturer le régime juridique, la nature, la dynamique interne des articles 8, 9, 10 et 11.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1422.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1435.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sur la justification de la mesure de retrait d'adoption, nous sommes d'accord avec le rappel des principes jurisprudentiels de l'arrêt de chambre, mais nous en avons une appréciation dans le cas d'espèces radicalement opposée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1435.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1446.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sur la vulnérabilité de X, la vulnérabilité particulière affirmée de l'enfant, elle est toute relative, elle est extrêmement à relativiser.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1446.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1467.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Outre le fait que cette vulnérabilité a été fortement contestée par les éléments du dossier, ainsi que par une juridiction, la cour d'appel dans son arrêt du 19 août 2009, j'ai en tête évidemment le rapport de la sage-femme, la chef sage-femme du 13 octobre 2008, diligentée d'ailleurs à la demande des services sociaux.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1467.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1495.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Force est de constater que si l'enfant souffrait d'un retard moteur et comportemental les premiers jours, les premières semaines de sa vie, il s'est toutefois très rapidement stabilisé, il s'est développé, stabilisé normalement au bout de deux mois seulement, comme le relève le rapport du BUP de décembre 2008, qui constate un développement tout à fait normal de l'enfant et une amélioration très nette de son infection une fois qu'il a pris son traitement médicamenteux.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1495.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1517.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si l'expert psychologue BS et la thérapeute familiale EWA, nommée par les services sociaux dans le rapport du 20 février 2010, ont conclu que X avait besoin de stabilité, de calme et de réconfort, alors pour ma part je ne connais aucun enfant de cet âge qui n'aurait pas besoin de calme, de stabilité ou de réconfort.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1517.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1526.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je n'en connais aucun qui aurait besoin d'une instabilité, d'un inconfort et d'une excitation permanente.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1526.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1551.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Finalement, ces expertises n'ont fait essentiellement, et l'ont réduit à leur substrat ces expertises, que dire que X était fatigué et nerveux à chaque visite, qu'il pleurait souvent, qu'il avait du mal à s'endormir et que cette anxiété, je cite, pouvait affecter sa capacité future à apprendre et à se développer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1551.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1556.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous laisse apprécier le flou d'une telle interprétation dans laquelle vous pouvez mettre tout ce que vous voulez.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1556.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1568.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous estimons pour notre part que ces motifs qui sont particulièrement vagues et faibles dans leur substance ne peuvent servir de fondement pertinent et suffisant pour justifier une telle mesure extrême.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1568.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1599.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Force est observée en outre que le test, le fameux test ASQSE, qui est un simple outil de dépistage téléchargeable sur Internet, qui est rempli en quelques minutes et qui a été rempli en quelques minutes uniquement par les services sociaux, uniquement par les services sociaux, le réponse donnée par la mère adoptive uniquement, et dont on ne sait pas grand-chose de son sérieux scientifique, et dont surtout ni la requérante, ni son conseil n'en ont obtenu une copie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1599.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1605.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous n'avons jamais obtenu ce test qui a eu une place centrale dans ce dossier.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1605.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1622.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et même ce test-là reconnaît que X a un an, le 16 octobre 2009, je me réfère au rapport médical à l'annexe numéro 63 du gouvernement, révèle un développement normal de l'enfant à un an.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1622.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1636.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sur l'incapacité éducative parentale permanente, permanente de la première requérante, mais non seulement de ma cliente, mais de toute sa famille, qui est derrière moi, elle est aussi plus que relative.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1636.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1671.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Outre le fait que cette supposée incapacité est aussi contestée par les nombreux éléments du dossier, le rapport de la sage-femme, l'avis de son psychologue privé, et aussi contestée tout simplement par les faits, puisque sa situation a évolué très positivement, j'observe que, par principe, la Cour nous dit que l'absence de compétences et d'expérience dans l'éducation des enfants, quelles qu'en soient les raisons, ne peut être considérée en soi comme un motif légitime pour restreindre l'autorité parentale ou maintenir un enfant dans un établissement public.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1671.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1679.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est vous qui l'avez dit dans l'affaire Kotschirov et Sergeyeva contre Russie, 29 mars 2016, paragraphe 106.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1679.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1712.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>J'observe que les formules retenues par les expertises MS du 3 mars 2000 et du rapport de BSEWA précités, à savoir le manque de confiance dans la mère, le manque grave des capacités requises dans le rôle de mère, on ne sait pas trop ce que c'est, les problèmes de régulation émotionnelle, on ne sait pas non plus trop ce que c'est, les compétences parentales de base inadéquates, on ne sait pas trop ce que c'est, sont particulièrement vagues, car on peut y mettre finalement tout ce que l'on veut.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1712.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1718.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cela a été dénoncé, comme je le disais en introduction, dans le rapport Giletschi, avec force.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1718.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1731.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>J'observe surtout que les autorités n'ont pas tenu compte de l'évolution positive de ma cliente, alors que la Cour considère habituellement que c'est le minimum à attendre des autorités pour voir si la situation de la famille s'est améliorée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1731.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1741.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Aujourd'hui, Mme Le Pen est mariée, elle est stabilisée, elle a un domicile, elle a deux autres enfants qui n'ont jamais posé problème.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1741.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1749.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Une enquête municipale du 21 mars 2012 n'a rien révélé de préoccupant, au contraire, le rapport était plutôt positif.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1749.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1760.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le rejet de la demande d'expertise, parce qu'elle a formulé une demande d'expertise, est assez contradictoire avec l'appréciation du gouvernement auquel ses capacités sont définitivement...</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1760.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1763.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est fini, Mme Le Pen.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1763.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1769.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous estimons que vos capacités parentales sont pour toujours inadaptées.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1769.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1773.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cela ressemble un peu à une peine capitale en matière civile.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1773.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1792.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On comprend mal comment une telle disparité d'appréciation est possible et on comprend mal comment les juridictions ont pu considérer qu'elle était incapable de s'occuper de X en 2012, alors qu'elle était mère d'un autre enfant à cette époque, et que, surtout à cette date, X n'était plus considéré comme particulièrement vulnérable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1792.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1823.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sur l'absence de lien psychologique, et là, nous sommes au coeur du dossier, l'absence de lien psychologique entre la mère et l'enfant qui a constitué le motif principal dans cette affaire, elle est, cette justification, particulièrement perverse, car elle relève directement de la responsabilité de l'Etat norvégien, comme dans d'autres affaires norvégiennes, et comme le relève le rapport Ghilici, les droits de contact ont été, en l'espèce, particulièrement limités.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1823.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1832.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Très tôt, le 2 mars 2009, on décide de ne donner à la mère que 6 fois 2 heures par an, 12 heures par an, à 5 mois et une semaine.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1832.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1839.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les autorités décident à 5 mois et une semaine que cette mère n'aura que 12 heures par an.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1839.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1849.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Hormis une courte période d'amélioration, le 22 avril 2010, à un an et demi, les autorités décident de ne donner définitivement que 4 fois 2 heures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1849.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1850.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est encore pire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1850.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1852.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>8 heures par an.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1852.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1853.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors j'ai fait le calcul.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1853.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1859.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans l'année, il y a 8 760 heures, 365 jours.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1859.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1862.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On a donné à ma cliente que 8 heures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1862.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1871.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>8 heures divisé par 8 760, cela donne un ratio de 0,0009 % de temps.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1871.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1883.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On a donné 0,0009 % de temps à Mme Lobène pour qu'elle construise un lien psychologique avec son fils.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1883.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1888.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Autrement dit, on a truqué le jeu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1888.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1894.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On a pipé les dés pour ne laisser aucune chance à Mme Lobène de faire quoi que ce soit.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1894.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1899.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En réalité, cette absence de lien, c'est ça qui est intéressant, a été voulue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1899.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1914.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Elle a été programmée dès le début de la procédure par les autorités nationales, qu'ils expliquent d'ailleurs très clairement dans leurs observations finales, je les en remercie presque pour leur transparence, du 25 septembre 2018.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1914.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1931.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En réponse aux observations de la République tchèque, qui voit dans cette limitation un problème systémique, le gouvernement norvégien nous explique et le revendique que nous avons pris la décision politique il y a longtemps de favoriser les adoptions au placement à long terme.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1931.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1940.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et nous mettons tout en oeuvre pour que cette décision politique fonctionne.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1940.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1943.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Paragraphe 121 est suivant des observations finales.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1943.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1949.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais surtout, le Royaume de Norvège l'admet au paragraphe 118 de ses observations finales.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1949.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1967.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il souligne que lorsqu'il est présumé, lorsqu'il est attendu, when it is expected, que le placement sera à long terme, alors le niveau de contact est réduit, à sa plus simple expression, dans le but de faciliter l'intégration de l'enfant dans sa famille d'accueil.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1967.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1990.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cela veut dire que dès le début de la procédure, sans même donner une chance à la requérante, on limite à l'extrême les droits de contact dans le but de favoriser son intégration avec la famille d'accueil, dans le but de favoriser l'attachement psychologique de cet enfant avec sa nouvelle famille d'accueil.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1990.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2001.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est ici, sous l'angle des obligations positives, que réside, à mon avis, la violation grave, très grave de l'article 8, car il est démontré qu'aucune chance n'est donnée à la mère pour récupérer son enfant.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2001.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2013.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est ici que les cartes du jeu apparaissent truquées pour Madame Lobène, favorisant ainsi, d'ailleurs, l'aliénation de l'enfant vis-à-vis de sa mère biologique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2013.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2018.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vois que le temps avance, donc je vais essayer d'aller un peu plus vite.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2018.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2029.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et puis, comme on aime les difficultés dans ce dossier, comme si cela ne suffisait pas, à cette difficulté, on en a rajouté une autre.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2029.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2051.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les conditions d'accueil dans lesquelles les contacts se sont déroulés, toujours en présence de la mère adoptive, toujours, même pas une fois qu'elle est sortie, même si elle ne soit pas sortie, avec un à deux agents administratifs, dont cette femme dont on me dit dans la presse la veille qu'elle avait un lien d'amitié avec la mère adoptive.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2051.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2054.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je tiens à le souligner.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2054.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2077.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Chez la mère adoptive, quelquefois, avec la mère adoptive, chez elle, dans son domaine, et la plupart du temps dans une chambre assez froide des services sociaux, où les tensions existantes, habituelles et compréhensibles dans ce type d'affaires ont constitué une circonstance aggravante pour ma cliente.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2077.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2085.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>De plus, celle-ci s'est toujours plaint régulièrement d'un harcèlement de la part des services sociaux, d'avoir été harcelé, même menacé par la mère adoptive.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2085.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2088.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En réponse, les autorités n'ont rien fait pour améliorer cette situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2088.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2096.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Elles ont uniquement changé une seule fois le superviseur et lui ont proposé une seule fois de lui payer un thérapeute.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2096.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2106.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors, moi, je veux bien, sauf qu'à cette époque, elle en avait déjà un, le psychologue KM, qui a été auditionné par la Cour d'appel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2106.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2111.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Elles ont en revanche systématiquement refusé qu'elle vienne avec un proche.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2111.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2115.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce n'est pas moi qui le dis, c'est eux, paragraphe 109 de leurs observations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2115.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2118.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ou alors qu'elle vienne avec son psychologue KM.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2118.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2124.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Elles ont refusé que les contacts se fassent chez elles, alors que c'était ça, en fait, la solution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2124.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2129.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et elles ont encore refusé que la mère adoptive sorte ne serait-ce qu'une fois, ou elles ont encore refusé d'augmenter les contacts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2129.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2147.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En définitive, alors qu'aucune solution alternative n'a été envisagée, telle qu'une assistance éducative en milieu ouvert, c'est-à-dire un placement chez madame avec un passage régulier des services sociaux, les autorités nationales ont tout fait pour favoriser le lien d'attachement avec la mère.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2147.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2159.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les juges internes ont en effet pu, en se basant sur une interprétation pervertie de la théorie en psychologie infantile dite de l'attachement, élaborée dans les années 60, prononcer la parole à la mère.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2160.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2164.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Maître, pardonnez-moi, pourrais-je vous demander de conclure, s'il vous plaît?</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2164.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2164.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je conclue donc.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2165.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2167.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>dans deux petites minutes, M. le Président.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2167.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2169.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Elles ont pu prononcer l'adoption définitive.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2169.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2190.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je dis pervertie parce que, alors que cette théorie qui n'a pas évolué depuis les années 60 implique de manière fondamentale la mise en place d'une proximité physique répétée de qualité pour développer un lien d'attachement, les autorités ont appliqué cette théorie, oui, à la lettre, mais pas pour ma cliente.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2190.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2192.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ils l'ont appliquée pour la mère adoptive.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2192.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2196.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>J'en finirai sur l'absence d'appréciation à long terme.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2196.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2209.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je crois qu'il y a aussi un problème dans ce dossier puisque, vous l'avez répété, dans l'affaire Janssen très récemment, vous avez reconnu le caractère impératif de la prise en compte des effets à long terme d'une séparation qui n'a pas du tout été le cas.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2209.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2211.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour toutes ces raisons, M. le Président,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2211.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2222.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>mesdames et messieurs les juges de la Cour, je vous demande de constater une violation de l'article 8, paragraphe 1 de la Convention et d'entrer en voie de condamnation à l'Etat à l'égard de l'Etat norvégien. Merci.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2223.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2225.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci, merci, maître.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2225.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2228.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I call Mr. Sejersted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2228.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2228.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please, you have the floor.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2232.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2233.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2233.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2237.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, members of the court,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2237.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2242.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>the case has been brought before this court by the first applicant, the biological mother.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2242.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2246.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But the main person in this case is the child, the boy.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2246.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2253.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the basic question should be, have his rights been violated under Article 8?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2253.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2255.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The answer is no.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2255.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2262.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the contrary, his rights, his best interest has been protected.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2262.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2268.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The national decision under review is, first and foremost, the city court judgment of February 2012.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2268.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2272.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>At that point in time, the boy was 3 1⁄2 years old.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2272.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2283.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And because of serious neglect at a very early age, he had been taken into foster care and had formed a strong attachment to his foster parents with whom he had been living for almost his entire life.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2283.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2294.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>He had had continuous contact with the biological mother, but they had not established close bonds, and their relationship was not developing in a positive way.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2294.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2297.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cases like these are always complex and controversial.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2297.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2323.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But in this concrete case of the diligent and extensive national judicial processes, the city court found that it would clearly be in the boy's interest to be allowed to continue living with the parents that he himself considered to be his family and to be allowed the security, the stability, and indeed the dignity of being formally recognized as part of that family by way of adoption.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2323.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2328.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This was not a violation of his right to private and family life under Article 8.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2328.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2329.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the contrary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2329.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2346.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And because it was not a breach of his rights, then in a case like this, it cannot at the same time be a breach of the rights of the biological mother because the paramount and overriding concern has to be the best interest of the child.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2346.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2353.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The case has been heard by a chamber of this court, and we have a majority judgment and a minority dissenting opinion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2353.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2358.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These are two very different texts reflecting very different approaches to the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2358.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2362.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The main argument of the Norwegian government is very simple.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2362.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2375.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We asked the Grand Chamber to follow the approach of the chamber majority, which in our view is not only correct, but indeed exemplary, both as regards legal interpretation and actual application of the law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2375.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2397.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And we invite the Grand Chamber to reaffirm your existing case law on what we consider to be the two most important legal questions of the case, namely first, the margin of appreciation in cases like these, and secondly, the position and the content of the principle of the best interest of the child in cases under Article 8 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2397.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2430.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In contrast, we respectfully but strongly advise against the approach of the minority, in particular their attempt to do a so-called forensic examination of the facts, which is not only contrary to the fourth instance doctrine of this court, which we will argue applies also under Article 8, but would also mean the risk of making the review arbitrary by trying to reassess facts that were firmly established by the national courts many years ago.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2430.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2434.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A few words on the scope of the case before the Grand Chamber.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2434.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2447.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As the chamber will know, the application concerns the decision made by the Social Welfare Board in December 2011, which was upheld after full review by the city court in February 2012.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2447.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2456.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The High Court and the Supreme Court refused to give leave to appeal, and the judgment became final in October 2012.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2456.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2471.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The proceedings and reasons given by the Social Welfare Board and the city court are described in detail in the chamber judgment, and the majority there has correctly focused its review first on the procedure and then on the reasons given by the city court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2471.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2483.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the most relevant point in time in this case is February 2012, and this is the situation as assessed by the city court at that specific time.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2483.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2501.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is obvious, but it still needs to be emphasized because both the applicant and my honorable colleague and the chamber minority and several of the third-party interventions also go into detailed argument about what happened three and a half years earlier when the boy was first taken into public care in 2008.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2501.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2503.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On this, we would like to make two points.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2503.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2511.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, that no violation of Article 8 took place in the first phase of the case between the years 2008 and 2011.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2511.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2522.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the contrary, it's well documented in the case that the boy suffered from very serious neglect and that the mother was not capable of taking care of him and that he had to be placed in foster care.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2522.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2532.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this was established in no less than two extensive processes before the Welfare Board and the city court and the high court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2532.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2545.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second, that of course, this first phase, the first three years of the case are part of the factual background, and it's necessary in order to understand the facts of the case, but it is still of limited legal relevance to the assessment that the chamber has to make.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2545.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2557.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The judgment from the first phase, and there are altogether five judgment, are not included in the application to the court, and they could not have been since national remedies were not exhausted, and of course, the time limit has long ago expired.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2557.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2559.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So they are not formally part of the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2559.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2575.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But even more important is the substantive point, that when you come to the year 2012 and the actual assessment in real time that the city court had to make at that time, then it was the situation of the parties in 2012 that was the relevant factor in the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2575.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2578.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that is what you have to assess as well.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2579.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2587.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will then make a few remarks on the legal and factual position of the individuals that are involved in this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2587.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2589.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The first applicant is the biological mother.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2589.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2596.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And seen from her perspective, this is a case about her right to protection of family life under Article 8.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2596.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2608.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this case, life with a biological son, which has not materialized, as the boy was taken into care when he was three weeks old, and they have not lived together since.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2608.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2624.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So her claim must, of course, be assessed under Article 8, but it's not so much a claim to reestablish an existing family life as rather to assert biological right, even under circumstances where there's little or no actual attachment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2624.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2628.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Must be added that in this case, there's no biological father.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2628.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2634.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The mother did originally name a father, but he was ruled out by DNA test, and she has not named any other.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2634.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2643.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And because of this action on her part, there's never been the alternative option, which would, of course, have been that the boy could have been cared for by his paternal biological family.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2644.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2650.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Then there's the person who has been, as he should, at the center of the case, the boy.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2650.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2655.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>He also has a right under Article 8 to protection of his family life.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2655.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2657.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But which family life is that?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2657.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2659.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Is it the biological bond to the mother?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2659.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2672.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or is it the only family life that he has ever known, with the persons who have taken care of him since he was three weeks old, and who are, in his mind, his actual parents?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2672.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2680.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Furthermore, he has the right not only to protection of family life, but also to protection of private life, including his best interest.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2680.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2688.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And these concepts are not necessarily always in line, though they have to be reconciled in the case law of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2688.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2693.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Finally, we also have the adoptive parents, who are today his legal guardians.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2693.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2697.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They are the ones who probably knows his needs and interests best.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2697.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2707.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Since they're not formally a party to the case, I will not speak anymore on their position, but we do invite the Grand Chamber to study their intervention with care.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2707.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2714.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this constellation of parties, the basic question is who speaks for the boy, formally and actually?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2714.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2718.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Who can claim to know and represent his best interest?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2718.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2725.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As the Grand Chamber is well aware, the biological mother has brought the case, both on her own behalf and on behalf of the boy.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2725.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2730.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And in the Chamber judgment, her claim to locust standy on behalf of the boy was accepted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2730.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2734.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With this, the government respectfully disagrees.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2734.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2740.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the memorial, we have made the argument why the mother should not be given locust standy on behalf of the boy.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2740.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2755.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In our view, the specific criteria in the judgment of Scosari and Giunta versus Italy are to be seen as an exemption, which relies on certain criteria, and these criteria are not fulfilled, as we argue, in this specific case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2755.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2771.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the Grand Chamber should be very reluctant to widen the scope of persons granted locust standy to represent children without being either the legal guardian of the child or without the explicit consent of the child concerned.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2771.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2773.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's, again, the formal argument.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2773.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2776.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then there's the substantive argument.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2776.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2788.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Regardless of whether the mother is given locust standy on behalf of the boy or not, she is simply not in a position to give his perspective and present his best interest before this court, and she has not really tried.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2788.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2795.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>When you examine the arguments put forward by her representative, they are about the situation and position and rights of the mother.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2795.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2800.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's not an attempt to describe or analyze or represent the best interest of the boy.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2802.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2808.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I turn then to the margin of appreciation in cases like these under Article 8.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2808.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2815.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In our view, the margin of appreciation was correctly applied by the chamber majority, and I will only add a few supplementary points.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2815.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2846.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, this is the first Grand Chamber case on child welfare measures and Article 8 since the adoption of the Copenhagen Declaration in April this year, in which the member states of the Council of Europe unanimously welcomed the further development of the principle of subsidiarity and the doctrine of the margin of appreciation by the court, and underlined that, and I quote, there may be a range of different but legitimate solutions which could each be compatible with the Convention depending on the context.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2846.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2850.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that is precisely the point in this case in our view.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2850.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2865.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And indeed, the Norwegian government finds it somewhat surprising that several of the countries that have adopted the Copenhagen Declaration and that in other areas are among the first to speak up for subsidiarity have intervened against Norway in this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2865.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2890.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We will not speculate on the grounds for this, but we would like to point out that the most interesting thing about some of these third-party interventions is another point, namely that they illustrate the fact that there's no uniform consensus within the Council of Europe as to the degree and threshold of government intervention in family affairs out of consideration for the best interest of the child.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2890.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2893.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Different countries have different approaches, and this is understandable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2893.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2904.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In an area that's complex and sensitive and where there are different cultural and social traditions and where different democracies have taken different policy solutions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2904.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2906.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But the legal implications are clear.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2906.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2912.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>When there's no European consensus, the national margin of appreciation should be wider.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2912.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2919.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thirdly, we would argue that the margin of appreciation should also be wider when there are competing individual interests at stake.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2919.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2926.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this case, the national court had to strike a balance between the interest of the biological mother and the interest of the child.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2926.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2945.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this is a very challenging task, and it requires a fairly wide margin of professional expertise and discretion and respect for the fact that the concrete balancing act in the concrete case can only best be done in real time and following direct contact with the people concerned.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2945.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2956.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Then we have to square this relatively wide margin of appreciation with the position formulated by this court that in cases concerning adoption, there should be strict scrutiny.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2956.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2958.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>How to reconcile these two?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2958.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2963.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The answer is that, yes, certainly there should be strict scrutiny.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2963.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2974.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But this scrutiny should be directed towards the domestic procedures and towards the reasons given by the national courts, whether they are relevant and sufficient.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2974.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2988.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Strict scrutiny cannot and should not mean a full review of the facts of the case based on the sort of forensic examination that the chamber minority has tried, I would say selectively, to apply.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2988.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2995.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I turn then to the principle of the best interest of the child under Article 8.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2995.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3001.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As the court is well aware, there's no separate article in the European Convention on the rights of the child.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3001.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3013.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And therefore, it has been for many years the duty and obligation of this court to interpret the best interest of the child into Article 8 on protection of private and family life.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3013.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3020.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this has been done by the court in a string of cases, and it was done by the chamber majority in this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3020.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3023.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And we think it was done correctly.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3023.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3046.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And we ask the ground chamber to reaffirm the interpretation on this point made by the majority on these points on the best interest of the child, reflecting to some extent that this is still an evolving area of law and that the need for clarification of interpretation is illustrated both by the minority dissent and several of the third-party interventions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3046.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3051.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the memorial, we have given extensive comments on the interpretation of the case law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3051.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3055.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I will only here highlight three basic points.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3055.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3065.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, that it has been established beyond argument that the best interest of the child is of paramount importance under Article 8.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3065.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3081.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And we invite the ground chamber to expand on the issue of paramount importance and, in particular, in line with the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child and the comments to that convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3081.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3091.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Second, it has been established that in cases concerning child welfare, including adoption, the child's best interest must come before all other considerations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3091.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3095.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This means that it's not only one among other factors, but the overriding concern.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3095.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3106.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, in other words, if there's a conflict between the best interest of the child and the interest of a biological parent, then the best interest of the child must prevail.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3106.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3128.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thirdly, as regard the meaning or content of the best interest, the court has formulated an approach with two elements, starting, of course, with the presumption that it is in general in the child's best interest to live and preserve ties to the biological family, but adding then immediately, unless the family has proved particularly unfit.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3128.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3132.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the concept of particularly unfit is central in the case law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3132.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3150.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this then ties in with the second criteria of the court, which is that it is clearly also in the child's interest to ensure its development in a sound environment, which in this context necessarily means a sound environment elsewhere than with the biological family.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3150.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3169.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To this, the court has, in effect, added a third criterion, which is that when a considerable period of time has passed since the child was originally taken into public care, the interest of the child not to have his or her de facto family situation changed again may override the interest of the parent in seeing the family reunited.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3169.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3179.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So when assessing what's in the best interest of any given child, the courts cannot make general assumptions based, for example, on the importance of biology.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3179.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3194.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They must look concretely on the de facto family situation of the child concerned, and they must make an individual assessment for the specific child at the relevant point in time, which may change over time.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3194.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3210.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And finally, the Grand Chamber should recognize that this concrete and individual assessment can only best be done at the national level by the national courts, based on evidence available in real time and direct contact with the people concerned.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3210.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3218.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I then turn to the application of the law to the case at hand, under which we would argue there should be strict scrutiny by this chamber on two points.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3218.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3225.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, the domestic process, and secondly, the reasons given by the city courts, and some words on each of these.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3225.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3233.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this case, it is uncontested that the domestic processes were extensive and thorough and diligent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3233.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3254.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the chamber judgment, the majority is precise, but relatively brief on this crucial point, and this does not seem to be disputed by the minority, which only briefly and very selectively refer to the national process, and where the main argument instead seems to be a warning against what they call the so-called excessive focus on procedures.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3254.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3269.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Against this background, the Norwegian government must emphasize before the ground chamber both the general importance of national procedures in the case law of this court and the very extensive procedural guarantees that were given in this specific case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3269.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3276.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And furthermore, we would emphasize that the procedural review is closely linked to the issue of substantive review.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3276.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3283.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The better the national process, the stronger the presumption that the facts of the case have been correctly assessed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3283.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3298.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or in other words, the more comprehensive the national domestic process, the higher the threshold should be for the court to set aside the findings of the national courts, except, of course, on points of pure legal interpretation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3298.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3311.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this is important to the case at hand because in this case, the national processes were comprehensive and they lived up to and indeed exceeded any procedural requirements that may flow from the convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3311.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3314.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To just remind the ground chamber on the basic points.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3314.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3321.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, in the first phase of the case, between 2008 and 2010, there were two rounds of judicial review.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3321.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3324.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, there was the judicial review of the emergency decision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3324.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3326.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That was heard by the Social Welfare Board and the city court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3326.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3331.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then there was the review of the permanent decision to take the boy into foster care.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3331.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3334.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That was heard by the Social Welfare Board, the city court, and the high court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3334.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3336.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that was only the first phase.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3336.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3345.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then comes the second phase, which is the one that has been brought before the court between 2011 and 2012, and which is the adoption proceedings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3345.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3354.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And they were heard once again, first by the Social Welfare Board, and then again with full review by the city court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3354.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3360.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In our case, this means that the contested decision was given a full judicial assessment in two rounds.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3360.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3363.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Each time there was an oral hearing lasting three days.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3363.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3370.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They usually start at nine in the morning and last until four in the afternoon, as well as extensive written submissions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3370.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3372.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Each time the whole case file was scrutinized.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3372.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3387.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Each time, 21 witnesses were heard and examined, including the applicant, witnesses called by her lawyers, witnesses called by the welfare authorities, and expert witnesses before the court in psychology and child welfare.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3387.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3394.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And each time the first applicant was represented by legal counsel paid for by the state.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3394.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3400.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This was then appealed afterwards to the high court, which found that the reasons given by the city court were sound and convincing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3400.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3405.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And finally, before the appeals selection committee of the Supreme Court, which held that the appeal could not succeed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3405.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3412.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So in conclusion, this was a national process that can stand up to any level of scrutiny, however strict.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3412.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3424.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this is important in itself, but it's also important as the point of departure for the next phase of the court's review, namely that of the reasons given by the city court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3424.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3436.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The criterion for the review of the national reasons is whether they are relevant and sufficient in order to justify the necessity of the interference under article 8.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3436.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3440.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the Norwegian government holds that the answer is clearly yes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3440.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3450.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The reasons provided were relevant and sufficient, again, by any standard, no matter how strict the scrutiny, no matter what margin or appreciation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3450.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3459.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On this point, we invite the Grand Chamber first to study a note that the reasons given by the Norwegian city court are detailed and extensive.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3459.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3467.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is written in the style that we use in the court in Norway, which is rather elaborate and more so than in many other European countries.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3467.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3483.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We then invite the Grand Chamber to study how the review was done by the chamber majority, which is indeed strict scrutiny, examining the reasoning of the city court point by point against the criteria established in the case law of the court for assessing cases like this.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3483.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3493.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And on this point, they concluded, the chamber majority, that yes, there were reasons to conclude that there were exceptional circumstances in this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3493.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3508.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And yes, there were reasons to conclude that the mother was particularly unfit, not in general, but particularly unfit to take care of a child that had spent three and a half years in foster care and with whom she had very limited and weak ties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3508.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3514.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And yes, there were reasons to conclude that the boy was vulnerable and had special needs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3514.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3518.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And yes, three and a half years is a considerable period of time in this context.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3518.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3528.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And yes, the child welfare authorities and the city court were clearly guided by the best interest of the boy and the need to strike a fair balance in a very complex case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3528.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3546.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And yes, seen together, these reasons are adequate and sufficient to conclude that it would clearly be in the boy's best interest to continue to stay with the only family that he had ever known and to be allowed the stability and security of becoming a full member of that family.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3546.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3555.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In contrast, the argument of the chamber minority is, in our view, more difficult to follow and to some extent mixes the timeline and the criteria for review.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3555.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3565.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It differs from the majority text on several important points, but there are, in particular, two which appear to be decisive and on which I will therefore comment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3565.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3570.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The first issue is that of the mother's caretaking abilities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3570.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3575.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And here, the minority simply does not believe in the validity of the national assessment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3575.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3584.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Instead, they point selectively to some of the elements of the case and, in particular, to the fact that in 2012, she had established a new family.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3584.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3592.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The response to this is that this is a factual assessment on a point which was extensively examined at the national level.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3592.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3603.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The new family life of the mother was established before the case was brought, before the Social Welfare Board and the city court, and it was precisely the starting point of the whole review by the Welfare Board and the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3603.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3607.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And on this point, her caretaking abilities, the court heard a number of witnesses.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3607.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3609.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They examined the mother herself.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3609.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3614.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>She could bring any witness she wanted, and they heard expert witnesses.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3614.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3624.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this is clearly reflected in the reasons given by the city court, which should be taken as the correct factual assessment at that point in time.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3624.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3637.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A second issue for the minority is whether the authorities have considered the long-term effect of the child or the permanent nature of adoption, which cuts the legal ties of the child to the biological mother.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3637.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3643.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And here, the criticism is that this is simply not reflected in the reasoning of the city court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3643.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3646.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With this, the government simply disagrees.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3646.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3652.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Of course, the long-term interest of the boy was assessed explicitly and implicitly.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3652.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3662.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This was a case about adoption, and adoption necessarily means cutting the legal ties to the biological parent and forming new legal ties to the foster parents.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3662.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3664.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that's what adoption review is all about.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3664.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3672.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this is what the city court considered, and this is reflected in the reasoning.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3672.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3686.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So this can be added that in situations like this, when the realistic alternatives are either prolonged foster care or permanent adoption, then under Norwegian law, there is a certain preference for adoption, which is stronger than in some other countries.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3686.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3694.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is an informed policy choice, which has been taken by the Norwegian legislature based on empirical research and democratic debate.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3694.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3702.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the reasons for this is, therefore, to be found in public reports and white papers, some of which have now been submitted to the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3702.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3708.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So there you will also find the reasons for this choice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3708.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3723.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A final issue, which has been raised by the applicant and several of the interventions, is whether the authorities have done enough to fulfil the positive obligation to the mother under Article 8 to work towards reunification of the biological family.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3723.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3730.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And here again, the government disagrees with the criticism, both as regards the presentation of the law and the actual assessment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3730.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3740.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As to the law, it's correct that in the case law of this court, reunification of the biological family has been formulated as an aim and a guiding principle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3740.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3757.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But it's also quite clear from the case law that this aim must be reconciled with the superior obligation to protect the best interest of the specific child and that there is no obligation to pursue endless attempts at reunification if there's no progress, especially not when this is harmful to the child concerned.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3757.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3767.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The decisive criterion in the case law is whether the national authorities have made such efforts as can reasonably be demanded.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3767.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3776.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And if we then apply that to the facts of the case, it's simply not correct that the authorities have not fulfilled their positive obligations to the mother.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3776.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3780.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the contrary, they have repeatedly tried to assist her and help her.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3780.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3790.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>She has repeatedly been offered counselling on how to improve her caretaking abilities and the relationship to the boy, which for the most part she has turned down.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3790.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3796.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And as for the visiting sessions, there were altogether 32 of these in the course of three and a half years.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3796.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3806.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the Grand Chamber now has the records from all of these sessions, which show that the authorities did their best to organise the sessions in such a way that her needs were met.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3806.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3809.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Some of the sessions worked well, some not so well.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3809.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3824.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But the overall picture was that there were no actual progress in her relationship to the boy or her understanding of the situation and his special needs and what it would require on her part to take back a child which had formed new bonds with a new family.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3824.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3839.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the fact is that the child welfare authorities did all that can reasonably be expected, but after three and a half years without progress, the professional assessment was that it would not be in the boy's best interest to proceed further.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3839.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3844.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that is an assessment which the court should respect.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3844.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3864.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Finally, a few words, almost finally, a few words on the more general aspect, which is the strong general criticism of the Norwegian child welfare that has been voiced in this case, both by the applicant and some of the third party intervention and on which my honourable colleague spent a lot of time in his statement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3864.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3877.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this case, there is a surprising general criticism of the Norwegian system and indeed the Scandinavian system, and it is being put forward as a systemic problem in some way.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3877.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3880.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To this, we have two responses before this grand chamber.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3880.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3883.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First, that it's not relevant, and second, that it's not correct.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3883.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3893.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's not relevant to this court because the grand chamber must review each case individually on its own merits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3893.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3900.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And second, it's not true because it's simply not correct that there's something basically flawed with the Norwegian child welfare system.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3900.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3916.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the contrary, this system is probably one of the best developed and professional child welfare systems in Europe, and it is also one of those, I would think, that takes the principle of the best interest of the child and the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child most seriously.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3916.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3932.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Having said that, there are certainly policy variations between states in this field, such as in this case, the assessment of what's in a child's best interest when the realistic choice is between long-term foster care or institutionalized care or adoption with a new family.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3932.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3936.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In these cases, the Norwegian law is more tuned to adoption than in some other countries.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3936.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3939.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Not all, but in some other countries.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3939.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3950.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this is a policy choice which is based on research, which shows that children, on average, have a more positive development than children, if they are adopted, than children who remain under public care.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3950.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3958.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And it's a policy choice that should be respected as well within the European national and democratic margin of appreciation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3958.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3968.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In response to the criticism, we have found it necessary to explain Norwegian child welfare in some detail in Annex 1 to the memorial, as well as in the final observations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3968.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3972.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And here, the Grand Chamber can find all the relevant facts and figures if you wish to consult them.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3972.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3977.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And of course, we are very willing to answer any questions on this part.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3977.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3985.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But the proper thing to do for this chamber would be to disregard these allegations altogether when you assess this concrete case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3985.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3987.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, members of the court,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3987.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3991.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>was this a difficult case for the national authorities and courts?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3991.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3992.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Yes, of course it was.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3992.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3998.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These cases are always difficult, always sensitive, always complex, always deeply personal.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3998.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4007.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this case was no exception, as seen by the fact that the city court spent three days in an oral hearing and examined 21 witnesses.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4007.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4012.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Were there elements in this process that, in hindsight, could have been better, maybe?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4012.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4013.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Processes can always be better.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4013.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4015.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There's always something to be learned.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4015.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4022.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the outcome of any child welfare case will always be controversial and debatable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4022.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4027.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But does that mean that Norway has violated Article 8 of the European Convention on Human Rights?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4027.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4027.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>No.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4027.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4029.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Emphatically, no.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4029.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4034.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the contrary, the basic story in this case is the opposite.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4034.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4038.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is a story of correct intervention by the child welfare authorities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4038.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4056.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is a case in which the national authorities have tried their very best to protect the best interests of the boy, as they are positively obliged to do, both under the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child, under the Norwegian Constitution, under Norwegian statutory law, and, indeed, we would argue, under Article 8 of the Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4056.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4059.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that cannot be in breach at the same time of this convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4059.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4059.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4061.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4064.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much Mr. Sejersted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4064.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4074.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I thank both parties for their interventions and now I invite my colleagues, the judges of the Grand Chamber who wish to do so, to put their questions to the parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4074.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4076.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I see Judge Pere Pastor. Please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Pere Pastor Vilanova</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4080.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4082.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup, M. le Président.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Pere Pastor Vilanova</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4082.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4085.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>J'ai une question qui est dirigée aux deux parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Pere Pastor Vilanova</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4086.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4088.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La question est la suivante.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Pere Pastor Vilanova</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4089.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4101.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Comment s'est déroulée, dans le détail, l'exécution de la mesure d'urgence du 17 octobre 2008 par laquelle X fut confié à une famille d'accueil?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Pere Pastor Vilanova</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4101.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4101.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous remercie.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4103.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4106.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup. Now, Judge Spano, please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4107.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4111.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4111.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4119.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This case is centered by the parties very much around what is the role of this court in cases of this nature.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4119.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4122.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And Mr. Sajistad, you said three things during your pleadings</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4122.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4125.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>which prompt my question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4125.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4138.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The first is you said we need to assess the situation at the point in time when the decision in question, the forced adoption decision was taken in 2012.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4138.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4147.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You accepted that the court must apply strict scrutiny and therefore assess whether there were relevant and sufficient reasons.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4147.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4153.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I want to proceed on the basis that that is something the court will agree with you with.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4153.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4154.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That remains to be seen.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4154.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4158.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But my question is on that basis.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4158.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4174.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this case, we have a court judgment, the city court judgment of February 2012, where the applicant presents a claim that the situation at that point in time had changed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4174.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4176.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>She was married.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4176.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4178.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>She had another child.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4178.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4191.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I want your view on how we and I should understand the city court's judgment in relation to that claim made by the applicant at that point.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4191.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4212.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The city court's judgment, this is page 11 of the judgment, the court says the court agrees with the county social welfare board that the mother has not changed in such a way as to indicate it is now highly probable that she will be able to provide X with proper care.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4212.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4215.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court endorses the county social welfare board's grounds.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4215.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4226.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the court's view, the mother's clear limitations as a caregiver cannot be mitigated by an adapted transitional scheme, assistance measures, or support from the mother's network.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4226.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4233.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Then the court says, and here is what I would like your input on, and I would also ask Mr. Diodone if he has a view.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4233.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4253.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The court will not discuss the other arguments regarding the mother's ability to provide care in more detail as returning X is in any case not an option due to the serious problems it would cause X to be moved from the foster home.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4253.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4257.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So my question is, Mr. Syestad, should I</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4257.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4285.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>read the city court's judgment as taking a clear position on the applicant's central claim as regards the situation in 2012 that her situation as regards marriage and her caregiving of another child was not examined as such, at least in the reasoning there is no reference to that?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4285.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4289.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or is there another way to read the judgment?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4289.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4312.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I also draw attention to your observations, paragraph 165, where the government makes its own assessment where it says, it would not have been correct to set the assessments with regard to exercise with reference to vague descriptions of the first applicant's care for her daughter.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4312.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4316.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>May I ask, why were they vague?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4316.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4333.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Was there a lack of information at that point in the file which would clarify the nature of that role and in the global assessment by the Drammenkurt?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4333.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4338.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So just a clarification on how I should read the Drammenkurt's judgment on that.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4338.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4344.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Just a second question, which is the issue in relation to the legal test we're applying.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4344.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4352.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government refers to the two-limb child best interest test.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4352.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4370.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now as you said, and my question is prompted by another part of your pleading, you said, the test presumes first that the child should remain with the biological family unless the parent is considered particularly unfit.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4370.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4375.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Then we would go to the second limb of the test, which is the stability of the environment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4375.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4377.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>May I ask this question?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4377.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4401.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If this court were to consider that the fitness assessment, the first limb, might be called into question because of lack of relevant and sufficient reasons, would you still consider that under the second limb there would be an adequate justification for the measure in question?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4401.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4409.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In other words, if the first limb of the child best interest test under the court's case law is not met, is there a violation already there?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4409.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4422.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or would you defend the claim further and say, even though it is not clear that she was particularly unfit, in any event, your argument would be there would be no violation under the second limb.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4422.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4426.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Could you clarify the relationship between the two?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4426.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4430.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I would also ask Mr. Diudonne to comment, if he so wishes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4430.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4430.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4431.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4433.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4433.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4434.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Judge Ravarani, please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4435.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4436.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4436.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4438.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will have a very small factual question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4438.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4441.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's perhaps difficult for the representative of the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4441.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4446.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The question is addressed to the government to answer, but I will nevertheless try.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4446.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4462.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Why didn't the assistant midwife who made an assessment at the moment when the applicant left the hospital, when the child was three weeks old, why didn't she appear in further procedures whereas others did?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4462.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4472.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>She disappeared after having given her assessment when the child was three weeks old, and others appeared further on, but she didn't.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4472.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4474.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Is there a reason for that?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4474.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4474.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4479.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4495.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There are no further questions, so the Court will now withdraw for 20 minutes, following which the parties will be able to submit their brief observations in reply to each other's submissions and reply to the questions from the judges.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4495.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4495.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The hearing is suspended.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5011.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5011.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5049.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5050.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Please be seated.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5061.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5063.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The hearing is resumed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5063.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5064.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The floor is yours.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5073.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5075.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, merci.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5075.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5081.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mesdames et messieurs de la Cour, je répondrai dans l'ordre, tout simplement, des questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5084.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5095.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce qui s'est passé, j'ai interrogé durant ces minutes de pause ma cliente et ses conseils, ce qui s'est passé concrètement dans le détail.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5095.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5099.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le juge, c'est assez simple.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5099.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5112.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le jour du 17, donc, nous sommes le 17 octobre 2008, X à quelques semaines, 3 semaines, les autorités sont venues.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5112.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5125.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, je dirais sans prévenir, Mme Le Pen n'a pas été prévenue, n'a pas été même conditionnée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5125.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5131.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On aurait pu attendre cela, au moins, de la part des autorités.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5131.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5141.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ils sont simplement venus, ont pris l'enfant et ont demandé, dans la foulée, à Mme Le Pen de faire ses affaires et de s'en aller.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5145.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5159.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Très concrètement, tout ce que j'avais à répondre sur cette question, elle s'en est allée, tout simplement, avec son sac, sans aucune explication, sans aucun support, assistance de quelque nature que ce soit.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5161.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5167.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour la question 2, alors, il y a plusieurs questions dans la question, si j'ai bien compris, M. Spano.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5170.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5196.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Première partie de la question, telle que je l'ai comprise, le Drammen City Court, 22 février 2012, le test à SQSE tient une partie significative dans ce jugement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5196.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5217.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est grâce à ce test-là, ou plutôt malheureusement, à cause de ce test-là, que Mme Le Pen a été évaluée sur la base centrale de ce test comme particulièrement indigne ou particulièrement incapable, plutôt, d'élever X.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5225.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5237.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors que, et donc c'est à la page 11 de ce jugement du 22 février 2012, c'est là, moi, où je vois une forme vraiment de peine perpétuelle, où c'est la double peine, où c'est la peine capitale.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5237.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5261.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et puis on l'a, comme l'on veut, en matière civile, on a, sur cet simple outil de dépistage qui est assez critiqué, la méthodologie au niveau scientifique, je ne vais pas développer les arguments ici, mais je vous renvoie à mon mémoire sur ce point-là, sur les critiques scientifiques sur la validité de ce test et sur, finalement, le peu de sérieux.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5261.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5273.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il y a ici une disproportion avec, basée de manière centrale, l'incapacité parentale de ma cliente sur un test qui est lui-même sujet à caution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5274.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5296.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Surtout, ce qui me choque, c'est qu'à la page 11, on estime que jamais Mme Le Ben ne pourra, il n'y a aucune forme d'assistance possible pour redresser la barre, et notamment même pas en se basant sur son family network.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5296.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5301.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors que ses parents sont juste derrière moi.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5303.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5313.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ma cliente a deux frères et soeurs qui n'ont jamais eu de problème avec les services sociaux.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5314.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5324.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ses parents n'ont jamais eu également de problème ou n'ont jamais eu également eux-mêmes aucun problème, aucune difficulté avec les services sociaux.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5324.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5339.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Comment peut-on dire à ma cliente que vous n'avez même pas, que ça ne sert à rien d'aller fouiller, finalement, d'aller voir si on pourrait envisager peut-être un placement dans la famille élargie, alors que cette famille n'a jamais posé de problème?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5340.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5353.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et puis, nous sommes en février 2012, mais en mars 2012, un mois après, le 21 mars 2012, une enquête des services sociaux de la ville d'à côté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5353.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5358.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dramen Child Welfare Authorities Investigation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5358.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5380.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le 21 mars 2012, quelqu'un des services sociaux de Dramen, un mois après, vient témoigner à la barre qu'il n'y a absolument aucune difficulté relationnelle, d'attachement ou de réponse émotionnelle entre Mme Le Pen et son nouvel enfant, sa fille, que vous voyez d'ailleurs ici.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5383.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5392.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors, c'est quand même surprenant, la motivation du jugement du 22 février 2012.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5394.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5411.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La deuxième partie de votre question, si j'ai bien compris, vous m'excuserez de ne pas avoir suivi dans le détail votre question argumentée, portée sur le paragraphe 165 de la décision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5411.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5424.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais moi, je suis aussi surpris de cette appréciation selon laquelle les capacités parentales de madame étaient trop vagues pour qu'on puisse se faire une idée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5425.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5427.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Là aussi, moi, j'attends plutôt la réponse de mes contradicteurs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5428.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5442.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sur la troisième question, il est tout à fait clair et assez très surprenant, voire même inquiétant, que durant les cinq premiers jours, tout allait bien.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5442.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5451.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La chef des sages-femmes, MB, s'est fendue d'un rapport très positif qui s'est basé notamment sur des...</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5454.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5467.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>journals, en anglais, donc sur des documents d'ordre médicaux motivés et étayés, que nous ne retrouvons d'ailleurs pas dans le dossier.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5469.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5471.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Elle a complètement disparu après trois semaines.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5473.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5493.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous nous en plaignons et nous ne comprenons pas pourquoi cette femme, qui était à la demande d'ailleurs des services sociaux, qui a rendu un rapport particulièrement positif pour la mère, qui était équilibrée d'ailleurs, parce qu'elle disait aussi, attention, elle a aussi besoin des fois d'aide.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5493.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5502.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce fut la même chose avec le psychologue privé de Mme Lobel, KM.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5504.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5508.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>KM est un expert sur les listes d'experts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5509.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5512.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors certes, il n'a pas rendu, malheureusement, de rapport.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5512.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5514.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il aurait dû... Bon, maintenant, c'est fait.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5515.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5523.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il a témoigné à la barre des capacités parentales et qu'à son avis, X devait être retourné avec une période d'adaptation à sa mère.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5523.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5526.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Lui aussi a complètement disparu des radars.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5526.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5529.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Voilà ce que je pouvais vous répondre. Merci.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5533.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5538.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup, maître. Now I call Mr. Sejersted, please. You have the floor.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5540.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5544.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President, members of the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5544.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5552.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As far as I can see, I received three questions, one from Judge Villanova, one from Judge Ravarini, and one from Judge Spano.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5552.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5556.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Although that was perhaps several questions from Judge Spano.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5556.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5562.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So I will first answer the two first ones, and then I will turn to the more extensive questions posed by Judge Spano.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5562.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5579.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As to the first question, that was, if I got it right, what exactly happened on the 17th of October 2008, when the decision, the first emergency decision, was taken to take the boy into foster care?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5579.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5587.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I have to say to this point that, again, but I've said this so often, that this is not, in the government's view, the most relevant point in time for the court's assessment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5587.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5601.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is a part of the background to the case, but almost, I wouldn't say regardless, but even though it might be debatable what happened on the 17th of October 2008, that is not the theme before the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5601.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5607.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The theme before the court is the situation in 2012, when the decision was made for adoption.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5607.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5614.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Having said that, of course, we are perfectly willing to discuss what happened in the first phase of the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5614.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5625.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I would, well, I would first and foremost refer the court to the places in the annexes where this is extensively described.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5625.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5633.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If you consult afterwards, appendix 18 to the government's memorial, you will find that that is the first emergency decision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5633.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5641.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's in Norwegian, but if you get the translation, you will see from that translation, it's a report of what was considered on the 17th of October.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5641.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5642.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's the decision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5642.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5654.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then you will find the decision by the county social welfare board on the emergency decision, explaining the facts of what happened at that date in appendix 20 to the memorial.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5654.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5657.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And as far as I remember, that's been translated into English.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5657.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5665.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then you will find the city court judgment on the emergency decision in appendix 23 to the memorial.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5666.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5673.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And again, in these documents, you will find all the details of what actually transpired on the 17th of October.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5673.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5681.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And it's also quite detailed explanation of this in the chamber judgment in paragraphs eight to 13.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5681.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5683.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So I refer you to these documents.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5683.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5690.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will only say that what happened is that the biological mother was with the child at the family care center.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5690.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5698.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the family care center is a specialized sort of institution that is provided for mothers or parents with special needs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5698.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5712.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's a high degree of public availability for parents to go to these child welfare family centers.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5712.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5714.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And she went there voluntarily.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5714.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5717.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then after three weeks approximately, she'd wanted to go home.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5717.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5722.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then the emergency decision was taken to take the boy into emergency foster care.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5722.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5729.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the reasons as you will find is that the personnel of the family center were deeply alarmed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5729.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5732.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They were actually alarmed for the life of the boy.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5732.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5742.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this can be debated 10 years afterwards in this court, but these were the people, and these are people who work every day with parents in special needs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5742.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5745.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They're not just any psychologist or any child welfare authorities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5745.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5749.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These are the persons who every day work with people with special needs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5749.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5758.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And these people concretely were disturbed and afraid, not only for the caretaking abilities of the mother, but indeed for the life of the child.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5758.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5759.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And this you will find explained.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5759.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5761.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So that's the start of the whole process.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5761.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5765.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And we have to, if we are to go into these details, you must start there.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5765.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5773.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But as we say, we do not think this is the most relevant, legally relevant part of the case, as it stands before the case, before the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5773.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5783.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Then there was the question on the testimony of the assistant midwife, and that's one of the midwives from this first phase.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5783.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5795.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I can supplement later if I'm not correct, but if I've understood correctly, this again, this pertains to the first phase of the case, the first judgment, which I'm not the one under review now.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5795.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5805.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But if I remember correctly, I understood the facts of the case correctly, this midwife, she wrote down a written report and that report was included in the case file.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5805.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5808.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So it's been in the case file the whole time.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5808.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5825.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And also in the proceedings on the, I think on several, but at least the proceedings before the high court in 2012, no, 2010, sorry, 2010, the high court on the permanent caretaking decision, then the midwife was a witness.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5825.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5834.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I refer here to appendix 41, where you will find the Retsbok, the court diary from the case where the name of this midwife.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5834.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5837.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So she was heard by the high court in 2010.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5837.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5845.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And as for the later proceedings in 2011 and 12, which is the one before the court, of course, the applicant had every chance through her.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5845.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5847.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>She had professional legal advice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5847.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5853.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>She argued, her lawyer argued the case quite extensively, and she had every opportunity of calling any witness she did.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5853.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5856.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>She called a number of witnesses, but not this midwife.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5856.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5859.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So it was not heard by in the second phase of the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5859.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5867.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And in our view, that's illogical, because that was no longer the relevant, the legally relevant part of the case, which had moved on to another assessment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5867.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5871.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So that's the second question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5871.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5875.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then I come to the questions from Judge Spano.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5875.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5886.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And there were three questions which were quite detailed, and maybe I didn't catch all the details, but the president assured that we would be able, perhaps to supplement in writing if we have more elaborate answers to some of these questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5886.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5902.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But if I understand you correctly, Your Honor, the first question related to the fact that to what extent did the city court in 2012 reflect on the new family situation of the biological mother with a new child?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5902.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5911.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And our answer to that, as I said in my submission, is that this was the starting point of the whole exercise.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5911.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5915.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>At that point, she had established a new family.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5915.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5923.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>She had a daughter before the case was brought, before the Social Welfare Board, and of course, before the city court judgment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5923.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5938.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And what they considered was her ability, among other things, they considered the total situation, her caretaking abilities, the vulnerability of the boy, the attachment to the new parents, the lack of attachment to the biological mother, the whole situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5938.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5952.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But as for her caretaking abilities, the starting point for the review on which they spent three days was her caretaking abilities in light of the fact that the situation had changed on her personal front, that she had established a new family life.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5952.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5963.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And there were inquiries made into the situation of the new family life, and there were assessment, and there were a number of witnesses heard on this point.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5963.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5966.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And she explained herself.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5966.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5994.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And they came to the conclusion that even if she has caretaking abilities for the daughter in the new family situation, she did not have the adequate understanding of what it would require as regards the boy, not the daughter that she's living with, but the boy who, in the meantime, had become three years old, three and a half years old, and had formed new attachment and had special needs, and what it would require on her part to be able to take back a child under those conditions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5994.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5999.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And on that point, and that was what they really examined.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5999.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6004.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We may discuss whether this is adequately reasoned in the text of the judgment from the city court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6004.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6017.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's annex 4, and you will find it at the bottom of page 8 and on the top of page 9 in the city court judgment, where they explicitly use several paragraphs on this issue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6017.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6024.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And they start by saying, I will not read everything, and you can read it for yourself.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6024.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6027.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's in English translation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6027.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6033.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They start at the bottom of page 8, the first paragraph, by saying, in some areas, the mother's situation has improved during the past year.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6033.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6035.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then they discuss this.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6035.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6041.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I will not go into the details, because they are personal, and would disclose details that we should not mention in open court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6041.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6045.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But if you read it yourself, you will find that this is the discussion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6045.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6048.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So that's my answer to the first point.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6048.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6072.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The second question was, that was related to paragraph 165 in the memorial, I think, where we, in the memorial, write on page 27 that we used the word with reference to vague descriptions of the first applicant's care for her daughter.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6072.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6074.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Perhaps the word vague is not the most precise.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6074.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6075.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is a very extensive description.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6075.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6078.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And we used a lot of words, uncertain.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6078.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6087.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The point is that the first applicant's care for the daughter, and now I'm repeating myself, was part of the examination.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6087.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6091.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Witnesses were heard on her relationship to the daughter.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6091.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6093.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They had made inquiries in the home.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6093.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6095.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There had been sort of inspection.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6095.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6096.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There were reports.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6096.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6099.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And these were not vague, but they were uncertain.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6099.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6104.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The conclusion, if you remember, is that they found that, yes, she could take care of her daughter.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6104.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6105.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But it was not absolutely perfect.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6105.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6111.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There were things that the child welfare authorities pointed out that she would need public counselling and assistance with.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6111.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6115.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And perhaps that's what we refer to with the word vague.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6115.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6121.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The main point is, this was examined in detail by the city court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6121.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6125.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then we come to the last question, which is the relationship.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6125.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6128.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Then we're on to the points of legal interpretation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6128.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6134.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the criteria put forward by the court for assessing situations like this.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6134.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6138.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And when it comes to the best interest of the child.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6138.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6146.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And you are asking a question about the so-called two-pronged approach and the relationship between the first prong and the second prong.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6146.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6151.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>To this, I would first say that these criteria are criteria established by this court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6151.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6158.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The only thing that Article 8 says is that there should be protection of private and family life, and there may be exemptions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6158.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6164.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the more detailed and elaborate criteria that the court may develop, are developed by the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6164.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6166.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They are evolving in this area, I would say.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6166.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6172.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The principle of the best interest of the child is still evolving into the interpretation of Article 8.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6172.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6180.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The realignment of Article 8 and the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child, which is very important, is still an evolving area of law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6180.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6193.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So I would urge the court to, if you find anything, I'm almost tempted to take the question back to the court and say, if you find anything that you are unsure about, about the two-pronged approach, then you can reinterpret or reaffirm or clarify it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6194.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6208.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The first prong is the biological presumption, but with the immediate addition that, unless the biological parents is particularly unfit.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6208.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6213.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the second prong is that anyway, the child has the right to a sound environment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6213.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6213.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's simple.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6213.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6228.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But we would say that in addition, in effect, what the court has done in a couple of recent cases, including the case of Hassan versus Norway this year, is that they have added this point, which I made, about the considerable period of time.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6228.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6242.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the considerable period of time, when a considerable period of time has passed, and in this case, three and a half years is a considerable period of time, then the de facto situation may change and the de facto situation may change.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6242.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6244.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the de facto situation has prevailed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6244.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6248.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We really see the considerable period of time as the third prong.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6248.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6251.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But all of this is just the total situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6251.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6254.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I mean, what you really have to look at is the total situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6254.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6260.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And in the total situation, the prevailing overriding paramount interest is the best interest of the child.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6260.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6265.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is as far as I can go now, but perhaps we will try to clarify this a bit more in writing if we have the permission.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6265.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6267.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, if I have your permission,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6267.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6270.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I would like to make one final point before I conclude.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6270.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6287.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>When child welfare cases are brought before this court, they are almost always cases in which the national authorities have intervened in the biological family, and this intervention is analyzed and reviewed under Article 8.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6287.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6290.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And these are important cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6290.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6305.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But we must not forget that at the national level, the biggest challenge with child welfare in Norway as in, I would probably think, all European countries, is not that the authorities intervene too often.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6305.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6316.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is that they intervene too seldom, with the result that children suffer serious neglect and long-term damages that could have been avoided given more resources and expertise.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6316.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6327.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And we should not forget that this may also be a violation of the Convention on the Rights of the Child, both under Article 8 and sometimes, even though not in this case, under Article 3.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6327.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6333.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that's the perspective that the national child welfare authorities and the national courts work under.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6333.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6339.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They go into these cases, and they have the protection of the best interest of a child as the paramount principle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6339.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6344.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is what they do, and this explains why the national judgment looks like they do.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6344.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6372.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And for this reason, we would strongly urge the Grand Chamber to be very careful in cases like this, how you formulate your criteria, both as regards to final conclusions, but also the premises that you send, so that you do not raise the threshold too high for legitimate intervention, and so that you do not create a chilling effect, which would in practice mean that the welfare authorities were afraid to intervene in cases where they absolutely should intervene.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6372.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6372.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6377.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6379.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much Mr. Seersted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6379.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6382.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We have now come to the end of the hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6382.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6391.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I thank both parties who have assisted the Court with their submissions and answers to the Court's questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6391.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6393.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Court will now deliberate on the merits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6393.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6396.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The judgment will be delivered later.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6396.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6400.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The parties will be informed of the date of delivery.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6400.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6400.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I declare the hearing closed.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

</transcript_3728313_17102018>
