<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<transcript_7694311_02032016>
  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>48.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>50.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous en prie, prenez place.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>58.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>66.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je déclare ouverte l'audience publique sous le fond de l'affaire Paroisses gréco-catholiques Lupény et autres contre Roumanie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>67.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>86.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>A l'origine de l'affaire se trouve une requête introduite devant la cour par la Paroisse gréco-catholique de Lupény, l'évêché gréco-catholique de Lougouy et la chuprête gréco-catholique de Lupény, qui ont saisi la cour le 14 décembre 2011 en vertu de l'article 34 de la Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>87.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>96.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La requête a été attribuée à la 3e section de la cour conformément à l'article 52, paragraphe 1 du règlement de la cour.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>97.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>102.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La requête a été communiquée au gouvernement le 18 décembre 2012.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>103.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>110.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le 19 mai 2015, une chambre de la 3e section a rendu un arrêt dans l'affaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>110.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>130.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans celui-ci, la chambre a déclaré recevable le grief tiré de l'article 6, paragraphe 1 de la Convention, seul et combiné avec l'article 14 de la Convention, quant au droit d'accès à un tribunal, au respect du principe de la sécurité juridique et en jugement dans un délai raisonnable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>130.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>133.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Elle a déclaré la requête irrecevable pour le surplus.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>133.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>151.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La chambre a conclu à la violation de l'article 6, paragraphe 1 de la Convention concernant la durée de la procédure et à la non-violation de l'article 6, paragraphe 1 de la Convention concernant le droit d'accès à un tribunal et le respect du principe de la sécurité juridique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>152.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>170.3</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Elle a également conclu à la non-violation de l'article 14 de la Convention en combinaison avec l'article 6, paragraphe 1 de la Convention et le paragraphe 1 de la Convention, ce dernier examiné sous son volet concernant le droit d'accès à un tribunal.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>170.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>180.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le 19 août 2015, les requérants ont demandé le renvoi de l'affaire devant la Grande chambre, conformément à l'article 43 de la Convention.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>180.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>187.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette demande a été acceptée par le Collège de la Grande chambre le 19 octobre 2015.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>187.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>213.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le gouvernement défendeur est représenté par son agente, madame Catrinel Brumar, du ministère des Affaires étrangères, assistée de madame Oana Ezer, conseillère, de madame Ioana  Dumitriu, secrétaire à la représentation permanente de la Roumanie auprès du Conseil de l'Europe, et de monsieur Cezar Păvălaşcu, chef de service auprès du Secrétariat d'Etat pour les cultes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>213.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>220.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les requérants sont représentés par madame maître Diana-Olivia Hatneanu, conseil.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>220.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>223.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je salue les comparants au nom de la Cour.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>224.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>229.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je salue également une délégation de magistrats français du Conseil d'Etat.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>229.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>251.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je dois expliquer qu'en sus de l'interprétation dans les 2 langues officielles de la Cour, l'anglais et le français, l'interprétation vers le russe a été autorisée au profit d'un groupe de professionnels du droit représentant le European Human Rights Advocacy Centre et venant de la Russie, de l'Ukraine, de l'Arménie, de la Géorgie et de l'Azerbaïdjan.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>252.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>260.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette interprétation n'est pas assurée par la Cour et ne fera donc pas partie de l'enregistrement officiel de la procédure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>260.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>268.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ayant consulté l'agente du gouvernement et la représentante des requérants, j'ai fixé ainsi l'ordre de parole.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>268.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>277.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous entendrons successivement maître Hatneanu pour les requérants, puis madame Brumar et madame Ezer pour le gouvernement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>277.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>280.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La parole est à maître Hatneanu. Je vous en prie, maître.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>284.3</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>288.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, honorable members of the Grand Chamber,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>288.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>293.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>the case brought before the Grand Chamber today bears on an important issue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>293.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>305.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Is a judicial procedure with a predetermined outcome based on the will of one party in the same procedure compatible with the requirements of right to access to a court?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>305.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>312.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Is there a legal provision providing for the access to a court, effective if not applied at all?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>312.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>323.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In order to answer these questions, applicants need to remind the context of the case, as it fully explains the outcome of the particular procedure complained of by the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>323.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>329.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The restoration of a Greek Catholic church in early 1990 came together with a difficult problem.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>329.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>336.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The fate of the church is once belonging to the Greek Catholics and now in the possession of the Orthodox.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>336.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>344.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The legislator believed in a solution of mutual understanding, deciding to leave the solution to mixed commissions of the two parties involved.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>344.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>359.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The debates underline that such solutions would have been the alternative use of the church in the communities where only one place of worship existed, or the weak equal division of churches where two places of worship existed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>359.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>367.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Unfortunately, what it seemed a reasonable solution was never efficient in practice, only a limited number of cases being solved.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>367.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>382.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Many Greek Catholics parishes had to resort to justice for a resolution of the dispute, although in many cases, the courts rejected their claims, may they be on property or use of the church, holding it was not a matter for the courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>382.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>405.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>14 years later, in 2004, and after an admissibility decision of the European Court of Human Rights, the government passed an emergency ordinance to amend Article 3 of the decree law 126 per 1990, a to provide for access to justice for the Greek Catholics based on the provisions of common law, in cases a mixed commission procedure failed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>405.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>411.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The phrase provisions of common law has a well-established meaning in the Romanian legal order.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>411.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>418.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It refers to the provisions of the civil law, and in particular, of the civil code, as opposed to the provisions of a special law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>418.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>422.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And it has been so since 1865.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>422.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>431.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The clear meaning of the phrase also results from the parliamentary debates of 2005, when the emergency ordinance was approved by the Chamber of Deputies.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>431.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>450.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In a lengthy speech, one deputy explained that voting in favor of the amendment would actually mean the churches would be returned to the Greek Catholics based on the civil code provisions alone, without taking into account the special status of the property at stake, and called for a negative vote.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>450.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>470.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the final speech before the vote, the president of the Chamber of Deputies clearly pointed that the scope of the amendment is to provide access to justice based on the general provisions and principles of civil law, in cases where the will of the believers was inefficient for 15 years in reaching a solution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>470.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>500.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this context, the vast majority of votes in favor of the amendment cannot have but one meaning, that the legislator created a system in which the will of the majority applies at the pretrial stage, during the miscommissioned procedure, and if no resolution of the dispute is reached, justice as a neutral party will intervene by applying the general provisions of civil code, which do not imply the will of any party involved.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>500.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>513.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, the applicants strongly disagree with the government's interpretation of the 2005 debates as meaning the amendment only allowed for access to justice, but not based on the general provisions of civil law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>513.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>524.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If the will of the legislator was as such, the final adopted text would have read, the interest party can address the courts without adding based on the common law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>524.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>545.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In time, the High Court of Cassation and Justice became quite constant in providing a totally different interpretation of the amendment, claiming that the will of the majority also applies during the judicial stage, or the role of the court cannot be to replace the legislator and provide interpretations that empty a legal provision of its purpose.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>545.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>547.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government submitted that at present.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>547.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>556.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The High Court developed a clear interpretation of the 2005 amendment, combining the general provision of civil law with the will of the majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>556.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>560.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the government's opinion, the interpretation is as follows.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>560.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>569.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The courts should make an application of the general provisions of civil law and analyze the title to property of the two parties.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>569.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>575.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If the Greek Catholics do not hold a valid title to property, their case is dismissed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>575.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>591.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If they do have a title to property, instead of applying the general provisions of civil law, the principle of majority is applied, and in the court cases provided by the government with only one exception, that will was of the orthodox party.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>591.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>604.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government also claims that the High Court developed other criteria for assessing the will of the majority beyond the purely statistical data, such as asking for concrete evidence or information on the current use of the church.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>604.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>615.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What is striking in the government's opinion and the current practice of the High Court is that one way or another, the Greek Catholics' claims will always be dismissed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>615.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>622.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The general provisions of civil law work only against them, and there is only one possible solution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>622.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>625.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The will of the majority prevails.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>625.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>646.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Even in cases where the government claims the High Court decided for a retrial on the merits of the case, such a decision of 19 March 2012 provided with the observation by the government, the reading of the judgment reveals that this was the non-application of the will of the majority by the lower courts that triggers a retrial.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>646.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>654.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Therefore, in reality, the so-called full analysis on the merits of Greek Catholic claims is an analysis of the will of the majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>654.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>662.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So one is wondering why there is a need for a court proceeding at all in these cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>662.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>665.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The two parties involved know their position.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>665.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>675.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And if the will of the majority is for the return of the church to the Greek Catholics, then such a resolution of the case will be reached without resorting to justice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>675.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>684.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If the will of the majority is against the return of the church, the minority does not need to go through lengthy court proceedings to find that out.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>684.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>694.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The purpose of a court is to decide a case based on mutual criteria, not the very will of the parties involved relevant in a non-judicial resolution of the case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>694.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>700.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In this case, the applicants wonder on the purpose of the amendment of the law in 2005.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>700.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>707.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Was it to allow for a court procedure with a predetermined solution based on the will of the majority?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>707.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>713.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The debates in the Chamber of Deputies and the resulting text of the amendment demonstrate the contrary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>713.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>717.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It was the High Court and the Constitutional Court which turned it inoperable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>717.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>735.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For the High Court, the only difference between the situation before 2005, when the law was amended to allow for access to court, and the one after, is that the formal decision of the mixed commission is not necessary in order to address the courts, which can now apply the will of the majority directly.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>735.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>740.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For the Constitutional Court, the amendment was no difference whatsoever.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>740.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>748.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And no difference was brought to the Greek Catholic communities, which still depend on the will of the majority for a resolution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>748.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>755.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that situation creates tensions, as seen in the reports quoted in the Chamber judgment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>755.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>759.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And no difference was made for the current applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>759.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>763.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The parish was re-established in Lupen in December 1995.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>763.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>766.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The mixed commission procedure had no result.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>766.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>769.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the Orthodox did not participate.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>769.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>780.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Six years later, the applicants addressed the courts for the return of the church, one of the churches in Lupen, and not for finding out that the Orthodox do not want to return to the church.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>780.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>782.14</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They already knew that.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>782.14</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>791.7</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Their case was initially dismissed as inadmissible, the court deciding that the resolution of the dispute can only be done via the mixed commission procedure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>791.7</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>802.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Only after the law was first amended in 2004, the High Court sent the case back for a retrial, considering that the courts are competent in solving the dispute.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>802.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>810.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In 2009, the Tunedwara Tribunal applies a general provisions of civil law and upheld the applicants' claims.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>810.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>821.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The decision was reversed by the Al-Bayouliya Court of Appeal and the High Court, with a majority of 2 to 1, by applying the will of the Orthodox majority based on census data.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>821.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>830.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants strongly disagreed that the court dismissing their claim had done a proper analysis on the merits, taking into account various factors.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>830.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>844.86</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Besides the general census data, the government indicated only one factor that the courts took into account, the fact that the church in question has been allegedly being built by Greek Catholics and Orthodox together.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>844.86</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>862.98</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or such a fact is actually disputed, as the Tunedwara Tribunal held, and also according to the history of the parish, a document drafted in 1934 and submitted by the applicants to the European Court, together with the observation of September 2013.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>862.98</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>869.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The main contributors to the building of the church was the Greek Catholic locals, both financially and in-kind.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>869.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>883.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The newcomers, mostly Orthodox, came only in the 1920s, after the church was built in 1906, and were indeed allowed to use a Greek Catholic church in the beginning with a Greek Catholic service, and then since 1912, having their own priest.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>883.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>893.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nevertheless, it is clear as from the last two judgments in the case that the main reason to dismiss the applicants' claim was the existence of an Orthodox majority, according to the census.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>893.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>904.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government failed to explain how any of the other findings of the court, even if contrary to what they have been, would have trumped the application of the will of the majority in the present case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>904.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>921.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The interpretation that the will of the majority prevails over the general provisions of civil law, as applied in the present case, therefore lacked foreseeability, legitimate aim, and proportionality, as developed in the written observation of the applicants before the grand chamber.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>921.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>933.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Neither the Alba Iulia Court of Appeal nor the High Court had taken into account the current situation in Lupeni to strike a fair balance for the interest at stake, as the government claims they had.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>933.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>950.46</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to the census at the time of the proceedings, there were more than 500 Greek Catholics in Lupeni in two parishes, but with no church, an aspect also taken into consideration by the Funaiduara Tribunal when deciding in favor of the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>950.46</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>957.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Not even at the time being there is any Greek Catholic church in Lupeni, more than 20 years after the parish was re-established.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>957.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>965.26</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Orthodox majority, grouped in three parishes, have three churches to use, out of which we are two are former Greek Catholic ones.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>965.26</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>975.66</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>According to the government's submission on the principles developed by the High Court, such an aspect should have been taken into consideration in the present case, but it was not.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>975.66</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>984.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the contrary, the fact that the Greek Catholics are a minority, even if a sizable one, was a very reason to dismiss their claim.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>984.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>999.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government is trying to imply that the fair resolution of the situation is by applying the will of the majority for the existing churches and by building of new churches for the minority, in the name of neutrality of the state towards the churches.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>999.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1011.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the applicant's opinion, for them, that equals with a flagrant denial of access to justice, as none of these avenues actually requires the involvement of the justice system.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1011.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1020.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants are again wondering on the purpose of the amendment of 2005, allowing for their access to courts if actually these are the solutions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1020.34</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1026.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They can be applied and actually were applied, even in the absence of the amendment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1026.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1039.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As regards the financial support of the Greek Catholics, the applicant stressed it is based on the general provision for supporting all churches in Romania and not on the provision of the special law, the Dictory Law 126.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1039.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1045.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And no support whatsoever was received in the particular case of the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1045.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1050.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I would also like to draw the Grand Chamber's attention to another important issue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1050.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1060.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Not reversing the chamber judgment in this case will result in a full application of the prevalence of the will of the majority in cases currently pending before domestic courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1060.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1079.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Government Annex 5 to the written observation before the Grand Chamber mentioned that the Timisoara Court of Appeal reversed its practice and started to apply the prevalence of the will of the majority as a direct result of the chamber judgment of 19 May 2015.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1079.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1087.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As regards the duration of the procedure, the applicant asked the Grand Chamber to uphold the chamber judgment, finding a violation of Article 6.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1087.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1094.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government has not requested a referral of the case on this account, and their current submissions are not supported by the facts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1094.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1100.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The procedure lasted for 10 years due to the authorities as detailed in the written observations.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1100.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1104.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Its aim was the return of the church where the applicant perished.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1104.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1111.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The main beneficiary of a potential positive result, irrespective of its formal capacity.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1111.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1121.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Two of the applicants were initially mentioned as representatives of the episcopate due to the organization of the church, the episcopate being the administrator of the church state.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1121.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1132.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What should matter is the purpose of the procedure when analyzing its duration and the fact all applicants were part in the trial at all times in various capacities.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1132.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1145.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As for the one year the case was suspending, the applicant stressed that even if that period is to be deducted, the procedure still lasted for nine years due to the authorities fault.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1145.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1161.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As regards the discrimination count, at the very beginning, we stressed that irrespective of various legal or judicial definition of interpretation of discrimination, at the very heart of the concept, there is a basic finding.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1161.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1170.78</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The rights of a minority are a pure illusion if left at the disposal of the will of the majority when competing interests are at stake.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1170.78</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1173.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is an essential issue in this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1173.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1187.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants are part of a minority and the domestic courts hold it against them without striking a balance between the interests of the majority and those of the minority in question to accommodate both.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1187.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1198.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The domestic courts were biased in handpicking only those arguments favoring the majority and in putting it to the heart of their reasoning the mere existence of a majority in the community.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1198.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1205.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As a government agreed at the material time, not all Greek Catholic parishes addressing the courts enjoyed the same treatment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1205.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1209.06</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For some, the court supplied the civil law alone.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1209.06</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1217.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants cannot find an objective and reasonable justification based on clear and well-explained criteria for it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1217.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1226.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In government's view, the justification is a need, of course, to accommodate amendments of the law in 2004 and 2005.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1226.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1229.1</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicants cannot agree.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1229.1</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1235.18</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Their case was decided by the high court in 2011, seven years after the amendment.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1235.18</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1247.9</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the issue was far from new, as even before 2004, Greek Catholics addressed the courts based on general provision of civil law, which existed for more than 150 years.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1247.9</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1254.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The high court put an end to the situation after the case of the applicants was decided only a couple of years ago.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1254.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1263.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Moreover, the solution found was an interpretation that renders the provision allowing for access to court ineffective in breach of Article VI.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1263.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1273.58</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For this reason, the applicants asked the Green Chamber to find that their right to access to a court in a reasonable time was violated and that they were victims of discrimination.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1273.58</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1284.02</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In a democratic and tolerant state, minorities, even religious ones, should be able to address courts when their interests are in conflict with those of the majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1284.02</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1293.62</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the courts should not devay their purpose of striving a fair balance between such interests by primarily resorting to the will of the one parties involved.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1293.62</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1293.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1295.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1298.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Mrs. Hatneanu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1298.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1302.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Maintenant, la parole est à Mme Brumar.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1302.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1302.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Vous avez la parole, s'il vous plaît.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1304.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1306.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous en remercie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1306.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1309.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>M. le Président, Mme et M. le juge,</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1309.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1314.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>c'est un honneur pour nous de comparaître devant la Cour en tant que représentant du gouvernement roumain.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1314.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1319.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ensemble avec ma collègue, nous partageons la tâche de présenter la position de celui-ci.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1319.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1330.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour ma part, je soumettrai à votre attention les éléments les plus importants relatifs aux droits d'accès en tribunal avec des références à la législation et la jurisprudence nationale en la matière.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1330.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1339.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ma collègue me succédera en présentant les aspects pertinents dans l'analyse de la prétendue discrimination soufferte par la paresse recurrente.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1339.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1353.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mesdames, messieurs les juges, la présente affaire fut portée devant vous suite à l'acceptation d'une demande de renvoi que la partie recurrente soumit au Collège envers un arrêt de la 3e chambre de votre honorable cours.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1353.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1374.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La partie recurrente considère que le rejet de son action en révendication d'un lieu de culte par l'application du critère de la volonté des fidèles est indicatif d'un simulacre de procès vu l'examen seulement formel des instances nationales sur l'existence et les effets de l'appartenance religieuse de la majorité d'une communauté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1374.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1386.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pourtant, de ce très bref résumé de critiques que la partie recurrente apporte à l'arrêt de la chambre et à la solution de son affaire au niveau interne, les particularités de ce cas apparaissent déjà à l'évidence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1386.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1396.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous prie de me permettre d'apporter quelques précisions essentielles avant de me pencher sur le respect du droit d'accès en tribunal pour la partie recurrente.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1396.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1412.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Son action en restitution d'un lieu de culte se grève sur un contexte général, historique et social, complexe et sensible, celui de la restitution des biens ayant appartenu à l'Eglise roumaine unie à Rome, greco-catholique, et repris par l'OTAN en 1948.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1413.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1422.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'Eglise roumaine unie à Rome prit naissance à la fin du XVIIe siècle en Transylvanie par l'union avec l'Eglise romano-catholique d'une partie de fidèles roumains orthodoxes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1424.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1438.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette union supposait l'acceptation des 4 principes fondamentaux de l'Eglise romano-catholique et garantissait aux fidèles roumains le maintien du rituel traditionnel, le respect des faits orthodoxes et leur égalité en droit avec les fidèles romano-catholiques.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1439.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1452.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Environ une moitié de la population orthodoxe rejoignit cette nouvelle Eglise, leur adhésion, que les historiens considèrent un parti non volontaire, s'accompagnant du transfert d'une partie des lieux de culte en faveur de l'Eglise greco-catholique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1453.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1465.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En 1948, l'État communiste décida le retour des paroisses greco-catholiques au sein du culte orthodoxe roumain, en cessant l'existence des organisations centrales et statutaires de l'Eglise unie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1466.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1478.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Comme effet de cette décision, les biens ayant appartenu aux organisations statutaires et centrales furent repris par l'État, à l'exception des biens des paroisses revenus au sein du culte orthodoxe roumain.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1479.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1487.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Après la chute du régime communiste, en décembre 1989, le décret de 1948 fut abrogé.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1487.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1503.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Suite à cette abrogation, l'Église roumaine unie à Rome fut reconnue officiellement et le 25 avril 1990 fut adopté le décret loi 126 afin de régler la question des biens appropriés par décision de l'État en 1948.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1504.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1521.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Comme les biens ayant appartenu aux anciennes paroisses greco-catholiques et consistant notamment dans des lieux de culte, maisons paroissiales et cimetières se trouvaient dans la possession des paroisses orthodoxes, il apparaissait que tout règlement de la question des biens devait se fonder sur l'entente entre les deux cultes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1522.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1549.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ainsi, avant l'adoption de cet acte normatif, les représentants des deux cultes, avec l'appui des autorités étatiques, ont agréé comme solution au problème de l'usage et de la restitution des lieux de culte la constitution de commissions mixtes au niveau central et local qui examinent les modalités pratiques de règlement dans un état de dialogue fraternel et sans que les situations litigieuses entraînent la division entre les fidèles roumains.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1550.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1561.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La solution retenue donc dans le décret 126 exprime les termes de l'accord convenu avec la prise en considération de la volonté des fidèles des communautés détendrices de ces biens.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1562.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1572.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toutefois, l'Etat n'ignorait pas son rôle car l'article 4 du même décret-loi prévoyait son engagement à appuyer la construction de nouveaux lieux de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1572.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1598.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Conscient de la pratique d'hivergence des tribunaux internes qui tantôt refusaient, tantôt acceptaient de juger des litiges portés devant eux par des paroisses mécontentes du déroulement de la procédure de la commission mixte, le gouvernement initia en 2004 un amendement au décret-loi 126 afin de reconnaître de manière expresse le libre accès à la justice en cas d'échec de la procédure amiable.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1599.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1621.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Contrairement à ce que la partie recurrente allègue, ni l'exposé des motifs des amendements ni les interventions des membres du Parlement et du président de la République pendant les débats sur ce projet de législation, de modification législative, n'ont eu la moindre intention de changer en substance le cadre déjà tracé pour clarifier la situation des lieux de culte en question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1622.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1636.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les pièces écrites déjà versées au dossier témoignent clairement de la portée de ces amendements limitées à confirmer la compétence des instances nationales de trancher les litiges visant la restitution des lieux de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1636.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1639.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ces amendements se bornaient à clarifier la procédure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1639.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1657.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La référence au droit commun visait seulement des questions comme le choix entre la compétence des tribunaux de première instance et celle des tribunaux départementaux, l'exemption des droits de timbre, la soumission aux règles générales pour l'introduction d'une action à justice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1658.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1673.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En même temps, les débats au sein du Parlement soulignèrent une fois de plus que le fond de la question de la restitution restait gouverné par le respect du alentendre entre les deux églises vu leur autonomie et la nature spécifique des lieux de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1674.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1690.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ainsi, sur le plan législatif, la portée et la sphère d'application du critère de la volonté des fidèles avisaient constamment la nécessité de respecter la liberté religieuse des communautés tant dans la procédure préalable que dans la procédure judiciaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1691.24</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1704.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette approche fut confirmée par la Cour constitutionnelle qui, dans sa pratique, a apprécié que la liberté de culte implique non seulement leur autonomie envers l'Etat, mais aussi le respect des croyances religieuses.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1704.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1725.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans les conditions où, dans la même communauté, des croyants orthodoxes et gréco-catholiques cohabitent, le critère social de l'option de la majorité des fidèles correspond au principe démocratique de la détermination de l'usage religieux de ce bien en fonction de la volonté majoritaire de ceux qui en sont les bénéficiaires.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1725.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1729.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La jurisprudence des instances internes suit le même raisonnement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1730.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1746.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le gouvernement ne nie pas et ne saurait le faire que la pratique des tribunaux nationaux fut, jusqu'au niveau des années 2011-2012, peu convergente et que les instances judiciaires ont tantôt accueilli que rejeté des actions en révendication classique des édifices de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1746.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1779.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toutefois, dans une pratique consolidée après 2011 et largement majoritaire, la haute Cour de cassation et de justice, l'instance suprême en Roumanie, estime qu'on ne pourrait pas ignorer le rôle du critère de la volonté des croyants dans la mesure où la réconstitution du droit de propriété sur un lieu de culte ne peut pas avoir lieu in abstracto en ignorant les réalités sociales et historiques et l'atténuation des anciens préjudices ne peut pas créer de nouvelles inéquités sociales disproportionnées.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1779.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1792.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ainsi, la majorité considérable des arrêts prononcés après l'année 2012 par la Haute Cour que par les autres instances nationales appliquent les règles d'une action en restitution spéciale.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1792.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1802.24</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le parcours de la jurisprudence interne indique ainsi la capacité de l'ordre juridique de résorber la divergence initiale de jurisprudence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1802.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1807.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mesdames et messieurs les juges, j'en viens maintenant à une autre précision essentielle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1807.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1815.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pourquoi ce critère spécial de l'action en restitution est affirmé par le législateur et confirmé par les instances internes?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1815.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1819.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Parce qu'il s'agit de la restitution d'un lieu de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1819.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1831.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La partie recurrente a maintenant parlé, dans ses observations écrites et orales, de la restitution d'un bien revendiqué par elle selon les règles de l'action en revendication classique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1831.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1838.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais un lieu de culte ne peut pas être considéré un simple bien immobilier, évaluable pécuniairement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1838.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1851.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tout au contraire, il est intimement lié à une communauté des fidèles et représente un corollaire de la liberté religieuse, une modalité concrète d'exprimer, d'extérioriser leur croyance.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1851.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1867.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Un lieu de culte ne saurait être perçu seulement d'une manière pratique, car il est inséparable de la composante humaine des croyants qui se manifestent pour le garder, croyants qui en exercent de cette manière aussi leur liberté de religion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1868.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1879.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Même si le lieu de culte figure dans le livre foncier comme la propriété d'une paroisse, il appartient en effet à la communauté que cette paroisse guide et aide.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1879.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1888.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, toute paroisse représente en premier lieu une communauté des fidèles et ne saurait justifier ou continuer son existence en leur absence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1889.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1908.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pour ces raisons, toute intervention d'une autorité de l'Etat dans l'utilisation et la détention du lieu de culte doit d'une part être caractérisée par le principe de neutralité et d'autre part par le but de ne pas produire de nouvelles conséquences négatives sur les intérêts de la communauté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1909.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1930.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le système juridique mis en place au niveau national a permis aux paroisses mécontentes du déroulement de la procédure de la commission mixte, tout comme le requérant, de porter leurs affaires devant les instants judiciaires compétents, de formuler leurs arguments, d'être assistés par un professionnel du droit et d'obtenir un jugement qui examine la substance même de leurs droits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1930.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1945.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cependant, l'analyse sur le fond de l'affaire ne serait signifiée que les instances devraient se bourner seulement à vérifier les inscriptions dans le livre foncier, justement pour le besoin du respect de la liberté religieuse de la communauté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1946.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1958.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tout au contraire, leur examen doit tenir compte des aspects spécifiques des actions visant la restitution des lieux de culte pour être en mesure d'établir la communauté qui est la plus liée à l'édifice en question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1958.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1987.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mesdames et messieurs les juges, s'il est vrai que, pour une bonne période de temps, les instances ont eu des difficultés à combiner les dispositions du droit commun avec les dispositions de la législation spéciale, ainsi que de décider la manière dont le critère prévu par la loi spéciale doit être appliqué, à présent, le problème de la divergence de jurisprudence quant à l'application du critère spécial dans les actions à restitution des lieux de culte ne représente qu'une issue de nature historique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1988.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>1995.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est notre ferme conviction que l'application du critère de la volonté des fidèles est à présent claire et prévisible.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>1995.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2006.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tout comme déjà indiqué dans mon intervention, les amendements à la loi n'ont eu la moindre intention de limiter son application seulement à la phase de la procédure de commission mixte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2006.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2026.84</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le recours au critère de la volonté des croyants seulement dans la procédure préalable et son ignorance dans la procédure judiciaire, si la procédure préalable n'est pas à parcourir, signifierait un enhantissement de la volonté de la communauté qui utilise et a même contribué au bâtiment du lieu de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2027.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2037.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans la pratique des instances nationales, afin de clarifier la volonté des fidèles, le nombre de croyants recensés dans une localité peut instituer une présomption.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2037.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2043.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toutefois, celle-ci peut être renversée par des motifs, par des éléments objectifs ou subjectifs.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2044.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2068.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En effet, les instances judiciaires sont appelées à déceler la volonté des croyants d'une multitude de facteurs, sociaux, historiques, juridiques, et à apprécier le bien fondé, et se penchent sur plusieurs éléments de preuve, comme les témoignages et les listes des fidèles et les procès verbaux des réunions des membres d'une paroisse, afin de confirmer ou de renverser cette présomption.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2069.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2084.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La partie recurrente considère que toute référence au nombre de croyants est incompatible avec le respect du droit d'accès, car de cette manière, le sort de toute action en justice est prédéterminé et le rôle des instances nationales purement formel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2084.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2089.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Avec tout le respect pour un argument juridique, on ne pourrait pas partager une telle position.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2089.68</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2103.68</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En 1990, au moment où l'acte normatif prévoyant la prise en compte de la volonté des fidèles fut adopté, toutes les options des membres de la communauté et des anciens paroissiens gréco-catholiques étaient ouvertes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2103.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2120.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cette potentielle restructuration de la communauté locale nécessitait aussi une solution pour la propriété sur le lieu de culte, en considérant que le sort de ce type d'édifice, de sa destination spécifique, doit être en accord avec la volonté des croyants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2121.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2132.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mesdames et messieurs les juges, les instances nationales sont confrontées de manière fréquente aux situations où elles doivent comparer les structures de la communauté en 1948 et à présent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2132.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2155.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans ces situations, vu qu'après l'écoulement d'un certain lance de temps, 15, 20, même 25 ans, le nombre de croyants n'a pas enregistré de fluctuation, les instances nationales considèrent que la volonté des croyants doit être interprétée dans le sens du maintien de leur appartenance au culte orthodoxe, choix qu'ils ont fait en toute liberté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2155.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2162.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toutefois, contrairement à ce que soutiennent nos contradicteurs, cette conclusion n'est pas la seule et limitée démarche des instances judiciaires.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2162.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2174.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En effet, comme la Cour suprême l'a constamment indiquée, elle est intégrée dans une analyse complexe et complète qui vise en substance la demande de restitution dans lieu de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2174.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2191.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans le cadre de cette analyse, les tribunaux internes appliquent dans un premier temps des règles générales de procédure afin de déterminer la qualité de parti et l'existence prima facie de leur titre sur la base des inscriptions dans le livre foncier et d'autres documents.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2191.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2197.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ensuite, il recourt à une vérification de l'objet du litige et de son existence physique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2197.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2214.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans une troisième étape, les instances judiciaires rétablissent la configuration actuelle de la communauté, sa structure et sa contribution au bâtiment ou à l'administration du lieu de culte litigieux avant 1948 et tirent les conclusions de ces éléments.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2214.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2239.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Quant à la prévisibilité de ce critère, il ne saurait être ignoré le fait que la pratique des instances nationales même avant et certainement après la date du 15 juin 2011, quand la demande en révendication des requérants était définitivement tranchée, indique que le critère de la volonté des croyants était pris en compte dans les décisions sur la restitution d'un lieu de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2239.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2250.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>De plus, bien avant la date du 15 juin 2011, la pratique de la haute cour indiquait la nécessité pour les instances d'appel de ne pas ignorer ce critère.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2250.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2268.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Sans vouloir revenir sur nos observations écrites, je me borne à souligner qu'à partir de l'année 2012, 40 arrêts rendus par la haute cour et figurant dans les annexes à ces observations, suivent la ligne d'argumentation telle qu'elle vient de vous être présentée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2268.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2271.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce nombre pourrait paraître à première vue modeste.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2271.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2279.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il n'est à sa puissance réelle que dans le contexte plus large des données globales sur la restitution des lieux de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2279.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2296.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les données officielles montrent que du nombre total de 242 lieux de culte restitués à l'Église gréco-catholique, plus de 70 % ont été restitués dans un cadre hors judiciaire en application du critère de la volonté de la majorité.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2296.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2299.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les situations concrètes sont certes différentes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2299.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2306.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Certains édifices ont été repris par les anciens paroissiens qui sont revenus au sein de l'Église uniate.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2306.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2310.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Certains lieux de culte ont été restitués suite au dialogue interconfessionnel.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2310.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2316.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Seulement moins de 30 % des lieux de culte ont été restitués par voie judiciaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2316.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2326.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>À présent, sur le rôle de tribunaux internes, sont inscrites 51 actions introduites par des paroisses gréco-catholiques et visant à la restitution des lieux de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2326.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2341.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toutefois, et cette précision est importante, une partie de ces affaires a été renvoyée par la juridiction de recours, le plus souvent à la haute cour, pour examen avec prise en considération du critère de la volonté des fidèles.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2341.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2372.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Vu le nombre de lieux de culte dont la situation est déjà réglée et la finalisation par décision définitive de la haute cour d'un nombre important de procédures judiciaires ainsi que le nombre assez réduit de procédures encore pendantes, je prie votre honorable court de constater que la situation des lieux de culte a été réglée au niveau national, la pratique nationale consolidée et entoffère au critère de la volonté des fidèles la confirmation de sa prévisibilité.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2372.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2392.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Revenir sur l'application de ce critère que la partie requérante prône ne contribuerait qu'à déstabiliser une pratique nationale convergente et les intérêts déjà clarifiés des communautés des fidèles en affectant une sécurité juridique qui couvre non seulement les solutions judiciaires mais aussi les solutions amiables.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2392.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2416.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Disons-le franchement, il serait incorrect d'accepter l'application du critère de la volonté des fidèles dans plus de 70% des cas si cette application entraîne la restitution des lieux de culte à l'Église gréco-catholique pour le reste de fermement dans une minorité de situations où la même volonté plaide pour que l'édifice reste dans l'usage de la majorité.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2416.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2438.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mesdames et Messieurs les juges, de tout ce qui précède, il résulte plus qu'évidemment que le but légitime de l'institution du critère de la volonté des fidèles a été la préservation du respect pour la liberté religieuse des communautés qui, guidés par les représentants de leurs clergés, sont mieux placés pour identifier une solution adoptée à leurs besoins.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2438.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2447.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Même votre Cours, dans l'affaire Vergos contre Grèce, a confirmé la légitimité de la prise en compte de la volonté de la majorité d'une communauté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2447.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2472.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les juges, c'est dans ce cadre général que les requérants ont soumis à l'attention du tribunal départemental de Hounedouara le 23 mai 2001, leur demande visant à l'annulation de l'expropriation opérée en 1948 relative à l'Église et aux cimetières situées à l'Upen, et la restitution de ces biens à la pareuse requérante.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2472.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2482.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Après une procédure qui connut plusieurs étapes et le gouvernement le reconnaît, plusieurs cassations avaient cramé pour réexamen, leur action fut rejetée comme mal fondée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2482.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2504.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'arrêt de la Cour d'appel d'Alba Iulia, confirmée en recours par la Haute Cour, constata tout d'abord sur la base de moyens de preuve déposés au dossier, des écrits et des témoignages que l'Église revendiquée avait été construite entre 1906 et 1920 par des orthodoxes que par des catholiques qui tout cohabitaient à l'Upen.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2504.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2509.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Après sa construction, l'Église avait servi pour l'office alternatif des messes pour les deux cultes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2509.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2513.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les cimetières avaient servi d'eux-mêmes les deux cultes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2513.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2526.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Également, la Cour d'appel constata qu'à l'Upen, la majorité des gréco-catholiques qui avaient changé leur religion vers l'orthodoxie dans les années 40 n'est plus revenue au culte uniate après les années 90.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2526.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2531.5</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dès lors, ils ont continué à utiliser l'Église en cause en tant qu'orthodoxe.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2531.5</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2541.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les Juges, force est de constater que les requérants ont pu présenter leur demande à la restitution du lieu de culte devant les instances nationales.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2541.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2562.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans l'analyse sur le fond, les instances s'admiraient qu'après 1948, les croyants gréco-catholiques furent obligés de quitter leur culte et de rejoindre l'Église orthodoxe, apprécièrent que dès son édification, le lieu de culte était partagé en ce qui concerne la contribution pour le bâtiment et l'usage.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2562.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2577.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, étant vu l'objet de l'action à restitution ainsi que les particularités de l'affaire, les instances d'appel et de recours ont pris en considération la volonté des croyants tant au moment de l'édification comme au moment de l'examen de l'affaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2577.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2585.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La solution retenue est en accord avec la jurisprudence de la Cour constitutionnelle et avec la pratique interne des instances.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2585.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2602.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'application du critère de la volonté des croyants ne pouvait pas représenter un élément imprévisible, surtout dans la situation de la paroisse requérante où le lieu de culte, bien qu'inscrit sous son nom, appartenait du fait de contributions à l'édification à la communauté locale dans son ensemble.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2602.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2607.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Une dernière remarque avant de vous prier de bien vouloir donner la parole à ma collègue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2607.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2615.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le gouvernement est tout à fait conscient du cadre qui fonde tout examen d'une affaire devant la Cour européenne dans une procédure de renvoi.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2615.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2635.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toutefois, le gouvernement note avec inquiétude que la partie requérante utilise ce cadre en principal non pour affirmer ses critiques par rapport à la procédure interne de la part courrieuse, mais pour promouvoir une actio popularis en critiquant la jurisprudence des instances nationales en général.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2635.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2649.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous considérons que, nonobstant les particularités d'un examen en pré-renvoi, l'analyse de la Cour reste marquée par les dispositions de l'article 34 et doit avec nécessité viser le cas particulier de la partie requérante.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2649.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2651.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous remercie et je vous prie de bien vouloir donner la parole à ma collègue.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2653.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2655.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup, Mme Brumar.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2655.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2658.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mme Ezer, vous avez la parole pour 7 minutes.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2660.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2673.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les Juges, permettez-moi de clarifier et de détailler maintenant certains aspects pertinents dans l'analyse de la prétendue discrimination soufferte par la paroisse requérante.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2673.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2681.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Tout d'abord, nous apprécions que la paroisse requérante n'a pas été placée dans une situation désavantageuse du fait de sa religion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2681.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2704.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le critère spécial n'a pas été introduit et n'a pas été appliqué dans la pratique afin de favoriser une certaine communauté, mais afin de permettre aux croyants de décider sur l'usage d'un bien qu'ils ont bâti, qui leur était destiné, dans un climat qui ne créait plus de désinjustices qu'ils essaient de corriger.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2704.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2717.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ainsi, la paroisse requérante n'a pas été discriminée ni par rapport aux communautés religieuses orthodoxes, ni par rapport aux autres communautés gréco-catholiques se trouvant dans une situation analogue à la sienne.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2717.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2736.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Comme déjà indiqué dans l'intervention de ma collègue, le critère de la volonté des fidèles a été prévu par la législation afin de tenir compte du contexte historique et social et de la nature spécifique des lieux de culte et de préserver le respect pour la liberté religieuse des communautés.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2736.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2753.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le lieu de culte étant considéré comme appartenant à la communauté, par la manifestation de la volonté des fidèles de réintégrer le culte niâtre ou de conserver l'appartenance au culte orthodoxe, les croyants qui utilisaient un lieu de culte avaient la possibilité de garder son usage.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2753.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2773.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le choix du législateur préservait en même temps la neutralité de l'État dans ses relations avec le culte et les intérêts des fidèles composant la communauté, de manifester leur liberté de religion et donner expression au respect pour l'autonomie des communautés religieuses reconnues par l'État.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2773.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2790.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous ne saurions ignorer que, dans un premier temps, dans l'application des dispositions légales confirmant l'accès à la justice pour la restitution des lieux de culte, certaines de telles demandes ont été solutionnées en application des règles spécifiques à l'action à revendication.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2790.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2819.76</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toutefois, je dois souligner de nouveau que ces solutions ont été prononcées dans l'intervalle du temps qui a été nécessaire à l'ordre juridique pour faire absorber la divergence du juridique sur la modalité de trancher les actions en restitution des lieux de culte et que, même dans le cadre de ces actions, l'application des règles de l'action à la revendication classique n'a pas eu comme effet l'accueil automatique de toutes demandes de restitution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2819.76</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2828.0</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Par conséquent, les requérants n'ont pas été victimes d'un traitement discriminatoire par rapport à d'autres paroisses gréco-catholiques.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2828.0</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2847.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La partie requérante plaide pour une application dans la présente affaire des conclusions de la Cour dans son arrêt paroisses gréco-catholiques Sumbatabichor contre Roumanie de 2010, car, à la différence d'autres paroisses gréco-catholiques, son action a été rejetée en application du critère de la volonté de fidèle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2847.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2861.96</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous rappelons que les conclusions de la Cour dans cette affaire portaient sur le libre accès à l'instance vu la réticence de certains tribunaux de se considérer compétents pour connaître d'une demande en restitution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2861.96</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2872.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais, après les modifications législatives, l'action de la requérante, comme les demandes en justice d'autres paroisses gréco-catholiques, a été examinée sur le fond.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2872.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2895.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans le cas des requérants, les instances nationales ont effectué une mise en balance des intérêts en cause en prenant en compte un ensemble d'éléments factuels concrets relatifs à l'édification et à l'usage du lieu de culte au fil des années, à l'interdiction du culte ignate, ainsi qu'aux choix opérés par ces fidèles après la réhabilitation de leur culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2895.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2918.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En ce qui concerne l'éventuel traitement discriminatoire par rapport à l'Église orthodoxe, en premier lieu, la partie requérante apprécie qu'elle fut placée dans une situation désavantageuse vu qu'elle initia la procédure de restitution en qualité de demandeur, tandis que le lieu de culte appartenait à l'Église orthodoxe qui pouvait donc refuser la restitution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2918.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2941.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Accueillir l'argument des requérants signifierait considérer que toute personne qui cherche la restitution d'un bien d'une autre personne qui le détient est placée dans une situation désavantageuse et donc discriminée par rapport au défendant, le propriétaire par rapport au possesseur ou le locateur par rapport au locataire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2941.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2948.04</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En tel argument, toute une philosophie juridique ne saurait pas être retenue.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2948.04</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2961.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>De plus, nous l'avons déjà dit, bien que le critère de la volonté des croyants ait été appliqué dans le cas de la partie requérante, il a été fait dans le cadre d'une analyse sur le fond de l'affaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2961.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2968.4</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La simple application de ce critère est constitutive d'une discrimination, se tient les requérants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2968.4</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2982.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais les paroisses gréco-catholiques ont fait aussi recours et ont bénéficié même de l'application du critère de la volonté des fidèles qui, par ailleurs, fut introduit dans la législation en termes suite à l'accord des deux cultes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2982.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>2999.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mesdames et messieurs les juges, un nombre important des lieux de culte est revenu dans le patrimoine de l'Église gréco-catholique suite à la manifestation de volonté des fidèles de rejoindre ce culte ou des fidèles orthodoxes de restituer volontairement le lieu de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>2999.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3027.48</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les requérants réclament à présent, 25 ans après l'adoption de la législation spécifique, une discrimination attirée par l'application de ce critère en voulant ignorer le choix fait par les membres de la communauté de rester au sein du culte orthodoxe et la valeur de ce critère en tant qu'instrument permettant aux communautés de trouver les solutions les plus appropriées pour satisfaire à leurs besoins.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3027.48</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3030.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Non en dernier lieu, nous devons l'affirmer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3030.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3042.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le législateur a réglé la manière de préserver l'équilibre entre les différents terrains à jeu en prévoyant des mesures réparatrices pour la partie qui perdrait le lieu de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3042.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3048.08</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nos observations écrites comprennent dans leurs annexes des exemples de ce type d'appui.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3048.08</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3064.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je me bornerai à mentionner ici que seulement dans les départements de Moureche, Timiche, Alba, Bichor et Maramoureche, cet appui a couvert le droit de 176 terrains pour l'édification des lieux de culte et une aide financière de presque un million de lirements.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3064.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3078.56</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les informations fournies par le Secrétariat d'État pour les cultes confirment cet appui de l'État, proportionnellement avec le nombre de fidèles en prenant aussi en considération les besoins réels de ceux-ci.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3078.56</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3093.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ainsi, pour la période 2000-2014, l'aide financière offerte par le Secrétariat d'État à l'Église Uniate, en montant de 21 millions de lirements, a représenté plus de 2,2% du budget global de l'institution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3093.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3102.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les fidèles de ce culte représentent, conforme au recensement, seulement 0,8% de la population.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3102.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3118.8</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>De plus, seulement en 2015, l'Église greco-catholique a reçu un financement pour l'édification des lieux de culte de plus de 3 millions de lirements, représentant 1,85% des sommes totales octroyées par cette institution.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3118.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3123.44</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Paroisse sur Caronne n'a pas voulu bénéficier de ce type d'appui.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3123.44</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3130.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Elle n'a pas sollicité ni du terrain pour l'édification d'un lieu de culte, ni l'octroi d'une autre forme d'aide.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3130.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3152.2</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En même temps, une autre paroisse de la même localité, à savoir la paroisse greco-catholique Berbatsène, s'est vue octroyée en 2012 par une décision des autorités locales, à titre gratuit, en terrain à surface de 1 500 m2 à Lupin, pour l'édification d'un lieu de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3152.2</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3178.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les Juges, Vu tous les arguments présentés devant votre cour et nos positions écrites déjà versées au dossier de la grande chambre, nous vous prions de bien vouloir statuer sur le respect par l'État défendeur des exigences de droit à un procès équitable et de l'interdiction de toute discrimination dans l'exercice du droit par la partie requérante.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3178.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3180.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous remercie pour votre courtoise attention.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3181.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3183.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup, Mme Ezer.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3183.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3187.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je remercie les 2 parties pour leurs interventions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3187.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3193.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et maintenant, je m'adresse à mes collègues pour les inviter à poser au parti les questions qu'ils souhaitent.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3193.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3193.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vois M. le juge Spano.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3197.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3200.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3200.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3212.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I am mindful that the way in which the case is presented to the Grand Chamber is that we are first and foremost dealing with an Article 6 complaint and not Article 9 or Article 1 or Protocol 1 complaint.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3212.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3228.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In that respect, I would like to ask the applicant mainly, but the government can respond as well, to clarify the essence of the right of access to court complaint.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3228.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3243.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In paragraphs 11 and 12 of the applicant's observation, it is stated that the right to access to a court implies an effective access to a decision on the merits of the case without a predetermined and a biased decision of the domestic courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3243.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3262.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's then explained in paragraph 12 more deeply, where it's stated, instead of comparing the titles to property of the two parties, the courts dismissing the applicant's claim over their church reduced their role to a formal one, deciding that the will of the majority applies, therefore the church should not be returned.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3262.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3267.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And here it's where I want to pose the question.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3267.87</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3282.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Assuming that the court would accept the government's invitation to look at the access to court issue, not in the abstract, but looking at it, how it was applied in your case, the applicant's case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3282.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3314.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If I read paragraphs 32 and 34 of the Chamber Judgment, where the Court of Appeal judgment is described and then the judgment of the High Court of Cassation, it says in paragraph 2 of the Chamber Judgment that the Court of Appeal explicitly looked to the fact that the title that the Orthodox Church received, even though initially unlawful, had become valid when the transfer was made, and then it says, with the result that the action to recover possession was ill-founded.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3314.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3329.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The High Court of Cassation also refers to the fact that for title to property to be assessed, there needs to be a possession under the ordinary rules.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3329.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3341.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So could you please clarify, is it your contention that in your case, no examination of the title deeds took place?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3341.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3346.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And as you described, therefore, the role of the courts were purely a formal one.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3346.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3357.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And if that is the case, could you please explain how the Grand Chamber should read the Court of Appeals judgments and the High Court of Cassation judgment on that particular issue?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3357.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3360.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the government, as I said, could clarify its position as well.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Robert Spano</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3360.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3360.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3361.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3363.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3363.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3365.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Maintenant, Mme la Présidente Karakaş.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Işıl Karakaş</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3369.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3371.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup, M. le Président.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Işıl Karakaş</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3371.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3375.64</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ma première question concerne pour les deux parties, je dirais.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Işıl Karakaş</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3375.64</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3388.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Est-ce que ces deux principes qui figurent en fait dans la législation, ça veut dire l'application du droit commun et les critères de la volonté de la majorité sont conciliables?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Işıl Karakaş</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3388.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3401.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous demande justement de faire une réponse à cette question tout en prenant compte la décision de la Cour constitutionnelle de 2012 qui conforme sa décision antérieure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Işıl Karakaş</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3401.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3408.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Deuxièmement, ma question concerne surtout le gouvernement, mais bien sûr aussi le récréant, si vous pouvez répondre.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Işıl Karakaş</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3408.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3420.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>J'aimerais savoir les exemples de restitution d'un lien de culte à l'Église gréco-catholique, même si la volonté des croyants orthodoxes n'était pas dans ce sens.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Işıl Karakaş</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3420.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3438.42</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, bien sûr, il faut mettre à part la décision de la haute cour de 20 juin 2013 qui concerne un bien qui n'est pas utilisé par les fidèles orthodoxes et qui ne fournit pas en réalité un exemple de ce type.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Işıl Karakaş</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3438.42</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3441.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Donc, j'aimerais savoir les autres exemples de justice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Işıl Karakaş</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3441.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3441.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3442.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3443.87</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup Madame. Judge O’Leary please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3448.8</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3450.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3450.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3458.28</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I have two questions which are principally addressed to the respondent government, but the applicant is free to answer these questions also in their reply.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3458.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3474.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>First of all, Article 329 of the Code of Civil Procedure, now Article 514, provides for the possibility of introducing an appeal in the interests of the law before the High Court of Cassation and Justice, where the same questions of law have been decided differently by different courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3474.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3479.72</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The purpose of this action is to ensure the uniform interpretation and application of the law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3479.72</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3491.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I'd like the government to inform us why this mechanism was never deployed in response to the divergent case law, which the government itself has recognized existed, on the restitution of places of worship.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3491.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3507.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My second question, which also refers to Romanian legislation, concerns Ordinance 94 of 2000, which provided that the legal status of buildings which serve as places of worship shall be established by a special law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3507.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3512.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>From the information in the case file before us, it appears that no such law was ever adopted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3512.92</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3521.32</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So it would be useful if the government could outline what that special law was intended to provide, and more importantly, why it was never adopted.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3521.32</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3543.52</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The question which is addressed principally to the applicants, but again, the government is invited or welcome to respond to it in their reply, relates to Article 4 of Legislative Degree 126-1990, which provides that the state may provide for support for the construction of new churches and may make available appropriate land and funds for that purpose.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3543.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3551.22</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Again, according to the information in the case file, many other Greek Catholic parishes have sought to avail of Article 4.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3551.22</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3554.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My question is therefore, has the applicant parish done so?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Síofra O’Leary</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3554.82</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3555.82</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And if not, why not?</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3558.84</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3560.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3560.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3561.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mr. President, Sajó please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3563.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3565.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3565.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3571.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>May I take up on the last question of my learned colleague?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3571.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3598.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Is there a law in place that would, in fact, provide details in regard to the legislative decree of 1990, in particular regarding Article 4?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3598.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3603.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So is there a law implementing it?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3603.27</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3614.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now, I'm sorry, but I really have to ask very elementary questions for those who know Romanian law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3614.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3616.91</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I'm not privileged in that regard.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3616.91</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3640.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So could the government, but of course the applicant's lawyer is free to comment, could the government explain to me what would be an ordinary vindicatio rei procedure or proceedings in a case that is not related to this specific situation?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3640.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3643.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And you emphasize that it is about a specific situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3643.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3646.31</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will come back to that.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3646.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3652.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I ask this, and I would like clarification, because of the following reason.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3652.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3672.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I've seen a number of judgments where, and it's also in the judgment of the chamber, that the procedure is generally, as in most countries, a comparison of titles.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3672.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3679.23</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now in the countries I'm familiar with, the more recent title shall prevail.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3679.23</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3693.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the more recent title in those countries I know would be the claim of the Orthodox, because in this case, in 1967, in other cases anyway after 1948, it was transferred to the Orthodox.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3693.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3704.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It seems to be that this is not the case in Romania, because if this were the case, there is no reason for the special law.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3704.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3716.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So I wonder what is really the situation in this type of return of property cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3716.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3731.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Without the interpretation given by the Constitutional Court, I understand that your position is that this is a specific issue because it is related to the exercise of freedom of religion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3731.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3736.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I understand that there can be arguments made that a special law applies.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3736.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3742.15</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But what if there is no special law?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3742.15</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3766.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Is it the case that the 1990 decree, legislative decree, in principle, annulled the titles, created a situation where possession matters, but title is not anymore in place, the 1948 title?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3766.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3769.63</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I just don't understand the situation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3769.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3778.47</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now may I ask again the government to explain the relevance of census.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3778.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3797.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Was the census taken with a specific provision indicating that those who declared to pertain to one or another religion express their wish to maintain property?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3797.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3805.67</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Was this purely statistical or was it an expression of will?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3805.67</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3815.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The people who were subjected to the census aware of possible implications of their choice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3815.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3829.51</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Secondly, is the declaration in the census an indicator of the actual religious practice?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3829.51</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3844.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Do you have data on actual religious practice compared to the census data?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3844.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3848.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>May I ask a hypothetical?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3848.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3865.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Imagine that there is a diocese where there were 100 Greek Catholic churches before 1948.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3865.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3876.43</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the Greek Catholics were also in the diocese in an absolute majority or relative majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3876.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3890.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Let's imagine, and this is my hypothetical question, that today, according to the statistical average, they are below 1%, but we have cases where there were 30%.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3890.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3893.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So imagine, let's take that scenario.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3893.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3905.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Let's assume that there are 30% believers of the Greek Catholic faith.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3905.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3937.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Is it the case that although there are 30% believers following the principle of the wish or will of the majority as expressed in the census, all 100 shall be returned, all 100 former Catholic churches shall be kept by the orthodox majority?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3937.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3958.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Is that result foreseeable in case the bill of the majority is followed as indicated by the or understood by the constitutional court?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3958.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3962.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I think that's one more question to the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3962.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3977.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Do I understand you correctly that this being a special law, the decisive consideration is the will of the majority?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3977.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>3995.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So in other words, if under the Vindicatio Rei title, it would be Greek Catholic to have the title, this is a precondition for a consideration by the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>3995.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4004.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And then the considerations of the religious majority shall prevail.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4004.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4011.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And if so, is this something that falls under the exceptions of Golder?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4011.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4015.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Because it is not an absolute right to have access to the court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4015.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4020.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the question is whether this is one of the exceptions recognized by Golder.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>András Sajó</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4020.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4020.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4022.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4024.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4024.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4026.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now, Judge Pinto de Albuquerque, please.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4028.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4031.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you, Mr. President.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4031.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4042.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>My question is addressed to the applicant, but of course the government can also take a position on this.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4042.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4056.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The applicant's position is that, and the core of the applicant's argumentation is that the rights of a minority are illusory if they are in the hands of the majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4056.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4085.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now, in order to check if Romanian law, the 1990 law, effectively protects in practical terms the property rights of the Greek Catholics, could you please provide the court with the overall market value for property returned until today to Greek Catholics in terms of buildings and building area?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4085.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4095.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And could you compare this market value with the market value for the property not returned?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4095.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4098.07</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You need not, of course, to be precise.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4098.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4100.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>An overall idea would suffice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Paulo Pinto de Albuquerque</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4100.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4100.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4102.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4104.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4104.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4109.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>S'il n'y a pas d'autres questions, donc la cour va maintenant...</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4109.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4111.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Pardon.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4111.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4113.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Oh, I'm sorry.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4113.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4113.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Monsieur le juge Ravarani, je vous en prie.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4115.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4117.34</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci, M. le Président.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4117.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4121.54</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>J'ai une toute petite question qui est posée conjointement aux 2 partis.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4121.54</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4133.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>J'étais étonné d'entendre pendant les plaidoiries que les 2 partis ne sont pas d'accord sur les travaux parlementaires qui ont donné lieu à la définition de la notion de droit commun, qui me paraît essentielle dans cette affaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4133.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4139.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il est tout à fait étonnant qu'on ne puisse pas se mettre d'accord sur ce qui a été finalement dit au Parlement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4139.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4147.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et il serait utile que les 2 partis puissent donner une réponse univoque sur ce que veut signifier droit commun.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4147.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4159.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Est-ce vraiment le droit traditionnel de la comparaison des titres, comme le prétend l'avocate de la partie récurrente, ou est-ce que c'est la règle de la volonté de la majorité?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4159.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4168.94</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On peut interpréter une loi, ça c'est tout à fait normal, mais on pourrait quand même pouvoir se mettre d'accord sur ce qui a été dit au Parlement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4168.94</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4178.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il m'intéresserait que les 2 partis puissent donner une réponse plus univoque et pas totalement contradictoire quant à cet effet objectif.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Judge</Role>
        <Name>Georges Ravarani</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4178.74</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4178.74</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous remercie.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4180.52</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4182.6</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4182.6</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4185.16</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Maintenant, il n'y a vraiment pas d'autres questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4185.16</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4188.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et alors, la cour va se retirer pour 20 minutes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4188.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4192.36</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je dirais donc qu'on reprend en 11 heures moins de 20.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4192.36</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4203.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Après quoi, les partis pourront présenter de brèves observations, réponses aux plaidoiries adverses et répondre aux questions des juges.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4203.12</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4203.12</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'audience est suspendue.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Announcer</Role>
        <Name>UNK</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4270.28</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4270.92</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour!</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4310.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4313.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous en prie, prenez place.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4314.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4315.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'audience est reprise.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4316.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4319.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et la parole est à maître Hatneanu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4319.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4320.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Vous avez la parole maître.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4325.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4329.55</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I will start my rebuttal on a more personal note.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4329.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4334.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This case is one of the hardest I ever litigated, but not because it is very complex.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4334.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4342.11</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the contrary, it is so straightforward and so self-evident that any additional explanation seemed superfluous.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4342.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4351.35</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This case is not about the European courts overstepping the state's margin of appreciation or acting as a force instance, as the chamber considered.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4351.35</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4361.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is about the effectiveness in practice of a provision allowing for access to a court, which was already adopted by the state based on its margin of appreciation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4361.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4379.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is about the effectiveness of a legal provision that, as a result of a biased interpretation, allows only one party to access court, only to find out it is always wrong, unless the other party in the procedure agrees to the contrary.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4379.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4391.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The government produced only one case in which a Greek Catholic won, despite the will of the other party, and the cases from 2012, when the High Court jurisprudence was not fully developed according to the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4391.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4402.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On this issue, it is not clear for me when, at the moment, the government considers that this interpretation, this jurisprudence, was finally established.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4402.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4407.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As in the original observation, it states about 2012, 2013.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4407.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4412.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And today, we heard about 2010, 2011.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4412.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4417.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This case is about the current applicant, which fully benefited of a sham of a judicial procedure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4417.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4422.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>No, the court did not need time to adjust to a new legal provision.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4422.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4428.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that provision in itself, access to court based on the common law, was rather old.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4428.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4436.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The courts, and especially the High Court, needed time to find a way to overturn a decision of the legislator and to preserve the status quo.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4436.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4440.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is not effective access to justice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4440.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4456.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Isn't it rather strange that in the cases presented by the government, and the one before you included, the lower courts, which are closer to the affected communities, were more willing to apply the civil law and to allow the Greek Catholic claims, while the High Court forced them against it?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4456.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4468.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Isn't it strange that the High Court developed an apparently complicated system of assessing the Greek Catholic claims on the merits, but which in fact has only one aim, to virtually always dismiss these claims?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4468.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4474.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Some of the so-called assessment on the merits criteria are quite relevant in their cynical approach.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4474.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4479.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Greek Catholics did not willingly leave the church in 1948.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4479.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4484.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Those who refused to do so were imprisoned, and many died in prisons.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4484.89</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4493.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So how their inexistent willingness to leave the church in 1948 can become a criterion on the merits of their case now?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4493.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4502.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or how can it be held against them that no Greek Catholics were born after 1948 if the church was forcibly and officially disbanded?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4502.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4505.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>What matters is that they exist now.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4505.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4512.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the precondition obviously met in the present case, where we speak about 500 persons.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4512.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4528.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The so-called criteria are in fact, in our opinions, most strings to cover the unmeaningness to look at the merits of the property case and to leave the solution to the parties, something that the government is also claiming as rational in the name of state neutrality.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4528.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4531.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is called denial of justice in my book.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4531.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4538.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the government should have had the courage to assume it as such, not by overturning the meaning of a well-established legal phrase.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4538.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4543.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>This is a context of this case and not its merits.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4543.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4551.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So I cannot agree with the government's submission that the applicant's application can be considered an axio popularis.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4551.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4561.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If our it's an axio popularis, then what is the defense of the government, who all concentrated only on the general issues at stake?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4561.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4599.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In the applicant's case, a court of appeal and the high court especially mentioned the reason for limiting their right to a court, such as the government and, at the more general level, the constitutional court did, not to correct an abuse with another abuse, notwithstanding the unfairness and bias in equaling applying the law today with a blatant abuse of the communist regime and not an act of reparation as the government tried to present the 1948 Act, the applicants wonder on what would the concrete abuse generating by applying the civil law in their case had been.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4599.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4603.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The opposing party would have not been left without a place of worship.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4603.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4606.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Its members would not have been forced to leave their church.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4606.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4612.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They would still have two churches for practicing religion, one of which former Greek Catholic.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4612.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4617.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But such an analysis was never made by the domestic courts finding against the applicants.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4617.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4623.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>If the chamber judgment stays as it is, no such analysis would ever be made.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4623.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4632.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The will of the majority will be applied with full power as a sole criterion as being endorsed by the European court.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4632.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4672.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With regards to the questions the judges addressed the applicants, in respect of the question on the so-called analysis on the merits done by the Alba Iulia Court of Appeal and the High Court, two of the three judges of the High Court of Cassation and Justice, it is our interpretation, while reading the domestic procedure, the domestic legislation, and the judgment, that there was not a full analysis on the merits and full comparisons of title to properties done by the exact same courts which applies a principle of majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4672.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4688.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Junidwara Tribunal and also the minority judge in the High Court also performed a comparison of the titles to properties based on the same legal provision of the civil code, but without applying the principle of majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4688.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4696.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And their result was the exact opposite of those of the judges applying the principle of majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4696.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4698.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So it is our interpretation.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4698.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4716.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that's why I have insisted so much on the context of the affair and of the jurisprudence of the courts, not because we want to challenge the law as such in this particular case, but really understand what is going on in these cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4716.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4732.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So the judges applying the principle of majority, putting it at the core of their judgment on the merits, so-called merits, will also find ways to overturn the provisions of the civil law as well.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4732.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4754.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>For example, in this particular case, and there were questions about comparing titles to property in the system as well, what it matters is to see, and there is a whole jurisprudence before the European Court on property cases against Romania as such, and probably you are familiar with it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4754.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4779.73</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The procedure through which these churches should have been passed from the Greek Catholics with the help of the state to the Orthodox was provided by the decree 368 per 1948, and together with the decree 177 of 48 on churches.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4779.73</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4792.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the provision, the procedure provided for in these particular pieces of legislation was not followed in this specific case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4792.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4798.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So that should have been taken into consideration when comparing the titles to property as well.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4798.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4808.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And in the Romanian system, what it matters is not what title is the newest, but what is the most consolidated, as we call it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4808.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4821.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And you have the initial title of the Greek Catholics, which was registered in the land book, and you have then a title, a non-existent title of the Orthodox, because they had no title.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4821.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4835.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They registered in the late 60s their property based on the decree 358 of 84, but without the conditions of that decree being met.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4835.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4839.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So that should have been the analysis of the courts comparing the titles to property.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4839.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4849.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>You will find that kind of analysis, but a very brief one, in the decisions which enforce the principle of majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4849.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4857.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On the other hand, you will find a detailed analysis of all pieces of legislation by the courts that are not applying the principle of majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4857.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4863.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And of course, I'm referring to the present case, not any other case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4863.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4871.13</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There was a question about how the principle of majority and the provision of common law are compatible.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4871.13</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4876.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Indeed, it is probably the heart of the matter if the two are compatible or not.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4876.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4886.33</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As under the common law, the will of a one party does not relevant at all to the outcome of the procedure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4886.33</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4896.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It is our interpretation, especially in the light of the jurisprudence quoted by the government, they say now it is quite constant, and we agree with it.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4896.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4898.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The Greek Catholics will lose.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4898.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4899.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We agree with that.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4899.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4932.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So that's why if there was a way to combine the two and to result in various outcomes, depending on various local factors from community to community, the jurisprudence and the interpretation and combining the two, the principle of the majority and the principle of the will of the majority and the provision of common law, which have resulted in a diverse case law where depending on the concrete facts, the Greek Catholics might lose or might win.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4932.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4935.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Yes, we would have agreed that the two can be combined.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4935.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4942.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But in reality, we see very clearly, and now even more, that in the material time, the applicants addressed the domestic courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4942.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4953.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There is no way to combine the two, because the only way they managed to combine them was to create a system when one party always loses.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4953.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4966.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Unless, of course, the other party agrees, because the government provided a couple of cases where actually the Greek Catholics won in court because the Orthodox agreed to return the church.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4966.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4971.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Why there is need for a court procedure for that, we don't know.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4971.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4977.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Another question referred to Article 4 of the decree law, 126 per 1990.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4977.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>4996.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Well, indeed, the applicants in the current case, I'm talking about the parish in Lupen, the Lupen parish, because there is another Greek Catholic parish in Lupen, but then did not apply for financial support based on Article 4.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>4996.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5009.01</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>These supports the applicants received, and it's mentioned on a more general scale to support Greek Catholics received from the state, is not based on Article 4.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5009.01</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5024.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's based on a general law that provides for financial support of all churches and recognized religions in Romania, not something specific for Greek Catholics as Decree 126 is.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5024.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5031.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But there was a well-founded reason why they have not asked for the financial support to build a new church.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5031.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5035.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that was related to the local conditions in Lupen.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5035.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5046.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As I said, there were two Greek Catholic churches in Lupen, and two Greek Catholic parishes were re-established after 1990.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5046.83</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5056.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And they thought, at the same time, that the two churches are with the Orthodox now, and the Orthodox have a third church as well.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5056.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5066.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So they thought it is rather normal that they would ask for this church in kind to have it as such.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5066.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5081.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And after that was not possible, and after all the fights, for the other church, they preferred not to ask it before courts, but to ask for some financial support.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5081.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5083.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The fact is, even today, there is no church built.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5083.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5091.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>They did receive land, but they have no money to build the church.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5091.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5102.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>That's why the applicants in the current case wanted at least to get one of the churches of Lupen back in order to be able to practice their religion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5102.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5115.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And I was stunned by the government's comments that giving back a church would actually mean infringement of the right to practice religion by the majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5115.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5125.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Why is it not the other way also, that if you're not giving a church back, and the minority does not have a church, why is not an infringement on their right to religion?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5125.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5129.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But that is not the subject matter of today's hearing.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5129.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5136.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As this part of the complaint, the breach of Article 9 is not before you today.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5136.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5147.45</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But in the chamber procedures, the government was quite strong in saying there is no breach of the minority's rights to a religion due to the fact they have no access to a church.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5147.45</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5153.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Now, why one way to the majority and another way for the minority?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5153.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5165.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With a question on the census, it was assessing the will in this particular case or not, according to our information.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5165.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5166.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There was no.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5166.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5177.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I mean, the local authorities do have the possibility to organize a form of consulting the population on a specific matter.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5177.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5180.25</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We are not aware of something like that.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5180.25</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5184.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We are not aware that something like that was done.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5184.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5198.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The data that are used by the courts when saying there are 500 Greek Catholics and 26,000 Orthodox in Lupen are part of the general census data, the previous one, not the latest.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5201.55</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5207.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And it's just a statement of the person that were interviewed during the census on their religion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5207.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5215.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It has nothing to do with the practice of religion, or to the use of a church as part of the practice.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5215.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5217.05</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's just general data.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5217.05</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5223.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And those were taken into consideration by the court in their reasonings.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5223.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5241.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>With referring to the question of the market value of the churches that were returned, and those who stayed, which stayed with the Orthodox, I'm not aware of any such analysis being performed so far.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5241.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5244.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I only know of specific cases.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5244.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5266.85</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>We have the data provided by the government with a number of the churches that, one way or another, were returned to the Greek Catholics via court proceedings only a couple of dozens, and via some form of local agreement or express of the will of the majority.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5266.85</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5273.21</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There are a bit more than 250, if I remember correctly, from the data provided by the government.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5273.21</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5281.77</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But from practice and from speaking with the applicants in the current cases, one is one that is aware of more cases than one.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5281.77</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5303.29</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Usually, the Orthodox are willing to give back churches that no longer use, which are old, and which are of no value to them anymore, even if they keep them closed, just not to return them to the Greek Catholics.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5303.29</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5339.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And if you look in the documents provided by the government and also by the applicants together with the applications, at some point when the mixed commission in Lupe was forced to meet upon the requirement of the Hunedoara Tribunal, they, the Orthodox, the other party, have tried to imply that the Greek Catholics should take the other church, the second former Greek Catholic church, which is a wooden, small church.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5339.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5350.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>The one that the applicants looked for in this procedure, it's a more important church, let's say.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5350.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5353.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So I do not have statistical data.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5353.71</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5369.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the findings I've told you are just based on what I acquired from specific cases and not a general analysis.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5369.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5382.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As for the requirement to agree, at least on what the parliamentary debates were, it seems, I think this is rather relevant for the whole context of this case.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5382.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5385.37</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's very hard to agree on anything.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5385.37</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5394.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And that was for the two parties involved in this sort of litigation for 26 years, almost.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5394.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5404.69</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So that's why you'd understand why, in the end, it's such a problematic issue and why it is not solved after so many years.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5404.69</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5411.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>In my opinion, in the parliamentary debates, there were various positions expressed.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5411.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5417.41</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And of course, each of the parties can find some position to support their own.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5417.41</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5427.97</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But in my opinion, as long as someone explained very clearly what the provisions of common law actually means, and that is in line with the whole jurisprudence of the Romanian courts.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5427.97</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5429.53</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>As I said, it's nothing new.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5429.53</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5434.81</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>It's something very usual, let's say, in the Romanian legal order.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5434.81</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5444.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>And the final speech before, which concluding the debates, was also very clear on the meaning of what they were voting.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5444.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5461.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>I don't think that various other positions expressed in the debates, and that's the nature of the debates, of having opposing positions expressed and trying to convince one party trying to convince the other one.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5461.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5475.09</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But as long as the concluding remarks were quite clear on the meaning of the amendment, in my opinion, that's quite clear on the meaning of what the deputies voted for.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5475.09</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5481.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Because it was explained to them what would mean not to vote for the amendment, and the vote was overwhelming.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5481.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5490.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>There were 177 votes for the amendment, three abstaining, and four against, or the other way around.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5490.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5493.49</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So it was an overwhelming vote.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5493.49</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5499.61</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>So for me, it is quite clear what the result of the debate was.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5499.61</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5502.17</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Of course, the other party will not agree.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5502.17</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5507.65</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>But as I say, that is the nature of the issue at stake, and for you to decide in the end.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5507.65</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5507.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Applicant</Role>
        <Name>AP1</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5507.93</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5507.93</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>en</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5508.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5511.57</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Thank you very much, Mrs. Hatneanu.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5511.57</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5513.89</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Maintenant, la parole est à Mme Brumar.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5515.31</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5516.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous remercie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5517.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5524.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vais essayer de systématiser les réponses aux questions posées par votre honorable cours.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5524.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5535.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et alors, je vais, dans un premier temps, réitérer quelques aspects sur la législation en la matière, en commençant justement par les travaux préparatoires.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5536.03</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5537.75</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et pour ne pas être...</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5537.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5574.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Bon, reprocher le fait que, conformément à une anecdote où il y a deux juristes, il y a certainement trois opinions, je vais seulement me bourner à remarquer, tel que les comptes rendus des débats parlementaires le montrent, et les comptes rendus sont annexes à nos observations écrites, plusieurs députés intervenant pendant le débat ont confirmé le fait que leur intime conviction était celle que les amendements portaient seulement sur des questions de procédure.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5576.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5595.27</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je ne peux pas nier le fait qu'il y a une intervention qui provient d'un député qui, au moment de l'élaboration du texte des amendements, était membre du gouvernement, qui avait une autre opinion.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5595.47</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5599.95</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais c'était son opinion exprimée pendant le débat.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5599.95</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5623.71</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Plusieurs députés ont souligné le fait qu'ils n'entendaient pas et qu'ils ne voulaient pas nuire à l'autonomie des cultes, ne voulaient pas intervenir en substance pour régler une question qu'ils considéraient appartenant aux deux cultes de régler par la voie d'entente interconfessionnelle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5626.07</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5646.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je ne veux pas dire que mon interprétation, c'est que le sens du travail préparatoire a été de limiter la portée des amendements aux questions de procédure et que la référence au droit commun visait seulement ces questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5648.11</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5662.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je renvoie au compte-rendu qui montre, par le biais de plusieurs interventions, justement l'approche voulue par les députés lors de l'adoption du projet de loi.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5666.75</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5697.03</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Dans le décret de 1990, que les amendements apportés en 2004 n'ont pas eu l'intention d'annuler les titres de propriété de l'Église orthodoxe et de faire renaître, par la portée même de la loi, les titres de propriété du culte uniat.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5697.63</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5722.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En effet, les instances internes sont convergentes en affirmant que la portée du décret-loi était limitée à la reconnaissance formelle de l'Église gréco-catholique, mais que la question de la restitution de l'œil de culte restait à déterminer par la procédure prévue par le décret-loi.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5723.43</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5739.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Alors, il ne s'agit pas d'une annulation au pelleges des titres suscéquents à la prise, à l'appropriation des biens du culte orthodoxe en 48.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5742.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5762.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Il n'existe pas de loi spécifique pour implémenter l'article 4 du décret-loi, qui parle de l'appui que l'État apporte au culte qui se trouverait dans une situation où il n'a pas de lieu de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5762.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5776.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En même temps, force est de constater, et nos annexes aux observations écrites le montrent, que l'article 4 était assez simple d'implémenter sans législation supplémentaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5778.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5795.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En effet, plusieurs demandes ont été faites en vertu de cet article 4, et les autorités étatiques au niveau central et local ont répondu par la fin de l'article 4 et par l'affirmative à ces demandes d'aide.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5795.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5823.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La seule condition, si vous voulez, c'est de formuler une telle demande.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5823.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5853.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est vrai que la législation qui régit la restitution des autres biens ayant appartenu au culte religieux et repris par l'État pendant la période communiste exclut de manière express les lieux de culte de son genre d'application.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5853.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5868.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'interprétation faite par les instances internes a été que le décret loi de 1990 doit être traité de loi spéciale, de loi spécifique à la matière.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5874.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5896.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>En ce qui concerne la pratique des instances internes, je vais commencer par confirmer qu'aucun recours dans l'intérêt de la loi n'a pas été introduit afin de trancher par une décision obligatoire de la haute cour en formation plénière la question de la manière à aborder ce type de litige.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5899.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5920.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je ne pourrais pas spéculer sur les motifs qui ont déterminé les titulaires de demander d'initier une telle procédure qui aboutit au prononcé d'un recours d'une décision dans l'intérêt de la loi ont eu pour ne pas initier une telle demande.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5921.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5944.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais en même temps, je tiens à réitérer le fait que la haute cour de cassation, même en l'absence d'une telle décision, a montré ses efforts pour qu'à partir de 2012, sa pratique soit consolidée et convergente dans le sens de la prise en compte du critère de la volonté des fidèles.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5945.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5964.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Et c'est la haute cour même qui reconnaît qu'avant 2011-2012, c'est la période qu'elle indique, la jurisprudence nationale était peu convergente mais qu'après, elle a été reconnue comme bien convergente, mais qu'après ce moment, elle ne se pose pas la question de divergence de jurisprudence.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5966.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5984.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est la haute cour qui indique aussi comment, à son avis, les règles du droit commun et la réglementation spécifique qui parle du critère de la volonté des fidèles doit être prise en compte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5984.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>5993.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Elle indique le fait qu'elle commence par appliquer la règle générale d'une action en justice qui vise la restitution d'un bien.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>5996.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6000.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Toute instance nationale commence par vérifier l'existence de titre.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6000.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6019.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si le demandeur n'a pas, au moins prima facie, une prétention soutenue par une inscription dans le livre foncier ou par d'autres documents, il est bien évidemment que son action sera rejetée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6019.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6032.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>De même, si son titre porte sur un autre bien que celui qui est revendiqué ou s'il porte sur un bien qui n'existe plus, son action va être rejetée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6032.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6081.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Seulement, si les premières étapes visant à vérifier le cadre processuel, l'existence du bien, sont accomplies, les instances nationales passent à la 3e étape où elles vérifient si, en conformité avec la volonté de la majorité des fidèles, la restitution du lieu de culte en faveur du culte niat va se faire ou si, au contraire, c'est la volonté des fidèles que le lieu de culte reste dans la possession de la majorité.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6085.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6099.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La référence aux données recensées, j'ai déjà indiqué dans mon intervention antérieure, n'est qu'indicative.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6099.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6115.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les données de recensement sont générales et elles ne visent qu'à l'appartenance à un culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6115.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6125.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Elles ne détaillent plus sur des questions spécifiques comme l'accord pour que le lieu de culte soit restitué ou non.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6125.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6137.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>C'est justement pour cette raison que ces données ne fonctionnent que pour fonder cette présomption, qui est une présomption relative qui peut être renversée.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6138.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6146.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Rappelons-nous que dans le cas concret de la recurrente, la Cour d'appel a entendu des témoins.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6146.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6160.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Un des témoins a confirmé qu'il figurait à tort sur la liste des fidèles voulant que le lieu de culte soit restitué à l'église d'Uniate.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6160.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6182.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Deux des témoins ont confirmé leur appartenance au culte orthodoxe, la volonté de la majorité de conserver l'usage du bien, et ont offert des détails sur les circonstances entourant l'édification de ce lieu de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6187.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6194.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Est-ce que l'application du critère de la volonté de fidèle est prévisible, en procédure préalable ou en procédure judiciaire?</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6196.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6220.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce que je peux vous dire, c'est qu'il est prévisible que le sort du lieu de culte va être établi en consultant la communauté, et que la réponse ne peut être apportée en dehors des plus éléments spécifiques.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6220.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6239.83</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Or, dans un cas hypothétique que vous mentionnez, on ne sait pas le nombre de lieux de culte dans la communauté, on ne sait pas si la communauté ne préfère pas aménager d'une manière pratique l'usage en commun du lieu de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6243.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6251.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On ne sait pas si la majorité orthodoxe décide de restituer le lieu de culte à l'Église niate.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6254.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6270.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce qu'on sait, c'est qu'on doit consulter la communauté, que la communauté est la mieux placée pour déterminer le sort de ce bien qu'elle utilise, et qu'elle a une signification spéciale pour elle.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6275.39</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6281.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Le gouvernement considère que la partie recurrente a bénéficié d'un accès effectif à un tribunal.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6284.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6298.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Si ma lecture des exceptions dans la règle d'or est correcte, ces exceptions visaient des cas où on ne permettait pas la saisie d'un tribunal.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6298.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6307.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les récurrents ont pu saisir le tribunal, les tribunaux internes se sont penchés sur le fond de l'affaire.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6307.79</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6309.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ils ont recherché comment l'Église a été bâtie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6312.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6327.59</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ils ont recherché à voir comment les contributions des gréco-catholiques et orthodoxes ont été faites pour l'édification du lieu de culte.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6329.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6341.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les instances nationales n'ont pas ignoré le fait qu'en 48, les fidèles gréco-catholiques ont été forcés de rejoindre le culte orthodoxe.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6342.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6356.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce que les instances nationales disent, c'est qu'après 1940, ces fidèles ont eu la possibilité de revenir au sein de l'Église pignate.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6356.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6357.79</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ils ne l'ont pas fait.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6357.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6377.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Vingt ans après, des fidèles orthodoxes utilisent une Église qu'ils ou ses prédécesseurs ont bâtie.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6378.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6384.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La conclusion de la haute cour, c'est que l'Église doit rester dans l'usage de la communauté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6385.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6394.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Qui a une structure différente à ce moment, mais que cette structure différente s'explique par le libre choix de ses membres.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6400.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6407.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous ai déjà dit que la position du gouvernement, c'est qu'un lieu de culte ne peut pas être évalué pécuniairement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6409.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6431.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Mais si vous me permettez d'autres informations statistiques qui ne visent pas la valeur pécuniaire, mais la valeur en termes de lieu d'édifice qui sert une communauté.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6431.59</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6441.99</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>On a à ce moment 16 millions d'églises orthodoxes et 400 églises gréco-catholiques.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6441.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6456.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les églises orthodoxes servent chaque église plus de 1 200 fidèles orthodoxes.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6457.99</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6469.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Une église gréco-catholique est destinée à répondre aux croyances de 400 fidèles gréco-catholiques.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6469.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6474.39</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Cela veut dire qu'une église orthodoxe sert plus de fidèles qu'une église gréco-catholique.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6483.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6489.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Ce sont mes réponses aux questions posées par votre honorable cours.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>Government</Role>
        <Name>GR2</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6489.19</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6491.19</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je vous remercie de votre attention.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

  <SpeakerSegment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6493.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6495.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Merci beaucoup Madame Brumar.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6495.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6499.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Nous en arrivons maintenant au terme de l'audience.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6499.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6507.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Je remercie les comparants qui ont assisté la Cour par leur intervention et leur réponse à ces questions.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6507.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6511.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>La Cour va maintenant délibérer sur le fond.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6511.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6513.88</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'arrêt sera rendu ultérieurement.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6513.88</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6517.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>Les partis seront informés de la date du prononcié.</text>
    </Segment>
    <Segment>
      <meta_data>
        <Role>JudgeP</Role>
        <Name>Guido Raimondi</Name>
        <TimestampBegin>6517.38</TimestampBegin>
        <TimestampEnd>6518.38</TimestampEnd>
        <Language>fr</Language>
      </meta_data>
      <text>L'audience est levée.</text>
    </Segment>
  </SpeakerSegment>
  

</transcript_7694311_02032016>
